<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0057">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Connolly to Éamonn Ceannt, 23 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Connolly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from James Connolly (1868-1916), socialist and revolutionary, to Éamonn Ceannt (1881-1916), Irish-Irelander and revolutionary. This letter was written at 7.30am to summon Ceannt to a meeting of the leaders of the Rising on Easter Sunday morning 1916. Connolly writes that both he and Thomas MacDonagh (1878-1916). another of the leaders of the Rising, felt it was necessary to hold a meeting. It was at that meeting that, owing to a number of set-backs, it was decided to postpone the Rising until the following day. Connolly was an active trade union and socialist organiser and commandant of the Irish Citizen Army. In 1916 he joined the military committee (later Military Council) of the Irish Republican Brotherhood and became intimately involved in the planning and execution of the Easter Rising. He was a signatory of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic and commander in chief of the rebel forces in Dublin during the Rising. He was executed on 12 May. Ceannt was an active cultural nationalist and separatist and was a member of the Gaelic League, the Irish Volunteers (where he was director of communications and commandant of the 4th Dublin battalion) and the Irish Republican Brotherhood. Ceannt was a signatory of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic and during the Easter Rising Ceannt commanded the garrison of rebels in the South Dublin Union. He was executed on 8 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Áine Ceannt Collection, BMH CD/94/4/1(a)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/57</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1403">James Connolly</persName>
              <date>1916-04-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0397">Éamonn Ceannt</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0057_img_1118_1"  type="Letter"  url="5d53025dc4fbf34b996f853322c7fb20.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0057_img_1118_2"  type="Envelope"  url="24dfc27f2f2f6e150865eb68671f0a72.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0057_img_1118_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="cd2af4ea1da0631542dfab0c2a609272.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0057_img_1118_1"/>
              McDonagh &amp; I agree that it is important <lb/>we have a conference immediately, as various <lb/>messengers are awaiting decision. <seg type="closer"> James </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0057_img_1118_2"/>
                IRISH TRANSPORT AND GENERAL WORKERS UNION  Head Office: - LIBERTY HALL, BERESFORD PLACE, DUBLIN.      Phones 3421 &amp; 4199  Eamonn Ceannt  2 Dolphin Terrace  Dolphin's Barn.    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0057_img_1118_3"/>
              Letter from James Connolly sent to <lb/>E. Ceannt Easter Sun. morning <lb/>(7.30 AM) summoning him to the <lb/> meeting at which it was decided to <lb/>go on with the Rising. notwithstanding <lb/>McNeills counter manding order  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>