<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3094">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne, 23 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter addressed to &#39;Emi&#39;, likely to be Emily Adelaide Wynne, probably a sister. Charles describes life as an officer, catching the Victoria train, and everyday matters such as the weather and eating breakfast and dinner. He also comments on how the Irish people &#39;know how to behave in public&#39;.

Charles Wynne served as a captain in the Royal Garrison Artillery during the First World War. His application to the Royal Flying Corps was denied in 1916 due to his poor eyesight. Charles ultimately died of wounds received at Armentieres, June 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>Trinity College Dublin</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3094</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-09-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0689">Stockcross</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Emily Adelaide Wynne[?]</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3094_img_250_1"  type="Letter"  url="936e1d46bcfc6d80bc5fffc553d667e3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3094_img_250_2"  type="Letter"  url="b48a53071dc10c1710fde352dc51ccc8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3094_img_250_3"  type="Letter"  url="6f44aab15090d4513c70a9f5756279de.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3094_img_250_4"  type="Letter"  url="0325b265a6062c4a79ae89a02338735d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3094_img_250_5"  type="Letter"  url="291977e99c70aa3a15d5933d1c3d4afd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3094_img_250_1"/>
             Stockcross   23<hi rend="underline">.ix</hi>.16   Dear Em,   I'm not quite sure how many <lb/>letters I have to acknowledge- I think <lb/>Win's was the last. Will you please <lb/>do the job for me. This I'm afraid <lb/>sounds awfully ungrateful but <lb/>it isn't really as you know how <lb/>I enjoy getting letters - Will you <lb/>please tell Aunt Fanny I hope to <lb/>write soon. I was very glad to <lb/>get Mothers but so sorry to hear <lb/>Father had a bad turn. I hope he's <lb/>all right now and all arrived <lb/> safely.   As I said to Mother <seg type="del">last</seg> <lb/>on Thursday night an officer was
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3094_img_250_2"/>
            was wanted from 182 to take a <lb/>party to Beskill - my luck was <lb/>all out and I was the only Officer <lb/>in the battery who was not going <lb/>on leave - the other  two  having gone out <lb/>for a bike ride, so of course <seg type="del">of</seg> <lb/>it fell to me - you can't imagine <lb/>how disgusted I was - as I had promised <lb/> to go. Yesterday morning I got <lb/>up about 6.0 and started on <lb/>the weary journey. - Five changes &amp; <lb/>I don't think even the D&amp;S. ER <lb/>Shillelah branch could have taken <lb/>7 hours covering I suppose about 70 <lb/>miles - but the South Eastern &amp; <lb/>Clapham did it all right. <lb/>however in due we got to Beshill <lb/>soon after 3.0 - The men <lb/>voted for a tram to <seg type="unclear">Coodeu</seg> so <lb/> we waited for one. The trams <lb/>are very diminutive and the first <lb/>one that came was nearly full <lb/>already, however after a little <lb/>gymnastics, the fo<seg type="del">ur</seg> r ty three men <lb/>and myself packed on nearly <lb/>leaving the conductress behind <lb/>in the process. By the time <lb/>I had handed them over at <lb/><seg type="unclear">Coodeu</seg> I found time had slipped <lb/>by in a nasty way and it was <lb/>well after 4.0 and the tram <lb/>gone. I had a haversack at the <lb/>SE &amp; C station and my  probable  train <lb/>left LB &amp; SC R station at 4.31, <lb/>the station was some two miles from
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3094_img_250_3"/>
            <seg type="unclear">Coodeu</seg> and I expected a wire <lb/>at Beshill P.O. from Miss Bauer <lb/><seg type="del">was</seg> to whom <hi rend="underline">I had wired</hi> <seg type="del">my</seg> <lb/>earlier - to finally decide my <lb/>movements. I did a sort <lb/>of walk run <seg type="del">h</seg> got haversack, <lb/>guessed contents of telegram and <lb/>ran hard towards the LB &amp; SC R <lb/>station; at 4.30'30" I shouted <lb/>to a passing motor for a seat, <lb/>flew to station rushed down steps <lb/>knocking astonished inspectors <lb/>left and right and got on one <lb/>end of platform in time to see <lb/>train <seg type="del">d</seg> moving off the other end, <lb/>however there my luck was in <lb/>as I discovered a rail motor. left <lb/>in 6 minutes which sometimes <lb/>caught the Victoria train at <lb/>Eastbourne. I talked  to  the conductor <lb/>and we just got to Eastbourne in <lb/>time for me to nip across into <lb/>the Victoria train, a fast one <lb/>non-stop arriving 6.40. I had <lb/>left a wire with the conductor <lb/>giving instructions for wire from <lb/>Miss Bauer to be forwarded to <lb/>Victoria and on arrival found <lb/>Mrs Temple couldn't have me <lb/>for the night so went to Paddington.   I think Father only believed a <lb/>small part of what I told him <lb/>at Sussex Gardens - perhaps it <lb/>will help to convince him when <lb/>I say that a regulation is out.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3094_img_250_4"/>
            that all officers up to rank <lb/>of <seg type="del">Mj</seg> Major(!!) when registering <lb/>in an hotel have to give their <lb/>station and name of commanding <lb/>Officer!!! Thank goodness at <lb/>least a  few  people in Ireland know <lb/>how to behave in public. Having <lb/>this sort of 'brand of the uniform' <lb/>wherever one goes irritates me <lb/>horribly- I remarked at the hotel <lb/>that it didn't say much for the <lb/>Army with which sentiment they <lb/>I think fully agreed. - I had to <lb/>leave a deposit at the Office <lb/>it's a wonder <seg type="del">Des</seg> they didn't <lb/>make me pay for the meals <lb/>as I took them!   Any<seg type="del">W</seg>way I had a real <lb/>grand slam dinner - I thought <lb/>it would be my last  for some time  so I <lb/>went straight ahead. 9 courses <lb/>I think there were - I thought <lb/>I'd be laid out in the morning <lb/>but I wasn't - <seg type="del">D</seg> so I had a <lb/>small slam breakfast. I quite <lb/>expected that would do for me <lb/>but I'm still going strong (5.30) <lb/>I hope Mother won't be horrified <lb/>I'm afraid I'm a regular <lb/>German. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3094_img_250_5"/>
             On arrival here I find that <lb/>the advance party and guns are <lb/>leaving Monday, and the battery <lb/>Thursday. I'm teasing the dentist <lb/>to get him to finish me off tomorrow.   Today is a perfectly heavenly <lb/>day, the weather altogether has <lb/>been grand since the rain.   I hope it's the same with you.   Yours in love   <hi rend="underline">Charles.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>