<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1988">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J. F. Henderson to Matthew Nathan, 28 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J. F. Henderson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from J. F. Henderson assistant secretary in the Home Office to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) the under-secretary to the chief secretary of Ireland Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Nathan was under-secretary until the 1916 Rising after which he offered his resignation. In the letter the men are discussing a case involving F. G. Kitts. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7621/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1988</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1169">J. F. Henderson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0856">Home Office, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1988_img_1435_1"  type="Letter"  url="0d353a5ff40ba8ecc9e74542a96592c2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1988_img_1435_1"/>
             HOME OFFICE, <lb/>WHITEHALL.   28th April, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to <lb/>his letter of the 10th instant, in the case of Mr. F.G. <lb/>Kitts, and to say that Mr Kitts is believed by his mother <lb/>to be residing at 69, Kenilworth Square, Rathgar: she <lb/>states that she has not seen or heard from him for 4 months.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   J. F. Henderson    The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   Chief Comms <lb/>D.M.P. <lb/>Please state <lb/>Mr Kitts' present address <lb/>EOF <lb/>8.V.16   Supt. E Div.   Sergt Megahey <lb/>for report <lb/>O'Kiernan Supt. 19/5/16   Castle Reg. <lb/>W.A.M. 9/5   First rep. not yet <lb/>recd. in Cen. Reg. <lb/>J.C. 18/5/16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>