<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1489">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major E. Reade to Mabel FitzGerald, 20 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>E. Reade</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from the governor of Dartmoor prison, Major E. Reade, to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). The Governor reports that Mr. FitzGerald has stated that he left a bicycle belonging to Michael &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) in a shop in Milltown and he wants her to follow up on it. The O&#39;Rahilly was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died there some time later.Mabel Fitzgerald was the wife of Irish Volunteer Desmond Fitzgerald. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1604/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1489</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0782">E. Reade</persName>
              <date>1916-06-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1395">Dartmoor, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1746">2 Loretto Villas, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1489_img_942_1"  type="Letter"  url="1f770629e0a986da0618246334d1325a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1489_img_942_1"/>
                H.M.Prison,  Dartmoor,    20th June 1916.   Madam,   <seg type="del"> I have to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the </seg><lb/><seg type="del">and to inform you in reply</seg><hi rend="underline">32 T. Fitzgerald</hi>  The above-named states that on <lb/>Easter-Monday he left The O'Rahilly's <lb/>bicycle in a shop in Milltown, on the <lb/>left hand side going to Mr.McNeill's <lb/>in Dublin, possibly in a Public House.   He wishes you to see to it. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Madam, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   E.Reade <lb/>Governor.   Mrs. D. Firzgerald  2 Loretto Villas  Bray  Co. Wicklow  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>