<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2667">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 14 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Arthur to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 to his death. 

In this letter Arthur refers to a letter previously sent by O‘Dwyer, in which the bishop sounded very pessimistic about things. In contrast, Arthur states that he believes the British forces grow stronger each day and the enemy weaker. Moreover, for him, British control over the seas ought to be a decisive factor. Arthur believes that both sides have made mistakes but that their side have fought with clean hands as they have been generous when sinking enemy ships and not a single female spy has been executed in England. This he regards as a sign of English chivalry. 

Arthur goes on to write that, sentiment aside, the loss of life and destruction caused by the war is lamentable. Arthur writes about the British withdrawal from the Dardanelles as a ‘ticklish’ operation, which was sure to have disappointed the Turks. Arthur wonders if any of his friends have shouldered a rifle before asking a favour of the bishop.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/F/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2667</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0475">Arthur</persName>
              <date>1916-01-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0100">Bannu, N.W.F., India</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2667_img_2090_1"  type="Letter"  url="b708c83cea6a08daaa4b7417a6088faf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2667_img_2090_2"  type="Letter"  url="d62caf3fef650cfa23339209a75749c0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2667_img_2090_3"  type="Letter"  url="26aab7e65451aa209c38b63e5fcc7d73.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2667_img_2090_4"  type="Letter"  url="ee3902c3fcc9cb31e687aa29e17b6f30.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2667_img_2090_1"/>
             Bannu <lb/>NWF <lb/>India   Jan 14 1916   My Lord   I was delighted to get <lb/>your very welcome letter, which <lb/>appears to have just escaped <lb/>the fate of the Persia.    I'm seen very pessimistic <lb/>about things. I am not one bit.   Every day we grow stronger <lb/>&amp; stronger — the enemy weaker &amp; <lb/>weaker, and our control of <lb/>the seas must prove a <lb/>powerful factor.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2667_img_2090_2"/>
             Of course we have made <lb/>mistakes — so have the enemy. <lb/>And one thing , we are fighting <lb/>with clean hands. — or do you <lb/>disagree? Even when we have <lb/>sunk enemy ships, we have behaved <lb/>generously towards them. <lb/>And has a single spy woman <lb/>in England been executed? Perhaps <lb/>its all <hi rend="underline">Quixotic</hi> chivalry — but still <lb/>it is chivalry.   But apart from all sentiment <lb/>it is terrible to think of the loss <lb/>of life, and destruction of farmers <lb/>works. Europe has been turned <lb/>into a shambles. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2667_img_2090_3"/>
             Our withdrawal from the Dardanelles <lb/>seems to have been skilfully planned <lb/>and executed. It must have <lb/>been as "ticklish" an operation <lb/>as has ever been carried out, <lb/>and it most sorely disappoint <lb/>the Turks that they haven't <lb/>"bagged" the crowd.   Is <seg type="del">Ralph</seg>  Vincent  Nash working at any <lb/>of the "operation theatres" ? And <lb/>have any of my other Limerick <lb/>friends shouldered a rifle, or <lb/>fixed spur to boot?    I see a great friend of mine <lb/>lost his life — namely <seg type="unclear">Fr Brown</seg> <lb/>By the way May I ask a
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2667_img_2090_4"/>
            favour. I haven't seen a " Clongownian " <lb/>for the last year. I wrote to the <lb/>Editor, but probably my letter <lb/>miscarried. I would be so <lb/>grateful if you could get it for <lb/>me?    I see the question of our promotion <lb/>out here is again being pressed &amp; <lb/>I hope the present state of things <lb/>will be remedied. It's hard luck <lb/>having " youngsters" passed over our <lb/>heads. &amp; after the war ( when)? will <lb/>not endure smooth working of <lb/>the service.    Hoping you are enjoying the best <lb/>of health.   Yours Affectionately   Arthur 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>