<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3635">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Stephen Gwynn to John Redmond, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Stephen Gwynn </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Stephen Gwynn (1864-1950) to John Redmond (1856-1918) regarding the aftermath  in Dublin and the lack of opportunity as a consequence of the Easter Rising.

Stephen Gwynn was an Irish journalist, Protestant Nationalist politician, and Member of Parliament. He represented Galway City from 1906 to 1918. At the request of party leader John Redmond, he wrote &#34;The Case for Home Rule (1911)&#34; and was in charge of publicity for the party, especially in response to criticism from Sinn Féin. 

John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers, Collection List No. 118; MS 15, 192/9/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3635</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0046">Stephen Gwynn </persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1950</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3635_img_3032_1"  type="Letter"  url="9a309750135b272a8636abc58af37046.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3635_img_3032_2"  type="Letter"  url="ccf1ed0f77accd6497b8a3d496b4a73d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3635_img_3032_3"  type="Letter"  url="abd7cf47024f122631d133e15f18cb1d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3635_img_3032_1"/>
             13&amp;-5-16   My dear Redmond   I went up yesterday &amp; <lb/>saw Willy to put before him my <lb/>view that we were more wanted <lb/>at home, in the present state of <lb/>things, than here - especially <lb/>as both of us are too old for our <lb/>job. I probably have a month or <lb/>so more in me than he, but <lb/>it is all a question of time before <lb/>he &amp; I be sent to the knackers' <lb/>yard in any case: and it is <lb/>far better to come home where <lb/>we can be of some service than <lb/>to accept nominal jobs here. So <lb/>I went yesterday to my C.O. &amp; <lb/>put this to him. It is not <lb/><seg type="unclear">recipay</seg> for W M. Hickie
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3635_img_3032_2"/>
            have been always pressing him in <lb/>that sense. No one has yet <lb/>proposed it for me, but when I <lb/>talked to <seg type="unclear">Lewis</seg> Conyngham he <lb/>said (&amp; he has just been in Dublin) <lb/>that he thought my place was in <lb/>parliament. What one can <lb/>do isn't a matter for hope - <lb/>but I'd like to be at hand. <lb/>It isn't the moment to disfranchise <lb/>our constituency   I do hope to God that we <lb/>may get to the point of <lb/>introducing the idea that it is <lb/>our <seg type="unclear">interestto have figureheads </seg> <lb/>in Dublin Castle. Any man <lb/>who is a man &amp; who will <lb/>work on the basis of accepting <lb/>the H.R. will as it stands
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3635_img_3032_3"/>
            ought I think to be welcomed as <lb/>an ally. But there is no use <lb/>in giving opinions at a distance, <lb/>except for this - that Tennant, <lb/>friendly &amp; capable though he has <lb/>been, seems to me a thoroughly <lb/>bad man for the job. I'd far <lb/>sooner have <seg type="unclear">Seely</seg> —   Anyhow, I may be back <lb/>quite soon. I've asked for the thing <lb/>to be treated as a matter of urgency - <lb/>&amp; Conygham thought there should be <lb/>no difficulty   Yours very sincerely &amp; in <lb/>the sincerest sympathy   <hi rend="underline">S. Gwynn</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>