<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5807">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sister M. Cyprian to Sinéad de Valera, 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sister M. Cyprian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter to Sinéad de Valera (1878-1975) from Sister M. Cyprian.  In this letter Sister Cyprian sympathises with Mrs. de Valera on her husband&#39;s imprisonment. She is praying daily for his release and return to his family. She encloses a letter and a pair of scapulars which she asks Mrs. de Valera to give to her husband.  Finally she asks Mrs.de Valera to bring her children to visit her at the Convent (Mercy, Cork St., Dublin) - a visit which, apparently, had been promised by her husband before his incarceration.

Sinéad de Valera (née O&#39;Flanagan), author and teacher, was the wife of Éamon de Valera (1882-1975). After the Rising, Sinéad was pregnant and without an income while her husband was in prison, and was forced to return to the family home in Phibsboro to care for her invalid sister and mother. Throughout much of the ensuing political upheaval she saw little of her husband, who was either imprisoned or on the run.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/531/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5807</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0009">Sister M. Cyprian</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0182">Cork Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1202">Sinéad de Valera</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5807_img_909_1"  type="Letter"  url="45c2b5a532dbf9ada78c96571b330add.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5807_img_909_1"/>
             Mercy Convent, <lb/> Cork Street, <lb/>Dublin   29.5.16   My dear Mrs De Valera,   I sympathize with you more than I can tell in <lb/> your present troubles &amp; loneliness. It is a deep draught of consolation <lb/> that Mr. De Valera has the gift of life, that it is rescued for Him who <lb/> has given <hi rend="underline">it</hi> to withdraw it — and D.V your husband will enjoy a long <lb/> life with <hi rend="underline">you</hi> yet. When things quiet down he will be released very <lb/> soon. God will never refuse our prayers for this — I trust him fully. <lb/> Since  1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> May  I pray every day at Mass &amp; Holy Communion at <lb/> 6.30 each evening I say the 30 days prayer to our B. Lady and I hope <lb/> to begin the '9 First Fridays' on  2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> June . I promise you to continue <lb/> praying &amp; to get all the prayers I can till I hear of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. De Valera's <lb/> return home. Of cource you must feel the seperation keenly but <lb/> when a man's only crime is his love for Ireland — it's a <hi rend="underline">glorious crime</hi>   In awaiting the sentence I consoled myself with the conviction <lb/>that a man with <hi rend="underline">his handwriting</hi> would never be executed. We <lb/> have got this much &amp; it is already a big grace — so let us hope <lb/>for all our desires in this matter — viz — that your husband may <lb/>be home <hi rend="underline">very very</hi>soon   I do not know what the rules about letters are in this <lb/>present circumstances but I enclose a letter &amp; a pair of scapulars <lb/> for M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> De Valera — as I have used not seditious language I can't <lb/> see that he should be refused to have them. However if you <lb/> think there would be no chance of his receiving then you can <lb/> burn the letter &amp; please tell him I have at least made this <lb/> attempt. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. De Valera had promised to bring Vivian to see me in <lb/> Easter week. I should love to see the children — any Sunday after next <lb/> Sunday would be convenient — perhaps you may be able to bring them some <lb/> time. Please give B. Flanagan kind remembrance &amp; tell her I quite recollect <lb/> her doing <hi rend="underline"><seg type="foreign">Pancratius</seg></hi> at an entertainment in Carysfort Good bye. Love to the little children.   <!-- Following written vertically along lefthand side --> Believe me my dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> De Valera you have my very deepest - sympathy - I trust &amp; hope for the very<lb/> best - &amp; we shall obtain it - <lb/>  Very sincerely yours in Jesus Christ   Sr. M. Cyprian 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>