<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5097">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 4, June, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his father. Rations at the front consist of frozen Australian rabbits, pickles, and pressed corned beef. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5097</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-06-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5097_img_None_1"  url="05b622a2f721ab4156f2162fa0edff5e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5097_img_None_2"  url="6b91f8708f944750ac5ffd1aa846af41.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5097_img_None_3"  url="3cd8642d44386214d4249d9fd441fb30.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5097_img_0_1"/>
              4 June 1917    My dear Daddy   I was delighted to get your lovely letter<lb/>and the t<hi rend="underline">wo</hi> parcels late last night. Really<lb/>you are too good sending so much. Everything<lb/>seems just exactly what I want. I told the<lb/>cook he must make a lobster salad tonight.<lb/>The cake is also delicious and a great treat<lb/>as we never can get any eatable cake out<lb/>here to buy. The lemon cheese is also delicious.<lb/>In fact everything is absolutely top-hole.  You have no idea what a joy those<lb/>parcels always are.  I am sory that the F. post cards are so un-<lb/>reliable. Any time I am near the line I will<lb/>always try to send a letter or even a post card<lb/>in an envelope. I wonder why they do not go as quick<lb/>as letters. The bootlaces are a thing I needed<lb/>badly too as one of <seg type="del">the </seg> my  laces was a nuisance as<lb/>there was barely an inch at each end to spare. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5097_img_0_2"/>
             I have no idea of Golly's address but will<lb/>enclose a letter to her in one of yours and<lb/>will you please address it.  I think we may be here for some time by<lb/>all accounts now so you know the sort of<lb/>place I am in <hi rend="underline">and do not expect a letter<lb/>everyday as I have absolutely not a word to<lb/>write about. </hi>  It is very hard lines on Boisie Mather &amp;<lb/>I cannot understand under what rules he can be<lb/>made to take off his stripes like that. The only way<lb/>I have ever heard of a man doing that is under<lb/>sentence. They do queer things in the colonial<lb/>regiments. I did not know that Whitfelt had been<lb/>mentioned. I am awfully glad. I did not see the<lb/>paper that had that list in at all. I did not get<lb/>my paper for a coupe of days while we were<lb/>wandering round the country. I am very glad to<lb/>hear that Mr. White is getting on well now and<lb/>hope he may soon be alright again. Did I tell<lb/>you that I sent a 2nd parcel of clothes home about<lb/>a fortnight ago so I hope they will arrive alright 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5097_img_0_3"/>
             it only consisted of my rug and some heavy<lb/>underwear.  There were some post cards of S. Omer<lb/>in one of them.  I forget which.  The weather is much cooler now which is a <lb/>great blessing.  The wind keeps it cool.  But I<lb/>am afraid the flies are beginning which is<lb/>a great nuisance.  The writing pad was also most acceptable<lb/>as this one is nearly used up.  My job here<lb/>is practically nil.  I just look after the rations<lb/>for the camp.  We get a lot of frozen<lb/>Australian rabbits in the rations now and they<lb/>are very nice.  We also get very good<lb/>pickles to go with our <hi rend="underline">pressed corned beef </hi>to<lb/>give it a <seg type="del">S</seg> grand name.  I hear our 1st Batt are somewhere in the district<lb/>but I can't find out exactly where.  According to Minnies letters she and Bobby<lb/>are having great times.  I am awfully glad that<lb/>he settled down so well.  With very best love to all and again a<lb/>thousand thanks for the parcels.<lb/> your most affec Son<lb/>Willlie   <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>