<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2913">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 6 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.

In this letter, Spender tells Lillian that he has spent all day writing his weekly report for the British Cabinet. The report, Spender writes, has been annotated and edited by so many people that it is growing at a worrying rate. Spender compares himself to &#39;an old hen&#39;, expected to lay two eggs for lunch and two before dinner, and notes that &#39;it is not pride which causes a hen to cackle but rather pleasure at being rid of the thing&#39;. Spender concludes the letter be inquiring after the health of &#39;Pater&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/377</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2913</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2913_img_2322_1"  type="NULL"  url="bc1d13150ef3542794383ee22486959c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2913_img_2322_2"  type="NULL"  url="96519d9b0ee2faedfc1e77b902a9f94d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2913_img_2322_1"/>
              D1633/1/1/377    Aug. 6   Sitting up rather late &amp; I will<lb/>follow the example of a p r tho’ I<lb/>disapprove of it! I have been busy<lb/>all day on my weekly report for<lb/>the Cabinet 9 sheets of typed foolscap &amp;<lb/>had actually one whole page without<lb/>an amendment by the numerous<lb/>criteria &amp; got all the body accepted.<lb/>Such   growth in one of my<lb/>numerous offspring makes me anxious<lb/>and I wonder if the Chief —   —<lb/>will now quash it. I am like an<lb/>old hen every morning with my<lb/>eggs 2 to be laid before lunch   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2913_img_2322_2"/>
             2 before dinner. HM is now <lb/>to get 3 a day also! My weekly <lb/>and monthly eggs send me out <lb/>for a long stout walk so that <lb/>I can cackle around the country. <lb/>It is not pride that causes a hen <lb/>to cackle merely pleasure at being <lb/>rid of the thing! <seg type="del">An extra</seg>   A letter from Ivy tells me that <lb/>the Pater is ill again. I hope you <lb/>always let me know as I am <lb/>much more anxious if I think <lb/>you don’t. I hear an extra mail <lb/>is leaving in a few minutes so <lb/>close but will write again   Your b w <lb/>WB Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>