<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1170">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 1 August 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the weather and a meeting with Father Garold and Father Molony. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/29, IJA/CHPI/54/29</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1170</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-08-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1170_img_3847_1"  type="Letter"  url="acde6bc8e0d5d02ea024fe8c2822f683.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1170_img_3847_1"/>
               P.S. when the Poona <lb/>Pay Dept. have fixed up <lb/>my financial affairs for <lb/>period March â December 1917 <lb/>I shall have a substantial <lb/>balance to forward to <lb/>Your Reverence. <lb/>FS.     Mesopotamia    1 August 1918.   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   A letter from your Reverence and a card <lb/>from F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley to hand last week. I am still going strong, and <lb/>not much inconvenienced by heat, though it is hot enough. A Father <lb/>Watson C.S.S.R. died on the Euphrates of heat stroke last week. August <lb/>will see the end <sic>ofthe</sic> really high temperatures . But there are various <lb/>other possibilities outside the weather.  Last night F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Garrold <seg type="unclear">S.</seg>J. , <sic>ofthe</sic> English Province, and I, entertained <lb/>our senior Chaplain, F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Moloney, to dinner in Baghdad, in honour <lb/><sic>ofSt.</sic>Ignatius. We had no status to read; but we both wished <lb/>we could hear ourselves consigned to some place like Galway or <lb/>St. Beuno's. However, I suppose that happy consummation will come <lb/>some day.  On Sunday I did a hot tramp <sic>ofa</sic> couple <sic>ofmiles</sic><sic>tosay</sic> Mass. <lb/>On arrival at the place I found I had left the missel behind. <lb/>I said the Rosary, and then tramped back and said Mass privately. <lb/>Memory is an uncertain quantity out here. I tried to write out the <lb/>proper <sic>ofthe</sic> Mass which I recite by heart most <sic>ofthe</sic> time, but <lb/>of course I came on sudden blanks, which wouldn't fill up no <lb/>matter how often I 'went back and took a run at them'.  During July I said 17 Masses for F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley. I should have had more <lb/>only I lost four mornings travelling up river, and said Masses for <lb/>F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Watson, two Catholic Officers killed in Trench Mortar accident, and <lb/>a cholera patient who is now on the way back after a strenuous attempt <lb/>to get out <sic>ofthe</sic>world.  A Catholic Times, Irish Catholic, and Weekly Freeman have reached <lb/>me. Many thanks <sic>towhoever</sic> sent them. <seg type="closer"> I recommend myself to the prayers of all.  Francis M.Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>