<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1944">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Telford to David Lloyd George, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Telford</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Robert Telford to David Lloyd George (1863-1945), a British liberal politician and statesman. His most important role was prime minister of the Wartime Coalition Government (1916–22), during and immediately after the First World War. The letter is a warning to Lloyd George about the sermons of certain Catholic priests in America who were sympathetic to the rebel cause. He included some newspaper snippets. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8937/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1944</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1463">Robert Telford</persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1085">179 Appleton Street, Cambridge, Massachussets, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0876">David Lloyd George</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1944_img_1392_1"  type="Letter"  url="6728a26fd01c57b74292067eaaca37a4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1944_img_1392_2"  type="Letter"  url="566cfbb5468c4a0e836c90d7de67c4cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1944_img_1392_3"  type="Letter"  url="73252b6a55dbe6ef89f0d246a31be891.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1944_img_1392_4"  type="Letter"  url="113df3b0a71769bcec5ed0bf478c3ba9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1944_img_1392_5"  type="Letter"  url="c20913be65dc5536b5dc3f2a39741863.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1944_img_1392_1"/>
             179 Appleton St,<lb/>Cambridge, Mass,<lb/>U.S.A.   May 9, 1916 <lb/><lb/>David Lloyd George   Dear Sir   You must<lb/>not feel offended at me taking the liberty<lb/>of bringing the following items to your notice.<lb/>I don't see how you can know all those<lb/>things, unless someone brings them to<lb/>your notice.  A few years ago, Cardinal O' Connel<lb/>of the Boston Diocese, sent Matthew<lb/>Cummings, President of the A.O.H. and<lb/>prominent in the Clan-na-Gael, to<lb/>Ireland, accompanied by a Priest<lb/>named Father Dunn (I believe that<lb/>was his name). Their mission was<lb/>never given out. It failed.  Their mission was to bring the A.O.H<lb/>in Ireland into affiliation with<lb/>the A.O.H in America, so that Irish<lb/>Politics <seg type="unclear">H</seg>, would be controlled in 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1944_img_1392_2"/>
             2<lb/>America. They saw Cardinal Logue<lb/>and I suspect he stopped the scheme.<lb/>Boston Archdiocese May 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/><!-- Newspaper Clipping --><lb/>In all, or nearly all, of the Catholic<lb/>churches of the archdiocese, at the<lb/>masses yesterday morning, in the pray-<lb/>ers for the dead, the congregations were<lb/>requested to pray for the souls of the<lb/>men who were recently shot for trea-<lb/>son in Dublin, men who died in defence<lb/>of the liberties of their native land<lb/>was added by many of priests.<lb/><!-- Newspaper Clipping -->  Washington, May 6 — The state-<lb/>ment in the German note to the United<lb/>States that twice within a few months<lb/>the German Government has indicated<lb/>its willingness to make peace, and<lb/>stands ready to consider peace on cer-<lb/>tain terms, is taken in some official cir-<lb/>cles here as a hint that American me-<lb/>diation would not be unacceptable to<lb/>the Kaiser.  This part of the note has already brought out a reply from England and at the same time a communication from Pope Benedict to President Wilson.  Archbishop Bonzano, the papal delegate to Washington, called at the White House today. He left with Sec Tumulty, for the President, a note from Pope Benedict. The White House explained that it was a strictly confidential communication and therefore it should not be made public without permission from the Vatican.  Cardinal Gibbons also spoke<lb/>yesterday, saying — There is<lb/>something in the wind, but it<lb/>is not for me to speak of it now. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1944_img_1392_3"/>
            3<lb/>  As matters have stood from the beginning <lb/> of the war, Germany stands convicted in <lb/> the eyes of the whole world as being <lb/> the cause of the war.   From what I learn by observing the <lb/> German and Irish here, their object <lb/> is to induce President Wilson to bring <lb/> about a suspension of hostilities with <lb/> the object of agreeing on Peace.   That would be a terrible mistake for <lb/> England to agree upon, once the <lb/> War Machine stopped it would <lb/> be rather difficult to start it again, <lb/> as there would be such a world wide <lb/> demand for Peace, Germany would <lb/> not agree, but most likely they <lb/> would be able to convince part of <lb/> the world that the blame for <lb/> keeping up the struggle was not <lb/> hers but Englands. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1944_img_1392_4"/>
            <!-- Newspaper Clipping --> The Herald will not be responsible for un-<lb/>solicited manuscript unless accompanied by<lb/>postage for return.  MONDAY, MAY 8, 1916  IS GERMANY BIDDING<lb/>STRONGLY FOR PEACE?  In the welter of words which make<lb/>up the larger part of Germany's re-<lb/>cent reply there is one passage which<lb/>has received very little attention,<lb/>although, if one reads between the<lb/>lines, it is of great significance. The<lb/>German government has been moved<lb/>to make its concessions, this passage<lb/>declares, by the thought of the<lb/>great doom which threatens the en-<lb/>tire civilized world should this cruel<lb/>and sanguinary war be extended and<lb/>prolonged.  From the German point of view<lb/>what does this paragraph imply? It<lb/>can mean but one thing. The great-<lb/>est doom that could threaten the en-<lb/>tire civilized world would be the ul-<lb/>timate wearing-down and overthrow<lb/>of German power. Down in his heart<lb/>the German official who wrote that<lb/>paragraph was not thinking of the<lb/>doom that would threaten English,<lb/>French or Russian civilization. He<lb/>was not thinking of kultur in this<lb/>country, for the Germans have never<lb/>credited us with having very much<lb/>of it. Not at all. It is simply a case<lb/>of blurting out what the rest of the<lb/>world has long since recognized,<lb/>namely, that anything which makes<lb/>for an extension or prolongation of<lb/>the war is sure to weigh in the scale<lb/>against the Teutonic empires. Hence<lb/>the professed readiness to make<lb/>great sacrifices in the interest of<lb/>world-civilization.  Now if Germany is strong enough,<lb/>as she alleges, and self-sacrificing<lb/>enough to give up the submarine<lb/>warfare which she values so greatly,<lb/>might she not also be found ready<lb/>to give up other things? To give up<lb/>Belgium and norther France, for<lb/>example? Surely the impending<lb/>doom of the entire civilized world<lb/>would be worth great sacrifices to<lb/>avert. In short, this cry against<lb/>the prolonging of a cruel and san-<lb/>guinary war looks very much like<lb/>a well-developed yearning for peace.<lb/>It is a far broader hint to the allies<lb/>than anything that has heretofore<lb/>been given to them.   Boston Herald<lb/>May 8th 1916  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1944_img_1392_5"/>
             5  as our Post Office is full of Pro German <lb/>Irish, I thought it best to register the <lb/>letter. I do hope that an election in <lb/> England will be avoided until <lb/>sometime after the war ends.   I am an ex. Liverpool Police Officer, <lb/>have seven relations in the army, <lb/>Sorry that I am rather too old <lb/>myself being 67.  Yours Faithfully <lb/>Robert Telford
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>