<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1331">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 22 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) anticipating their married life and thanking May for sending on the local news.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1331</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-02-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1661">National Health Insurance Commission, Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1331_img_650_1"  type="Letter"  url="0590fe50683615870405408f642c1266.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1331_img_650_2"  type="Letter"  url="b0fa6ab9ea7faff9779520aacef9c70f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1331_img_650_3"  type="Letter"  url="86928755a597003fee6f3955ac52f7b7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1331_img_650_1"/>
                NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION (IRELAND),  PEMBROKE HOUSE,  UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN.    22 Feby. 1916   My darling girl,   Today again I am <lb/>afraid I must put you off with a <lb/>very short letter. I have been extremely hard <lb/>pushed all day and am writing now under <lb/>pressure in order to catch the post. Since <lb/>I finished that last sentence I have been <lb/>twice interrupted so I hope you will <lb/>sympathise with my sad case. Since you’re <lb/>talking of pettishness, I may say I’m <lb/>as fond of sympathy as any child so <lb/>from all points of view you’ll have a <lb/>hard time with me when you have  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1331_img_650_2"/>
              to put up with me every day for the <lb/>remainder of our natural lives. My <lb/>mother had a letter from Mrs Seery <lb/>this morning letting us know the good news <lb/>about Johnnie. We were all delighted on <lb/>his account and hope he starts on his <lb/>new job soon and that he will have <lb/>the best of luck in it. I failed to keep <lb/>my promise to you to write to her yesterday <lb/>but I must try and manage a minute or two now to write her a line. <lb/> I suppose I had better say that I will <lb/>go down on Saturday and that I will <lb/>meet you in Mullingar. I was amused <lb/>to hear that Mrs John Duffy is only an <lb/>object of curiosity in the country now. I <lb/>expect we’ll be the same presently but <lb/>that they will all be coming to see me <lb/>and not you as the object of curiosity <lb/>to see what you could see in me to <lb/>induce you to marry me. Glad to hear <lb/>about all the romances. You can trust me <lb/>to keep a quiet tongue in my head about <lb/>them all. I haven’t the pleasure of knowing <lb/>Miss Fox’s appearance but I expect she’s <lb/>good looking all right or Ned wouldn’t <lb/>be after her. How about your own <lb/>brothers? They ought to be on the warpath <lb/>soon if they take after their sisters who <lb/>are all early birds. By the way, thanks <lb/> for kisses which I succeeded in finding  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1331_img_650_3"/>
              although in one or two cases you were <lb/>mean enough to try to hide them by <lb/>blots. That was hardly fair was it? <lb/>Hope I won’t have so much difficulty <lb/>next time in getting the real thing.  I have been again three times <lb/>interrupted since I wrote page 1 so I will <lb/>bring this rambling epistle to a close. <lb/>In fact I’m so bothered and worried <lb/>just at the moment that I don’t <lb/>know what I have written so <lb/>will you please, like a darling, forgive <lb/>me. Probably I’ll write again to— <lb/>morrow. With my warmest love to <lb/>my own darling and with heaps of kisses <seg type="closer"> From her loving  James </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>