<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3042">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Colonel G.A. French to Brigadier General, Queenstown (Cobh), 2 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Arthur French</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Colonel George Arthur French, commanding troops, Wexford, to the Brigadier General of the commanding troops in Queenstown, Cork. He reports on the armed rebellion at Enniscorthy, detailing military arrangements and events on 30th April and 1st May 1916. He also proposes some post-event arrangements regarding local community, security, etc.

Sir George Arthur French (1841-1921) was born in Roscommon, Ireland. He was educated at the Royal Military College, Sandhurst, and the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich, and commissioned in the Royal Artillery in 1860.  In 1871, at the request of the Canadian government, he was sent to Canada as a military inspector, eventually becoming head of the School of Gunnery at Kingston, Ontario. He was appointed to organize the North-West Mounted Police on its creation in 1873, and the next year he led the force on its famous march to the foothills of the Rockies. French resigned in 1876 and returned to duty in the British Army, eventually attaining the rank of major-general. 

The organizational skills developed in Canada were used to establish local defense forces in India and Australia. In September 1883 he was appointed Commandant of the Queensland Local Forces with the local rank of colonel, and arrived in the colony on January 4, 1884. Colonel French married Janet Clarke in 1862, daughter of the late Robert Long Innes, formerly of the 37th Regiment. Colonel French retired in 1891, and returned to England. When French retired in 1902 he received a knighthood and for the next 19 years much of his time was spent guarding the crown jewels in London, where he died on 28 July 1921.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Wexford County Archive</repository>
                  <collection>Wexford County Archive, WXCA/P190/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3042</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0796">George Arthur French</persName>
              <date>1916-05-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1432">Wexford, County Wexford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Brigadier General</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1182">Queenstown (Cobh), County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1921</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3042_img_2440_1"  type="Letter"  url="72813f1e3801e5da0d2f8053804d9d9c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3042_img_2440_2"  type="Letter"  url="42f73c06840b87a8709afea25cfada4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3042_img_2440_3"  type="Letter"  url="efe2f952189000de667314290bf12bfc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3042_img_2440_4"  type="Letter"  url="243315542d5c54a8f75f094921c58950.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3042_img_2440_1"/>
             I<lb/><lb/>Report.  <hi rend="underline">Confidential.</hi>   From Colonel G.A. French,<lb/>Commanding Troops,<lb/>Wexford.<lb/><lb/>To Brigadier General,<lb/>Commanding Queenstown Garrison,<lb/>Queenstown. <lb/><lb/> Wexford. May 2, 1916. <lb/><lb/> Sir,   With reference to the Armed rebellion at Enniscorthy,<lb/>I have the honor to report as follows.  On the evening of April 30, at 6 p.m. I held a conference<lb/>at my Head Quarters to make the necessary Military arrangements<lb/>to meet with the emergency in the event either of (1) uncondit-<lb/>ional surrender or (2) refusal to surrender.  In both cases Lieutenant Colonel Digan, Commanding the<lb/>Column, wished to move his force by one route and not to split<lb/>it up. As I was not in possession of any accurate information<lb/>as to the numbers of the insurgents or their disposition, and<lb/>as a conservative estimate of the numbers was about 600 (six<lb/>hundred), possibly more, with a considerable number of modern<lb/>firearms, I considered that Col. Digan's proposal was reasonable<lb/>and I concurred therein. I recommended his concentrating his<lb/>whole force at KILLURIN (about six miles north of Wexford), at<lb/>6-30 a.m. May 1, whether it was either a case of surrender or<lb/>no surrender. After this concentration I recommended in case of<lb/>attack his moving from KILLURIN eastwards over the bridge (which<lb/>together with the WEXFORD and FERRYCARRIG bridges I had held<lb/>with strong military guards and barricaded since the arrival of<lb/>troops at Wexford) by KYLE X Roads, OYLGATE, COOLNABAY, DARBY'S<lb/>GAP, <seg type="unclear">BELL</seg> GRACE HOUSE, to ENNISCORTHY (reference 1 Ordnance map)<lb/>taking up good gun positions for 4.7 and 18 Pr. guns as the<lb/>Infantry advance would ensure such positions, to bring the<lb/>artillery fire on ENNISCORTHY  &amp;  to shell Vinegar Hill with shrapnel.<lb/>His first objectives being the destruction of the Road and Rail<lb/>bridges (to cut rebel forces in two parts), the rebel strong holds<lb/>in the Castle and Assembly rooms at ENNISCORTHY. It was my in-<lb/>tention in the event of attack to have remained with Lieutenant<lb/>Colonol Digan throughout, and, should circumstances so warrant, 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3042_img_2440_2"/>
             to assume command myself as I had previously informed your<lb/>General Staff Officer by telephone.  In the event of surrender I left the advance into<lb/>ENNISCORTHY in the hands of Lieutenant Colonel Digan, but re-<lb/>commended his adhering to the route laid down for attach, as<lb/>that roadway was clear of trees and other barricades and ob-<lb/>structions. I,however,stipulated that all the usual military<lb/>precausions should be taken and not to place too much reliance<lb/>on freedom from attack.  On April 30, as you<seg type="del">r</seg> were informed by telephone, two<lb/>rebel leaders were despatched by Motor to Dublin to consult<lb/>with Pearse (their imprisoned leader). They returned here<lb/>about 7-30 p.m. same date, and I gave them till mid-night to<lb/>notify me the decision arrived at by the rebels at ENNISCORTHY.<lb/>At mid-night, April 30,May 1, a deputation arrived from<lb/>ENNISCORTY (headed by Fr. Fitzhenry as head of Peace Mission<lb/>but not associated with the rebel movement in any way) bearing<lb/>a despatch stating that <hi rend="underline">4</hi> leaders would surrender, but re-<lb/>questing that the rank and file should be spared. To this I<lb/>replied that the surrender must be unconditional and the surrender<lb/>of <hi rend="underline">6</hi> leaders (whose names I knew)would be insisted upon, and<lb/>that their followers would also be arrested either at once or<lb/>rounded up later. I also stipulated that all arms and warlike<lb/>material was to be surrendered, stolen and looted property re-<lb/>turned without delay,and all barricades and obstacles removed.<lb/>I also informed the peace deputation that in the event of the<lb/>troops being fired upon by any of the insurgents extreme measures<lb/>would be immediately adopted. The deputation stated that it<lb/>would do its best to ensure the fulfillment of unconditional<lb/>surrender and the other conditions,but doubted whether the<lb/>leaders could prevail upon their followers to give themselves<lb/>up. As however the names of most of their followers were known<lb/>to the police I did not consider their immediate surrender im-<lb/>perative. The deputation informed me,however, that it would do<lb/>its best in this respect and would <seg type="del">do its best</seg> endeavour to see<lb/>that the six leaders surrendered at once. It returned to<lb/>ENNISCORTY about 1 a.m. May,1, and I instructed Lieutenant<lb/>Colonel Digan to march on ENNISCORTHY on <!-- it appears as if \'in\' was written first, with the o later placed over the i --> the Surrender basis. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3042_img_2440_3"/>
             I directed him to time his march so that the troops would<lb/>actually be marching through the town at the hour I had<lb/>arranged to make the arrests .  <seg type="del">with t</seg>  T he infantry (which were<lb/><seg type="unclear">encamped &amp; malles </seg> to the South of Wexford). I told Lieutenant<lb/>Colonel Digan to move by rail WEXFORD to KIMURIN and I in-<lb/>structed the railway authorities to this effect.  On May 1, accompanied by District Inspector OHARA,R.I.C.,<lb/>and Colonel Jameson Davis, Commanding National Volunteers Co.<lb/>Wexford, I motore d  direct to ENNISCORTHY without molestation<lb/>in any way and there found that the Armoured train was at the<lb/>station ; the damage to the railway having proved trifling<lb/>and easily repairable by the R.E.Detachment with the train.<lb/>I commandeered the sports field for accommodation of the<lb/>troops, ascertained that the 6 rebel leaders were awaiting<lb/>arrest at Assembly Rooms , but that their followers had vanished<lb/>(the bulk having come in from the surrounding country) and<lb/>taken all modern rifles with them. Steps are, however, being<lb/>taken to locate these arms and it is anticipated that a number<lb/>will shortly be rounded up. I then awaited the arrival of the<lb/>column, and as soon as it had entered the town I arrested the<lb/>leaders,took possession of the Assembly rooms,and collected<lb/>arms,explosives, &amp;c. (vide list attached). By arresting the<lb/>leaders whilst the troops were marching through the attention<lb/>of the crowd and sympathisers was distracted and the arrest<lb/>was quietly effected. I despatched the prisoners to Wexford<lb/>by Motors under Armed guard,and at 7-45 a.m this morning they<lb/>were railed to Waterford in charge of District Inspector<lb/>O'Hara,R.I.C.  The troops were well received on the whole,but it is<lb/>apparent that there are large numbers of the populace with<lb/>Sinn Fein sympathies.  The following points I wish to bring to notice :-  (a) That the damage to property was not extensive,and on the<lb/>whole the insurgents were, generally speaking, well behaved.<lb/>All the public houses were closed and there were only a 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3042_img_2440_4"/>
             few reports of the use of firearms,notably two cases,viz. that<lb/>a firing on Dr. Furlong and the R.I.C.Barracks, one Constable<lb/>woundedbut the member of shots fired at the Barrack could not<lb/>have been numerous as evidenced by the windows and walls of<lb/>the building. Several telegraph poles were cut down.  (b) It is essential that the Echo newspaper should be<lb/>suppressed. This paper is responsible for much of the Sinn<lb/>Fein movement in the town.This I have learned by reports re-<lb/>cieved from trustworthy sources.  (c) There was a certain amount of looting and commandeering<lb/>of food,bedding,arms, &amp;c. in the town, but not to any very<lb/>serious extent. There were,however, numerous cases of Motor<lb/>cars, &amp;c. being forcibly commandeered both in the town of and a<lb/>radius of about 7 miles. There were also some cases of looting<lb/>cattle and sheep by the insurgents for food,notably one case<lb/>at OULART.  (d) I consider that it would be advisable to retain the<lb/>column <sic>despactched</sic> under Lieutenant Colonel Digan within the<lb/>County of Wexford for some time (less the 4.7 gun and armoured<lb/>train) with its Head Quarters at ENNISCORTHY and sending out<lb/>flying columns therefrom as I may direct. The present garrison<lb/>of Wexford should remain for some considerable time until the<lb/>bulk of the arrests have been effected and the district has<lb/>resumed its normal peaceful state.  (e) I will arrange strong patrols combined of both military<lb/>and R.I.C. proceeding by motor from Wexford to all outlying<lb/>disaffected areas and will in most cases accompany same myself.<lb/>I intend to have all troops, both those at Wexford and Ennis-<lb/>corthy, very much in evidence, and will arrange accordingly.<lb/>I, of course,assume that I can instruct O.C.Troops,Enniscorthy<lb/>to supply much flying columns,&amp;c. as I consider necessary, and<lb/>that he is under my orders whilst within the County of Wexford.  I have the honour<lb/>to be<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient servant,   Colonel.<lb/>Commanding Troops,<lb/>Wexford.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>