<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0639">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James O'Shea to John Grenfell Maxwell, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Canon O&#39;Shea</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Fr James O’Shea (1873 – 1927), to General John Grenfell Maxwell (1859 – 1929). This letter concerns the conduct of Fr Michael Hayes (1873 – 1934), and Fr Thomas Wall (1877 – 1956). According to the letter Maxwell considers both Hayes and Wall a dangerous menace to the peace and safety of the realm. In the letter O&#39;Shea reports that the bishop of Limerick, Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), has been made aware of the complaints but has no right to punish the priests in question except on definite charge supported with evidence. Maxwell had been appointed commander in chief of the British forces in Ireland after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. He arrived in Ireland on Friday 28 April, the fifth day of the insurrection. As acting military governor of Ireland, Maxwell dealt with the rebellion according to his understanding of martial law which had been earlier declared by the Lord Lieutenant.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/239/1/2, LDA/BI/ET/239/1/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/639</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0192">James Canon O&#39;Shea</persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1865">Abbey View, Kilmallock, County Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1039">Irish Command Headquarters, Parkgate, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0639_img_2109_1"  type="Letter"  url="58b27d4010ad1e90bb8bb0e0bed527f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0639_img_2109_2"  type="Letter"  url="23a64c60301d3d46a9e3e7763040ba03.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0639_img_2109_3"  type="Letter"  url="cb2cc9b07dc2177723ea5b0acef101e3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0639_img_2109_1"/>
                Abbey View  Kilmallock    May 9th, 1916   Sir   I am directed by the <lb/> Bishop of Limerick to acknow<lb/> ledge the request on this receiv<lb/> ing of your letter of the 6th inst.<lb/> which has been forwarded to <lb/> him at the above address.  The Bishop desires to <lb/> point out that the actions<lb/> which you suggest to him to<lb/> take towards Rev Father <seg type="del">The</seg><lb/><seg type="del">Wall</seg>and Rev Father <seg type="del">Michael</seg><lb/><seg type="del">Hayes</seg> would be a very severe<lb/> punishment which the <lb/> Bishop has no right to <lb/> inflict on these priests  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0639_img_2109_2"/>
              except on a definite <lb/> charge supported by evi- <lb/> dence.    If then you are good<lb/> enough to specify the <lb/> grounds on which you con- <lb/> cider their presence <lb/> in the neighbourhood of <lb/><seg type="del">Dromcollogher</seg> and <seg type="del">Newcastle</seg><lb/><seg type="del">West</seg> is a 'dangerous menace<lb/> to the peace and safety of <lb/> the Realm' The Bishop will <lb/> investigate the matter and <lb/> inform you of his decision.   But whatever may <lb/> be the rights of the Military <lb/> authorities acting under  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0639_img_2109_3"/>
              martial law, a Bishop <lb/> in the exercise of his au- <lb/> thority has to follow the <lb/> rules of ecclesiastical <lb/> procedure. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be <lb/> Sir <lb/> Your obedient servant  James Canon O'Shea <lb/> Pro. Secretary   To,  To Right Honorable  General, Sir J G Maxwell, General  Commandant in-chief  of the Forces in Ireland.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>