<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4337">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from MW O'Reilly to 'A Cara', 1 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M.W. O&#39;Reilly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Volunteer M W O’Reilly to an unidentified friend, written while imprisoned in Knutsford, 1 June 1916. The letter mentions the conditions of prison life. Mentions The O&#39;Rahilly and (Paddy) Shortis. Mentions he read in the papers that Dublin is in a distressed state and that organisations have been formed to help people. Mentions the Bishop of Limerick. Mentions they have ample paper and stamps at the prison for writing letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>The Jackie Clarke Collection </repository>
                  <collection>1-12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4337</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1028">M.W. O&#39;Reilly</persName>
              <date>1916-06-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0459">Knutsford Prison Cheshire</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">A cara</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4337_img_3696_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa12dc130c2666647735823e14fe5e37.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4337_img_3696_2"  type="Letter"  url="ea81dea9bc20c6dad62e13fb3d0342e5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4337_img_3696_3"  type="Letter"  url="2c7c19c61aa3b1cfddf78b850133f91d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4337_img_3696_4"  type="Letter"  url="408668aad9c874fab8da3fd4ca9ae53d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4337_img_3696_1"/>
             M. W O Reilly B81<lb/>Irish Prisoner<lb/>Knutsford<lb/>C/o Chief Postal Censor<lb/>London   1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June 1916    A Cara , Mor    Your letter to hand<lb/>this morning, which was most<lb/>welcome, I was indeed glad<lb/>to hear from you and to<lb/>know you are well and safe.<lb/>We had had Some experience,<lb/>since I last had the pleasure of<lb/>seeing you, although they have<lb/>not all been very pleasant. It<lb/>were better to have them than never<lb/>to know of such things.  Experience is always most<lb/>enlightening even if unpleasant, 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4337_img_3696_2"/>
             I fear very much for our<lb/>Dear Friend Shortie, the last<lb/>I saw of him was in Moore St.<lb/>and he was not far from<lb/>O Rahilly (God Rest Him).  Our treatment here during<lb/>the first Three weeks could not<lb/>have been anything our worst<lb/>Enemy could have wished<lb/>for, but now our Status has<lb/>been raised and we are being<lb/>treated as privileged Prisoners<lb/>of War, having freedom of<lb/> course with one another<lb/>and other little things that<lb/>count a good deal when  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4337_img_3696_3"/>
             ones under lock and key.<lb/>I have been greatly disappointed<lb/>at hearing that something<lb/>you were interested in was not<lb/>working and I hope that<lb/>the interview Kitty and yourself<lb/>had, resulted satisfactorily.<lb/>I see by the papers that some<lb/>organisations have been started<lb/>to cope with the distress that<lb/>prevails in Dublin and Ireland<lb/>generally, and trust they<lb/>will able to meet all<lb/>the difficulties that may beset<lb/>them, so to carry their work<lb/>to a successful issue.<lb/>I saw a recent issue of the  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4337_img_3696_4"/>
             Evening Mail in which was<lb/>some correspondence from<lb/>General Maxwell and the Bishop<lb/>of Limerick, I should not like to<lb/>have missed the reply of the latter, I<lb/>It was Some reply.  I trust you Mother Sisters<lb/>and Nephew are all in good<lb/>health, as this leave me  <lb/>we can write to all our Friends<lb/>provided we have paper and<lb/>stamps of which I fortunately<lb/>am amply supplied.    With renewed thanks for your<lb/>kind thoughtfulness and best<lb/>wishes for <hi rend="underline">your</hi> future which<lb/>is I believe assured.  I am a Cara <seg type="unclear">mor</seg><lb/>Yours very sincerely<lb/>MW O Reilly 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>