<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2734">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Tate to his mother, Millicent Tate (née Farren), 18 May, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Tate </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Tate to his mother in which he describes his time in the club headquarters in Rawalpindi. Tate responds to a previous letter from his parents in which he refers to family members at home. 

James&#39;s father, Alec C Tate, also served with British army in India before he married Millicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. James spent the majority of the war in India during which time the Indian Expeditionary Force was dispatched to Mesopotamia. This letter is part of a collection that he wrote to his parents detailing his movements and his day to day experience.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Tate Papers, D2859/2/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2734</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0064">James Tate </persName>
              <date>1916-05-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0766">The Club, Rawalpindi, India</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Millicent Tate</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1676">Slieve na Failthe, Whiteabbey, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2734_img_2154_1"  type="Letter"  url="d72af490cfa25647f21c75746e882815.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2734_img_2154_2"  type="Letter"  url="97b8d777fced2e6a8d97c2b7ad530f82.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2734_img_2154_3"  type="Letter"  url="eed6105b7b06cae2ad700965381991fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2734_img_2154_4"  type="Letter"  url="8e6d37d3b7e3bdd92c9fd26cd9b909c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2734_img_2154_5"  type="Letter"  url="2dec18036a5c101147d639a22d853f3d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2734_img_2154_1"/>
             Rawal Pindi Club <lb/>Rawal Pindi   18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916.   My dear Mother   I have not written to you for ages so here <lb/>goes. As you see I have moved into the club <lb/>quarters. For one thing the Royal Hotel has has closed <lb/>here &amp; opened at Murree. also there are tons of <lb/>quarters vacant here now. There are 18 in <lb/>all &amp; in the cold weather they are crammed <lb/>with the staff etc.   No more news come about my going off <lb/>to the garden of Eden or up that way. From
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2734_img_2154_2"/>
            all accounts it is an over rated place. Leastwise <lb/>for the next three months. I hope there is <lb/>a field company job going when I get there. <lb/>They have just started to build a Railway from <lb/>Bushra up the bank of the river &amp; I see <lb/>possible visions of cooly driving. Which would <lb/> be rotten. Prince got a letter from the division <lb/>asking for suggestions for the formation of bombing <lb/>schools one in the Murree hills. I expect he <lb/>will get the job as he wrote in <seg type="unclear">soreeds</seg> about <lb/>it. If he does he says he will put in for <lb/>me  as an assistant bottlewasher etc.  which will ruin my chances of getting <lb/> off. I tried to argue the point but he was <lb/>not having any. The thing has to go up
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2734_img_2154_3"/>
            to our old friends the God of India so I <lb/>expect they will sit on it for a year at <lb/>least. If so I shall be safe.   I am going on leave on 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June up to Gharial <lb/>I am going to stay with Martin in tents <lb/>on the Gharial Flats. (Where N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 13 <sic>Coy</sic> was last year) <lb/>There is a Col Smallwood R.A. in command <lb/>of the Arsenal here. he says he knows Daddy <lb/>well &amp; wished to be <sic>rembered</sic> to him. <lb/>he says he once sold him a horse called <lb/>Whadhurst. &amp; that It ought to have been <lb/>run in steeple chases — not on the flat. <lb/>Please Thank Phil for her last weeks mail
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2734_img_2154_4"/>
            &amp; tell her I will answer it next week. <lb/>also Ander for his long letter. I am sorry <lb/>to hear that he has developed a liking <lb/>for old square face so young   From your loving son.   Jimmy  <lb/>P.S. <hi rend="underline">No news from Billy.</hi>
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2734_img_2154_5"/>
             Mrs. A. C. Tate. <lb/>Slieve-na-Failthé <lb/>Whiteabbey <lb/>Co Antrim   <hi rend="underline">IRELAND</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>