<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4271">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 6 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/208</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4271</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4271_img_3636_1"  type="Letter"  url="a4d81130c0556de03123a9300d04494a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4271_img_3636_2"  type="Letter"  url="01c69373115d00d4d6288a3358f27257.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4271_img_3636_3"  type="Letter"  url="215f7c72f3988ad5ffaa5c33c2fea499.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4271_img_3636_1"/>
             April 6   My pr   Rather an overworked bw - 16hours <lb/>real hard labour every day but I think <lb/>Place will gradually get into things &amp; <lb/>be good. He strikes me as a useful man <lb/>&amp; if so it will be good for the Div which <lb/>is all that I really mind.   So sorry about your headache do hope <lb/>it is all right now. If you really <lb/>think the counrty is right well &amp; good <lb/>but I dread for you the hard work of <lb/>going back &amp; forward in stuffy trains, &amp; <lb/>your committee may be extra busy in July 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4271_img_3636_2"/>
             I am not thinking of expense as I honestly <lb/>think your health is of great importance to <lb/>the Div &amp; of even more importance to Sir <lb/>E &amp; our Ulster Cause.   I rely on the committee being able to <lb/>get over the mistrust which is spreading like <lb/>a canker because Sir E has not been out &amp; <lb/>Redmond has. I wrote to Craig about it yesterday.   I think Rex's would be best plan for <lb/>us if I come home  on leave  but this looks very <lb/>problematical at present.   Not out yesterday nor today so <lb/>little news but much work   Best love   Wilfrid BSpender   If Rex's house weren't so far from station
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4271_img_3636_3"/>
            it would really have done delightfully as <lb/>your premium resort &amp; the train service <lb/>is excellent but I think 6 miles <sic>byke</sic> <lb/>a day would be too much. The extra <lb/><seg type="unclear">expense of a season</seg> I should not mind <lb/>as it is "in the family."   It would be jolly if we could <lb/>see our own furniture at Rex's &amp; <lb/>the woods should be at their <lb/>best in another fortnight or 3 <lb/>weeks 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>