<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1502">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Lemass, solicitor, to John Dillon, 23 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Lemass</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Henry Lemass (1883-1946) to John Dillon (1851-1927). Lemass, who is acting for Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington, is writing to Dillon confirming the contents of a wire which he has already sent him, as Dillon has been making representations on her behalf at Government level. The solicitor has been informed that the Court-Martial (of Bowen-Colthurst) is to take place on the day after, 24 May, and, although he hasn&#39;t been told when or where it is to take place. He fears that this court-martial, which carries no rights for his client, other than the right to attend, might be construed as fulfilling the Prime Minister, Herbert Asquith&#39;s promise of a Public Inquiry. Both solicitor and client are concerned that the Court-Martial is due to take place while Mrs. Sheehy-Skeffington&#39;s Counsel, Mr. Healy, is absent in England. The solicitor has written to General Sir John Maxwell and encloses a copy. He is also writing directly to the House and has sent a similar wire to Mr. Healy.John Dillon was an Irish Party MP in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to her husband&#39;s murder and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, TCD MS6837/23/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1502</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0457">Henry Lemass</persName>
              <date>1916-05-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0359">Parliament Chambers, 31 Parliament Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1201">House of Commons, Westminster, London, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1502_img_960_1"  type="Letter"  url="50f68231a87780150bcc323ac705d93a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1502_img_960_2"  type="Letter"  url="723e074a6d45b70cdc339250d875b461.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1502_img_960_3"  type="Letter"  url="1713c0f5ad1c854deccd4c0c59d59324.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1502_img_960_1"/>
              HENRY LEMASS. <lb/><hi rend="underline">SOLICITOR</hi><lb/>COMMISSIONER FOR OATHS     TELEPHONE NO. 3323.  PARLIAMENT CHAMBERS.  31 PARLIAMENT STREET.    May 23 1916    John Dillon Esq. M.P.   House of Commons,  Westmister, London SW   Dear Sir,   I beg to confirm my wire today as follows:-  'Provost Marshal Richmond Barracks informed Mrs <lb/>' Skeffington today that <sic>Courtmartial</sic>will be held tomorrow <lb/>'open to public at which we can attend but will not <lb/>'be allowed to intervene. We fear this <sic>Courtmartial</sic><lb/>' may be construed as <sic>fulfilment</sic> of Prime Minister's <lb/>' promise to hold full Public Inquiry. Our view is <lb/>' no steps should be taken in absence of Counsel (Healy) <lb/>' and without our having reasonable opportunity of <lb/>' considering our attitude as asked for in letter to General <lb/>' Maxwell. Suggest you should see Prime Minister <lb/>' to ensure adjournment by wire from him until after  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1502_img_960_2"/>
              ' Healy's return here and the holding of promised Public <lb/>' Inquiry afterwards. Writing fully to House by this <lb/>' evenings post which read early tomorrow morning <lb/>' I have sent similar wire to Healy'   I enclose a copy of my letter to General Maxwell <lb/> above referred to. Mrs. Skeffington would not consider a <lb/>Courtmartial even though open to the public a <sic>fulfilment</sic> of the <lb/> Prime Minister's pledge - especially if she could not tender evidence <lb/> or be allowed by her Counsel to cross-examine the Military <lb/> witnesses. If the <sic>Courtmartial</sic> is however only the preliminary <lb/> to a proper Inquiry of course no objection could be taken &amp; it <lb/> might even prove of some value in enabling us to elucidate what  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1502_img_960_3"/>
              happened after the arrest of Skeffington as to which we are <lb/> absolutely in the dark at present. In any event she <seg type="unclear">considers</seg><lb/> even a <sic>Courtmartial</sic> of the officer responsible for her husband's <lb/> death should not be held on such short notice (I have <lb/> not yet received any intimation as to when or where same is to be <lb/> held) or whilst her Counsel is absent in England. Our <lb/> Junior Counsel Mr Philip White is also averse to doing <lb/> anything in Mr Helys absence. It may be that the <lb/>authorities have not yet decided to hold the <sic>Courtmartial</sic><lb/>but in view of what the Provost Marshal told Mrs Skeffington <lb/> today Mr White suggested I should write you as I did in <lb/>case it might be an attempt to deny the full <seg type="del">the</seg> Investigation <lb/> of the whole matter promised by Mr Asquith  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  Henry Lemass </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>