<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0243">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Driscoll to Patrick English, 13 August 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Driscoll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Robert Driscoll (b.1898) to Patrick English (1894-1970). The letter discusses the fact Patrick has yet to return home and accounts the activities of Patrick&#39;s friends who have returned home from the prison. Robert goes on to discuss speaking with Patrick&#39;s sister. He also asks if some of his friends are still in Frongoch, asking Patrick to give one of them a smoke to remember him by.This letter is from a collection Patrick English, an Irish Volunteer imprisoned in the Stafford and later Frongoch Prisons. He had at least six cousins fighting with the British Army in France during his incarceration.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/243</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0616">Robert Driscoll</persName>
              <date>1916-08-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0463">High Road, Cashtown</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0243_img_1415_1"  type="Letter"  url="842361bb05622a5cb90ee3f690341f7d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0243_img_1415_1"/>
                High Road Ashtown    13.8.16   Dear Paddy   I never thought I would have to write <lb/> to you I was expecting you home every day I don't know what <lb/> they mean by keeping you after letting us all home however <lb/> don't be downhearted it is very <sic>lonly</sic>over here I wish I was <lb/> back again I never got a minute since I came back I miss <lb/> all the fun very much all the other Boys are going about <lb/>doing nothing except J Mooney and Kit Duffy. I do be talking <lb/> to your sister often they are <sic>nocked</sic>about very much over <lb/> you. however I told them not to mind that you would be <lb/> alright I told her about all the sport we had in <seg type="unclear">hut</seg> 20 <lb/> together Let me know if O'Leary and Joe McDonnough is <lb/>still in camp let me know the   number I have forgotten it <lb/> I want to write to<sic> bouth </sic> of them I called to O'Learys house <lb/> last week but he was not home then. I very often meet some <lb/> of the boys in the City they all wish to be back again <lb/> Don't think bad of me sending you this order for <sic>sigarettes</sic><lb/>I know you will want plenty of smoking and if O'Leary <lb/> is with you give him a few in rememberance of me. But don't <lb/>forget to write to me. And remember me to all the other lads <lb/>that I knew in camp. <seg type="closer"> Sincerely yours  R O'Driscoll </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>