<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6669">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles J. Foy to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 16 February 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles J. Foy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, Charles J. Foy asks Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, as the experienced publisher of the daily newspaper &#34;Ireland&#34; for advice. Foy is thinking about pressuring the Premier of the Dominion of Canada to properly express the feelings of the Irish in Canada within the upcoming Peace Conference. Nevertheless, he does not want to harass the Irish Parliamentary party.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph C. Walsh Papers. Letters Earls - Foy</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6669</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0085">Charles J. Foy</persName>
              <date>1917-02-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0512">Perth, Ontario, Canada</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1742">8 West 40th Street, New York, NY, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6669_img_None_1"  url="phplMIDio.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6669_img_None_2"  url="phpx8POvF.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6669_img_0_1"/>
              Charles J. Foy.    Barrister.    SOLICITOR FOR THE MERCHANTS BANK OF CANADA.    Perth, Ont. Feby. 16. 1917.   To The Editor.   Ireland Publishing Co.,    8 West 40th St., New York.    New York. U.S.A.    Dear Sir;   I am taking the liberty of introducing myself because I am<lb/>a Subscriber to your Publication which I value most highly inded for<lb/>its full and lucid consideration of Irish Affairs, to ask your advice<lb/>in a matter which effects all Irishmen but in this case, the Irishmen<lb/>of Canada more particularly. To me it appears that signs are not<lb/>wanting, that in the near future something will take place regarding<lb/>the great struggle now being waged in Europe and that peace will be<lb/>declared. The thought has struck me that the Irishmen of the Self-<lb/>governing Dominions of the British Empire should be in some position to<lb/>make their presence felt and their voice heard in connection with<lb/>Irish affairs whe the Peace arrangements are being discussed.<lb/>I believe that Ireland should have a voice in such matters and it can be<lb/>only accorded her by the concerted action of the Irish throughout the<lb/>world. The idea presents itself to me in connection with this matter<lb/>and it is this, that the Irish in Canada should bring such pressure as<lb/>may be thought advisable, to bear upon the Premier of the Dominions, so<lb/>that he, as Canada's representative at that conference, might give<lb/>expression to the feelings of the Irish in the Dominion of Canada regard-<lb/>ing this very vital question. Another matter presents itself and it is<lb/>this, that I would not like to do anything that would in any way    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6669_img_0_2"/>
              Charles J. Foy.    Barrister.    SOLICITOR FOR THE MERCHANTS BANK OF CANADA.    Perth, Ont. Feby. 16. 1917.   - 2-  seemingly harass the Irish Parliamentary part or otherwise disrupt<lb/>their plan of attack, so that I am writing you for advice in the<lb/>matter. I know and feel that you are in touch with the Honourable<lb/>Mr. Redmond and would know his views and sentiments upon this matter.<lb/>I woud therefore ask you for a favour to let me know what you think<lb/>would be the best to be done under-the-circumstances. How would you<lb/>suggest it being done?if your ideas are not in accordance with<lb/>the foregoing?  Thanking you in anticipation of an early reply.   I remain.    Yours truly.    Signature     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>