<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2668">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. C. F. Maher to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 16 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cornelius Francis Maher</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Fr C. F. Larkin to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 to his death. 

In this letter Larkin informs O’Dwyer that he has settled into life with his Division. He notes that there are approximately 1,000 Catholics in his division, the majority being English and very ‘slack’ as to their religion. Larkin records that the most disheartening feature so far is that the men do not appreciate the seriousness of what is before them. 

Larkin writes that the field hospital in the camp takes up a large part of his time but that he has adequate facilities for his ministrations to the men. Larkin states that the details of mobilisation for his unit have been changed though the men and officers look forward to going to the Front. Despite the majority of the officers in his mess belonging to the Church of England, Larkin notes that they have the utmost respect for his Roman Catholic customs. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/F/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2668</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1194">Cornelius Francis Maher</persName>
              <date>1916-04-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0849">2/3 Field Ambulance, 3A Camp, Larkhill, Salisbury Plain, Wiltshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1918</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2668_img_2091_1"  type="Letter"  url="25e78dd7154a42b5e2eecddc6732c1a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2668_img_2091_2"  type="Letter"  url="84cec09e70f5e183c5783dd34be110db.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2668_img_2091_1"/>
             2/3 Field Ambulance, 3A Camp, Larkhill,<lb/>Salisbury Plain, Wilts   16 April, 1916    My dear Lord,   After three weeks' residence in Camp,<lb/>I am now well into my work. I am to-day<lb/>finishing a short mission for the Catholics<lb/>of my Division, numbering over a thousand<lb/>They are mostly English - very few Irish or<lb/>even of Irish parents. I find the majority<lb/>of them very <hi rend="underline">slack</hi> as to religion: quite a<lb/>number married in regist. office, since 1908,<lb/>yet willing enough to have matters set right.<lb/>The most disheartening feature is that they <hi rend="underline">will</hi><lb/>not see the seriousness of what is before them.  There is a military hospital in the camp claim-<lb/>ing a good deal of my time. My Brigadier Gen.<lb/>is brother of the late Fr. Lassiter, C. Ss. R., whom<lb/>the Brigadier tells me your Lordship knew very well.  The B.G. has very a d Catholic tendencies <seg type="unclear">this</seg><lb/>brother, Major Lassiter, also of this Division is a<lb/>convert. I have more than the ordinary facilities<lb/>for my ministrations to the men  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2668_img_2091_2"/>
             There are two other priests in this camp, so that we <lb/>have the luxury of regular confession. <lb/>This Division was foremost on the <seg type="unclear">list</seg> of three <lb/>to go abroad, but the order has been changed, and <lb/>we have no idea when or where we are to move.   Both officers and men are very keen on going <lb/>to the Front. We have a <seg type="unclear">depot</seg> of the Flying <lb/>Corps here, and the whirring of air-cradt is <lb/>constantly over us.   I had a visit from Mgr. Count <seg type="unclear">Beckastaffe</seg>-Drew, <lb/>  Senior Chaplain: he is most interesting in <lb/>his accounts of life at the Front.   The officers of my mess are all Ch. of Eng. men, <lb/>but they are almost scrupulous in this respect <lb/>for my "R.C. Customs." Quite <hi rend="underline">on their own</hi>, they <lb/>have annulled my dispensation from abstinence, <lb/>by providing me with special and ample Lenten <lb/>fare. Neither strong drink nor strong language <lb/>is ever in evidence at meals, or indeed, as <lb/>far as I can see, at any time.   Asking Your Lordship's blessing,      Ever <seg type="unclear">faithfully</seg> yours <lb/>C. F. Maher, OFM 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>