<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5651">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 9 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie (1892-1975) joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle until being called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France. Marie later founded the Medical Missionaries of Mary.
Marie writes some news that she heard about her brother, Charlie (1895-1915), who is who is missing-in-action.  Charlie is a soldier with the Royal Dublin Fusiliers who was fighting on the  Salonika front. She has just received the news from someone who was part of his regiment.  He told her that Charlie had suffered a wound to his shoulder and in the letter to her mother, Marie expresses her concern for his welfare.  She also describes the conditions in the hospital for a V.A.D and she mentions how excited she is about going home and seeing her mother.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Malta Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5651</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-04-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1540">Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_1"  type="Letter"  url="5a360faf2575783009c0e5cd844b03b2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_2"  type="Letter"  url="9db3cc71ce64f7f76cfff57c8b667e0b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_3"  type="Letter"  url="0c9cd885ee3c61fe39535d1639619205.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_4"  type="Letter"  url="d5382988d47591e757bb8df604835133.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_5"  type="Letter"  url="bf891e055157c3c671c11d37db35fa16.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_6"  type="Letter"  url="1f7a36544d074fa6ab2d29e30943e5c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_7"  type="Letter"  url="1b4c98bfd58c90f0e49945855d22bbdd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5651_img_743_8"  type="Envelope"  url="f947ef0c4e66f726eeb23b2a40668b9c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_1"/>
             9. 4. 1916  <lb/><hi rend="underline">2.30 a.m </hi>  My dearest Mother,   A thousand thanks for your <lb/>two very nice long letters dated March <lb/>23 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> &amp; 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which I received on Friday. I would <lb/>have answered by return only I heard of <lb/> a man out of Charlies Reg: who was up <lb/>at St David's Camp &amp; I thought I <lb/> would see if he had any further news <lb/> before writing. I was not able to <lb/>go yesterday owing to a lecture in <lb/>the morning I did not get to bed till <lb/> after 10<sic>'ck</sic> so was not able to get up <lb/> early to wlak up and see him but got up <lb/> this afternoon &amp; had a long chat with <lb/> him (Pte Ferguson) who has been in P. Comp <lb/>ever since the beginning. His story is  the division sign  <lb/> On the morning of the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Charlie stood up <lb/> on the parapet to say something to the <lb/> men &amp; they all called to him to get down <lb/> &amp; keep undercover but from what I could <lb/> gather he seemed to get a little excited <lb/> &amp; they say he had a terrible responsible <lb/> position, he was wounded shortly afterward
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_2"/>
            right through the shoulder, he says he was <lb/>badly wounded &amp; unable to carry on, so <lb/>they sent him up to A Company <lb/>&amp; very shortly afterwards they all had <lb/>to retire both to C &amp; A Company &amp; Charlie <lb/>manage to get down with them about <lb/>15 miles when he &amp; 30 others were captured <lb/>by Bulgarians, they were unable to dress <lb/>Charlies wound as there was no time <lb/>but he says that is the 1st thing the <lb/>Bulgarians did when they took wounded <lb/>prisoners . I hope you will have heard <lb/>something from W.O by then if now I <lb/>suppose we must only trust in Our <lb/>Divine Lord that he is safe somewhere &amp; <lb/>being well looked after he spoke very highly <lb/>of Charlie &amp; he said the reception Charlie <lb/>got on his return after being wounded <lb/>the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> time was a great sight, he said he <lb/>never met anyone so popular &amp; thoughtful. <lb/>This man says it was disgraceful <lb/>the way they were treated never getting <lb/>any support &amp; they were absolutely left <lb/>without any artillery to support them <lb/>of course they did not know this at <lb/>the time, infact they were told when they
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_3"/>
            were retreating that the Artillery was there <lb/>supporting them but on going down they <lb/>found they had retreated a good while <lb/>before — these two <sic>companys</sic> got down. He <lb/>said when they left Charlie &amp; found all <lb/>their Officers either killed or wounded <lb/>they took their lives into their own hands <lb/>&amp; every man for himself &amp; as he says <lb/>he was very lucky &amp; every one who escaped <lb/>were lucky — He is very depressed because <lb/>he is not getting home, he had dysentery <lb/>&amp; now has to have all his teeth removed. <lb/>I shall of course send him up cigarettes <lb/>etc.   I am still on night duty as you will see <lb/>I may come off tomorrow when I will <lb/>have been on a month or perhaps if <lb/>it suits Matron I shall stay on, it <lb/>is really such a short time before I <lb/>start for home, 5 weeks &amp; we might <lb/>be in London, I shall in a way find <lb/>it very hard to leave here as I really <lb/>love the work, but at the same time <lb/>I am just longing to see you all &amp; get <lb/>home even if it is only for a short <lb/>time. I bubble over with excitement
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_4"/>
            sometimes &amp; just long to kiss you all once <lb/>again &amp; as for my little bed &amp; room <lb/>how I shall appreciate it, for the last <lb/>week I have been sleeping 3 in a <lb/>much smaller room than mine but I <lb/>hope there will be only two tomorrow. <lb/>Night duty is not so bad really especially <lb/>now as Matron has put on another <lb/>V.A.D it was horrible when Sister Travers <lb/>went off I* was the only V.A.D left <lb/>on, I used to sit down &amp; have my <lb/>meals all alone which was preferable <lb/>to having with the company, now the <lb/>two of us meet and have it together <lb/>We are just after getting a terrible <lb/>fright as we heard a terrible loud <lb/>cry for the orderly &amp; as we have <lb/>several bd heart cases &amp; one who <lb/>had had an attack about an hour <lb/>ago, we were sure something had <lb/>happened so tore round our wards <lb/>to find all sleeping &amp; none calling <lb/>so we said it must be another <lb/>block so went across to find <lb/>all sleeping &amp; then went on to G to <lb/>find it was a patient calling for
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_5"/>
            a drink this Block is about 200 yds <lb/>away so you can guess how he called — <lb/>I was <sic>delight</sic> to get Tommy's letters, he <lb/>writes in great form I hope they <lb/>will keep him there some time, I <lb/>do not know that I would not rather <lb/>have him go to France than Mesopotamia <lb/>I am glad to be able to say my <lb/>feet are better, the one days massage <lb/>did them a lot of good but unfortunately <lb/>I am unable to get the supports here &amp; <lb/> It is not worth sending them out I <lb/>would be nearly gone before they <lb/>arrived &amp; also the size is difficult <lb/>I think I shall have them massaged <lb/>when I get home for a bit if they <lb/>are not better. <lb/>Certainly the holidays are very early <lb/>this year I suppose they will <lb/>all have returned by the time I <lb/>get back — I was talking to Matron <lb/>today she is very upset when I told her <lb/>I was going home but really I do not <lb/>feel I am not playing the part as there <lb/>is really absolutely nothing to do out <lb/>here just now . The day staff are having
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_6"/>
            every second day off &amp; half on the day <lb/>they are on &amp; still there were too many <lb/>for the work there is to do. That is the <lb/>one good thing about night duty one <lb/>has a lot to do — I believe I shall <lb/>get 2 days off as I have been on a <lb/> month so shall have nice long rests. <lb/>It is beginning to get very hot out here <lb/>&amp; the flys &amp; mosquitoes are starting <lb/>again.   I hope nothing has happened to Gerald G <lb/>as I have not heard since he went <lb/>back from him. I see in the papers <lb/>there has been a fair amount of fighting <lb/>near him so perhaps he has been too <lb/>busy to write or perhaps his letter has <lb/>gone astray — I am very glad to hear <lb/>Gerald is getting on so well, it must <lb/>have been hard on him going back. <lb/>Beatrice writes in great form I read <lb/>a letter to A Lily from her yesterday. <lb/>Se seems so happy at <seg type="unclear">Hannton</seg> now <lb/>every things seems to have blown over. <lb/>I had a nice long letter from Aunt <lb/>Sissy, I so glad to hear from
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_7"/>
            her &amp; that they all are well at Clyde <lb/>Rd.     I hope this letter will reach you quickly <lb/> they always seem to take such a <lb/>time, there was a mail in today <lb/>but as yet I have got no letters, it <lb/>is very soon after the other. <lb/>I do not think I shall wire you <lb/>when we are starting as it will <lb/>only worry you but shall wire <lb/>when we arrive at Southampton <lb/>or elsewhere &amp; really we never know <lb/>till the last minute when we go <lb/> Now, I shall end this long &amp; silly <lb/>epistle. With every loving thought, good <lb/>wishes &amp; the best of luck. <lb/>I hope we will hear something about <lb/>Charlie soon.   Give Andrew &amp; Desmond my fondest <lb/>love &amp; a big kiss X X X Also take <lb/>a big one for yourself . I am so <lb/>glad to hear Violet is looking so <lb/>pretty &amp; well — she must be one of <lb/>the star turns by now . Who is the <seg type="unclear">artist</seg> on the list! With love —  Your loving &amp; grateful daughter   Marie 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5651_img_743_8"/>
             On Active Service   Mrs Martin <lb/>Greenbank <lb/>Monkstown <lb/>Co Dublin <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>