<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5301">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to the Tyrell Family, 16 December 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Jr. writes to wish his family a good Christmas. He assures them that he is very comfortable and safe. The men speak of peace often; &#34;the general idea out here seems to be that Lansdownes letter was written purposely&#34;. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5301</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-12-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Tyrrell Family</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5301_img_None_1"  url="89a7fa7b0aadd24d4a75e0d41d06073a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5301_img_None_2"  url="9fb90270d935b4dbe775d3c01ff86fa3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5301_img_None_3"  url="e2f86e6243e415045f8520bd00327463.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5301_img_None_4"  url="ad370f265aa5d030f58460293a6e4ac9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5301_img_0_1"/>
              16 Dec, 1917    My dear Everybody,   It's time now that I wrote you<lb/>a good Xmas letter as otherwise you<lb/>will probably not get it at all by Xmas.  To begin with myou may make your<lb/>mind quite easy that we are alright<lb/>as we are billleted in a nice village<lb/>miles + miles from any war and in<lb/>real civilisation. We will be here a<lb/>considerable time as we are out for a<lb/>complete rest.  I was delighted to get letters form<lb/>you and Minnie uesterday and really<lb/>you are too good about parcels. You<lb/>send everything exactly right. I am sure<lb/>those parcels will come quite alright.  I did not get any first today so I am<lb/>ahead of the batallion for billeting. I<lb/>am writing this sitting at the fire in<lb/>a nice French house in a nice quiet 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5301_img_0_2"/>
             country village with no signs whatever<lb/>of war. I have just had a good<lb/>feed of omelette bread + butter and<lb/>coffee so feel in a better writing<lb/>humour. Last night we spent in<lb/>tents and there was about <seg type="unclear">20 <hi rend="superscript">0</hi> post</seg><lb/>but I have <seg type="unclear">inumerable</seg> blankets<lb/>which I got right under and being<lb/>rather tired I slept soundly until<lb/>7am when I got up. I then came<lb/>here in a motor through a most<lb/>interesting country but absolute<lb/>desolation. I was quite close to<lb/>where I was on  July 1 1916  and<lb/>through the town where I spent the<lb/>preceding month. I passed my old<lb/>billet but could not stop as I<lb/>should have liked to do. There are people living in it now and there are numbers of stops all over the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5301_img_0_3"/>
             3  town. I should have loved to have<lb/>the day to wander round but had to<lb/>just rush along in a motor.  I had a long letter from Miss Ball<lb/>yesterday and she says she sent<lb/>me a parcel from <seg type="unclear">Fintinium</seg> + Masons.<lb/>It's awfully good of her. I am<lb/>writing to her tonight. I am tryng<lb/>to polish off all the Xmas letters now<lb/>and am hoping they wont be late.  I wish that I could be home for<lb/>Xmas but as that is impossible I<lb/>will have to make the best of things<lb/>as they are and a jolly good best<lb/>they will be too. I am sure you<lb/>will all have a real good time. It<lb/>would be lovely if you had Uncle Joe<lb/>too. I have not seen Garrett since the<lb/>day I told you about so do not know<lb/>what his movements are.  There is great peace full on at present 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5301_img_0_4"/>
             4  and the general idea out here seems to<lb/>be that Lansdowne's letter was<lb/>written purposely. It is quite<lb/>possible. It is snowing hard<lb/>tonight but We don't care if it rains<lb/>+ we donts care if it snows etc .  I am very glad Bobbie's football<lb/>is a success. It is a great thing<lb/>that he likes the game as it is the<lb/>best he could play.  Now I do not think there is a<lb/>word more news so I will just have<lb/>to wish you all a very very<lb/>happy Xmas and you may be<lb/>sure I will be thinking of you as<lb/>well as enjoying myself. I found<lb/>myself a billet with a nice little<lb/>girl in it.  With very best love<lb/>Your most affec<hi rend="underline"><lb/>Willie</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>