<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0384">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Brown to Matthew Nathan, 19 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Brown</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Robert Brown, assistant manager at the National Marginal Company in Leith, Scotland. He is writing to the Under-Secretary Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. Before the war British households tended to put butter on the table, and reserve margarine for cooking purposes. But because during the War rations for margarine were more generous than for butter, margarine worked its way out of the kitchen and into the dining room. In this letter, Brown discusses the case of Henry McCambley, who was accused of fraud, stated that he has yet to be fully compensated for his attendance of the trail. He goes on to state that he was surprised at his treatment by officials regarding the case, namely John. Moorhead (1859-1936) the Crown Solicitor for Belfast and Robert Dunlop, the District Inspector for the Commissioner of the R.I.C. Belfast. Brown encloses a letter from Moorhead which Brown claims is disrespectful.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/1385/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/384</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1431">Robert Brown</persName>
              <date>1916-01-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1243">10 Quality Street, Leith, Edinburgh</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0384_img_1644_1"  type="Letter"  url="bf9ab3c75b91bd84b9501307e67a3b39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0384_img_1644_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="d3ecf29a2eb6a7b87ac37578eb7ea790.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0384_img_1644_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="c5c6896d06670337d4f8b14327ac30bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0384_img_1644_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="2df9284f4d17a5d78dd56b8d14d9fc83.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0384_img_1644_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="de89b83c4b042dcd3db6e2ce523662bf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0384_img_1644_1"/>
                THE NATIONAL MARGARINE COMPANY  LIMITED  10 QUALITY STREET  LEITH    19th June 1916    To The Under Secretary,  The Castle,  Dublin.   Dear Sir,   With reference to my letter of 17th inst. I beg to enclose <lb/> letter together with cheque received to-day from John R Moorhead, <lb/> Crown Solicitor, Belfast.   It will be apparent to you that Mr. Moorhead has replied to my <lb/> enquiry in a most disrespectful manner and I must protest against <lb/> such treatment.   The cheque enclosed has been made out on the basis of a cert- <lb/> ificate granted without the slightest consideration being given to <lb/> 'out-of-pocket' expenses necessarily incurred to enable me to attend <lb/> the assizes.   Seeing that I mistakenly rendered my claim to Robt. Dunlop, <lb/> Commissi-oners office.R.I.C. Belfast he might have had the courtesy <lb/> to inform me that the claim had been sent to the wrong person. <lb/> I trust you will now give orders for payment of my claim,  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly, <lb/> Rob Brown </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0384_img_1644_2"/>
             <seg type="head">COUNTIES OF ANTRIM AND BELFAST</seg>   Crown Solicitors Office,  30 Rosemary Street,  Belfast   20th January 1916     <hi rend="underline">The king v McCambley</hi>   Inspector General R.I.C.  Full report please <lb/> With reference to A <lb/> in the Brown <lb/> Solicitor Report <lb/> please state how <lb/> mr. Brown traveling <lb/> expenses to the <lb/> assigns have been <lb/> dealt with <lb/> Also please attach <lb/> the papers relative <lb/> to the claim of this <lb/> witness in respect of <lb/> attendance in Belfast <lb/> petty sessions   24-1-16   Commt  Please report on the <lb/> point referred to in first <lb/> paragraph of above minute   25-1-1916     J. I. Taylor Esq.,  Chief Secretary's Office,  The Castle,  Dublin.    Dear Sir,  Relative to attached communication <lb/> from Robert Brown, Assistant Manager of <lb/> the National Margarine Co. Ltd., I beg to <lb/> report that this claimant is without <lb/> exception the most <hi rend="underline">cantankerous</hi>, <hi rend="underline">truculent</hi>, <lb/><hi rend="underline">insolent</hi> and <hi rend="underline">troublesome witness</hi> it has <lb/> been my experience to come across. He <lb/> described himself as the assistant manager <lb/> of this Margarine Company which purports <lb/> to have a number of branches in important <lb/> English and Scotch towns. So far as I <lb/> have been able to learn the only place <lb/> where the company has any  substantial  existence is <lb/> at Leith and some business appears to <lb/> have been done by them in foreign margar- <lb/> ine    The claimant makes a virtue of <lb/> assisting the Police. the boot is <lb/> really on the other leg. the Company <lb/> had an agent or Canvasser in Belfast <lb/> named McCambley whose office was apparent- <lb/> ly the only 'warehouse' they had here. <lb/> McCambley was dishonest; embezzled small <lb/> sums collected for the company amounting <lb/> to about £20, and also converted some <lb/> stock of margarine (value for a somewhat <lb/> similar amount) to his own use. The  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0384_img_1644_3"/>
              Company have really been getting the benefit of the criminal law to <lb/> collect this money from McCambley who pleaded guilty and whose <lb/> brother (a school teacher) has paid into court by way of restitution <lb/> ywo sums of £10 and £5  respectively  and is to pay a further sum of £6 before the <lb/> March Assizes.  in all £20  It will therefore be for you to consider <hi rend="underline">whether <lb/> or not a portion of this restitution should not be appropriated <lb/> towards the cost of the prosecution. </hi>   The Claimant Brown from the very start gave the police a lot of <lb/> trouble about his expenses and constantly threatened to leave. <lb/> The Police in the case warned me that I should have trouble with him <lb/> over his expenses. When I came to make out my certificate I was <lb/> informed <hi rend="underline">that all his travelling expenses had been paid by the police</hi>. <lb/> In connection with the preliminary stage of this prosecution he was <lb/> paid, in pursuance of your minute, by my cheque of the 2nd December <lb/> 1915 £2. 10. 0 for two days and three nights attending Petty Sessions. <lb/> At the Assizes I ascertained from the Police that he was detained <lb/> six days and six nights. <hi rend="underline">Four</hi> of the <hi rend="underline">days</hi> and <hi rend="underline">four of the nights</hi><lb/> were for <hi rend="underline">actual attendance at the Assize</hi> and two of the days and two <lb/> of the nights travelling to and from the Assize by rail and boat. <lb/> I considered htat he was entitled to allowance for the two days <lb/> travelling as well as for the 4 days in attendance at Assize and I <lb/> calculated these six days at 10/- per day, namely, £3. Of the six <lb/> nights, two being spent on the boat, the cost of his accomodation <lb/> was already included and paid for in the travelling expenses paid by <lb/> the police. I considered him therefore entitled only to f <hi rend="underline">our nights</hi><lb/> hotel expenses and estimated this at <hi rend="underline">6/- per night</hi>, the two figures, <lb/> £3, and £1.4.0 being accordingly the amount of my certificate. <lb/> I had some hesitation in allowing the 10/- per day; I thought it was <lb/> the limit, and I thought the 6/- per night amply sufficient.   Being warned by the Police while the witness was in attendance <lb/> at the Assizes that he was a most troublesome man and was constantly <lb/> talking about his expenses  asking for money  and threatening to leave; at the request <lb/> of the Police I went <seg type="del">down</seg> to the hall of the court and saw him and <lb/> told him that if he left he would have to take the consequences. He <lb/> was grumbling that he had no money and wanting an advance towards his  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0384_img_1644_4"/>
              <lb/> expenses. I told him I had no power to make any advance and  that  at the <lb/> close of the case I could only make up my certificate upon which the <lb/> Clerk of the Crown would issue a chegue for him for the proper amount. <lb/> I knew from his talk about his loss of time that he would be dis- <lb/> satisfied with any reasonable amount and I explained to him that I <lb/> was bound by Treasury Regulations which, if I exceeded, I was liable <lb/> to be personally surcharged and that <seg type="del">when he got his cheque</seg> if he were <lb/> dissatisfied with the amount of his cheque when he got it his only <lb/> remedy was to lodge his claim with the Under Secretary, The Castle, <lb/> Dublin, <hi rend="underline">explaining that <seg type="del">in</seg> after  my certificate was issued I should have <lb/> no further control over the matter </hi>. Notwithstanding this, on the <lb/> 8th inst. he wrote me enclosing the Clerk of the Crown's cheque <lb/> stating that he' did not know what it was for.' On the 10th inst I <lb/> replied returning him the cheque, stating that it was the Clerk of the <lb/> Crown's cheque for the witnesses expenses issued in pursuance of my <lb/> certificate, and reminding him that I had personally explained to him <lb/> that if dissatisfied with the amount his proper remedy was to make <lb/> a complaint to the Under Secretary, and also reminding him that I had <lb/> told him I was bound by Treasury Regulations. On the 12th <lb/> January he again wrote me expressing 'surprise' that the cheque was <lb/> for him and asking to be informed what the amount represented and <lb/> stating that he intended to apply to the Under Secretary as soon as <lb/> he had learned what the item or items were that I had refused to pay <lb/> for his expenses. In this letter he further states that he estimates <lb/> the 'loss of business profits' through being away from the business at <lb/> not less than £12 but that he had claimed a' modified fee' of £8.8.0 <lb/> which would leave him considerably out of pocket. I had never <lb/> seen the claim referred to but that letter showed me the futility of <lb/> attempting to satisfy him by correspondence and as he had intimated <lb/> his intention of forwarding his claim to you I decided not to discuss <lb/> the matter with him. Accordingly I merely acknowledge receipt of his <lb/> letter and returned him his cheque limiting myself to again pointing <lb/> out that if he was dissatisfied his proper course was to apply to the <lb/> Under Secretary. To my letter of the 15th (consisting of a single <lb/> sentence as above) he replied on the 17th by what I considered a  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0384_img_1644_5"/>
              truculent and insolent letter beginning with the words 'We are in <lb/> receipt of your favour of the 15th and I am surprised at your <hi rend="underline">inept <lb/> remarks </hi>'. Seeing that I had made no remarks of any kind, inept or <lb/> otherwise,but merely referred him to the Under Secretary,I considered <lb/> his letter and his lecture insolent. With it he again enclosed me <lb/> the cheque which I again returned to him by letter dated 18th inst <lb/> intimating that if he forwarded the cheque to me again I should not <lb/> take the trouble to send it back, calling his attention to the <lb/> wording of the cheque itself, and intimating that it was intended to <lb/> cover six days' allowance to a person *in poor circumstances* <lb/> 'pursuant to the Statute', and also his hotel expenses while attending <lb/> the Assize. I have never seen this man's claim for £10.10.11 <lb/> 'loss of business profits'. Apparently whatever this figure refers <lb/> to must be <hi rend="underline">not the witness's loss</hi> but the  limited <hi rend="underline">Company's loss</hi> of his <lb/> services with which I had nothing to do. I considered the <lb/> amount certified for the witness (10/- per day in addition to £1.4.0 <lb/> for the 4 nights) the full amount that this witness is entitled to <lb/> and I again direct attention to the fact that £14 by way of <lb/> restitution to this Company has been paid in since the trial by <lb/> the friends of the accused and other £5 is promised,no fraction <lb/> of which could be recovered apart from the prosecution,  so that the <lb/> Company will have more than recouped their 'loss of profits'    This witness gave both to me and the Police more trouble than <lb/> all the other witnesses at the Assizes put together.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Yours faithfully,   John R Moorheed <lb/> Crown Solicitor. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>