<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1939">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John F. Smyth to Robert Chalmers, 25 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John F. Smyth</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from a Monaghan based solicitor John F. Smyth to the under-secretary Sir Robert Chalmers (1858–1938). After the Easter Rising of 1916 Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), his chief secretary. Smyth is writhing on behalf of Miss Kate Rooney, and is asking for a response for a previous letter which included a petition from Miss Rooney for a Temporary License for her premises in Castleblayney, Monaghan. Smyth is asking for a quick reply as the answer is needed before the end of the month.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8909/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1939</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0850">John F. Smyth</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0464">Castleblayney, County Monaghan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1939_img_1388_1"  type="Letter"  url="0c80a8703a989debc7605faac19374f2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1939_img_1388_1"/>
             Castleblayney, <lb/>Co. Monaghan.   25th May, 1916.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">Re James Rooney Dead</hi>  Sir,   I shall feel obliged to you letting <lb/>me know the result of Miss Rooney's <lb/>Petition sent you on the 13th inst. The <lb/>matter is rather urgent and I would be <lb/>glad to hear from you before the end of <lb/>the week.   I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   John F. Smyth   The Under Secretary, <lb/>The Castle, <lb/>Dublin. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>