<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0481">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs. Michael McLoughlin to the War Office, 17 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs. Michael McLoughlin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from the widow of Detective Sergeant Michael McLoughlin to the Officer in Charge of the War Allowance Department seeking advice as to how she might apply for a War Allowance after the death of her son who died, not on the field of battle, but nonetheless on ‘War duty’.The letter was apparently referred by the War Office, London, to the Chief Secretary&#39;s Office, Dublin. Accompanying the letter is a letter dated 26 July 1916 advising Mrs. McLoughlin that her letter has been received by Herbert Samuel (1870-1963), British Home Secretary, and will receive his attention.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/12873</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/481</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1521">Mrs. Michael McLoughlin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1429">Foilnadrough, Kilcommon, Thurles, County Tipperary, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1030">War Office, 45 Grosvenor Road, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0481_img_1844_1"  type="Letter"  url="96c981c581cc8db0ebd6024545c4b73c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0481_img_1844_2"  type="Letter"  url="48a185536f7cf587316979ded5910d8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0481_img_1844_1"/>
                <seg type="del">Knock</seg>  Fouln<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>dough  Kilcommon, Thurles    July 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    The Officer in Charge  War Allowance Dept.,  London   Sir   I am a poor ignorant woman left <lb/>in poorer circumstances than ever by the <lb/>death of my son <hi rend="underline">Detective Sergt. A McLoughlin</hi><lb/>and I have been advised to write to you for <lb/>instructions as to how I am to apply for a <lb/>War allowance. If my son did'nt die on <lb/>the battlefield he surely died on War duty <lb/>and I'm sure the Government to whom <lb/> he gave the best of his life for years, devoted <lb/>all his abilities, and his <seg type="del">f</seg>life <lb/>in the end will not see his poor mother <lb/>suffer.  Officers like you are noted for <lb/>courtesy and I only ask, Sir, a few <lb/>words of plain directions for which I <lb/>will feel very <seg type="del">gr<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>atf</seg> grateful to you  Hoping I'm not too much trouble <seg type="closer"> <sic>Yrs V respectfly</sic>  Widow Mich<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> Mcloughlin </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0481_img_1844_2"/>
                26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July, 1916.   Dear Madam   I am desired by Mr. Samuel to acknowledge the receipt <lb/>of your letter of the 17th instant, which shall have his <lb/>attention. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully   (Sd.) ARM.   Mrs M McLoughlin,  Foilnadrough,  Kilcommon,  THURLES.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>