<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3319">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Sir Robert Chalmers, circa 22 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10586-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3319</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3319_img_2732_1"  type="Letter"  url="e30d3cc2cf4989820e149d58d3c23020.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3319_img_2732_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="55a014a9433a3605c0c0e1d8c547b6c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3319_img_2732_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="44082d94ab536cc824c866dd955727a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3319_img_2732_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="ee53803d0e49a5157b4dfc1f7f63ca43.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3319_img_2732_1"/>
             CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>10586 —  22.JUN.1916 <lb/>OFFICE   Under Secretary,   Please see Mr Magills draft reply<lb/>to Mr Whites question No.38 for tomorrow.  Mr Clary MP wrote to you on the 18th May<lb/>suggesting that a clause be inserted providing that<lb/>neither the unrepealed portions of the Whiteby Code<lb/>nor the Criminal <seg type="unclear"></seg>   code shall be applicable to cases<lb/>arising out of the rebellion. In reply to him on<lb/>the 20th item you said, as to the question of claims<lb/>for malicious compensation it is proposed to put a<lb/>clause in the Bill making this quite clear and I am<lb/>obliged to you for making the suggestion.   It is understood that many cases of the kind in<lb/>question are pending before the Recorder of Dublin.<lb/><!-- initials -->  21/6    Reply that I agree to draft reply<lb/>&amp; telegraph what A.G says<lb/>RC   21/6/16     Also<lb/>Telegraph to Mr Magill<lb/>what Clary said &amp; what I replied,<lb/>with dates. RC 22/6   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3319_img_2732_2"/>
             POST OFFICE TELEGRAPHS.<lb/>Message Received in Chief Secretary's Office.<lb/>Date 191<lb/>Handed in at the} J.C Office at Chief Secretary's Officce T.O Dublin Castle  JU 21 16  Received here at} 1.580 TS<lb/>From Magill To Brennan  CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>10586 —  22.JUN.1916 <lb/>OFFICE   Whites 38. The Home <sic>Secy</sic> has<lb/>not yet decided   to sub section<lb/>six of the draft bill. I think we<lb/>must fire a non committal<lb/>answer &amp; suggest following for<lb/>Under <sic>Secy's</sic>Consideration (begins)<lb/>'The question referred to by the Hon<lb/>Member is under Consideration in<lb/>connection with the legislation which<lb/>the Govt hope to introduce dealing<lb/>with Considerations which have arisen<lb/>out of the recent disturbances in Ireland'<lb/>(ends).  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3319_img_2732_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Urgent</hi><lb/>PARLIAMENTARY QUESTION  N.I.   <lb/>date and hour of Receipt<lb/>11am<lb/>CHIEF SECRETARY'S OFFICE T.O. DUBLIN CASTLE<lb/> JU 21 16   CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>10586 — 22 JUN 1916<lb/>OFFICE <lb/>Attorney General<lb/>For favour of your observation.<lb/>J. B.   21/6 <lb/>FROM ...... Power<lb/>TO ...... U.S.  [Table not fully transcribed. See image/table.]  Item notice for Thursday 22nd June No.38<lb/>Mr Patrick White to ask the Prime Minister<lb/>whether it is the intention of the government<lb/>to assist the passage of leglisation exempting<lb/>the Corporation of Dublin from any claims<lb/>that it may be responsible for in consequence<lb/>of injuries to property owing to the recent<lb/>Rebellious outbreak, and whether having<lb/>regard to the promise made that no legisaltion<lb/>of a contentious nature would be introduced<lb/>during the war period no assistance will be<lb/>given to any measure relieving the<lb/>corperation of any liability until all<lb/>claims are fully met from other government<lb/>sources.  <lb/> I don't quite follow this part at A, unless the suggestion if that if the Corporation<lb/>all claims of liability, before compensation has been presented by this Govt.<lb/>The latter might find to provide the required compensation which the aggrieved person <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>the <seg type="unclear"></seg> know list his sight against the   As to the first part of the question,the answer<lb/>must depend on what is the Govt. policy. I have on several occasions stated my view in writing to<lb/>the effect that? as no reason for exempting the Corporation from liability<lb/>in any area in which upon the facts,legal liability <seg type="foreign">foreign language text</seg> <!-- initials RC -->  22.6.16     
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3319_img_2732_4"/>
             <hi rend="underline">URGENT</hi><lb/>PARLIAMENTARY QUESTION  N.I.   <lb/>date and hour of Receipt<lb/>11am<lb/>CHIEF SECRETARY'S OFFICE T.O. DUBLIN CASTLE<lb/> JU 21 16   CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>10586 — 22 JUN 1916<lb/>OFFICE <lb/>FROM Power<lb/>To U.S  [Table not completely transcribed. See image/table.]  Item notice for Thursday 22nd June No.38<lb/>Mr Patrick White to ask the Prime Minister<lb/>whether it is the intention of the government<lb/>to assist the passage of leglisation exempting<lb/>the Corporation of Dublin from any claims<lb/>that it may be responsible for in consequence<lb/>of injuries to property owing to the recent<lb/>Rebellious outbreak, and whether having<lb/>regard to the promise made that no legisaltion<lb/>of a contentious nature would be introduced<lb/>during the war period no assistance will be<lb/>given to any measure relieving the<lb/>corporation of any liability until all<lb/>claims are fully met from other government<lb/>sources. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>