<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0692">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, S.C. Davidson, 27 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara. This letter describes Christmas celebrations behind the lines in 1915: mass in the morning, a football match between in the afternoon, then an &#39;excellent&#39; dinner for 30 in cafe where billeted followed by party in the mess. The highlight of the party was convincing three French maids that it was an English tradition for maids to kiss the Colonel on Christmas Day. He thanks his mother for all the parcels he has received from her and others.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/692</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-12-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">S.C. Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0692_img_2183_1"  type="Letter"  url="55b644a3fdf8caace18c9e9711836b39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0692_img_2183_2"  type="Letter"  url="e035b472d1cef294726a68b0b4dc7ba2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0692_img_2183_3"  type="Letter"  url="1729301c5a9c4ac338d6a9762b8433c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0692_img_2183_4"  type="Envelope"  url="ed0ba082262e59c0ab88776174f380e3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0692_img_2183_5"  type="Letter"  url="8cd4cd0d04c7b05ca7a450499e3216c0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0692_img_2183_1"/>
                27/12/15   My dearest Mother   Xmas has come &amp; gone <lb/> for another year 芒聙聰 I wonder how <lb/> things will be when the next one comes <lb/> round.  We spent a very cheery <lb/> Xmas indeed 芒聙聰 nothing much during <lb/> the day 芒聙聰 went to mass in the Cathedral <lb/> in morning to hear the music, in the <lb/> afternoon there was a football match <lb/> between the 13<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> &amp; 11<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> &amp; then in the <lb/> evening 30 of us sat down to a most <lb/> excellent dinner in the cafe where I am <lb/> billeted. One of the special delicacies <lb/> was snails 芒聙聰 I need scarcely say I <lb/> did not experiment but many did &amp; <lb/> quite enjoyed them.   The great feature <lb/> however of the evening came after the coffee. <lb/> A few of us before the dinner explained <lb/> to the 3 maids that the English custom <lb/> on Xmas evening was for the maids  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0692_img_2183_2"/>
              to kiss the Colonel; they took this quite <lb/> seriously &amp; so when the coffee had been <lb/> served one of them went up behind Col. <lb/> Savage, made a little speech about <lb/> following English custom which he did <lb/> not understand &amp; then much to his surprise <lb/> bent down &amp; gave him a real good <lb/> kiss. Of course everyone simply yelled <lb/> &amp; the poor old Col. did not know what <lb/> to do or say but attention was soon <lb/> drawn from him as we insisted that <lb/> everyone should be kissed in turn &amp; <lb/> all 3 maids did the round. Quite a <lb/> tall order but they seemed to enjoy it <lb/> &amp; it created great amusement as you can <lb/> imagine.   After that we had <lb/> songs &amp; speeches 芒聙聰 everyone had to do <lb/> something &amp; as I could not sing I was <lb/> let in for a speech.  Later we started <lb/> dancing &amp; the party did not break up <lb/> till about 2am so I think we did  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0692_img_2183_3"/>
              not do badly. The plum pudding which <lb/> came the day before was a great success. <lb/> I also received a Scotch Bun but it has <lb/> not so far been sampled as till today I <lb/> could not find out whether it was supposed <lb/> to be eaten cold or heated. I understand <lb/> now it is to be eaten cold but it seems <lb/> most indigestible stuff.   Have received <lb/> all kinds of parcels since I last wrote 芒聙聰 <lb/> one with pyjamas, one from K. with muffler <lb/> raisins etc. &amp; also 2 from Malcolmson's <lb/> with butter, cake etc. It was so nice <lb/> to get all these good things in time 芒聙聰 thanks <lb/> ever so much dear Mother &amp; would you <lb/> also thank Kathleen for her present &amp; letter. <lb/> I already have a muffler, but the second <lb/> one will probably be wanted later on. <lb/> Malcomson always includes a tin of caf脙漏 <lb/> au lait which I never use so it would <lb/> be better if they sent instead say a <lb/> box of dates, or sweets.   There was <lb/> a special parcel of 4 lbs of butter came  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0692_img_2183_4"/>
              in addition to the lb. in Malcolmsons <lb/> parcel so I am well supplied in this <lb/> direction &amp; it is really one of the <lb/> most acceptable things out here.   However it will be quite sufficient if <lb/> you can arrange to have one lb. sent out <lb/> each week as the Bde. Major &amp; others also <lb/> get butter sent out to them.   No news <lb/> of any move yet 芒聙聰 it will be great luck <lb/> for us if we are able to spend the worst <lb/> of the Winter in our present quarters.  We are kept very busy &amp; its simply <lb/> wonderful how the time goes. Was <lb/> so glad to hear your good news of <seg type="unclear">Hammie</seg>. <lb/> It must have been most interesting to hear <lb/> all his accounts of the fighting at Gallipoli.  With fondest love to all &amp; and best wishes for <lb/> the New Year. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  Jim </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0692_img_2183_5"/>
              On Active Service  <hi rend="underline">Sent</hi> 31st Dec 1915     Mrs. S. C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>