<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0793">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 9 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender writes of a correspondence he has recently sent and received, and refers to his brother Rex, recently arrived at the front, who is currently positioned in a dug-out. He briefly mentions a visit to the office by the King and the Prince of Wales. He recounts a visit of his own to 4th Army Headquarters, and a comment made by General Rawlinson&#39;s Chief of Staff that the records Spender is working on will make him &#39;the best hated man in the army&#39;. Spender suggests that he will be moved back to a Division before long, hopefully leaving the records with a different &#39;father&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund. This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/382</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/793</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-09T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0793_img_2334_1"  type="NULL"  url="2792020fd563e2100014d9b3be2b5551.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0793_img_2334_2"  type="NULL"  url="6355c0b7753441d4879ded98a0f625c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0793_img_2334_3"  type="NULL"  url="3a5a50d47d1d7a82f4c8f6df33a00632.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0793_img_2334_4"  type="NULL"  url="ca5ace7fbbaeeed903d05a4293e83b06.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0793_img_2334_1"/>
                9 Aug   My pr   No grumbles tho' no letter, if it means <lb/>you are taking things easier, especially after <lb/>2 fat ones yesterday. I should have felt <lb/>a little more sorry for the pr 2 days <lb/>without a letter if I had not at the <lb/>same time got an older letter with her <lb/>bag of 3 in one day. A very nice packet <lb/>from <seg type="unclear">Crowborough</seg> including a long one from <lb/>Laddie and a brave effort by Reggie, which <lb/>I suppose must go on to Rex. I think <lb/>owing to his being at a course his letters <lb/>and parcels must be delayed but he will  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0793_img_2334_2"/>
              probably be able to make better arrange— <lb/>ments when he settles down next time. <lb/>It is all very strange to him &amp; things are <lb/>difficult in a dug out.  Yesterday the King was here and the <lb/>P of W came to our office when I was out <lb/>but  he  is very likely to come in fairly often. <lb/>I am sorry Hayes is in the 38<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, which <lb/>did <hi rend="underline">not</hi> do well. Perhaps its best to leave <lb/>it at that.  I went to the 4 Army yesterday &amp; <lb/>got a most kindly welcome from Gen' <lb/>Montgomerie — Rawlinsons' M Gen' Gen Staff <lb/>and he tried to drag me into tea by <lb/>my belt; but I remained firm at my <lb/>desk compiling records which he says <lb/>will make me the most hated man in  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0793_img_2334_3"/>
              the army. However I may have got  to  a division <lb/>before long and some one else may father <lb/>my offspring.   Please file <seg type="unclear">Carnsmerry</seg> receipt <lb/>carefully or better put in cash box.  I enclose Elsie's nice letter. I <lb/>suppose all letters except the pr's <lb/>are extraneous!!   <seg type="unclear">Mag</seg>wants you at Crowboro'. <lb/>You would be kept pretty busy but it <lb/>would be a complete change. She says <lb/>you are looking pale &amp; I don't wonder. <lb/>It is better to chuck work for a week <lb/>than crock up.  I have just heard there is a  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0793_img_2334_4"/>
              morning post today! Must stop tho' <lb/>I won't promise a better scrawl later.  <seg type="closer"> Your b w  WBSpender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>