<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6639">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward W. Joyce to John J. Hearn, 5 February 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward W. Joyce</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph Cyrillus Walsh Papers. Letters: Hearn, John 1921</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6639</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0326">Edward W. Joyce</persName>
              <date>1921-02-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1205">782-786 Washington Street, Boston, Massachusetts, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John J. Hearn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0901">Westfield, Massachusetts, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6639_img_None_1"  url="phpzIImSN.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6639_img_0_1"/>
              Joyce Bros &amp; Co.<lb/>Incorporated<lb/>Clothing<lb/>For Men, Women and Children<lb/>Telephone Beach {2010 2011<lb/>782 -786 Washington Street<lb/>Boston, Mass.  2/5/21     Mr. John J. Hearn,<lb/>Westfield, Mass.    Dear Mr. Hearn:   Reverend Mr. Regan (Kervin Dorbeen) who spoke at the<lb/>meeting of the George Frisbie Hoar Branch of the A.A.R.I.R. Sunday January<lb/>30th, has informed me that you were anxious to obtain a copy of the speech<lb/>I made at that meeting with a view to publishing it in aid of the cause.<lb/>I take pleasure therefore in enclosing a copy for your perusal.  Since writing this, I have thought of a few points that<lb/>could be introduced which would make the article very much stronger:<lb/>first a fuller treatment of the principle of de facto recognition,<lb/>second, an illustration of an application of these principles, using<lb/>Mexico as an example, third, cursory reference to a number of historical<lb/>precedents, such as Henry Clay's stand on the question of recognizing<lb/>the South American republics in 1820, fourth, a paragraph giving a<lb/>condensed view of Irish history with the purpose of proving the<lb/>absolutely unquenchable spirit of independence, which is the best argument<lb/>for the continued existence of the present republic.  If you think this article will be of any use, I shall be<lb/>only too glad to make these additions, which I am certain will greatly  strengthen it and I shall be only too pleased to donate it gratis to the<lb/>cause. It happens however, that I have already sent a copy to the<lb/>publication AMERICA, but if you wish this article for use of the  Association as propaganda, I shall at once request the Editor of<lb/>AMERICA to return my copy, unless they wish to publish it knowing that<lb/>you are going to use it.  Trusting you will always consider me as at the service of<lb/>the A.A.R.I.R and with kindest personal wishes, I beg to remain.   Yours truly,    Edward W. Joyce     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>