<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3393">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Wallace to his friend Stíophán Conneely, 29 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Wallace</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A short letter from Michael Wallace to his friend Stíophán Conneely. In the letter Wallace enquires about friends and family in the Aran Islands, while passing on some details on life in the trenches. These are few though, as Wallace suggests that he would not be allowed to tell more. He also evidently prefers reminiscing about home. Wallace thanks Conneely for sending him an image of Agnes Dei and hopes that the letter reaches him before he leaves home.

Michael Wallace and Stíophán Conneely were both natives of Inis Mór, in the Aran Islands. In July 1916 Michael, a stonecutter and labourer by trade, was serving as a private in the 7th Leinster Regiment in France. Wallace was 32 when he lost his life in the battle of Guillemont, part of the Somme Campaign, on 5 September 1916. A gloss put on the letter by Conneely alludes to this. Conneely would go on to become a priest with the Redemptorists and would achieve some notoriety as he actively led a series of religious missions against póitín distilling in the west of Ireland in the early 1930s, known as &#34;the póitín missions&#34;. Conneely died in 1965, aged 72. Curiously, while both were native speakers of Irish, and while Conneely would carry out much of his religious duties through Irish, this letter is in English.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Redemptorist Provincial Archive, Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>RPAD CON/51</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3393</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0884">Michael Wallace</persName>
              <date>1916-07-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Stíophán Conneely</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0502">Inis Mór, Aran Islands</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3393_img_2805_1"  type="Letter"  url="c3162ba0931ab53eae1d2b2efdda6cf6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3393_img_2805_2"  type="Letter"  url="1ea23d4b062c589bffc7eeec4a27b69b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3393_img_2805_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">On Active Service</hi> <lb/>WITH THE BRITISH <lb/><hi rend="underline">EXPEDITIONARY FORCE</hi>  <lb/>Y.M.C.A  29=7=16   M.G.S 7th Leicester Regt <lb/>B. F. Forces <lb/><hi rend="underline">France</hi>   R. I. P Amen   Dear Stephen,   I am taking the pleasure of writing to you <lb/>these few lines. Hoping to find you in the best of health. As <lb/>I am at <sic>preasant</sic> thank God. Hoping this note will find you in the <lb/>same. Dear Stephen I have not much news to tell you. In fact <lb/>I could not tell you properly <sic>untill</sic> I go home please God. That was <lb/>a real good letter you wrote for patcheen. I laughed enough anyhow. <lb/>It was very funny. How is your Father &amp; Mother also the Brothers. <lb/>When did you hear from John or Paddy. I hope they are well also. How <lb/>is B. Hernon tell her I was asking for her. We have very fine weather <lb/>here. I hope it will continue. for the rain is very bad for the trenches <lb/>if there is any rain <sic>atall</sic> you would be up to your two eyes in buttermilk. <lb/>I had a letter from Patt about a week ago. He seems to be quite happy. <lb/>I am sure Patcheen feels <sic>quare</sic> when he has the pledge. I don't know <lb/>how long will he keep it a few weeks I suppose. I had a letter from <lb/>Mickleen he told me he had a great time when he was at home. <lb/>I hear the fishing was real good this year with the Boats. I hope <lb/>it will be as good for the Canoes. Dear Stephen I am very thankful <lb/>to you for the Picture of Agnes <sic>die</sic> you send me. It was very good. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3393_img_2805_2"/>
             of you  to think of it. I am sure the times are very dull in Aran now. Also <lb/>I am sure they are very <sic>buisy</sic> spraying the potatoes. I hope there are good <lb/>crops this year. Dear Stephen I am afraid that this letter <sic>wont</sic> reach you <lb/>before you leave home but I expect it <sic>ill</sic> be sent after you. I have written <lb/>to Patcheen a few days ago. I have seen no sight of Master Erry so far. <lb/>He might not be sent to this Division <sic>atall</sic> he might be sent to <lb/>some other one. I would like to see him now the last I saw of him <lb/>was in Eng. Dear Stephen I have not much more to say so I must <lb/>close &amp; finish with best wishes from your old friend. M Wallace.   I remain <lb/>Yours sincerely   M Wallace  <lb/>Mr Stephen Conneely  Good Bye write <sic>soone</sic> again <lb/>&amp; tell me all News <lb/>Hoping we <sic>ill</sic> all meet together next Xmas please God  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>