<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1172">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V Nolan, 29 August 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the weather and the death of a child in the refugee camp. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/31-32, IJA/CHPI/54/31-32</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1172</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-08-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1172_img_3849_1"  type="Letter"  url="e53f9d8e49e5fd3856995bdd2af876c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1172_img_3849_2"  type="Letter"  url="d0a0bcba9adee228d91c23c4d3361f80.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1172_img_3849_1"/>
                Mesopotamia    29 Aug. 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   We are just beginning to 'haloo' <lb/>in this part <sic>ofthe</sic> world, as there are signs of our being <lb/>out <sic>ofthe</sic> wood. In other words, the hot season is fairly <lb/>over. It was not nearly as bad as last year. The highest <lb/>temperature was, I believe, just about 118<hi rend="superscript">0</hi> in these parts; but <lb/>that is taken in the shade at H.Q. which is the <lb/>best shade <sic>tobe</sic>had. In tents it must have been <lb/>up to 126<hi rend="superscript">0</hi>! Last year the highest official mark was 128 <hi rend="superscript">0</hi>. <lb/>but it was 136 <hi rend="superscript">0</hi> in many hospital and camp tents. One <lb/><sic>ofour</sic> chaplains, a Father Watson C.S.S.R. died this year of <lb/>heat stroke, on the Euphrates. R.I.P. A few days ago <lb/>I was called across the river for a burial. On arrival <lb/>I found that a little Armenian child had died in the <lb/>refugee camp of starvation and exposure. It was 2 years of <lb/>age. Four Catholic Indians carried it <sic>tothe</sic> grave, and so <lb/>it got a military funeral. The grave was a great big one, <lb/>over seven feet long and about three wide, while the little <lb/>body was hardly two feet long. We are very short of <lb/>priests. Five or six are knocked out by illness, and others <lb/>are at the end <sic>oftheir</sic> contract. We would require about <lb/>a dozen or more extra to do the work really well. I have <lb/>had Irish papers up <sic>toabout</sic> 12 June, from an Irish priest at <lb/>Basra. They just get up <sic>tothe</sic> eve <sic>ofthe</sic> East Cavan election. <lb/>I hope sometime <sic>tosee</sic> the comments on the result.  An old 'Irish Catholic' has an account of F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Omahony's one <lb/>day retreat in Egypt. F<hi rend="superscript">superscript text</hi>Molony, our Senior Chaplain, is <lb/>having a kind of mission in Baghdad next week. I <lb/>hope to have one in my district when another priest <lb/>comes for the other side <sic>ofthe</sic> river. At present the most  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1172_img_3849_2"/>
              I can aim at is to prevent the out-lying parishioners <lb/>from becoming 'rustici'. I am hoping <sic>tohave</sic> a church <lb/>built here. At present the hospital is being put up, and <lb/>is nearly finished â the canteen, the open-air stage, the <lb/>tennis-courts etc are either completed or under way, but <lb/>churches are not <sic>tobe</sic> thought of until everything else is <lb/>settled. I never saw such a lot, as they are in this <lb/>country.  There was a rumour current that the mails from <lb/>England for us for the second half of June have gone <lb/><sic>tothe</sic> bottom. So if there were any suffragia at that <lb/>time it would be well <sic>tosend</sic> a second notice. I got <lb/>the notice for F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Hassett and B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Florian in Australia. <lb/>I said another Mass for an R.a.m.c. orderly, who died <lb/>suddenly here; but by giving your Reverence some <sic>ofmy</sic><lb/>own Masses and an extra Sunday Mass, I have been <lb/>able <sic>tosay</sic> 18 for your intentions during August. I shall <lb/>send F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley a separate note, but it would be well <lb/>to tell him in case the under-the-sea boats get a hit. <lb/>17 for July and 18 for August. I suppose the status <lb/>did not disrupt the Province. All I want is <sic>toget</sic>buried <lb/>away in some out <sic>ofthe</sic> world spot for the rest <sic>ofmy</sic><lb/>life. I see my Bishop's name prominently in the <lb/>papers I have. I'm proud that he should be one of <lb/>the most active in the cause.  I recommend myself <sic>tothe</sic> prayers <sic>ofall</sic>. It will <lb/>be better <sic>towrite</sic><sic>tome</sic> still c/o Archbishop's House, <lb/>Bombay. My present unit is 65 British General <lb/>Hospital. The hospital I began my chaplain career in, in <lb/>France, no.3. B.General is now in this country. I spent a <lb/>day or so as a patient in it last May on my way down to <lb/>Basra. <seg type="closer"> FrancisMShaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>