<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4299">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Thompson to Edward Carson, 18 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Thompson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Thompson (1839–1918) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Robert Thompson, MP,  was President of Ulster Flax Spinners&#39; Association and President of the Board of Governors of Campbell College, Belfast.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4299</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1549">Robert Thompson</persName>
              <date>1915-12-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0750"> Bertha House, Malone Road, Belfast, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1918</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4299_img_3661_1"  type="Letter"  url="738addca8eb3421963c85a8833575f0f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4299_img_3661_2"  type="Letter"  url="c7505ed3a6ab6408ea8bcecda727aecd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4299_img_3661_1"/>
             Bertha House <lb/>Belfast   <hi rend="underline">December 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915</hi>   My Dear Sir Edward   Yours of 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> has just <lb/>reached me coveying to me the <lb/>pleasant surprise that you had put <lb/>forward my name for one of the coming <lb/>New Year's honours, and that an Irish <lb/>Privy Councilorsh ip had been granted.   I do no know how to thank you <lb/>sufficiently for this undeserved kindness,   I am now glad I accepted un—
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4299_img_3661_2"/>
            hesitatingly your advice last summer, <lb/>on the occasion of the Lord Lieutenant's <lb/>visit at the opening of the Thompson <lb/>Graving Dock Ceremony, as this honour <lb/>quite supercedes any I could then have <lb/>anticipated, besides it comes through the <lb/>Leaders of our own Party and therefore <lb/>much more highly appreciated by me.   Kindly accept my warmest thanks for <lb/>this very great honour and <seg type="unclear">believe</seg> me   Yours very devotedly   <hi rend="underline">Robert Thompson</hi>   The Right <seg type="unclear">Honble</seg> —<lb/> Sir Edward Carson <lb/> K.C.M.P. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>