<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2463">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Isabella Gifford to Sister Francesca, Mary MacDonagh</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Isabella Gifford</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is mainly concerned with Muriel MacDonagh&#39;s situation following the death of her husband.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 33,567 /7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2463</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0478">Isabella Gifford</persName>
              <date>1916-06-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0569">8 Temple Villas, Palmerston Road, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sister Francesca, Mary MacDonagh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1989">Star of Sea Convent, Tramore, Waterford</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2463_img_190_1"  type="Letter"  url="3bfffa43bf1fa3a4d209617e4df478e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2463_img_190_2"  type="Letter"  url="29674b5f426d3f9b2bd1166f994d62f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2463_img_190_3"  type="Envelope"  url="09bde6eed75ff72914b1184b9ba2d4da.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2463_img_190_1"/>
              33 367 (7)    8 Temple Villas<lb/>Palmerstown Rd    21 June 1916    I am so<lb/>sorry your<lb/>brother is in such<lb/>a bad state. May<lb/>God save him<lb/>&amp; bring him back<lb/>to you again.    My Dear Sister Francesca,   I should have replied to your<lb/>letter before now, but I have been so busy<lb/>and upset by one thing or another that I<lb/>have no time for anything but business<lb/>letters. All the same, I am really grateful<lb/>to you for all your kindness to Muriel and<lb/>her children. I assure you, she is a very<lb/>difficult person to deal with, and I fear your<lb/>goodness is not appreciated. As to Muriel<lb/>settling down in the country, I don't think<lb/>it at all  likely  she would content herself there.  I am glad you are getting a change to<lb/>Tramore. It will do you good. I hope you<lb/>get out to the sea &amp; that you don't have to<lb/>wear that appalling dress &amp; veil, which<lb/>are enough to kill the patience of any poor<lb/>human. I'd just like to see you dressed in<lb/>a nice white dress, with a nice dainty pair<lb/>of shoes on your nice little feet. However<lb/>I suppose you prefer to mortify the flesh,<lb/>&amp; you do it with a vengeance. Now as to<lb/>Muriel's story about her box being broken<lb/>open and rifled. I think the probable<lb/>solution of the affair is what Liebert told me.<lb/>He said that she had it so tightly packed, that<lb/>he had to get into it &amp; dance on the contents<lb/>before he could lock it, and that after that<lb/>Muriel opened it again &amp; put in more 'stuff''. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2463_img_190_2"/>
             as he called it. Probably and most likely the box<lb/>burst open, of its own incapacity to contain so<lb/>much, and that if Muriel enquired at the station<lb/>at Thurles, she might get her things back.  Liebert says he did not pack the cup and<lb/>has no idea where it was put. But I hope<lb/>it will turn up all safe. The last time I saw<lb/>it was in 29 Oakley Road, when the baby was<lb/>sitting in her high chair banging this mug<lb/>on the handle of it, and I dared to suggest<lb/>to Muriel that a penny tin mug would give<lb/>the child quite as much pleasure, besides<lb/>being lighter to handle. I also suggested that<lb/>it might be advisable to put the silver mug<lb/>in a place of safety, preferably to lock it<lb/>up. But what she did I cannot say. It is<lb/>very good of your brothers to offer to help Muriel<lb/>but at present, at least she has plenty of<lb/>money, and I don't think it would be wise to<lb/>let her think she can spend it foolishly, and<lb/>then expect help elsewhere. I am saying all<lb/>this in confidence, as I know Muriel much<lb/>better than you could. I am losing dear<lb/>Liebert tomorrow. He is sailing from Liverpool<lb/>on Friday afternoon. He crosses tomorrow(Thursday)<lb/>by the 9.20 boat from North Wall, I shall be very<lb/>lonely without him. He is such a kind, loving<lb/>son, but God will keep him and we shall meet<lb/>again, if not here, in a better world, where<lb/>there is no sin, no heart-soreness, and where<lb/>we shall see the face of the Dear Saviour, who<lb/>loved us and will love us to the end. God grant<lb/>that we may all have this glorious experience.<lb/>Good bye, dear sister.  Ever your loving friend   <hi rend="underline">I.J. Gifford</hi>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2463_img_190_3"/>
             Sister Francesca <lb/>Star of Sea Convent <lb/><hi rend="underline">Tramore</hi>   <hi rend="underline">Waterford</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>