<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5209">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Rev. J O'Flynn to Cornelius Daly, 15 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J O&#39;Flynn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/8/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5209</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0701">J O&#39;Flynn</persName>
              <date>1923-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1601">Ellinwood, Kansas, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Cornelius Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5209_img_None_1"  url="d3e1af33611d5b65f571f0adfdec8049.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5209_img_None_2"  url="6efec430dc168b30e0e20aa350ea00d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5209_img_None_3"  url="acfd874a188fdd9be3c4bbfbfd2110d5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5209_img_0_1"/>
              P4118/10    Ellenwood<lb/>Kans    March 15th 1923     Dear Cousin Con.    I have just<lb/>heard of poor Charley's execution<lb/>I sincerley and with heart-felt<lb/>sorrow sympathize with you and all<lb/>the family at the loss of such<lb/>a noble son. Of all the boys who<lb/>fought against the black &amp; tans and<lb/><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear"><hi rend="underline">freak</hi></seg></hi> </hi>staters none was so dear<lb/>to me as poor Charley. I hear<lb/>about <seg type="del">them</seg> them in every letter    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5209_img_0_2"/>
             of all the many cousins I had in the<lb/>dear old <hi rend="superscript"> land </hi>there was none I loved so<lb/>much as poor Charley. I hope<lb/>Mrs Daly is keeping up alright under<lb/>such <seg type="del">trying</seg> dreadful sorrow. I hear<lb/>the priests in Ireland refuse to pray<lb/>for <seg type="del">them</seg> the murdered republicans<lb/>God help us! they don't amount to<lb/>much. Give my sympathy to all<lb/>the family, and daily I will pray<lb/>for the <seg type="del">so</seg> happy repose of Charley's<lb/>soul.  Trusting you will <seg type="del">ber</seg> bear up<lb/>alright under such drastic circumstances<lb/>and with every good wish   I remain your<lb/>Fond Cousin<lb/>Rev J O'Flynn  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5209_img_0_3"/>
             since I left home. How the three<lb/>of them were arrested by the <seg type="unclear">freak</seg><lb/>staters, but the terrible blow of<lb/>poor Charley execution was the last<lb/>I expected. A man who did the very<lb/>best from the very beginning. I hope<lb/>Tom and Bill won't be executed.  I have said 2 high masses for his<lb/>soul already, but I know that<lb/>sinless soul of his is gone to<lb/>a better land.  His  patriotism only<lb/>came second to his religion, so don't<lb/>be depressed. You gave him for a<lb/>noble cause. It's well I rember<lb/>him going to confession at Tralee every<lb/>saturday. Will you please send<lb/>me a photograph of his. One in<lb/>uniform if you have it.       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>