<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1254">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fred J. Allan to Mr Walker, 26 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fred J. Allan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Frederick James Allan (1861-1937), a member of the Irish National Aid Association, to a mister Walker. The letter refers to the printing of armlets for the Belfast branch of the fund. The association was founded after the Rising to provide relief to the dependents of those who were executed, killed in the fighting or had lost their employment. It later merged with the Irish Volunteer Dependents&#39; Fund to form the Irish National Aid and Volunteer Dependents&#39; Fund. Fred Allen was an Irish Nationalist and republican. During the Parnell era, Allan was one of the most influential and powerful men in the IRB. He later resigned from the organisation in 1912. Allan opposed the 1916 Rising, viewing it as a futile gesture, yet he would go on to be heavily involved in the politics of the Irish War of Independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Joseph Michael Stanley Collection, BMH CD/4/3/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1254</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0038">Fred J. Allan</persName>
              <date>1916-07-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0680">Electricity Supply Committee Offices, Cork Hill, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr Walker</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1254_img_444_1"  type="Letter"  url="9bd9ef98e26bfc5633d831b6a9e6f89d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1254_img_444_1"/>
              Letterhead on righthand side of page  Telephone: —<lb/> 3601, — Branch 21).<lb/> Fred J. Allan,<lb/> Secretary and <lb/> Commercial Manager.    Electricity Supply Committee,  Dublin Corporation,  Offices and Showrooms —  Cork Hill,  Dublin    26 July 1916   Dear Mr.Walker   The Belfast<lb/> National Aid Asso. want, as<lb/> quickly as possible, 6 doz armlets.<lb/> They can go through our account.<lb/> You might send word over to me<lb/><seg type="del">as</seg> (to Exchequer St) as to when <lb/> you think you can have them.  What about the Pearse<lb/> job too? <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely  Fred Allan </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>