<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0621">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Henry Gill SJ to Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ, 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry V Gill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter from Fr Henry Gill to Fr Thomas Nolan, details the opening days of the Somme offensive, the death of one of the chaplains of the division (Fr Donal O&#39; Sullivan of Killarney, Kerry, who died 5 July 1916 at the age of twenty-six) and the horror of the war.The Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Henry Gill SJ (1872-1945) was the son of H.J. Gill, head of the publishing firm, M. H. Gill &amp;amp; Son. He was educated at Clongowes Wood College and University College Dublin. He possessed an acumen for mathematics and science and studied in Louvain and under Professor J.J. Thompson, Cavendish Laboratories, Cambridge (1906 - 1908). Fr. Gill had a special interest in seismography: &#39;Experiments with Spinning Tops to illustrate earthquake reactions&#39; was the title of a lecture given by Henry Gill at the Cavendish Laboratory, 16 June 1908. It is recorded that the hardship of four years as a chaplain in WWI, had a lasting effect on him. Fr. Henry Gill SJ gained the Military Cross and the Distinguished Service Order with the 2nd Royal Irish Rifles, 3rd Div., II. Brig., B.E.F., France. Fr. Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/25/50, IE IJA/CHP1/25/50</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/621</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0012">Henry V Gill</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0244">Somme, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0621_img_2040_1"  type="Letter"  url="368cc7eb8d3671d7a0481d791571e1b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0621_img_2040_2"  type="Letter"  url="b92946913c9c22104cd2fd92f911cc66.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0621_img_2040_1"/>
                2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> R I Rifles  B.E.F. France    11/7/16   Dear F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Provincial P.C.   Just a line to say <lb/> I am still alive. We are, of course, as<lb/> always, in it. I have been wandering<lb/> about trenches and dug outs recently captured<lb/> from the Germans. I believe I may not say <lb/> how many casualties we had during the <lb/> attack, which is I suppose the first of a <lb/> series. Fr O'Sullivan, one of the Chaplains<lb/> of this Division was killed last week.<lb/> I was speaking to him a few hours before,<lb/> then we gave each other absolution.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0621_img_2040_2"/>
              He was a splendid young fellow and <lb/> will be hard to replace. This is about the <lb/> fifth attack I have been in and I feel I <lb/> know more than I want about shells of <lb/> all sizes and conditions. It is a horrible <lb/> and squalid business. Trenches full of mud <lb/> with bodies of dead Germans and British <lb/> lying unburied all along. Please God it will <lb/> end soon and that we may be able to <lb/> forget it all as quickly as possible. The <lb/> outstanding thing is real courage and <lb/> wonderful scruples of officers &amp; men in the <lb/> midst of the awful wounds and death and <lb/> squalor all round. Possibly death has lost its <lb/> terror for me <seg type="closer"> With kind regards<lb/> I remain dear Rev Father<lb/> Yours   <lb/> H.W. Gill S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>