<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5641">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William O'Brien to Augustine Birrell, 26 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William O&#39;Brien</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from William O&#39;Brien (1881-1968), president and acting secretary of the Dublin Trades Council, to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), Chief Secretary for Ireland. Birrell was appointed Chief Secretary in January 1907. In 1916 he resigned as he willingly accepted the political responsibility for the outbreak of the Rising in 1916.
The letter encloses a resolution by the trades council protesting against the lack of action taken by the government in allowing shipowners to amass huge fortune while taking advantage of the needs of the people.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3733/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5641</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1436">William O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date>1916-02-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0406">Trades Hall, Capel Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1968</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5641_img_733_1"  type="Letter"  url="0c1cb6cd6c87aa20eb90fa46a0df0408.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5641_img_733_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="6d4d9c98102dddf361e8217debc8d4a4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5641_img_733_1"/>
             Dublin United Trades Council<lb/>AND<lb/>labour league<lb/>Trades Hall Capel St.<lb/>Dublin   Feb. 26th 1916    Sir,   I am directed to forward you the <sic>inclosed</sic> resolution<lb/>dealing with the control of shipping.   Faithfully yours,       William O'Brien <lb/>Acting Secretary. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5641_img_733_2"/>
             RESOLUTION<seg type="del">X</seg>   That this Council, representing the workers of Dublin, <lb/>enters its strongest protest asgainst the inaction of the <lb/>Government in allowing the shipowners to amass huge fortunes <lb/>by exploiting the necessities of the people, and declares <lb/>that the high freightage is almost entirely responsible for <lb/>the unprecedented increaase in the cost of Food; that we demand <lb/>that the Government shall immediately take over the entire <lb/>Mercantile Marine, as the only method calculated to be effec- <lb/>tive in stopping this shameful robbery of the people, which <lb/>will continue so long as shipping remains a private monopoly. <lb/>That copies of the foregoing be forwarded to the Prime Minister, <lb/>the President of the Board of Trade, the Chief Secretary for <lb/>Ireland, Mr. J. E. Redmond, M.P., and Mr. G. J. Wardle, M.P. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>