<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4241">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 28 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/80</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4241</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-28</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4241_img_3609_1"  type="Letter"  url="c818691833802e4f82b6cfce11db6d03.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4241_img_3609_2"  type="Letter"  url="6d13a7e765aeebd7b0ca568a07bbc2c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4241_img_3609_3"  type="Letter"  url="4b68f03e94a2a4678e66bf1392e21458.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4241_img_3609_4"  type="Letter"  url="c40b99efff4988867089be4562e3dd68.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4241_img_3609_1"/>
             28.   The PR.   I think wolves turn grey &amp; gaunt in the winter, but <lb/> p rs only turn more rosey, &amp; gamble with squirrels, whilst the b w <lb/> cannot even find an ordinary r in this country. However perhaps <lb/> in the new place we may discover a delightful <sic>Contesse</sic>, &amp; then.   I am sorry you should write with a headache, do not <lb/> make a <seg type="unclear">burden</seg> of it, but simply scamper a few paw <lb/> marks over the paper &amp; shut up.    I am not altogether satisfied with your Committee <lb/> work it seems to be getting rather in to an impasse, &amp; <lb/> some of your co workers will not mind, I'm afraid. However <lb/> I've faith that you can square out something with Lady R <lb/> &amp; Mrs Barr &amp; smooth thing out. I'm rather glad you <lb/> should see a little of the <sic>relicts</sic> of the smart society way <lb/> but how absolutely nauseating all that dress flummery is. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4241_img_3609_2"/>
             I have written to Crichton   that you are paying visits <lb/> but will hope to see him when you get settled down.   There is a lot of news I want to hear from you <lb/> Our flat, your family ! migration, what Lady C <seg type="del">thinks</seg> says  <lb/> of my outburst to Sir E, your arrangements with Lady R <lb/> etc etc.    I fancy K S must be like his wife. he was running (?) <lb/> an outpost scheme of the 14 RIR when the GOC went out <lb/> &amp; watched. After 5 mins the battalion was ordered to march <lb/> home ! Gen <hi rend="superscript">C</hi> said he was not out to watch children's play.   Our new "old Art<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>" is being detrained by Richardson <lb/> who will have rather a poor time of it I fear the next <lb/> 48 hours. I wanted to relieve him, but had to be toed <lb/> off for other work.   Gen' <seg type="unclear">Brandon</seg> is not coming out. Too old I suppose! <lb/> We have rather a large division just now but I suppose our
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4241_img_3609_3"/>
             Art<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>will leave shortly.   Gen N is not at all keen about a separate Ulster <lb/> &amp; would wilingly compromise with the Nationalist party <lb/> if it meant support by the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. There is no fervour about <lb/> his faith in this respect &amp; he will want watching later <lb/> after the war. I think Sir E ought to know this. It <lb/> is not against him of course but simply that he has <lb/> quite different convictions to the stalwarts of the Covenant <lb/> &amp; believes in the possibility of agreement. He showed his <lb/> true colours when L Leitrim Ricardo &amp; I went for <lb/> him &amp; tho he changed again at that time it was <lb/> not a conversion of mind.   I'm sure old thing it was good for the Mater <lb/> to have you with her. Lately her tone has been very <lb/> much of the old age spirit &amp; a desire for peace &amp; rest. <lb/> It is so different from her old tone, but I do hope she <lb/> won't lose all her old fighting spirit, tho' there is something
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4241_img_3609_4"/>
            fine in the change too. I really think you have <lb/> been a comfort to her, tho' I expect you have not quite <lb/> escaped all criticism.   The <seg type="del">Q</seg>new Div taking over from us here ha s <lb/> been passing through &amp; have some <seg type="del">a</seg>positive bounders among <lb/> their COs. To think of England being flooded after the war <lb/> by all these Colonels !   My love to both families. You have hardly <lb/> told me a word of <seg type="unclear">2q's </seg> doings.    Greedy little animal expecting to get all the <lb/> letters to yourself. As if Mater mightn't have 1 <lb/> a week addressed to her. Oh p r ! All the same <lb/> I rather like you.   Your b w    WB Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>