<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0065">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegram from P.S. O' Hegarty to George Gavan Duffy, 18 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>P.S. O&#39;Hegarty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A telegram from P.S. O&#39;Hegarty to George Gavan Duffy advising him that Ernest Blythe is to be tried in Abingdon on Thursday for failure to report to the police and asks if Duffy can be there to represent him.Patrick Sarsfield O&#39;Hegarty (1879-1955) was an Irish writer, editor historian and a former member of the Supreme Council of the Irish Republican Brotherhood. He worked in the Postal Service at a number of locations, including Welshpool, Wales. He went on to support the Anglo-Irish Treaty of 1921. The telegram is addressed to George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951), an Irish politician, barrister and judge. Gavan Duffy unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising. The telegram makes reference to Ernest Blythe (1889-1975) an organiser for the Irish Volunteers who was arrested under the Defence of the Realm Act. He was released from prison before the Easter Rising but was rearrested during Easter week 1916. He went to serve as Finance Minister in the Cumann na nGaedheal government.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD/45/3/11/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/65</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0784">P.S. O&#39;Hegarty</persName>
              <date>1916-04-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0567">Welshpool, Wales.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1653">4 Raymond Buildings, Grays Inn, London WC, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0065_img_1133_1"  type="Letter"  url="e58a87e2e2cf04eae3e1698a50715ef3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0065_img_1133_1"/>
              Hand in at 11/aa<lb/> Office of Origin and Service Instructions Welshpool<lb/> Words 29<lb/> TO{ reply paid <lb/> Gavan Duffy<lb/>  Cane Illis Yeathley Willis  4 Raymond Buildings  Grays Inn WE.    Blythe Oxford prison being tried<lb/> Thursday Abingdo not reporting police<lb/> can you go up OHegarty  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>