<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0155">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alfred Gerald Crofton to Lady Clonbrock, 13 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alfred Gerald Crofton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Alfred Gerald Crofton (1882-1942) to his aunt, Augusta Caroline Dillon, Lady Clonbrock (1840-1928). In the letter, Crofton informs &#39;Aunt Tweety&#39; that he will be joining the Canadian army having enlisted in the Canadian Expeditionary Force and lists his reasons for doing so. The first is to &#39;serve my country&#39;. The second relates to a large debt that he has accrued on his ranch and is unable to pay. He hopes that Lady Clonbrock will cover the debt, which he will repay on his return from war, and that his wife will be able to live off the &#39;separation allowance&#39; that she will receive.Crofton had emigrated to Canada aged fifteen and was a rancher in Ganges, Saltspring Island, British Columbia. Lady Clonbrock was a prominent member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, founded to provide aid and assistance to Irish prisoners of war and the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock. Lady Clonbrock paid the debt and Crofton survived the war, remaining in Ganges until his death.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54, Ms. 35,797 (1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/155</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0824">Alfred Gerald Crofton</persName>
              <date>1915-12-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1723">Harbour House, Ganges, Saltspring Island, British Columbia, Canada</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1381">Ahascragh, County Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0155_img_1284_1"  type="Letter"  url="01da007fde1bf6628cb231a1241d5714.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0155_img_1284_2"  type="Letter"  url="839130e21a862090e142f74b8f77ca04.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0155_img_1284_3"  type="Envelope"  url="24c661aaa669c6282e06001ec38580f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0155_img_1284_4"  type="Letter"  url="6e48147389793a9742761bf257cae73a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0155_img_1284_1"/>
                Harbour House  <hi rend="underline">Ganges</hi>    <hi rend="underline">Dec 13/1915.</hi>   My Dearest Aunt Tweety.   I am writing to let you <lb/>know that I am off tomorrow to join the <lb/>Canadian Army having been sworn in <lb/>a few days before into the 88<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Regiment <lb/>C.E.F. There are two reasons for my doing <lb/>so 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> to serve <seg type="del">the</seg>my country every man <lb/>being needed &amp; 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> its a long story but I am <lb/>going to tell it all to you. I have been <lb/> unable to keep my head above water &amp; its <lb/>only with a hard struggle I <seg type="del">am</seg>have  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0155_img_1284_2"/>
              been able to keep things going at all. I have <lb/>kept it all to my self as I did not want to worry <lb/>my mother. There are certain  debts  I have accrued <lb/> which I am unable to meet at the present time <lb/>&amp; I dont want to leave the country for the war <lb/>with this hanging over my head leaving Nona <lb/>to have to face it. Norman her brother is going <lb/>to look after the place for her with half interest <lb/>but as he has his <sic>ranche</sic> &amp; wife &amp; children to <lb/>look after but he cannot resume the re- <lb/>sponsibility of this debt of $400 = <seg type="del">8</seg>£80. <lb/> I have never written <seg type="del">of</seg>or had to ask for <lb/>help since I came out here 18 yrs. And if <lb/>you can raise it for me it will be the <lb/>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> debt paid on my return from the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0155_img_1284_3"/>
              war as Nona &amp; her brother are going to <lb/>run a boarding house in Ganges in this <lb/>house &amp; hope after the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> year to be able <lb/>to make it pay. I have nearly settled all <lb/>my other debts &amp; as we had depended <lb/>on selling land to help out since the <lb/>war there has been nothing but very hard <lb/>times. With <seg type="del">my 1/2 pay</seg>1/2 my pay &amp;  her  separation allowance <lb/>for a wife &amp; six children Nona will be <lb/>have something for her to live on <seg type="del">consisting</seg><lb/>I will not most likely leave Canada for <lb/>England till the spring when I hope to <lb/>have enough leave to be able to meet <lb/>you somewhere in England or Ireland <lb/>&amp;&amp; then I will be able to tell you everything  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0155_img_1284_4"/>
              I hope it will be a happy New Year for <lb/>us all &amp; I am taking this <seg type="del">best</seg>step hoping <lb/>it all for the best. I will write you <lb/>again telling you how I like the life. <lb/>Again wishing you all a happy <lb/>Christmas <seg type="closer"> Ever Yr Affec Nephew  <hi rend="underline">Fred.</hi> <lb/>My address is :   Private A.G. Crofton.  88<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Victoria Fusiliers  C.E.F.  Willows Camp  <hi rend="underline">Victoria</hi>  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>