<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2999">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Note from Countess Constance Markievicz to Mrs Connolly, [April or May, 1916]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Constance Markievicz</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Countess Constance Markievicz (1868-1927) was a militant republican, a labour activist, a suffragist and a politician. She was an executive member of the radical women&#39;s nationalist movement Inghinidhe na hÉireann, the nationalist Boy Scouts movement Na Fianna Éireann, the Irish Neutrality League, and the revolutionary socialist movement the Citizen Army. During Easter Week of 1916, Markievicz served as second-in-command of the St. Stephen&#39;s Green Citizen Army garrison. In 1918, she became the first woman to be elected to the British parliament, and in 1919, she became the second woman in Europe to serve as a cabinet minister.

Mrs. Lillie Connolly (1870-1938) was the wife of the trade unionist, revolutionary socialist, and executed leader of the Easter Rising James Connolly (1868-1916). In this letter, Markievicz tells Mrs. Connolly that she &#34;want[s] Miss ffrench-Mullen to have Pappet&#34;, the Countess&#39;s dog.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Brother Allen Collection, Kathleen Lynn Collection, IE/AL/KL/1/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2999</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1231">Constance Markievicz</persName>
              <date>1916-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillie Connolly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Last Letters before Death</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Last Letters before Death</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2999_img_2401_1"  type="Letter"  url="037675abfbecc458b64d77ae0a709d4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2999_img_2401_2"  type="Letter"  url="1b62679c6ce9ce2990fd00cca82267ed.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2999_img_2401_1"/>
             Dear Mrs Connolly   I want Miss French <lb/>Mullen to have <lb/>Pappet   with love   <hi rend="underline">CdeM</hi> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2999_img_2401_2"/>
             Note in the handwriting of Countess <lb/>Marckievicz, written while in prison after the <lb/>Rising, in which she directs that her dog, Pappet <lb/>be given to Miss ffrench Mullen. <lb/>. . . . . . . . . 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>