<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1547">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George C. Townshend to Lady Clonbrock, 18 October 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George C. Townshend</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from George C. Townshend to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Dillon), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Lady Clonbrock was a prominent member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, founded to provide aid and assistance to Irish prisoners of war.

The writer is looking for information about two men so that his committee may be able to help them.
His committee is in the process of setting up a hostel (for ex-soldiers). He says that they can only help those who want to help themselves and that there  will be no room for &#39;inebriates or other bad cases&#39;. They will be running classes for the men and he expects that there is a lot of interest.
He awaits Lady Clonbrock&#39;s recommendations which will be &#39;carefully considered by the Committee&#39;.  
A note added to the letter (by Lady Clonbrock) indicates her intention to bring the matter before her committee meeting on the following week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/10/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1547</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1209">George C. Townshend</persName>
              <date>1916-10-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1406">County Club, Cork, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1547_img_1014_1"  type="Letter"  url="e67131900d0a6326ee70bb22ff9e6045.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1547_img_1014_2"  type="Letter"  url="c6abcece19ea7f199c946041a9b53421.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1547_img_1014_3"  type="Letter"  url="0de3d9985eb009052004af5d3b8178d3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1547_img_1014_1"/>
             AU? <lb/> Would bring <lb/> matter before <sic>Com-tee</sic> <lb/>Meeting <hi rend="underline">on Wed: Oc br 28</hi>   County Club, Cork   18/10/16   Dear Lady Clonbrook,   Yr letter addressed to <lb/>Tipperary has reached me.   If you w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> let me <lb/> have the necessary information <lb/> as to a couple <lb/> of men I hope to be <lb/>able to write you that <lb/> the Committee will <lb/> be able to help them.   We have only just
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1547_img_1014_2"/>
            succeeded in getting <lb/> hold of a reliable <lb/> ex N.C.O. and his wife to <lb/> take charge of a Hostel <lb/> we are opening &amp; which <lb/> sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be in working order <lb/> within three weeks.   You will of course <lb/> understand that we <lb/> can only help men <lb/> who are conscientiously <lb/> anxious to help <lb/> themselves, &amp; that
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1547_img_1014_3"/>
            we cannot undertake the responsibility <lb/> of inebriates or other bad cases.   The Commandant of the Depot has <lb/> given leave for the discharged men, <lb/> in whom the joint Committee interest <lb/> themselves, to avail of our classes.   The Hostel is being run on as near <lb/> military lines as is possible in the <lb/> case of men who are not under <lb/> actual military discipline, &amp; <lb/> judging the number of cases we have <lb/> anxious to avail of its advantages <lb/> the need must be great. We <lb/> will be able to help 20 or 25 <lb/> in first instance, but must make <lb/> a charge of 10/ for maintenance <lb/> owing to the heavy drain on our <lb/> limited resources. On hearing <lb/> again from you I shall have <lb/> the recommendations carefully <lb/> considered by the Committee.   Yrs faithfully,   George C. Townshend 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>