<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5302">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to Victoria Mary Tyrrell 21, December, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Tyrrell Jr. expresses gratitude for his many christmas parcels. He has received so much food he fears he will be sick stateing, &#34;you might have sent a bottle of caster oil or something that way to be taken after x-mas!&#34;. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5302</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-12-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5302_img_None_1"  url="2e289d615f156f1d59bf17860d13ca77.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5302_img_None_2"  url="32eecf1216bac5ec9d32b44c4320488e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5302_img_None_3"  url="58d2ff37cda155ed1b77c460bb4620d4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5302_img_0_1"/>
              21 Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1917   My dear Minnie  Millions of thanks to you<lb/>all for the parcels. I got a whole<lb/>ship load today. Enough to keep<lb/>me fed for a month of Sundays<lb/>and Xmasses. The exact numer<lb/>was five and one from Miss Ball<lb/>making six. The turkey is in<lb/>perfect condition and so is<lb/>everything else. Don't you imagine<lb/>I got them too soon as they will<lb/>keep for weeks in this weather<lb/>without coming to any harm.  You have no idea what a joy<lb/>those parcels are. I wish you could<lb/>have seen me open them. First of<lb/>all I walked down the street followed<lb/>by two men carrying my parcels<lb/>and letters. The stuff is at<lb/>present piled about two feet high 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5302_img_0_2"/>
             in the corner of my room awaiting<lb/>disposal when I choose to eat<lb/>Amongst the things most acceptable<lb/>are boot laces and pencil +<lb/>envelopes as I have none.  I will tell you according as I<lb/>eat things how nice they are. The<lb/>cake is in perfect condition too.<lb/>decorations and all not a bit<lb/>squashed. The peppermints I can<lb/>tell you now are awfully nice.  The clothes have also survived<lb/>and are A1. I am sure to be sick<lb/>this Xmas. You might have<lb/>sent a bottle of castor oil or<lb/>something that way to be taken<lb/>after Xmas! 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5302_img_0_3"/>
             I also got a delicious letter with<lb/>a red seal saying not to break<lb/>the seal until 25 so I just slit the letter<lb/>along the top. I simply can't tell<lb/>you how splendid everything is.  At present I am in command of C<lb/>company but don't expect that to last<lb/>long. I am goig on a Lewis Gun<lb/>course on the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> for one week. I<lb/>will be near to C. Davison and may<lb/>get over to see him. I am sure it will<lb/>be A1 down there.  You ar right in your guess about<lb/>the souvenir. It is one something<lb/>like the one  which  I paid £7 <seg type="del">fr</seg> for Bernie.  The heavy frost and snow continues<lb/>I must now say goodnight and<lb/>run off to bed.  Again a million thanks<lb/>Very best love from<lb/>Your affec brother<lb/>Willie 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>