<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0151">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edmund Loftus Wickham to Augustine Birrell, 1 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edmund Loftus Wickham</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Mr Edmund Loftus Wickham (b. 1889) to the Chief Secretary of Ireland Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Wickham writes to request a cadetship in the RIC, a position that Wickham had failed to achieve previously. Wickham lists his qualifications and referees in this application for a job in the police force.Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) served as the Chief Secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish educational system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Birrell offered his resignation on May 1.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7533/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/151</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0340">Edmund Loftus Wickham</persName>
              <date>1916-05-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1906">Lifford Cottage, County Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1564">Queens Gate, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0151_img_1275_1"  type="Letter"  url="2ddbf362e6e47ee063034803097eb283.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0151_img_1275_2"  type="Letter"  url="c68a9670402ca6e99cc798f18400c2dd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0151_img_1275_3"  type="Letter"  url="b372df1d128e3dd1d21db73047049981.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0151_img_1275_1"/>
              J.G. <lb/> Will you<lb/> answer this<lb/> please<lb/> 4/5    LIFFORD COTTAGE,  LIMERICK.    May 1916   Sir,    I was an unsuccessful candidate at the R.I.C Cadets Examination<lb/> held in Nov. 1914, failing to get through in one subject only, (History)<lb/> by 4 marks. I did well in all the other subjects especially<lb/> in those really vital to the duties and responsibilities of a Police officer.  I am, by personal contact, a competent judge of the average<lb/> Irishman's character, and have a good knowledge of most of the<lb/> Southern counties of Ireland, being associated with them more or<lb/> less, through my business as assistant Land Agent  (for past 7 or 8 years)  to Mr. Ernest<lb/> Brown <seg type="unclear">J.P.,</seg> of <seg type="unclear">Clarboy,</seg> O'Brien's Bridge, Co. Clare, who has offices at<lb/> 5 Glentworth St., Limerick.  I am desirous, if possible, now of assisting the government in the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0151_img_1275_2"/>
              present deplorable circumstances, &amp; will be glad, therefore, if<lb/> You could see your way to appoint me to a Cadetship in the<lb/> R.I.C. I have the qualifications, &amp; a good experience already,<lb/> &amp; would I am sure make a competent Police Officer. I would<lb/> for reference refer you to the following gentlemen, Mr Ernest Brown J.P.,<lb/> address as before stated, Mr. Thos. D Atkinson D.L., of Glenwilliam Castle, <lb/> Ballingarry, Co. Limerick, &amp; the Rev R.H Temple <seg type="unclear">m.a.</seg> ( Presbyterian Minister) 80 George St, Limerick. If the papers in connection with<lb/> my nomination are referred to letters from the latter two gentlemen<lb/> will be found.  My father is retired Telegraph Superintendent G.P.O, here and<lb/> two of my uncles ( Arthur &amp; William Wickham) are retired army<lb/> officers, while my only brother William is in the Army (royal  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0151_img_1275_3"/>
              Fusiliers, Public Schools Corps). <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir,<lb/> Your obedient Servant,  <hi rend="underline">Edmund L. Wickham</hi> <lb/> To<lb/>  Rt. Hon. A. Birrell <seg type="unclear">QC MS.,</seg>, Chief Secretary of Ireland  Irish Office  Queens Gate  London  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>