<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2010">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to William Field, 19 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Andrew Philip Magill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941) the Private Secretary for the Chief Crown Secretary of Ireland, Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) to the M.P. William Field (June 1843 – 29 April 1935). In the letter Magill informs Field that Birrell acknowledged his previous letter. The Under-Secretary, Sir Matthew Nathan, has written a number of comments on the letter in reference to the subject of Field&#39;s correspondence regarding a raid on the office of the Gaelic Press, a complaint by Field about a member of parliament and the case of two boys who had been arrested.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7801/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2010</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date>1916-04-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0260">William Field</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0141">16 Booterstown Avenue, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2010_img_1456_1"  type="Letter"  url="7e09a2c09bdea67916e7ca64765b4e07.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2010_img_1456_1"/>
             18th April, 1916.   Dear Mr. Field,   I am directed by Mr. Birrell to acknowledge the <lb/> receipt of your letter of the 14th instant, and <lb/> enclosures, which will have attention.   Yours faithfully,   (Sd.) A.P.M.   U.S.<lb/> <lb/> Mr Field mixes up 3 things <lb/> I. As to the Gaelic Press — I don't think we need <lb/> take any notice of this. <lb/> II. Kenny's advertising agency. This letter to Mr. <lb/> Field is marked 'private' &amp; it is just as well. I <lb/> <sic>wd.</sic> be inclined to say that this was a matter for the <lb/> <seg type="unclear">A.</seg>G. &amp; that in any event the C.S. must decline to <lb/> take any notice of a letter making <lb/> a wholly unwarranted attack on a <lb/> prominent official in whom the C.S. <lb/> has the greatest confidence <lb/> III. The Mulligans. This is probably an <lb/> industrial school case. We are replying to a <lb/> general question on the subject of children sent to <lb/> Indus. Schools but it might be well to send a <seg type="unclear">reply re the Mulligans</seg> <lb/> <hi rend="underline">A.P.M</hi>.   William Field, Esq., M.P., <lb/>16, Booterstown Avenue, <lb/>DUBLIN. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>