<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0453">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert W. Hawkins to the Home Secretary for Ireland, Dublin, 5 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert W. Hawkins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Herbert W. Hawkins (living in London), a keen philatelist (stamp collector), writing to the Chief Secretary&#39;s Office to obtain &#39;Rebel postage stamps&#39; before they are destroyed. These stamps (or more properly labels) and their use were not sanctioned by the Post Office.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7426/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/453</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1494">Herbert W. Hawkins</persName>
              <date>1916-05-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0518">Vigo Street, London, W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Chief Secretary for Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0453_img_1797_1"  type="Letter"  url="84e523c26e7fc6a1d3ad6e44219760ab.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0453_img_1797_1"/>
                4 Vigo Street,  London W.    5.5.16.'   Dear Sir,   It is as a philatelist that I <lb/> beg humbly to approach you.  Before all the Rebel postage <lb/>stamps are destroyed by the British <lb/>Authorities may I ask that you <lb/>will be so very considerate and <lb/>send just a set (in blocks of 4 <seg type="unclear">greatly</seg><lb/>preferred) if this can be spared and <lb/>dispatched to me entirely of your <lb/>own convenience  Very best thanks in anticipation <lb/>Believe me, dear sir, <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  Herbert W Hawkins   The Rt: Hon:  The Home Secretary  for Ireland,  Dublin  </seg> Inform that the Irish <lb/>Govt. have no such stamps.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>