<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4100">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Carey to  John Langford, 30 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Carey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Carey to John Langford regarding an offal contract with a local victualler, John Hurley. Enclosed with the letter is a copy of a letter sent to Margaret Hurley regarding a bond for the contract. 

Patrick Carey (1853-1934) was the Union Clerk for the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians. Poor law unions and their workhouses were established by the Poor Law (Ireland) Act, 1838, as a response to widespread poverty, and were each governed by a Board of Guardians. This letter comes from the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians Minute Book.

John Langford (1863-1930) served as the Killarney Workhouse master from 1899 to 1922. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians BG104/B/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4100</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1557">Patrick Carey</persName>
              <date>1915-11-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1721">Killarney, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Langford</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1721">Killarney, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4100_img_3478_1"  type="Letter"  url="de0a201dd74b857fbf90d3a8217dfd7f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4100_img_3478_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="dd32411ef80471ac2e67214d3241eb44.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4100_img_3478_1"/>
             30th Novr.1915,  Re: Contract for Offal. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Contractor :Timy Hurley, deceased.</hi>  Dear Sir,   I enclose copy letter which I have today <lb/>addressed to Mr John Hurley, Surety for Contractor.   Yours faithfully,   Clerk of Council   J. Langford Esq, <lb/>Master Workhouse, <lb/>Killarney. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4100_img_3478_2"/>
             30th Novr. 1915  <lb/>Contract for Offal to 30th Sept 1915, <lb/>Tender accepted 28th Augt. 1915 <lb/><hi rend="underline">Rate: 6/3 per week.</hi>  Dear Madam,   You have not perfected bond for above <lb/>although repeatedly asked to do so. As this bond <lb/>will be required at the Audit of the Accounts I shall <lb/>thank you if you attend here with your sureties <lb/>tomorrow to sign it,   Yours faithfully,   Clerk of <seg type="del">Council</seg> Union,   Mrs Margt Hurley, <lb/>High St, <lb/>Killarney, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>