<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0850">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Nally to WB Yeats, 9 January 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Nally</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Thomas Nally (1869-1932) to W.B. Yeats (1865-1939). The letter concerns Nally&#39;s decision to change the names of some of the characters in his play &#39;Spancel of Death&#39;.Thomas Nally was an Irish playwright and colleague of WB Yeats. His work, the Spancel of Death, was due to open on Easter Tuesday 1916, the play was cancelled due to the Easter Rising. William Butler Yeats was an Irish poet and a central figure in the Gaelic Revival, the Irish National Theatre Society and Patron of the Abbey theatre. Yeats had famously written that &#39;Romantic Ireland is dead and gone, its with O&#39;Leary in the grave.&#39; The events of Easter 1916 challenged his views and brought his attentions back to Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Thomas Nally Papers, 213/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/850</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1110">Thomas Nally</persName>
              <date>1916-01-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1604">Sandymount, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0850_img_241_1"  type="Letter"  url="cd6602bda7fd93e0475b6fcc2e061fb8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0850_img_241_2"  type="Letter"  url="2e7a9f4950ceb984a96a15424a0aaf19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0850_img_241_3"  type="Letter"  url="e27076a456de3cd8fda509f89f997d3d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0850_img_241_1"/>
                Gilford Lodge  Gilford Road  Sandymount  Dublin    <hi rend="underline">9.1.16</hi>   Dear Mr. Yeates   Mr. St. John Ervine tells me<lb/> you have suggested changing the<lb/> names of the characters in 'The<lb/> 'Spancel of Death' lest their retention<lb/> might cause pain, or give offence,<lb/> to any living descendants of the<lb/> persons dealt with.  Needless to say I should be exceedingly  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0850_img_241_2"/>
              Sorry to give offence to any one, and<lb/> therefore before writing those names I fully<lb/> considered such a possibility, there<lb/> was — up to about five weeks ago — just <lb/> one person living who might possibly <lb/> feel agrieved. — Miss Lynch—Blosse,<lb/> an old lady of 94 years, who was a<lb/> great grand niece of Sir Harry Lynch—<lb/> Blosse. But she died at Monkstown<lb/> about five or six weeks ago, and there<lb/> is no one else left. As for Sibella<lb/> Cottle, all the remains of her is merely<lb/> a memory. She was not a native<lb/> in the district. Neither was she a<lb/> peasant. There remains then but the<cb/><lb/> name of the old peasant sorceress<lb/> Judy Holian. and whilst there<lb/> are still some peasant descendants<lb/> of remote kinship to her they most<lb/> certainly would not claim the<lb/> connection.  Beyond all this, <seg type="del">all</seg> the names<lb/> mentioned by me are given in<lb/> Archdeacon's book, published some<lb/> sixty years ago, and subscribed for<lb/> at the time by the then existing<lb/> Lynch Blosses, Moores. Blakes and<lb/> others whose names happen to<lb/> occur in 'The Spancel of Death'   <sic>The</sic> rather gloried in the notoriety   You may possibly remember<lb/> also that Mrs Tynan Hinksom  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0850_img_241_3"/>
              at that time — K.Tynan — published a<lb/> story dealing with the same<lb/> incidents and giving the correct<lb/> names. I happened to tell her the<lb/> story once at Whitehall and she<lb/> subsequently published it in some<lb/> local journal. I remember she<lb/> did not change the names. So I <lb/> really do not think it necessary.  Of course, if you still think otherwise<lb/> I shall, <hi rend="underline">but with regret</hi>, part with<lb/> the names; for they are dear to me.   You might please let me know as<lb/> the play has not yet been put into<lb/> rehearsal. <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely  T.H. <hi rend="underline">Nally</hi>. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>