<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1304">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ella Young to Alice Stopford Green, 6 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ella Young</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Ella Young (1867–1956) to Alice Stopford Green (1847-1929). In this letter, written on 6 August 1916, Young reports on the collection of signatures for the reprieve of Roger Casement, who was hanged for treason on 3 August, as well as the local reaction to his death.Young was a poet, republican, and mystic actively involved in the Celtic Revival. Alice Stopford Green was an Irish historian and nationalist. While not a supporter of armed rebellion, her house provided a space for leading nationalists to meet. Stopford Green had collaborated with Roger Casement on Congo Reform and, after the Easter Rising in 1916, she tried to save him from execution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, List no. A15, Ms. 13,088 /9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1304</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0825">Ella Young</persName>
              <date>1916-08-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0618">The O&#39;Curry College, Carrigaholt, County Clare</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1304_img_522_1"  type="Letter"  url="fc5a8c415d171a6fb5b4210d089f9ab0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1304_img_522_2"  type="Letter"  url="9fef7d5373e6502f66a5bb3438ea8939.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1304_img_522_3"  type="Letter"  url="fc893cd68ef7dc58dafdb2ac96cf2cc8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1304_img_522_4"  type="Letter"  url="4224c4c6feeec48477e2191285ac0c3e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1304_img_522_1"/>
                The O' Curry College  Carrigaholt  Co. Clare    6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> August, 1916.   Dear Mrs. Green,   Colonel Moore has asked <lb/> me to give you particulars of the <lb/> petitions which a group of people <lb/> working from this College originated. <lb/> I am enclosing a list but <lb/> think that it does not represent <lb/> the total sent in, as in each <lb/> case the people to whom forms <lb/> were sent were asked to enlist <lb/> their friends in these districts <lb/> and some of them did so. <lb/> Mr. Claud Chevasse wrote out a <lb/> form of petition in Gaelic which <lb/> he sent to some friends in <lb/> Gaelic districts. I think it highly <lb/> probable that in each place these <lb/> petitions were signed &amp; forwarded, <lb/> but only in two instances did <lb/> the people concerned write to <lb/> say they had forwarded the <lb/> petitions. Mr. Claud Chevasse  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1304_img_522_2"/>
              <lb/>has left the college, but if you <lb/> write to him at Temple HIll Terenure <lb/> Dublin, he may be able to procure <lb/> definite information as to the work <lb/> done in each place. <seg type="del">Mr L. Mac</seg>  Mr. L. Mac Eochadda got many copies <lb/> typed and procured nine petitions <lb/> through friends in various places. <lb/> He thinks that more than nine <lb/> were sent in &amp; I have asked <lb/> him to provide particulars as <lb/> to these &amp; let you know.  Among those who worked very <lb/> hard were Mr. Francis Ormsby, <lb/> Ranelagh Schools Althlone &amp; <lb/> Miss Mac Mahon of this College. <lb/> He instructed the people in each <lb/> case to send the petitions directly <lb/> to Mr Asquith so cannot estimate <lb/> the number of names signed. <lb/> I heard that a great number of <lb/> names were attached to the Galway <lb/>&amp; <seg type="unclear">Carlow</seg> petitions &amp; Father <lb/> Creghan of <seg type="unclear">Grange</seg> told me <lb/> he had got all the best <lb/> names in Sligo. The <lb/> Carrigaholt petition has <lb/> I think between 70 &amp; 100 names  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1304_img_522_3"/>
              <lb/>was signed by all the local people <lb/> of importance.  We were greatly hampered <lb/> in our work by the shortness of time <lb/> &amp; by the fact that all news reached <lb/> us a day late. We had only two <lb/> typewriters and Miss Nellie O'Brien <lb/>&amp; Miss Noreen Fox had to work <lb/> very hard. There is not a district <lb/> in Ireland that would not have sent <lb/> petitions. These people only needed <lb/> to be told what to do &amp; where <lb/> to send the petitions, but I am <lb/> afraid many districts did not <lb/> even know till too late that <lb/> petitions could be sent. Letters <lb/> on the subject were not allowed <lb/> in the <seg type="unclear">Dublin</seg> papers till near <lb/> the end. We got as many letters <lb/> as possible into local papers <lb/> but many of them are only published weekly.  Mass was said on <lb/><seg type="del">Thursday</seg> Wednesday for the life <lb/> of Mr. Roger Casement &amp; you  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1304_img_522_4"/>
              <lb/>on Friday. We would have had Mass on <lb/> Thursday but did not know the <lb/> reprieve had been refused. News only <lb/> reached us in answer to wire in <lb/> the afternoon. Everyone here was <lb/> filled with rage &amp; grief &amp; we <lb/> all hope that means will be <lb/> taken to let people all over <lb/> the world &amp; especially in <lb/> America know the brutal <lb/> details of this latest example <lb/> of English rule in Ireland.  Nothing could illustrate better <lb/> than the fate of Sir Roger Casements <lb/> and Sir âPyle. Mr. Pyle was a <lb/> fishmonger who grew rich enough <lb/> to get himself voted into the Lord <lb/> Mayorship of Dublin as a <lb/> strong nationalist. At the right <lb/> moment when Queen Victoria paid <lb/> a visit to this country he <lb/> turned traitor to his party and <lb/> was made a baronet as a reward <lb/> for proposing the address of welcome<lb/> Note running up the side of the page: <lb/> Miss M. O' Farrelly the Irish College Gortahork Co. Donegal <lb/> could give you particulars of those sent from Donegal. <lb/> I know too that petitions were forwarded from<lb/> Very illegible text continued along top of page <lb/>section. <lb/> We have <lb/> not <lb/> particularly. <lb/>perhaps <lb/>Miss Helen <lb/>Ui Neill <lb/>would tell you. <seg type="closer"> Sincerely yours  Ella Young </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>