<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5759">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Patterson to the Home Office, 14 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Patterson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by William Patterson (b.1877), a dentist from Londonderry. The letter is concerned with the alleged death and criminal activities of Patrick Campbell (c.1873-1915), a housing agent from Londonderry.
The letter alleges that Patrick Campbell was involved in criminal activities in connection with fraud and Derry building societies. Patterson mentions that due to circumstances following Campbell&#39;s death only one person saw his body and he therefore wants proof that Campbell is actually dead.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/4011</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5759</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1478">William Patterson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2064">16 Great James&#39; Street, Londonderry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0034">Home Office</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5759_img_859_1"  type="Letter"  url="0d2e3dd7237b7b149dd453435af6f0fb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5759_img_859_2"  type="Letter"  url="b093de6f57eedc856b6084730792455c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5759_img_859_3"  type="Letter"  url="68f6c838a47067ed6c9bba93e0dcb1f7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5759_img_859_1"/>
             16, Great James' Street, <lb/>Londenderry,   Feby. 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   W<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">M</hi></hi> Patterson wishes <lb/>to bring before the <lb/>notice of the Home Office <lb/>a few particulars of <lb/>the alleged death <seg type="del">of</seg> <lb/>and reports in circulation <lb/>concerning <seg type="del">the</seg> a man <lb/>called Patrick Campbell <lb/>House agent Londonderry   This man formed <lb/>several Building Societies <lb/>and with the funds of one
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5759_img_859_2"/>
            called the New Century <lb/>he misused in some <lb/>way, and from reports <lb/>his position had become <lb/>most critical even under <lb/>threat of Writs it is <lb/>alleged ( I understand there <lb/>is some thousands of pounds <lb/>involved)   Now what is causing <lb/>much private comment <lb/>is the fact that this <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Campbell very <lb/>suddenly takes ill, is <lb/>nursed, medically attended, <lb/>dies, and is buried <lb/>I believe in something <lb/>like a week   some reports to have it <lb/>that owing to the corpse <lb/>having turned <hi rend="underline">black</hi> no <lb/>one was allowed to see his <lb/>face   Though the man was <lb/>prominent in some ways <lb/>yet it is beyond a doubt <lb/>he has been a rogue <lb/>of the first water <lb/>and nothing should be <lb/>left to doubt that <lb/>there was something more <lb/>than a coffin buried <lb/>Such men must be <lb/>treated as <hi rend="underline">worst</hi> class <lb/>of criminals because
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5759_img_859_3"/>
            a criminal (in the sense) <lb/>only generally injures one person <lb/>or two, but Criminals of <lb/>this sort injure hundreds <lb/>and generally <hi rend="underline">escape free.</hi>   This is the second building <lb/>society Fraud in Derry <lb/>recently the other man did not <lb/>manage to die, he cleared <lb/>out of the country and the <lb/>law has never tryed to <lb/>bring him to justice   I am interested in the <lb/>New Century society to the <lb/>extent of £200 and would <lb/>be easy in mind to know <lb/>that a second fraud has not been managed. Certificates <lb/>will not satisfy the people .  Why are such men not classed <lb/>as criminals and followed to the ends <lb/>of the earth   WP 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>