<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0643">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Helen Duffin to Celia Duffin, 16 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Helen</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Helen Duffin (b.1891) to Celia Duffin (1883-1979). Helen provides news from home about the coming and going of various people. She seems particularly impressed by the rank of a number of officers.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA. Celia Duffin was a VAD with the 3rd London General Hospital in Wandsworth which opened in 1914. She was an accomplished poet, publishing, amongst other volumes, a book of poetry with her sister Ruth.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/29</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/643</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0878">Helen</persName>
              <date>1916-03-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1592">3rd London General, London SW, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0643_img_2114_1"  type="Letter"  url="32d6b81c3e7399716e095ec1395dd7f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0643_img_2114_2"  type="Letter"  url="7cd4f014a9204c12df6d35bcace6154d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0643_img_2114_3"  type="Letter"  url="d262b9d5f36015342c7f004d84d5e11d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0643_img_2114_4"  type="Letter"  url="9641411fa1bc87ced41ff6b0826287ca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0643_img_2114_1"/>
                Dunowen, Belfast    16/3/16   My dear Celia,   Thank you very much for<lb/> sending the gazettes they are quite amusing.<lb/> How do you like nursing the Editor?   I am glad you saw Olive and had<lb/> a day off. Dorothy is by way of going<lb/> to England to-morrow. She meant<lb/> to go to the Swannicks first, but<lb/> Hilda has been near some case of<lb/> German measles &amp; is afraid she may<lb/> take it so D. plans now to go to<lb/> Epsom if Aunt Fanny can have<lb/> her. I suppose you will see her soon.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0643_img_2114_2"/>
              I wish to goodness Olive could get<lb/> another job I think her present one<lb/> is a dreadful life.  Dorothy &amp; I went for a walk with<lb/> Marjorie on Tuesday — poor dear — it is<lb/> a pity to see her. She evidently can<lb/> make no plans &amp; does not know what<lb/> to do with herself. Charley has got<lb/> a job at home or rather he is<lb/> doing a course in England before<lb/> taking command of his battery. I hope<lb/> Marjorie may join him until he<lb/> goes back again.  Did you hear that Elsie <seg type="unclear">Kingan</seg>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0643_img_2114_3"/>
                 Dunowen, Belfast    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0643_img_2114_4"/>
              turned up for tea here yesterday. Molly<lb/> &amp; I are helping at a buffet for <lb/> Mrs Campbell. We have to go to the<lb/> Midland Station once a month &amp;<lb/> give buns, coffee, etc. to soldiers.<lb/> Peters' &amp; Molly's photographs are <lb/> to come to-night — I'll send you <lb/> one if they are good.  Don't forget your shamrocks<lb/> to-morrow! <seg type="closer"> Ever yours  <hi rend="underline">Helen</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>