<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0360">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Irish Prisoners, Frongoch to Alfred Byrne, MP, 13 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Michael Staines, on the behalf of Irish prisoners in Frongoch, to Alfred Byrne. The letter lists a number of books in the Irish language, including a copy of the New Testament, which have been sent to prisoners but which haven&#39;t been given to them. It would appear that the books are held up by the censor and the writer suggests that there should be a censor with a good knowledge of Irish.Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; due to the influential effect it had on its inmates.The letter was signed by Michael Staines (1885 - 1955). Staines was a member of the Irish Republican Brotherhood and served as Quartermaster in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was elected Head Leader by his peers.The letter was addressed to Alfred Byrne (1882-1956). Byrne served as a member of parliament in the British House of Commons at the time of the Easter Rising. He would later serve as a TD in Dáil Éireann.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD45/4/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/360</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0137">Frongoch Internment Camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1405">Alfred Byrne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1638">House of Commons, Westminster, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0360_img_1598_1"  type="Letter"  url="143a798f1784cffa8ee98a75c5b34a8d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0360_img_1598_2"  type="Letter"  url="196a57db3be5449a8a4ca055b4c00302.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0360_img_1598_1"/>
                Irish Prisoners, Internment Camp,  Frongoch,    13th Oct. 1916.    Alfred Byrne, MP  House of Commons,    I enclose herewith a list of various Irish books which have<lb/> been forwarded to the prisoners here and never received by them:-  <hi rend="underline">History of Ireland.</hi> by Geo.Keating, Forwarded by, P.J Flinn<lb/> Esq. Alexander Park, Manchester, to:-192<lb/> J.O'Hanlon on 2nd July.<lb/> Forwarded to:-1668 Owen O'Brien<lb/> in July.  <hi rend="underline">One Irish Grammar</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">Three Irish Text Books</hi><lb/> Forwarded to:- 1784 Thomas McGrave.  <hi rend="underline">Aesops Fables</hi> (in Irish) Forwarded by Miss O'Connell Main St..<lb/> Charciveen<lb/>  <hi rend="underline">Irish Books</hi> (various) ) Forwarded by:- Miss O'Connell, Dominican<lb/> Convent Dublin to:- 1379 Mortimor<lb/> O'Connell in September.  <hi rend="underline">Two Irish Books.</hi> Forwarded from Belfast to:-1120 Martin Gleeson<lb/> on 29th Sep. (these belonged to a parcel of<lb/> six, five of which were delivered.)<lb/> Forwarded to:- 1320 M.Collins on 6th Oct  <hi rend="underline">'Notes of an Irish Exiles'.</hi> Forwarded by J.J.King Esq.45 St<lb/> Patrick's Road, Drumcondra, Dublin<lb/> to:- 362 W.J.Brennan Whitmore on<lb/> 7.9.16.  <hi rend="underline">* New Testament</hi> (in Irish) ('An Tioma Nua') Taken from Brian O'Higgins on his<lb/>arrival here on 10th July, and sent to<lb/> London for censoring. Never returned. I should feel very much<lb/> obliged if you could see your way to make inquiries into the<lb/> cause of the non-delivery of these books, as, of course, great  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0360_img_1598_2"/>
              inconvenience and annoyance have been given to the various<lb/> addresses all of whom are earnest and dilligent celtic students.<lb/> It is strange that with so many Irish scholars here, and such a<lb/> quantity of Irish literature being forwarded to them that a<lb/> censor with efficient knowledge of Irish should not have been<lb/> appointed to the camp. <seg type="closer"> Thanking you in anticipation,<lb/> I am, etc.,  M. Staines  Head Camp Leader.   7, 1916,  </seg><seg type="postscript"> <hi rend="underline">*P.S.</hi>I desire to draw your earnest and early attention<lb/> to the <hi rend="underline">enclosed</hi> cutting taken from ________. This<lb/> explanation of the non return of Brian O'Higgins copy of the<lb/> 'New Testament' (in Irish) discloses a scandalous state of<lb/> affairs connected with the censoring of the private property<lb/> of the Irish prisoners. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>