<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0686">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 1 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary. In this short and rushed letter, James sends his fondest love and wishes to his mother and family as his company makes arrangements to move back to action in the trenches. Unlike the conditions and fighting he has already experienced in previous locations, he notes that the trenches his company will now be posted to are located at a very bad part of the front line.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/686</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0686_img_2178_1"  type="Letter"  url="d06951b35b173f7f30e5d7191bbf855f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0686_img_2178_2"  type="Letter"  url="43c0877c5e45d9b8e06432166003ec66.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0686_img_2178_3"  type="Letter"  url="e9c09cb54d18e33f6c8bc568dbb6d159.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0686_img_2178_4"  type="Letter"  url="8262ad169763ecd6d5406fe984d7f38d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0686_img_2178_5"  type="Envelope"  url="b1b8056fd0f29b2c83584b5d8326499d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0686_img_2178_1"/>
                1/2/16   My dearest Mother —    We <lb/> start for the trenches to- <lb/>morrow so I am sure <lb/> you will excuse a <lb/> very wee line as you <lb/> can understand what <lb/> a lot I have to attend <lb/> to.   It was bad enough <lb/> trying to get my Coy <lb/> organised &amp; into running <lb/> order but now on the <lb/> top of it all this comes <lb/> the order to move &amp; with <lb/> it of course all the extra <lb/> preparations. I simply  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0686_img_2178_2"/>
              <lb/>don't know what way <lb/> to turn but everyone <lb/> is working hard &amp; <lb/> so things are gradually <lb/> getting straightened <lb/> out.   You need <lb/> not be anxious if <lb/> you don't hear from  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0686_img_2178_3"/>
              <lb/>me for a week or more <lb/> as there will be little time <lb/> for writing until we have <lb/> actually taken over &amp; <lb/> as it were settled down.  Please thank K. for her <lb/> letter — was so glad <lb/> to hear that she is able <lb/> to be out of doors a little. <lb/> What bad luck about <lb/> poor wee Binkie, I fear <lb/> there is not much chance <lb/> of him recovering from <lb/> such a bad accident.   The parcels all arrive <lb/> safely &amp; regularly &amp; I <lb/> have no alterations to  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0686_img_2178_4"/>
              <lb/>suggest meantime in <lb/> the contents.   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0686_img_2178_5"/>
              <lb/>On Active Service <lb/>RCd 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb 16   Mrs S. C. Davidson  Seaport  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland  <lb/> J Davidson   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>