<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5593">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Desmond FitzGerald to Mabel FitzGerald, 8 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Desmond FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGErald (1888-1947) to his wife Mabel Fitzgerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958) from Mountjoy prison.
Desmond FitzGerald had served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Mountjoy, Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.
This long letter refers to personal and family matters, news and events and contains instructions and information for Mabel.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Desmond FitzGerald Papers, P80/1540/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5593</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0538">Desmond FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-02-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0259">H. M. Prison, Mountjoy, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_1"  type="Letter"  url="21b1d4cd1e667ad7396fb5f303ded96b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_2"  type="Letter"  url="01eb6a2cd052cfaec5c1d641cb5f503b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_3"  type="Letter"  url="ba311f68706b58991e7c0b9bb964534d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_4"  type="Letter"  url="2a104d9e59d02e928f1c24d359af5bc1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_5"  type="NULL"  url="839e6d84929a3e945ed7c38b2b6faa1a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_6"  type="NULL"  url="ad8286b239ab723f666a96c2434baac0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_7"  type="NULL"  url="3ebb6e77bb9f5619f50c1845c6f9cbde.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5593_img_687_8"  type="NULL"  url="078829ed30349ef857b986f87204b523.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Form 21.</hi> A.D <lb/>In replying to this letter please address the envelope as follows:- <lb/> Number 1817 Name T D FitzGerald IV stage H.M. Prison, Mountjoy<lb/>  The following regulations as to communications, by visit or letter, between <lb/> prisoners and their friends, are notified for the information of their correspondents.   the permission to write and receive letters is given to prisoner for the pur- <lb/>pose of enabling them to keep a connection with their respectable friends and not <lb/>that they may be kept informed of public events   Prisoners are permitted to receive and to write a letter at intervals, which <lb/>depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry and good conduct; but <lb/>matters of special importance to a prisoner may be communicated at any time by <lb/>letter (prepaid) to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof, if expedient.   In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving and writing a letter may be <lb/>forfeited for a time    Money, Books, Postage Stamps, food, tobacco, Clothes, &amp;c. should not be <lb/>sent to prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received at <lb/> Prison for that purpose.   Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce any <lb/>article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine or imprisonment, and any prisoner <lb/>concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.   Prisoners' friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorized persons, to send <lb/>money, &amp;c., to them privately, under pretence that they can apply it for the benefit <lb/>of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such persons endeavour to <lb/>obtain money for themselves. Any letter containing such an application, received <lb/>by friends of a prisoner, should be at once forwarded by then to the Governor.   Prisoners are allowed to receive visits from their friends, according to rules, <lb/>at intervals which depend on their stage.   When visits are due to prisoners, notification will be sent to the friends whom <lb/>they desire to visit them.  <lb/>(6209) Wt.2774-7.10,000.7/15. A.T. &amp;Co., Ltd. (sch.139.)
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_2"/>
             My dear Mabel:-  I am writing this right away, as I want you to be <lb/> able to convey from it good wishes to my mother on her birthday, Friday 11th <lb/> (feast of Our Lady of Lourdes). Also, the next letter out, and the next letter in, date <lb/> from this letter, and your letter to me respectively. I was so bewildered on Saturday <lb/> that I couldn't collect my thoughts. There were all sorts of things I noticed sub- <lb/> consciously, and remembered afterwards - thus, your coat was very nice, reminded <lb/> me somewhat of Dollie's. Also the blouse seemed nice, and I liked that black <lb/> shot silk thing underneath. I observed also that Sean (whom I was very pleased to <lb/> see) had a new overcoat. Dem was the picture of health God bless him, and <lb/> very nice with his daddy. I noticed that once he began talking to me in English <lb/> and changed to Irish. Of course it can't be helped, poor wee son. Piaras was <lb/> lovely. He has got on wonderfully since I saw him before. Struck me as remarkably <lb/> pretty. And very full of himself. It amused me the unmissable way he proceeded to get <lb/> down from that counter, with never a thought of the distance to the floor. By the way wouldn't <lb/> some one, with the art of teaching, and a good knowledge of Irish - as for instance that <lb/> Miss Browne who gives lessons to Dolly - start a little kindergarten class for the <lb/> Irish speaking children. It would be so nice for Dem if we came to live in Dublin. There <lb/> are quite a lot of children about the same age. Miles G.R. C. Brughs little sons <lb/> and a lot more. It could be run under the auspices of the <seg type="unclear">euig cuigi</seg>. What do <lb/> you think? I was very pleased with the photograph of my mother. I thought it <lb/> remarkably good of her, and I am so glad you had it taken. Dem's face was no good <lb/> in it, but the suit looked very nice. It is a pity about the moving. I know — who could <lb/> know better than I — how hard a thing it is to find a house which doesn't <lb/> exist, when you have only a very limited time to find it in. I can't think how to <lb/> manage about the furniture. You couldn't lend some of it to some of the pals, could <lb/> you. About the moving, get Pickfords to do it. They are probably the best. Let <lb/> them do the whole business - lift carpets, and put them down again, and warn them <lb/> to be very easy with the furniture as it has had so much stuffing about that it won't <lb/> stand much more handling. As for packing cases, and the packing of the books, <lb/> I am sure McCarthy would help. He is very smart at that sort of thing, and he <lb/> could probably get cases better than you could. Also he is quite a carpenter. <lb/> In my last letter you will see I ask for tooth paste. You might also send a brush <lb/> as my present one is nearly worn out. I am so sorry about all this moving worry <lb/> falling on you, dear. If you want to consult with me on that or any other matter <lb/> apply for permission. You may rest easy that whatever you decide or wherever <lb/> you move to I shall be content and not growl about it afterwards. Do go to <lb/> bed at a reasonable hour. Otherwise I shall find you a wreck when I do <lb/> get out. You looked pretty well on Saturday, but I know you would have looked <lb/> better, if you had kept better hours. I am glad B. H. and the others go down that <lb/> way. You know I want you to be as happy as possible while I am here. I am glad the <lb/> whist drive was a success. I hope there are lots of ceilis &amp; things. I suppose <lb/> there will be lots of concerts &amp; entertainment for St. Patrick's day. But I should see <lb/> you before then. And when that comes, I shall consider myself almost <lb/> released. I was <seg type="del">b</seg> a bit sore at first about the memorial — I couldn't think who <lb/> had sent it. I am quite thankful to the English S. Lieutenant for his lack of <lb/> clemency. It is fine the way <seg type="unclear">Dundee</seg> is. I am glad that they gave such a reception to <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Ernest</seg>, and that his <seg type="unclear">pare</seg> is in such good form. Indeed all your news was excellent. <lb/> The west seems particularly good. I suppose the midland counties are the worst. <lb/> Though I shall tell you a little incident from Queen's county — when I see you — that is <lb/> particularly encouraging. I was so sorry to hear that poor Liam Sayers was <lb/> dead (God rest him). He was very delicate poor fellow. But such a good chap. Remember <lb/> me to Mrs O'Shea. Tell her I shall be sorry to miss her when she comes to Dublin. <lb/> Also remember me to Stoner. I hope to see him when I get out. Thank him for the <lb/> booklet &amp; ask him to explain to Flint &amp; the others (shouldn't it be Mr &amp; Mrs <lb/> <seg type="unclear"><hi rend="underline">Aldington</hi></seg>?) how it is haven't received them yet. By the way the papers that the <lb/> police lifted from our house were left here. I received notice on the 18th Jan <lb/>, but I think they came a couple of days before that. I glanced through. I hadn't <lb/> time for more. Ask Moloney will he give his word that everything <lb/> was returned. If he says yes, ask was the typed paper of <lb/> the speech which he referred to in court returned. It may be there, but I did  Letters must be legibly written  <!-- Pre-printed prison instruction on bottom of sheet -->
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_3"/>
            <lb/>not see it among them. I had meant to tell you to <lb/> buy yourself a new hat as a xmas present from me. It is rather late now. But do it all <lb/> the same dear. Who is the genial friend who you introduced to mother and Kate - will to me? <lb/> I am glad you hear from those friends in right of <seg type="unclear">Rathmines</seg>. My greetings to them. <lb/> Also say that their confreres are doing well. Tell them that when the war is over <lb/> you hope they will come along to a party to celebrate the occasion. To revert to <lb/> the moving, I suppose I don't need to advise you on certain household points e.g. that <lb/> if there is no garden, all laundry must be sent out. That new blinds are now <lb/> additional expense etc. Of course you will convey my greetings to all friends - GR, <lb/> Pim and all the others. I hope Ernest will be in Dublin at the end of March. I am <lb/> glad that Dolly has 'spoken'. I hope she will rapidly make a hit, though I imagine that <lb/> it would have to be a very big hit indeed before the instrument would amount to anything. <lb/> It is interesting to think that my mother &amp; Kate found Dublin bright &amp; gay <lb/> after London. I am sure that they enjoyed the holiday immensely. It is a pity about the <lb/> burglary, just as well that they take it so philosophically. Saturday and today (Monday) <lb/> are really the first times that I have felt the cold. The mornings get light now at such an <lb/> unnecessarily early hour that we are out in the wood yard at about 10 to 7. Soon <lb/> we shall be going out at 6.30 I think. The days were delightfully short at <lb/> xmas tide. Still only 7 weeks next Friday. Tell all my friends that I am all right <lb/> — cheerful and happy. Fatter, but not so fat as Burrell implied. I have read a lot of <lb/>   recently. Tell me of some novels in the <seg type="unclear">7th</seg> series that they might have <lb/> here that would interest me. I can never think of anything when I want a book. They <lb/> have none of Hardy (at least not that I haven't recently read) I have read <lb/> all the Meredith. There are no Gissing. Tell me some names. For instance <lb/> isn't Mrs de la Pasture pretty fair? Let me know what you have been reading. <lb/> I am glad that you are kept well supplied. Is there nothing worth while at the <lb/> theatres these days? By the way I am rather relieved that that could well be over <lb/> before I am out. I <sic>shd.</sic> be rather embarrassed if I felt that it was in my honour. Of <lb/> course I look forward to a great letter from you. Let me have all news — <lb/>  and Terry McSweeney. If you see McC congratulate him <lb/>   suppose T. McSweeney will be sent up here. I forgot to ask how <lb/> Monaghan had got on. Tell me about him. Remember me to Seamus G. C. <lb/> Be nice to poor Pim. You are so apt to be down on people. Remember me <lb/> also to the Miss Griffins. Incorporate <seg type="del">largely</seg> your letter. I suppose your <lb/> people will soon be off to the S. of France now. Send me the news of my mothers <lb/> weekend in Bucks, if she goes. It is amusing to me to think of the standing <lb/> army at Kimmage. The children seem almost overwhelmed with toys. <lb/> I am glad that it will be Xmas over again when I get out. Fancy, Xmas <lb/> is nearly as far away behind us as my getting out is before us. At present I <lb/> think the things I shall like are sweets, dried figs, raisins, dates in boxes <lb/> and things of that nature. I have a pleasure even in writing of them. <lb/> I hope Ciss is well, and Ulick and Gerald. Any more news about Flora? I found <lb/> it very amusing about B. Bray. By the way, what sort of fellow was that <lb/> McDonall? F. Daly seemed to think a lot of him. Tell G. (the second of my friends) <lb/> when you write to him, that naturally without him, dots &amp; dashes are missed. <lb/> Did I understand that a fellow named Robinson had been arrested in Glasgow. You <lb/> will of course give me all the news. When McCabe gets out (if bail is allowed) <lb/> see that he is well treated. It has been very hard luck for him. And it is <lb/>   that they <sic>shd.</sic> keep him in when they know they can't get a conviction <lb/> against him. I suppose you had a talk with the milkman, after my case. Do <lb/> you ever see Higgins. Of course you see I.Kenny. It will be extraordinary to me <lb/> to be out again. I should be very bewildered. I can't <lb/> even realise that there will be a time when I shall say
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_4"/>
             another week and I shall be out! At present I can say 7 weeks on Friday. You know <lb/> I shall probably be deposited outside the gate at about 7.30 in the morning. When next <lb/> you come to see McCabe ask to see the mats and rugs. You know you can buy <lb/> them here I don't know whether we need any or <seg type="del"></seg>needing, if we can afford <lb/> them. I believe the rugs are 1/- per sq. foot. I think these boots will last out <lb/> my time here all right. When I get out I may need some new things — certainly <lb/> a hat. But I am all right here. Did you hear any more of the pal who was <lb/> to look France up. He was unfortunate after you saw him, I think. I suppose <lb/> you have the pal's on the look out for a house. Of course I don't know Dublin. I agree <lb/> with you in regarding all north of the pillar as out<seg type="del">u</seg>lawed wilderness. It always <lb/> depressed me. What is the East like, near Phoenix Park? I suppose that <lb/> really the only possible part is in the South. Is there <seg type="del">now</seg> no chance near <lb/> Seán, or near B. H. or Cathal Brugh. I suppose you never see M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Campbell. <lb/> If you are writing to <seg type="unclear">Dyer</seg>, <!-- probably Dwyer --> tell him I am just the same, with the same daily <lb/> routine. How did I look with the beard. I don't bother having it clipped as I shd. <lb/> Want to see that the scissors were sterilised, and there is no need to give <lb/> unnecessary trouble. I will let it go till I am about to come out, and <lb/> then get it clipped. After that the shaving should be an easy business <lb/> for some time as the beard will be so soft. Remember me to Eileen &amp; tell <lb/> her that I look to her to counteract all English influences with the children. <lb/> I am sure the <seg type="unclear">Somers'</seg> are very good to Dem. If you have moved into Dublin <lb/> before I get out, I shall of course, go down to see them. How is Annie <lb/> getting on with Mrs M. I hope that we shall be able to take the trip up <lb/> Easter. Though of course, I shall quite understand if there is much Zepp. <lb/> activity. I suppose you didn't write to Lespinasse &amp; to Margarite. Don't <lb/> let these things worry you my dear, I know you have more than enough to do. <lb/> You understand that these things come into my mind here, but they aren't <lb/> at all urgent. In spite of Eimar's sisters' persistence tell him from me that <lb/> I hope he is working up for his final. Poor boy, it will be a good thing to <lb/> have it over him. Be very nice to him. Tell him I often smile when I <lb/>think of him in here. It is true that G.R. would say that all is bearable <lb/> since pyjamas are permitted. It is <hi rend="underline">really</hi> wonderful how one <lb/>settles down. Think. There was a time when I said '22 weeks' <lb/> and now I say 'a little over seven!' Isn't it wonderful. The time <lb/>glides by — sometimes a week seems long, and then another <lb/> seems to pass unnoticed. And how extraordinary it will be when <lb/> the time is up. I shall have been separated from my dear ones <lb/> for practically 24 weeks. And I have been very fond for 16 of them <lb/> and I think I shall been for 24 of them. It has been hard luck on <lb/> you, dear one, but think how wonderful when it is over. I don't know <lb/> whether I shall have improved or otherwise. A habit which I may have <lb/> of falling asleep in the early evening will of course be nothing new. <lb/> You can assure Sean and Eimar that they need build upon no false hopes. I <lb/> shall have the usual capacity for Bird's C. as ever. I hope that Jn MacCarthy <lb/>and his family are well again now. I know I don't need to urge him <lb/> to work hard with things there. Does he ever go out to Kilmacanogue. <lb/> I don't think much of that place, but I hope something is being done <lb/> <seg type="del">or</seg> or will be done with Kilcool and Ashford. They are rather  a  long <lb/> way off for anyone from Dublin. Of course the whole county isn't much <lb/> good. But one can only do one's best. I hope, darling, that you will <lb/> have someone with you every weekend — Sean &amp; B. H., &amp; Miss C and <lb/> Dolly. I imagine it is on the Sundays that you must feel loneliest. <lb/> What do you think of the idea of the Kindergarten? Mention it to GR. <lb/> First thing would be to get the right one to run it — Good Irish and <lb/> some idea of educational methods. <sic>Montesori</sic> could be adapted. <lb/> I <sic>shd.</sic> think that the Norma Borthwick books would be suitable for <lb/> teaching the alphabet phonetically. Once you have the right <lb/> person I should think Miss French could arrange to <seg type="del">then</seg> let them 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_5"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Form 21.</hi> <lb/>A.D.> <lb/>2988/1902   In replying to this Letter, please address the envelope as follows:- <lb/> Number <hi rend="underline">1817</hi> <hi rend="underline">Name T D FitzGerald</hi> <lb/>H.M. Prison, <hi rend="underline">Mountjoy</hi>   The following regulations as to communications, by visit or letter, between <lb/>prisoners and their friends, are notified for the information of their correspondents.   the permission to write and receive letters is given to prisoners for the pur- <lb/>pose of enabling them to keep a connection with their respectable friends and not <lb/>that they may be kept informed of public events    All letters are read by the Prison Authorities. They must be legibly written <lb/>and not crossed. Any which are of an objectionable tendency, either to or from <lb/>prisoners, or containing slang, or improper expressions, will be suppressed.   Prisoners are permitted to receive and to write a letter at intervals, which <lb/>depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry and good conduct; but <lb/>matters of special importance to a prisoner may be communicated at any time by <lb/>letter (prepaid) to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof, if expedient.   In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving and writing a letter may be <lb/>forfeited for a time.   Money, Books, Postage Stamps, Food, Tobacco, Clothes, &amp;c. should not be <lb/>sent to prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received at the <lb/>Prison for that purpose.   Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce any <lb/>article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine or imprisonment, and any prisoner <lb/>concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.   Prisoners' friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorised persons, to send <lb/>money, &amp;c., to them privately, under pretence that they can apply it for the benefit <lb/>of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such persons endeavour to <lb/>obtain money for themselves. Any letter containing such an application, received <lb/>by friends of a prisoner, should be at once forwarded by them to the Governor.   Prisoners are allowed to receive visits from their friends, according to rules, <lb/>at intervals which depend on their stage.   When visits are due to prisoners, notification will be sent to the friends whom <lb/>they desire to visit them.   (6209) Wt.2774-7.10,000.7/15. A.T. &amp;Co., Ltd. (sch.139.) 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_6"/>
             have the Cuig gCui room for say three afternoons a week from <lb/><seg type="del">to</seg>2 to 4. You, or GR. could then write an article on the thing in <lb/> the <sic>Clay Solais</sic>. How urgently necessary it is if advantage is to be made of the <lb/> patriot efforts of Dublin parents. Give an outline of scheme of work - say <lb/> one hour work &amp; one play. The play very important, both educationally, and <lb/> as the children are generally isolated, among non-Irish speakers. If there were <lb/> eight or a dozen young children at it, it would be the best work the League <sic>wd</sic> <lb/> be doing in Dublin. You <sic>shd.</sic> go see Mrs. MacDonaghs if you have time <lb/> and inclination. Remember me to them if you go. I hope you won't knock into <lb/> the Livingstones. That might be rather unpleasant. Though I suppose it <lb/> is pretty certain to happen. I was thinking that it will be a pity if <lb/> Marguerite attributes our not writing to neglect, as it may be that as that <lb/> property she inherited was in Germany, and as her father's business is mostly <lb/> in Germany, it may be that it is all confiscated, as, though her mother was German <lb/> she is a Russian subject. I am sure that if she were less well off, one <lb/> would think that we, at least were friends she could rely on. You <lb/> need not trouble to write to that young man Woodfield till I get out. <lb/> Keep his letter, of course for one to see, and for the address. About the papers <lb/> that the police took. As I have said, I would only take a very cursory <lb/> glance through them. There were your pamphlets, a number of letters, <lb/> apparently every letter written in Irish, including those from Cájt &amp; Nance. <lb/> Also some notes on Greek that were out of some old note book I had at school. <lb/> Apparently, the Greek was Irish to the D. I. and the Irish Greek. All the <lb/>stuff I had written towards the 'felon setting'. And they seem to have gone <lb/>through it pretty thoroughly, as when I wrote about the Rathdown board of Guarding <lb/> they had written 'Lucy Griffin' in the margin, as it was her case I referred to.     Letters must be legibly written  <!-- Pre-printed statement on prison paper. --> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_7"/>
             as far as I could see there was nothing that mattered in the least. I noticed a <lb/> post card with notes by you in your most illegible (and you know what that is). It <lb/> was probably a note of letters you had to write — Dora French <seg type="unclear">E Hyward &amp; co.</seg> <lb/> It was because some of the names were in Irish that it was taken. You can take <lb/> the parcel away with you at the next visit, or let it stay till I go out. They <lb/> had a couple of the <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> copies of the Cinema play — I thought that they <lb/> would take that — and 'Flight' you may remember, in 'Flight' the <lb/>nephew andjoined the army to the G Hussy's dissatisfaction. It is amusing <lb/> the zeal they showed in the search, <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>. Did you hear <lb/>anything about M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Murray Robertson? I wonder if she will return to Dublin <lb/> now that so many (including G. Moore, you say) are coming back. I <sic>shd</sic> like <lb/> to see her again. I suppose <seg type="unclear">Stover</seg> will stay in Ireland till the end of the <lb/> war, all right. Do you remember R. Lynch's letter to you? I believe he said <lb/>that Stover and Hulme (whom he seemed to regard as two quarrelsome Irish <lb/> nationalists) were both in the English Army. I suppose Hulme has joined. <lb/> I am not at all anxious to see Hulme. I shall like to see Flint again. <lb/> He always has it in his favour that he is fond of me. I suppose you see <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Trannaum</seg> sometimes. He would be a good chap to go to Kilcool and Ashford. <lb/> You <sic>shd.</sic> tell him and Patsy O Ryan and others to have a look round for a house. <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Patsy</seg> would probably the most efficient one you would get. I suppose you <sic><hi rend="superscript">d</hi></sic> <lb/> hardly care to live a little <hi rend="underline">out</hi> of Dublin — within easy cycling distance? <lb/> I know you hate cycling, dear, and of course I wouldn't press you to <lb/> take to it again against your will. Only I know how miserable it is <lb/> to go looking for a house in a limited area, where you can never get <lb/> all the required conditions together. I am sorry it all falls on you .<lb/> But as I said before if you want to consult with me about it apply    on the ruled lines and not crossed. <!-- typed rules on paper from prison --> 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5593_img_687_8"/>
             for permission, as it is obviously impossible for you to manage <lb/> everything. I hope you will get this in time to be able to write <lb/> to my mother for her birthday. Tell her I shall be thinking of her <lb/> on that day. And you know that Sunday also is another anniversary. <lb/> I suppose if all the London G. L. central branch are over here, that <lb/> St. Patricks day at the Queen's hall will be very poor this year. I wonder <lb/> if my brother William will go. I hope that Lollie succeeds in getting a house to <lb/> her liking — also my mother. We all seem to be moving just now <lb/> except Ciss. I suppose Ina will be married before I see you again. <lb/> Congratulate her and Bill on his appointment from me. And congratulate <lb/> them on their marriage — if they married. When this letter is finished I <lb/> shall remember what I wanted to say. I ought to have a pencil to make <lb/> notes. I never can remember things otherwise. I shd. only have had one sheet <lb/> but have this second by special permission. What I forget can wait till <lb/> I get out I suppose. By the way the 'Egoist', was a most extraordinary <lb/> portrait of my bother William — another link between him and Meredith. <lb/> I hope the papers are getting on well. Does Griffith's keep up its standard. <lb/> Convey my 'hommages' to all my friends. I hope I shan't have to write to all <lb/> of them when I get out. I look forward to your letter. As you know, I <lb/>urge succinctness, terseness and economy of diction, only as literary qualities <lb/> in a general way. I don't want them to apply to your letter, by any means. <lb/> Have as good a time as you can — go to every dance and every entertainment. <lb/> Go to bed as early as you can — don't stay up till four in the morning except <lb/> occasionally. Have friends down for week ends. Kiss the wee sons for me. <lb/> I hope I shan't be fidgetty when I get out — I shall certainly be a little <lb/>bewildered. Goodbye, my darling —   I shall not growl <lb/> about moving or any other matter when I get out.  Your fond husband   T. Desmond FitzGerald  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>