<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1137">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alexander McDowell to Edward Carson, 20 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alexander McDowell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Alexander McDowell (1853-1918) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Alexander McDowell, Esq., was the joint director of Ireland for the Ministry of Munitions.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1137</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0654">Alexander McDowell</persName>
              <date>1916-07-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1859">51 Royal Avenue, Beflast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1137_img_3717_1"  type="Letter"  url="12a4b29978cca36b693a9ccd24f99a7f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1137_img_3717_2"  type="Letter"  url="67167f49ed8b6f40880c76f6c84c9563.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1137_img_3717_3"  type="Letter"  url="367a6696856bc82bdd49447a94390d2b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1137_img_3717_4"  type="Letter"  url="c86ffff3611649b2cda3ae0b057b0dc7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1137_img_3717_1"/>
                51 ROYAL AVENUE,  BELFAST.    20th July 1916.   Dear Sir Edward,   There has been a good deal of underhand dirty work <lb/>going on here for a very considerable time past in the shape of attempts <lb/>being made by Unionists outside our district to create a feeling that <lb/>would be prejudicial to the arrangement for the exclusion of the six <lb/>Counties. I am glad to say, however, that the efforts have not been <lb/>successful and I think the business people and our working people are <lb/>more satisfied with the arrangement now after all the discussion that <lb/>has taken place than they were when the matter was origianlly put <lb/>before them. Amongst the Business community they have commenced to <lb/>appreciate thoroughly the advantages to be gained from getting an <lb/>arrangement now such as is proposed and they foresee pretty clearly <lb/>the risks connected with a postponement to the termination of the war. <lb/>Evidently what has happened vindicates thoroughly the course which you <lb/>adopted and the advice which you gave and the underhand work which has <lb/>been going on has to a very great extent removed the sympathy that <lb/>formerly existed. Major Saunderson's action is reprobated, while that <lb/>of the Monaghan people is adored and your treatment of the matter as <lb/>appearing in the Press is as usual diplomatic and able.  There has been a good deal of talk recently emanating <lb/>principally from the South of retaliation on the part of the Southerners  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1137_img_3717_2"/>
              against the North for consenting to the exclusion and this takes the <lb/>shape of something in the nature of a boycott through the Great Northern <lb/>Railway.  About two-fifths of the Co's line would be outside <lb/>the excluded area, the three-fifths which is within the excluded <lb/>district is the more important but the idea is that if the Dublin <lb/>Parliament is to have control of the Railways within their district <lb/>they could by legislation so block and obstruct operations on the <lb/>Great Northern Line as to bring about what would practically be <lb/>tantamount to a blockade of the North.  There have been several private meetings of leading <lb/>business men in relation to this matter and in the end I was asked to <lb/>go across and see you with the view of putting the position before you <lb/>to see if anything could be done in connection with the proposed Bill <lb/>that would obviate any risk of the adoption of such a procedure. I <lb/>do not know what is intended with regard to the Railways in Ireland <lb/>generally. I have gathered from the Newspapers that so far as the <lb/>Harbours are concerned they are to remain under Imperial control but <lb/>the Harbours remaining under Imperial control will be of very little <lb/>service if the Railways are not also kept under Imperial control for <lb/>a Harbour without a Railway is practically of no service beyond <lb/>shelter in bad weather. At the present all the Railways in Ireland  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1137_img_3717_3"/>
              are subject to the Board of Trade but the arrangement with regard to <lb/>the Telegraph service is in Ireland different from what it is in England. <lb/>In Ireland the Postmaster owns all the wires and posts along the railway <lb/>and the Railway Coys. give him <sic>wayleave</sic> getting in exchange a free <lb/>telegraph service and that would be one very good reason for the <lb/>Imperial Government keeping the control at present of the railways as <lb/>well as the Harbours. If an Irish Government got control of the <lb/>railways and anything took place like what happened at Easter it is all <lb/>very well to say under the Defence of the Realm Act the Government could <lb/>take possession of the railways but the railways without those to work <lb/>them could be of very little service and I think there can be no doubt if <lb/>the Irish Government have control of the railways it will only be a <lb/>question of time and that a very short one before all the servants on <lb/>the railways would be practically nominees of one party. Of course if <lb/>the Railways are excepted from the jurisdiction of the Irish Parliament <lb/>and kept as they are subject to the Board of Trade the question of a <lb/>boycott or retaliation from the south is out of the question.  I wired you this morning to know if you could have seen <lb/>me to-morrow or Saturday and it was to talk this matter over with you <lb/>I wanted to see you but I got your wire that you would be out of town.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1137_img_3717_4"/>
              <lb/>I will be in London on Tuesday and if it would be convenient for you <lb/>to see me then I would arrange to call on you at any time you <lb/>appointed. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  Alex McDowell   Sir Edward Carson, K. C. M. P.  5 Eaton Place,  London S. W.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>