<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1051">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Davidson to Lieutenant William Ashcroft, 7 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Cleland Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Samuel Cleland Davidson (1846-1921) to Lieutenant William Worsley Ashcroft (1879-1918) regarding the death of Captain James Davidson (1877-1916). Davidson thanks Ashcroft for sending on the particulars of his son&#39;s death at the front. He mentions receiving similar correspondence from Captain Wilfrid Spender (1876-1960) but requests a few additional details so as to better picture the circumstances of James&#39; death. Additionally, Davidson references the progress of his two latest weapon developments, a trench pistol and shells. Before signing off Davidson inquires about the safety of other acquaintances at the front.Sir Samuel Cleland Davidson was an Irish inventor and founder of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast. During the First World War the Sirocco Engineering Works manufactured and exported equipment for cooling, drying, dust collecting, heating, ventilating, pneumatic conveyance for the Royal and Merchant Navy. Initially commissioned with the 13th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles in 1915, Lieutenant William Ashcroft landed in France in October 1915. He was promoted to the rank of Major with the Machine Gun Corps before he was killed in action on 11 April 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-8a, Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-8a</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1051</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1149">Samuel Cleland Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-07-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0356">Sirocco Ironworks, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1059">William Worsley Ashcroft</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1051_img_3140_1"  type="Letter"  url="7fd0eaf0c4aee0e9db6c85fb681897c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1051_img_3140_2"  type="Letter"  url="fe162391dc5a74fc19efcdf872f6cac1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1051_img_3140_3"  type="Letter"  url="40d13ade8de5c977ca79a272bca4f9e1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1051_img_3140_4"  type="Letter"  url="c3fdcb80b36cf0761b448e37a0245844.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1051_img_3140_1"/>
                Sirocco Engineering Works,  Belfast, -- Ireland    7th July, 1916.    Lieutenant W.W. Ashoroft,  Machine Gun Company,  108th Infantry Brigade,  36th Division, B.E.F. France.   Dear Mr Ashoroft:-   I have to-day duly received your letter of <lb/>3rd inst., addressed to Mrs. Davidson and myself, and please <lb/> accept our joint thanks for your thoughtful consideration in <lb/> letting us have particulars of how our dear son fell as a true <lb/>patriotic soldier for King &amp; country.   I yesterday received a letter from Captain <lb/> Spender, Headquarters Staff, of same date as yours, but he was <lb/> not able to give me any very definite particulars, as all he <lb/> knew was only what he had heard, and I daresay at second-hand, <lb/>whereas your description is from personal observation, and I can <lb/> hardly thank you enough for writing me direct, as your letter is <lb/> the only eye-witness information I have had up to the present.  It was also extremely good of Captain Spender <lb/> to write me personally as, in reality, his was the very first <lb/>intimation I received that Jim had been killed. I had met Mr. <lb/>Sharman D. Neill coming off the train at ten o'clock yesterday, <lb/> at the County Down Station, and he anxiously asked me if I had <lb/>any news from Jim, and I told him that I had no news then, <lb/> which I hoped was good news, and I asked him if he had any of <lb/> Dermot, and he replied similarly. But, on arriving at my Office, <lb/> I found Captain Spender's letter awaiting me with the sad news, — <lb/>the only consolation in it being that Jim had fallen nobly as a <lb/> true soldier on the field of battle The Press here learning <lb/> that I had got this letter, asked me for liberty to publish it, and <lb/> I gave them a copy of it, which has accordingly appeared in both <lb/> the 'Whig' and 'News-Letter' of this morning, and I am sending you <lb/> a copy of the 'Whig' under separate cover.  Captain Spender's account, and yours, although <lb/> slightly different, are practically to the same effect, only that  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1051_img_3140_2"/>
              Captain Spender had heard that Jim was being carried off the <lb/> field, after being wounded, when he was shot dead, whereas you <lb/>give more definite particulars, namely, that it was when going <lb/>back a second time for reinforcements,and after having been <lb/>wounded in the knee, and still working his gun, that he got shot <lb/>through the head.  Then an hour or so before your letter came in to-day, <lb/> I received my first official intimation from the War Office, by <lb/> the following telegram:-  'Deeply regret to inform you that Captain J.S. Davidson <lb/>'Machine Gun Corps was killed in action on 1st July. <lb/>'Army Council express their sympathy, <lb/> Secretary, <lb/> War Office'  It is very comforting to know from you that Jim was so <lb/>much thought of, not only by his fellow Officers and his men, but <lb/>also at Headquarters, the latter being also confirmed by the <lb/>fact of Captain Spender writing me a personal letter direct.  In the 4th paragraph of your letter, you mention:-  'although shot through the knee, he refused to be <lb/>'carried back; alternately he fired his gun and threw <lb/>'bombs until he had to retire to bind up his wound; <lb/>'he returned, and did what he could, and finally started <lb/>'back to try and find reinforcements. He was shortly <lb/>'after shot through the head.'  Now I would like if you would say whether the following <lb/> would be a correct detail interpretation of the above:-  'after binding up his wound, he returned to his Gun, <lb/>'and did what he could, and finally had to leave his <lb/>'Gun to try and find further reinforcements, an on <lb/>'his way back was shot through the Head.'  I would be glad to know if, in returning from his Gun, he <lb/> had to cross over No Man's Land between the trenches, and was he <lb/> shot in crossing that, or was he shot in a trench, and, further, <lb/>when he was firing his Gun, was it on surface of ground, or under <lb/> the shelter of a trench, or other protection? Please excuse my <lb/> asking for these particulars, but if you don't mind the trouble of <lb/> writing me again, it would give me a clearer mental picture of the <lb/>circumstances.  I feel that the details which you have given me are  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1051_img_3140_3"/>
              exceptionally clear, more especially as you were still in the <lb/>turmoil of the battle at the time you wrote, and that the further <lb/>particulars, which I would like to have, would not at the moment <lb/>occur to you.  I am much interested in your reference to seeing me <lb/>as a solitary figure on Hankley Common, when the Division was <lb/>moving off after the King's Review, and indeed what you say is <lb/>exactly correct, namely, that my feeling was that possibly I <lb/>might never again see my son, or many of my friends in the <lb/>Division, but as they were all going as good patriots, to fight <lb/>for their King &amp; country, it was right that they should go, and after <lb/>watching my son on his horse, and the other Officers and men all <lb/>disappearing down the far side of the hill, and on turning around, <lb/>I found to my astonishment that I really was the solitary occupant <lb/>of that large Common, which half an hour before had over 20,000 <lb/>men moving about upon it, and truly I did feel lonely to a degree.  I have no doubt that, after the great attack at Thiepval, <lb/>and so many of your friends having fallen in it, you too, as you <lb/>say, are now feeling both lonely and sad, and I heartily recipro- <lb/>cate your wish that we may meet personally some day later on, <lb/>perhaps this might even be at the Front,— it being within the <lb/>bounds of possibility that later on I may be asked to go over <lb/>there to give instructions in the use of my new Trench Pistol <lb/>and shells, which I am glad to say I have, after ten months work, <lb/>been able to develop up to a high degree of efficiency, and so <lb/>much so that if I were called upon to manufacture them here, I <lb/>could probably turn out 30,000 of my shells per week, and possibly <lb/>a couple of hundred Pistols as well, loaded and complete in every <lb/>way, r<hi rend="underline">eady for sending to the trenches</hi>. The Pistol weighs only <lb/>16 lbs, and the shell before firing 1 <hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi> lbs, but the part that is <lb/>thrown weighs 1 <hi rend="superscript">1/4</hi> lbs, and, on bursting, breaks up into from 38 <lb/>to 45 fragments of cast iron about the size of a hazel nut, any <lb/>one of which would go through a <hi rend="superscript">5/8</hi>' board within a radius of 25 <lb/>to 30 ft from where it bursts. The Pistol can be held in the <lb/>hand, but preferably is hung upon the edge of a trench board, or <lb/>on the edge of a vertical post driven into the bottom of the <lb/>trench, and throws the shell at an angle of 45 degrees a maximum <lb/>distance of about 200 yards. When shorter distances are required <lb/>it is only necessary to move a little lever down or up as the <lb/>case may be to give the exact required distance of throw, and yet at the same angle of trajectory.  I would like you to let me know whether Corporal Robert <lb/>Wright came through the attack safely, as he called with me here <lb/>when he was on leave on the 16th June, and not only saw my Pistol <lb/>and shells, but actually fired one or two, and saw an explosion,  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1051_img_3140_4"/>
              and could therefore tell you a good deal about it.   I would also like to know of Tommy Patterson, who <lb/>was No 1 Gunner under Corporal Wright, got through safely, as <lb/>before joining the Division, he was one of my best men in my <lb/>Gardens at Seacourt.  I shall also be extremely grateful to hear from you <lb/>where my brave son has been buried, and if it is possible for you <lb/>to get anything in the way of a headstone to mark his grave, I <lb/>would much appreciate your doing this for me, and any expense you <lb/>re at, I shall very gladly refund you. Perhaps too you could find <lb/>out if his personal belongings have been sent Home, or facilitate <lb/>this being done, and whether the identification bracelet, which he <lb/>always wore, was sent with same, as we would particularly like to <lb/>have this <sic>memento</sic> of him  I am afraid I am asking you a great many questions, <lb/>which you may not have time, or opportunity, to reply to, while <lb/>this terrible crisis continues.  Hoping to hear from you again when you have time, and with <lb/>my best thanks for you explicit letter. <seg type="closer"> Believe me, <lb/>Yours very sincerely,  SC Davidson </seg> P.S.  I feel certain that if you could give anything like the <lb/>same particulars as to how Dermot Neill fell, in a letter to his <lb/>Father, —Sharman, D.Neill, Donegall Place, Belfast, — he would <lb/>immensely appreciate it.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>