<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2635">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to Maria Duffin, circa 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olivia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Olive Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin (1854-1954) detailing her journey to London. Dorothy writes that she had a good passage but has been feeling a little unwell soon. While uncertain about when exactly she should be called for service she notes that those with three months training are more likely to be called by the War Office first.

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/A/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2635</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0801">Olivia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2635_img_2060_1"  type="Letter"  url="45b89d4fc2851e3fc8d9b16b466bfd50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2635_img_2060_2"  type="Letter"  url="d72fd0a6b19bdf8a3677fd1da02a9322.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2635_img_2060_3"  type="Letter"  url="066a7b55f2e9319fc9a1e7bc0175b67b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2635_img_2060_1"/>
             1916 <lb/>Wed morning   Dearest Mamma,   I am scribbling this <lb/>in bed in order to catch the <lb/>early post. I am staying in <lb/>bed for breakfast as my throat <lb/>&amp; chest are a little raw &amp; ruffled <lb/>&amp; I have <seg type="unclear">plastered</seg> myself with <lb/><seg type="unclear">thermofene</seg>, but it is nothing <lb/>much &amp; I shall get-up later. <lb/> I had quite a good passage <lb/>but started with being sick &amp; <lb/>then was <sic>allright</sic> after!   Ted Leffer &amp; Peggy were on <lb/>board, &amp; Bob Kinahan, &amp; Dorothy <lb/>Richardson. I had a nice cabin <lb/>to myself. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2635_img_2060_2"/>
             The train was very slow &amp; 1 1/2 <lb/>hours later. I am afraid Celia <lb/>can have seen little of <seg type="unclear">Lerry</seg> <lb/>if it was as late when he went. <lb/>Great difficulty in getting <lb/>porters or taxis.   I had some time to wait in <lb/><seg type="unclear">London</seg>. Tell D. I went to <lb/>Devonshire House &amp; saw, not, Mrs <lb/><seg type="unclear">Furze</seg>, but a nice sensible looking <lb/>lady in charge. She said they <lb/>had a good long list waiting <lb/>but they never knew how many <lb/>might be called for by the W. O. <lb/>at any time. Those with 3 months <lb/>hospital training would have more <lb/>chance of being called first. <lb/>She said certainly to say she <lb/>would like to go to Landsworth <lb/>— no nurses are being sent to Egypt <lb/>at present. She seemed to think <lb/>that if Celia or Emma had done <lb/>well &amp; were favourable <seg type="unclear">nurses</seg> to <lb/>their matrons, the matron could ask <lb/>for another sister if she chose. <lb/>They evidently <hi rend="underline">can</hi> ask for any <lb/>one if they like.   I forgot all about the gloves to <lb/>be changed at the Glove Co. <lb/>Perhaps Celia could do it, if we <lb/>told her what each wanted.   Miss Hollins leaves this morning <lb/>&amp; was the sister Do, sho was <lb/>suddenly ill &amp; thought there might <lb/>have to be an operation, but she <lb/>seems to be better.   Katherine Leach is here.   I was very weary last night <lb/>&amp; it is quite nice to stay <lb/>lazily in bed. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2635_img_2060_3"/>
             Let me know any news of Terry. <lb/>Best love to all. <lb/>I loved being at home &amp; <lb/>hated coming away again. <lb/>It is fine &amp; mild here &amp; <lb/>all the sheep &amp; cows were <lb/>out in the fields, coming <lb/>along &amp; men <seg type="unclear">pursuing</seg>.   Ever your loving   Olive. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>