<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4306">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Crawford McCullagh to Herbert Asquith, 8 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Crawford McCullagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Crawford McCullagh (1868-1948) to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928). Asquith was Liberal Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1908 to 1916. Sir Crawford McCullagh, Unionist politician, was the Lord Mayor of Belfast from 1914 to 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4306</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1040">Crawford McCullagh</persName>
              <date>1916-05-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1316">City Hall, Belfast, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0003">Herbert Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0632">10 Downing Street, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1948</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4306_img_3668_1"  type="Letter"  url="e9481d037d7bf45fe11b86522ea3e1cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4306_img_3668_2"  type="Letter"  url="1576a23eb59dec1ba6eac3b60d9d77f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4306_img_3668_3"  type="Letter"  url="d7f2cc5a151991877b1770e0c959244c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4306_img_3668_1"/>
             D1507/A/16/8  COPY  Lord Major of<lb/>Belfast  1906  CITY HALL,<lb/>Belfast.<lb/><lb/> 8th May, 1916 <lb/> Sir   I have just learned that a suggestion has been made<lb/>that a Proclamation should be issued directing that all Arms<lb/>in Ireland should forthwith be delivered up to the Crown and<lb/>as I am satisfied an attempt to enforce such a Proclamation<lb/>would be fraught with great risk to the peace I have deemed<lb/>it my duty as Lord Mayor of the City and responsible to a very<lb/>large extent for its peace to intimate my views to you.  I have occupied the position of Lord Mayor for over<lb/>2 years. I have also occupied the position of Hon. Director<lb/>for Recruiting in Ulster and in both capacities I have come<lb/>into contact with not only Belfast but Ulster opinion.  Since the beginning of the war Belfast and Ulster<lb/>have practically ceased their political and religious wrangles<lb/>and their energies have been devoted to the production of<lb/>Munitions and at the same time Belfast and the district have<lb/>contributed toward the fighting forces of the Empire in round<lb/>figures about 60,000 men.  There are undoubtedly Arms in this district but<lb/>outside the Arms which would be covered by the Proclamation<lb/>already in force with regard to the Sinn Feiners I am<lb/>satisfied there are no Arms held by anyone with any disloyal<lb/>motive. If an order is made now to have all Arms delivered<lb/>up, I fear an attempt to enforce it would very possibly lead<lb/>to disturbance as it would be looked upon by the population<lb/>that they were being punished for the offence of the Sinn Feiners 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4306_img_3668_2"/>
             with whom they have had no connection and which movement has <lb/>had their strongest disapproval.   Throughout the excitement of the past few weeks <lb/>Ulster has retained its normal condition and has been able in <lb/>many other ways to assist and relieve both Military and Police <lb/>for the establishment of peace in the disaffected areas in <lb/>other parts of the Country. Anything that would disturb the <lb/>feeling of confidence and rest that now exists will be very <lb/>dangerous not only so far as the peace of the district is <lb/>concerned but also so far as the supply of munitions is <lb/>concerned. To show the interest which the population here has <lb/>taken in the latter work I may say that although the resent <lb/>disturbances took place during the Easter holidays the return <lb/>of labour after the holidays in the Belfast Shipyards and <lb/>Engineering Works never was so good as at the present time. <lb/>The people here are intensely loyal and I would deplore very <lb/>much anything that would cause a revival of either religious <lb/>or political animosity at the present time, as I am satisfied <lb/>action such as suggested would do.   So far as the safety and peace of the country are <lb/>concerned, there is no necessity for anything of the kind and <lb/>I sincerely trust that in the steps taken to put down the <lb/>rebellion nothing will be done which would interfere with or <lb/>reflect in any way upon the loyalty of those who stand for the <lb/>King and Constitution.   I have felt so uneasy since I heard the rumour
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4306_img_3668_3"/>
             referred to, as to what the effect of it would be, that I have<lb/>deemed it my duty to confer with the principal people in this<lb/>district dealing with the working-class population and the views<lb/>which I have expressed above are their views also. They further<lb/>express the view, in which I agree, that this is not a matter<lb/>in which the <sic>poeple</sic> would be willing to follow the view of any<lb/>political leader. I am not, however, writing from the political<lb/>aspect at all; I am only writing from the point of view of the<lb/>peace of the City and the district and I feel satisfied that<lb/>that peace and willingness to serve the Empire which now exist<lb/>will not be helped forward by any interference with the peaceable<lb/>and law-abiding subjects such as is rumoured.  I have the honour to remain,<lb/>Your obedient servant  <lb/>(Signed) CRAWFORD M'CULLAGH,<lb/>LORD MAYOR.   The Rt. Hon. H. H. Asquith, M.P.,<lb/>10, Downing Street,<lb/>LONDON, S.W.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>