<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1294">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J.S. Northcote to Gertrude Bannister, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.S. Northcote</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from J.S. Northcote of St. Andrew&#39;s Vicarage to Gertrude Bannister (later Parry), a cousin of Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written in relation to the decision of Queen Anne&#39;s school to terminate Banniter&#39;s employment there as she had received wide publicity for her Casement campaign. She is informed, however, that the governors of the school will not make the reasons for the termination public. The writer asserts that she had given satisfactory employment and that he is happy to testify to this if she seeks similar work.The letter was written while Casement was imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. Bannister was heavily involved in raising public support for Casement during his trial for treason.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15, Ms. 13,075 /1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1294</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0069">J.S. Northcote</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0538">St. Andrew&#39;s Vicarage, 20 Ashley Place, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1365">Gertrude Bannister</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1294_img_507_1"  type="Letter"  url="b6d1081203545755279f9312ac02f2aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1294_img_507_2"  type="Letter"  url="f44197cdee9f11ee7f09ef053cd92582.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1294_img_507_1"/>
                Telephone  3788 Victoria  St Andrew's Vicarage,  30, Ashley Place, S.W.    July 31. 16   Dear Miss Bannister   W. Spencer Smith has <lb/> forwarded to me your letter <lb/> of July 29.  It can if you wish it be <lb/> laid before the Governors <lb/> at their next meeting. <lb/> The Governors have however <lb/> decided not to state the <lb/> reason for terminating <lb/> your engagement with <lb/> them. I can assure <lb/><seg type="del">I can however</seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1294_img_507_2"/>
              <lb/>you that the work you did <lb/> at Queen Anne for many <lb/> years gave them complete <lb/> satisfaction, and if you <lb/> seek elsewhere employment <lb/> of the same kind I shall be <lb/> glad to bear testimony to <lb/> this fact. <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly  JS Northcote </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>