<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2543">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Arthur Wynne to Henry F. Brennan, 9 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry F. Brennan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Henry Arthur Wynne (1867-1945) to Henry F. Brennan, crown solicitor for Kings County. Henry Arthur Wynne was appointed to the vacant position of chief crown solicitor following the death of Sir Malachy Kelly (1851-1916).

In his letter, Wynne states that the Attorney General consents to his request for leave. Brennan&#39;s original letter requesting leave, dated 5 August, is enclosed. 

This letter states that it is Brennan&#39;s intention to take leave of absence from 14 August to 5 September. He intends to stay at the Grand Hotel, Malahide, County Dublin for much of that time but will remain in contact with his Tullamore and Dublin offices. He states that he will be able to attend at the Tullamore office for some days during the period he wishes to be on leave. His business partner, Sydney Matthews, will provide cover. There are no contentious cases scheduled for the period.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5620/13588</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2543</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0210">Henry F. Brennan</persName>
              <date>1916-08-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0507">Tullamore, County Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">H. A. Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2543_img_1973_1"  type="Letter"  url="551b355d53d51251aa76443c5f335598.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2543_img_1973_2"  type="Letter"  url="5cf6626089843748ccf254e116315107.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2543_img_1973_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="bbe004fbf1d46a536d2712ed313a3a1f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2543_img_1973_1"/>
              9th August 1916   Leave of Absence   Dear Sir, <lb/>The Attorney General consents to your having the leave<lb/>asked for.   Yours truly, <lb/>Henry Arthur Wynne   Henry F.Brennan Esq.,<lb/>Crown Solicitor,<lb/>Tullamore. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2543_img_1973_2"/>
             Telephone No.5 Tullamore<lb/><lb/>Hoey &amp; Denning<lb/>Solicitors<lb/>George J.Hoey<lb/>Henry F.Brenan. L.L.D.<lb/>And Also At<lb/> 12, Trinity St. Dublin. <lb/><lb/>Tullamore<lb/><lb/> 5th August, 1916 <lb/><lb/> Sir,   I beg to enclose my application for leave of Absence from<lb/>the 14th inst. to the 5th prox.  During this period mentioned it is my intention to stay at<lb/>the Grand Hotel, Malahide, and I will be in daily telephonic communicat-<lb/>ion with my Tullamore and Dublin Offices.  It will probably be necessary for me to be in Tullamore<lb/>on some days during the period mentioned. In the event of the Crown<lb/>Solicitor's attendance being required either I or my proposed substitute  who is my partner in the Dublin office <lb/>can reach Tullamore at the shortest possible notice.  At the present time there are two cases returned for trial<lb/>for the Quarter Sessions commencing on the 17th October. The cases in-<lb/>volve charges of assault and malicious wounding and they do not appear<lb/>to present any  unusual  difficulty.   I am, Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,<lb/>Henry F. Brennan.<lb/><seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2543_img_1973_3"/>
             CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>13588 - - 7.AUG.1916<lb/>OFFICE<lb/><lb/>I Henry F Brennan Crown Solicitor<lb/>for Kings County<lb/>beg to apply for leave of Absence from 14th August<lb/>to 5th September 1916, (inclusive).<lb/><hi rend="underline"></hi>  <hi rend="underline">First Schedule.</hi><lb/>Proposed Substitute. Qualifiction. Date admitteed.<lb/>Sydney Matthews Solicitor 1915<lb/>12, Trinity St Dublin &amp;<lb/>1, Leinster Terrace, Kingstown.<lb/>of Holy &amp;   Solicitors.<lb/><hi rend="underline"><lb/>Second Schedule.</hi><lb/>Crown Cases pending of which the Crown Solicitor has<lb/>been ordered to take charge of which may possibly<lb/>come on during his absence:-<lb/><hi rend="underline"><lb/>Title of cause.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Nature of Case</hi><lb/>None<lb/> Dated this 5th day of August 1916. <lb/> Signed Henry F. Brennan.      Attorny General<lb/>Do you approve?        7.VIII.16    I approve<lb/> 9.8.16    <hi rend="underline">Registrar</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>