<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2860">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his family, 19 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>WIlfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from the collection of  Lady Lillian Spender, wife of Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his &#39;dear folks&#39;, presumably his mother and family. Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

In this letter, Spender discusses important preparations he has been making at the front. He mentions that some of the men have requested that he run as MP for Belfast following the war. He tells an anecdote about dentistry and the courage of Ulstermen. He discusses Russian progress on the Eastern front, mentions a recent bombardment by German shells, and says that it is likely his brother Rex will be sent again to fight in Ireland. There is also a brief message from Rex himself in the margin of the letter.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/317</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2860</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0708">WIlfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2860_img_2272_1"  type="NULL"  url="b4b7ce75f8639478b1c7278781ed6eac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2860_img_2272_2"  type="NULL"  url="127d1a4708114825f6afa1eb19cc5486.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2860_img_2272_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Mater</seg><lb/><seg type="del">Mr. Dean<seg type="del">?<lb/>Edmund<lb/><seg type="del">  </seg><lb/><seg type="del">Rex</seg></seg></seg>  Please return finally to Lil  June 19   No time to write anything except<lb/>a message of my love. <lb/>I hope you are all well now.   Rex   My dear folks.   I am matching time for a few  , having <seg type="del">  </seg> but<lb/>the port! I was out at the front on a very important<lb/>piece of work which will not be finished for some time,<lb/>but for which a heavy responsibility rests on one till tomorrow, as<lb/>if my arrangements go wrong before, a disaster of some magnitude<lb/>might ensue. However, one can only do one’s best &amp; hope that<lb/>fortune may shine on it.   I have been very much touched by a little piece of attention<lb/>by our RE. On a higher ridge than most, 500 yards behind the<lb/>front line an observation fort was being out up with a dug out under<lb/>neath &amp; a thing like a steel rabbit hutch on top through which one<lb/>looks. I want to visit it one day, &amp; mentioned that I was<lb/>going to be there in any big battles as a matter of instinct.  A few days later I was there again &amp; found it most beauti—<lb/>fully fitted up with bedstead of rabbit  , shelves, table, etc<lb/>Altogether most snug ; when I mention that the general’s own<lb/>quarters 2 miles behind, which are also dug in, are not nearly<lb/>as nice you will see that I have not been a Staff officer<lb/>of the UVF for nothing!   Another thing that touched me was a request by some<lb/>of the men that I should become their member in Belfast after<lb/>the war. I am not quite sure who I am to turn out,<lb/>tho’ there is one Unionist whom I would replace with<lb/>pleasure.  These little things help &amp; the final announcement that<lb/>the Home Rule settlement is postponed till the end of the war 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2860_img_2272_2"/>
             has raised my spirits immensely &amp; made me far fitter<lb/>for the heavy work ahead. The storm is rather heavy,<lb/>I have been up to 2AM (rum time luckily) 2 nights<lb/>running, so you can guess one is busy, &amp; I have to do<lb/> more writing now as my own shorthand Staff <sic>Sergt</sic><lb/>  has had to go to the base about his teeth &amp; will<lb/>probably not return. Before we left Belfast he was told his<lb/>teeth were so bad he would not be able to go back to<lb/>the front. He went to the Dentist &amp; had 14 out that day,<lb/>&amp; a set of false teeth made which I suppose did not fit well<lb/>in the time, so for a year he has been chewing with<lb/>no teeth &amp; no wonder his digestion is bad! This feck—<lb/>less courage is typically Ulster.    The new of the Russian Victories is good but<lb/>there is much to be done before the war is finished.<lb/>I hope the treacherous Greeks &amp; the Romanians —<lb/>not much better — may now come in to share the spoils.  We have had some heavy bombardments &amp; I was in one<lb/>yesterday, some trenches 50 yards away getting it rather hotly<lb/>whilst some big   went over our heads, luckily for us.   Such a nice little note from Walter   should get an<lb/>answer, but both he &amp; Jimi will forgive me if my <seg type="del">let</seg><lb/>replies don’t start till I go to my dug — out when I hope to<lb/>have plenty of time, tho’ somewhat a noisy one I expect.   I’m afraid Rex is likely to see further fighting in Ireland in<lb/>the next few weeks. It is probable a whole heap of men will be<lb/>sent to him as drafts from England as they must keep up a large<lb/>garrison now. I wish I could give you a true account of this Home Rule<lb/>intrigue of which a Cabinet minister gave Farnham a full story. There<lb/>were resignations of ministers &amp; I think the Government would have fallen<lb/>but for the postponement. Best love my dear folks all.   Wilfrid B Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>