<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5800">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn 31 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active though, like many in the Civil Service, James was obviously somewhat activated, learning Irish, probably Gaelic League, and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in it. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
May has not yet yet read the letters between Maxwell and h Bishop also mentions Bulfin</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5800</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5800_img_901_1"  type="Letter"  url="4787a58c60e4413af9ec31a0991978ed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5800_img_901_2"  type="Letter"  url="74bad301e016e704011ddb939c0cc79b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5800_img_901_1"/>
            <!-- Writing on the upper left hand side written sideways --> I had to get my papers<lb/>signed I was near drawing<lb/>back altogether rather than<lb/>brave the Mullingar or priest<lb/>so now you see what<lb/>I sacrificed for you<lb/>I was ashamed of my life<lb/>I am sure he  (the priest)  was pitying<lb/>the <seg type="unclear">news/man</seg> <!-- Beginning of letter --> Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar   My dearest James,   I got your letter this morning I am sure you were<lb/>expecting a letter from me, but the post leaving <hi rend="underline">advance</hi> time<lb/>&amp; the men working by old time <seg type="del">makes</seg> leaves the post gone<lb/>before they even quit, as you will see I had the letter written on Monday<lb/>&amp; posted it in Mullingar yesterday. —We had a nice day in<lb/>town— better than today anyway I had my dress fitted it looks<lb/>very well I think &amp; my hat also but I can tell you I was very sick<lb/>of the job of turning &amp; twisting &amp; standing all the time while being<lb/>fitted. We settled about a motor, <hi rend="underline">booked</hi> one for me &amp; one<lb/>for you he said any car he'd send would be all <hi rend="underline">right</hi><lb/>&amp; he'll charge by the mile so he could not say what<lb/>either would come to. we could not let him know the hour<lb/>at the time but you can tell him Tuesday night when you<lb/>arrive in Mullingar I suppose <hi rend="underline">8.30 old time</hi> would be about<lb/>the hour would that suit you let us know &amp; it will be alright<lb/>what time will we have to  leave  this at do you know? I think we<lb/>wont fast that morning I mean for Holy Communion the drive<lb/>would be very long for you we can go the Sunday before<lb/>instead like the woman going to Mass on Sat instead of Sunday 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5800_img_901_2"/>
             About the ring I asked you to send me the card<lb/>although a hole I would make my self in a card<lb/>would do just as well I suppose but about the ring<lb/>itself — I know I never could wear any but the two<lb/>rings on that one finger so whether it be large or<lb/>small I dont know which would be the best I think I will<lb/>leave it to your taste I liked your taste in the watch &amp;<lb/>as well you have the advantage of having seen both the<lb/>ring &amp; the finger I dare say unless you have great eye<lb/>&amp; memory altogether you forget my finger is fat and short<lb/>I got my first present yesterday from Mrs Keelan<lb/><hi rend="underline">A silver tea pot</hi> I hope you will get something nice<lb/>for yourself.  We did not see the Cork Examiner and Jennie always sends<lb/>it to us when there is anything on it she must not have<lb/>got it but I will ask her. I heard that Belfin was in<lb/>the G.P.O. &amp; in uniform so he cannot get off <seg type="unclear">to call</seg><lb/>I have no more news so good bye I hope we wont have<lb/>weather like this for our wedding what ever about the honeymoon  <lb/> best love from your own loving <lb/> May<lb/>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>