<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4243">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 27 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to family. Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/80B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4243</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4243_img_3610_1"  type="Letter"  url="ea653548d820159b41cf8552b4304c52.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4243_img_3610_2"  type="Letter"  url="d02e403148cca621a7cee3f7992b1a94.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4243_img_3610_3"  type="Letter"  url="35d3d3c60da453a2278cab46729d2b99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4243_img_3610_4"  type="Letter"  url="75b8a411289f27338cba477e853e4d99.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4243_img_3610_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Please return to Lil.</hi>   <seg type="del">Mater</seg>   <seg type="del">Rex Mabs <seg type="unclear">Edm </seg>  </seg>   Nov. 27.'   My dear folks,    A very nice budget from you arrived nearly midnight yesterday <lb/> with an account of your tea party, &amp; breakfast party with the squirrels <lb/> &amp; also a very nice letter from Mater. I was afraid that she would feel <lb/> Will's promotion as rather a blow, but as regards our respective positions <lb/> &amp; responsibilities <seg type="unclear">out</seg> there is no doubt mine is far the higher appoint- <lb/> ment as well as more pay. Respecting the future however things will <lb/> be different, but I think England &amp; not India will be our probable <lb/> home, or still more probably Ireland where my  army   rank will not <lb/> count in <seg type="del">my</seg> the position which you &amp; I have won.   I am so glad you are with Mater to make things clear <lb/> to her, &amp; that she can see for herself by the way your work <lb/> is appreciated by the "first statesman of our times" that our past <lb/> work has not been altogether wasted.   We are all getting busy for the move of our division, which <lb/> has already begun but I must not tell you the destination. <lb/> Have I missed a letter from you? I thought you were seeing <lb/> the proposed flat on Tuesday, but I have not had a line either <lb/> of its description or of <seg type="del">its</seg>the results, &amp; I'm sure Mater would be <lb/> full of her criticisms of it !   We have a very wintry day but the roads are hard, &amp; <lb/> make good going for the troops marching &amp; that is important.   You will be glad to hear that another Division has reported on our
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4243_img_3610_2"/>
            men in the trenches that they <lb/> appear absolutely fearless, most <lb/> anxious to learn everything, &amp; the reasons of everything in an <lb/>  intelligent way which compares more than favourably with any troops <lb/> including the old army.   The General is now getting quite anxious to get back the <lb/> 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Bde. If he had known this perhaps he would not have been <lb/> so severe on them before their departure. Yes I am sorry for Crozier. <lb/> He is a good chap &amp; there is no comparison between him &amp; the <lb/> boys who are now commanding some of these Infantry battalions, <lb/> but it all comes back to the slackness of some of the COs in <lb/> obeying the orders we gave them in the old days to which so <lb/> litlle attention was paid by some. All the same any man <lb/> who deserted the Division a year ago is either promoted high above <lb/> those who stayed on, or has been killed or wounded.   There was a photo in the sketch yesterday of the King's <lb/> review of the Ulster division with this inscription, <lb/> "Review by H M of the Royal Ulster Volunteers which cheered <lb/> Redmond in the trenches". Can you imagine a more wicked <lb/> deliberate misrepresentation, &amp; to think that no permission could be <lb/> obtained for these photos to be printed until now when they could <lb/> be used for this lying purpose.   Really I think the war will go on till we get a pure <lb/> Government instead of a mixture such as we now have. I think <lb/> peace <seg type="del">or a success</seg>with  some of  the present Ministers to claim  it as  their success <lb/> would be almost worse in the end than another year's war. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4243_img_3610_3"/>
             I am not at all sure that Jessie is not spoiling Lily. Certainly <lb/> by all accounts from the letter she &amp; Mater are doing their best to do so, <lb/> &amp; I think that when I come back I shall have to be very strict.   I hope Douglas called in &amp; gave a good account of me &amp; of <lb/> himself &amp; that he will be able to return with a happy feeling that his <lb/> wife is better. I am sending instructions to his house today but if he <lb/> should not get them please tell him to report at the "new place", <lb/> which he will know, &amp; to get the entraining officer to wire if he <lb/> questions this.   My groom is not quite the same as an indoor orderly, but <lb/> managed to give me a nice hot bath last night.   Rex apparently thinks he may be ordered out at any time <lb/> &amp; I hope to be able from my lordly cháteau to supply him with any <lb/> kit which he may lack &amp; to make things a little more comfortable <lb/> for him in his dugout.    I shall have no time for a letter these next 3 days so <lb/> do not expect one for some little time.   I must say how grateful I am to Mater &amp; Jessie for <lb/> their kind care of Lily, but that this would be the case goes without <lb/> saying.   I am sorry Edward has had so much trouble with his men. He <lb/> takes such a personal interest in each one of them that he gives himself far <lb/> more work than the ordinary officer. I'm afraid some of them do not deserve his <lb/> care. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4243_img_3610_4"/>
             Everyone from home writes most optimistically of Affairs. They <lb/> did so last year, &amp; surely it is obvious that the Germans are allowing <lb/> a pessimistic<seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">f</seg></seg> note to appear mainly to prevent our being pushed into <lb/> compulsory service by our fears. <seg type="unclear">Russell</seg>the late mil<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>attaché at Berlin says <lb/> the British public always have been taken in by the Germans in the <lb/> past &amp; will continue to be so in spite of the openness of their snares.   Another cause I fear is to be found in some of our <lb/> Generals who like Ian Hamilton when questions are being asked <lb/> as to their reported failures become most optimistic. Two of my <lb/> political friends say the war will be over before April.   Best of love to all my dear folks.   I wish Edmund was not getting the additional work of <lb/> the old trust accounts. I will I hope be able to make it up to him <lb/> some day by taking on additional responsibilities. I hope Lily is giving <lb/> satisfaction with her portion. Has the Margate house been let yet ?   Wilfrid BSpender. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>