<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0712">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegram from Samuel Cleland Davidson to Captain SJ Davidson, 6 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Cleland Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A telegram from Samuel Cleland Davidson (1846-1921) to his son, James (1877-1916). The telegram refers to an injury reported by James to his mother in his letter of 29 February and is from his father noting he was injured, returned to duty and enquiring about his health.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme. Sir Samuel Cleland Davidson was an Irish inventor and founder of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast. During the First World War the Sirocco Engineering Works manufactured and exported equipment for cooling, drying, dust collecting, heating, ventilating, pneumatic conveyance for the Royal and Merchant Navy.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/712</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1149">Samuel Cleland Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-03-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0295">Sirocco Works, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0712_img_2212_1"  type="Letter"  url="229c73fa351840eea429396125ef6993.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0712_img_2212_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">COPY OF TELEGRAM</hi>  <hi rend="superscript">From</hi> DAVIDSON &amp; CO., Ltd., SIROCCO ENGINEERING WORKS, BELFAST   <lb/>Date,   6th March, 1916.   19 <lb/>TO   Captain J.S. Davidson  Machine Gun Company  108th Infantry Brigade  36th Division B.E.F. FRANCE    WAR OFFICE REPORTED YOU WERE SLIGHTLY WOUNDED <lb/> TWENTYNINTH BUT RESUMED DUTY TELEGRAPH IF <lb/> ALLOWABLE HOW YOU ARE NOW  <seg type="closer"> DAVIDSON   S.C. Davidson,   Sirocco Works, Belfast.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>