<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2621">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Terrence Duffin to his mother, Maria Duffin, 31 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terrence Duffin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Terrence Duffin to his mother Maria Duffin, 31 December 1915. Terrence is writing to his mother to inform her that he is going on leave shortly and coming to see her in Ireland.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109 - D/9/4/C/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2621</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0973">Terrence Duffin </persName>
              <date>1915-12-31</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2621_img_2047_1"  type="Letter"  url="08d5739f0b984502372694482490a53e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2621_img_2047_2"  type="Letter"  url="d915ce8930ac2df360ee9f88da8f1799.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2621_img_2047_3"  type="Letter"  url="6973edcf051e451afa334c878dd678d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2621_img_2047_4"  type="Letter"  url="fdf9e202e0f4a09066fbd8ae6674b02e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2621_img_2047_5"  type="Letter"  url="6c6beb5df8c282dc8a0fb9d4f72c5cab.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2621_img_2047_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/C   <hi rend="underline">Dearest Mamma</hi>   This is just a line to give<lb/>you the good news which I<lb/>have just got tonight that I<lb/>am to go on leave next week.  I leave here on Friday<lb/>or Saturday - If Friday<lb/>I should be home on Sunday<lb/>the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>but if I leave on Satur-<lb/>day I probably won't be able<lb/>to cross till Monday 10<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>to  39 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2621_img_2047_2"/>
             D2109/9/4/C  Ireland. Anyhow<lb/>I will find out in London<lb/>when I arrive and let<lb/>you know. If stranded<lb/>in London I will get a<lb/>chance of seeing Celia—  I will be glad of the change<lb/>as you can imagine for I<lb/>have been thronged lately!  Tomorrow we move our<lb/>entire Bde. Hd. Qrs -  Today I have had  40 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2621_img_2047_3"/>
             D2109/9/4/C  to find complete new billets<lb/>and could find no place<lb/>for the Staff but an empty<lb/>house without a stick of<lb/>furniture or means of cooking<lb/>tomorrows meals. I have<lb/>been on my knees to the R.E.<lb/>and have persuaded them<lb/>to stick up a stove of<lb/>sorts and have also <seg type="unclear">tasked</seg><lb/>the Divl. Interpreter to<lb/>try and find some  41 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2621_img_2047_4"/>
             D2109/9/4/C  chairs &amp; tables. In a<lb/>day or two we may settle<lb/>down again! - Tonight at<lb/>11.20pm I am still wading<lb/>through paper in the office!  Had a line and some<lb/>cigarettes from Emma and<lb/>have written back to let<lb/>her know I am alive &amp;<lb/>well.  Nothing else new to<lb/>relate meanwhile - Thanks  42 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2621_img_2047_5"/>
             D2109/9/4/C  for letters from yourself<lb/>Edmond, Ruth &amp; Dorothy  Best love and hope<lb/>to see you all soon.  Ever Your own  Terry  31/12/15 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>