<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4244">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 29 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/81</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4244</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4244_img_3611_1"  type="Letter"  url="586e3e35495a0eb505d9cb1008715920.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4244_img_3611_2"  type="Letter"  url="144d72831afda8e513f7a2c1c6fdfae7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4244_img_3611_3"  type="Letter"  url="74d76bb68b7d5e329bbcf4e7176cd806.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4244_img_3611_4"  type="Letter"  url="a9e9f351607d873ce4ceee09c46599e4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4244_img_3611_1"/>
             Nov. 29'   P.kest of P Rs   I quite approve of your proposed dis- <lb/> sipation "for the children" even tho' it probably <lb/> means your sharing a box with Lady C.    I do not mind a little extravagance on <lb/> children's pleasures if it is not overdone &amp; the <lb/> children made blasé &amp; peevish.   You might do something for the other 2 <lb/> families Eds and Mab's either in the way of <lb/> Xmas presents or of a show. Grown-up presents <lb/> are off this year at least mine are. I am <lb/> distinctly alarmed at the prospect of what
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4244_img_3611_2"/>
            Douglas has told you that I lack. I honestly <lb/> can think of nothing &amp; already my kitbag <lb/> is bellowing, so please to not enlarge. I do <lb/> not think it pays to stint myself of essentials <lb/> whilst I am quite sure it is a mistake to <lb/> multiply non-essentials.   Please tell Gen' Powell that the regular <lb/> Brigade which Gen' Nugent was so anxious to <lb/> get in place of the 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> has not proved <lb/> at all a success, &amp; he now wants to get <lb/> the 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> back again. They however are so <lb/>dispirited by his  farewell remarks to them that they <lb/> are working heaven &amp; earth not to return. It
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4244_img_3611_3"/>
            is such a pity. We had officers like Crozier with <lb/> plenty of experience, but Gen' N has taken the <lb/> line that they are all no good &amp; brings in <lb/> over their heads men of 7 years service.   He really does not understand how to lead <lb/> Ulstermen. They are not African niggers.   Perhaps he is getting to realise this &amp; <lb/> will try to get a little more geneal to them.   I don't think he likes the way a <lb/>certain triumvirate or inner Cabinet are run- <lb/> ning things, &amp; shall not be surprised if he <lb/>does not help to make things a success. <lb/> The contrary perhaps. The more you deal <lb/> direct with your unit committees the better <lb/> I think, but let their requests be carefully checked
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4244_img_3611_4"/>
            as they may quite possibly put in for socks <lb/> etc which are easily obtainable form Government <lb/> sources, &amp; which some COs are too lazy to indent <lb/> for.   I forward Mater's letters tho' I fear they <lb/> may rather add to the size of the PR 's head. <lb/> However if she remembers that other letters have gone <lb/> round the family which I have not yet seen, perhaps <lb/> she will then become a proper sized PR.   I leave my present quarters with some <lb/> regret they have been unusually comfortable <lb/> &amp; I don't like a chateau   Best of love to the family <lb/> but still <lb/> Your <lb/> BW   WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>