<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0582">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Chief Secretary’s Office to Francis Caldwell, 3 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from The Chief Secretary&#39;s Office to Francis Caldwell (c.1860-1934), Head Constable, Liverpool City Police Force.The CSO is considering the payment of a war bonus to the constabulary in Ireland, and is inquiring as to the practice in Liverpool.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13692</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/582</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-08-03T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0109">Francis Caldwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1699">Liverpool, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0582_img_1983_1"  type="Letter"  url="c0e34874079fbad73f28b94af184c6a8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0582_img_1983_1"/>
                DUBLIN CASTLE    3rd August, 1916.   Dear Sir,   The Irish Government have lately been <lb/>dealing with the question of a War Bonus for <lb/>the Police Forces in Ireland. In this conâ <lb/>nection it would be of interest to know what <lb/>Bonus, if any, has been granted to your Force <lb/>since the outbreak of the War, whether it <lb/>applies to all ranks, and to married and single <lb/>men.  I should be much obliged if you could <lb/>supply this information. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,   The Head Constable,  City Police Force,  Liverpool.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>