<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0261">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Bay to Sir Matthew Nathan, 18 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Bay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter addressed to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). The letter writer states that the volunteers of the Belfast Volunteer Defence Corps, under John Bristow, have proved useful on patrol. The writer believes they would be more useful if they were sworn in as special constables and understands that such an application has been made he wishes to make his support for the idea known.Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7964/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/261</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0726">John Bay</persName>
              <date>1916-04-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0785">Headquarters, Belfast Garrison, Victoria Barracks, Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0261_img_1446_1"  type="Letter"  url="cec0900407262d804b4f3a0d60c5119c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0261_img_1446_2"  type="Letter"  url="38cba50a1f2f1740c9d209543208f4b3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0261_img_1446_1"/>
                HEADQUARTERS, BELFAST GARRISON,  Victoria Barracks,  BELFAST.    18.4.16   My dear Nathan,   The Volunteers here under <lb/> Mr. John Bristow, Commandant, are <lb/> affiliated <seg type="unclear">properly</seg> and organised — <lb/> some 220 or so of them are doing <lb/> useful patrol work in the Docks— <lb/> I believe it would be better if <lb/>they were sworn in as special <lb/> Constables (without pay), as they <lb/> have no status now to enable them <lb/>to arrest any one.  I understand some application has <lb/>already been made about this, and I  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0261_img_1446_2"/>
              wish to support it. <seg type="closer"> <seg type="unclear">Sincerely</seg>  <seg type="unclear">John Bay</seg> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>