<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3487">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Tadhg Barry to Tomás Mac Curtain, 28 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Tadhg Barry</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Tadhg Barry (1880–1921) to Tomás MacCurtain updating him with as much news as he can although he is wary of saying too much in a letter as his boss has ordered him &#34;to write no more politics&#34;.

Tomás MacCurtain (1884–1920), republican, was born Thomas Curtin in Ballyknockane, Co. Cork, on 20 March 1884. MacCurtain was a founder member of the Cork executive of the Irish Volunteers, and in the time leading up to the 1916 Rising, he travelled the county organising new Volunteer units. MacCurtain was arrested in Cork in May 1916, and sent to Dublin before being deported to Wakefield prison on 30 May. On 10 June he was moved to Frongoch in north Wales and on 11 July to Reading gaol, where he remained until his release in December 1916. He continued to lead the Cork Volunteers despite being imprisoned on other occasions in 1917. On 30 January 1920 he became the first Sinn Féin lord mayor of Cork. On 20 March 1920,  MacCurtain was shot dead in his bedroom a major escalation in the spiral of violence that marked the last year of the war of independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork Public Museum</repository>
                  <collection>T. Mac Curtain Collection, L1966.176</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3487</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0903">Tadhg Barry</persName>
              <date>1916-09-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0079">54 Blarney Street, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0338">Tomás Mac Curtain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1457">Reading Gaol, Berkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1921</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3487_img_2895_1"  type="Letter"  url="9dad729b53d68c1a5d46b693c8df298d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3487_img_2895_2"  type="Letter"  url="b45f6c76667c0c61797d7d767a4a6759.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3487_img_2895_1"/>
             recd Oct 4/1916   54 [Questionable reading.]  <lb/>15 <seg type="unclear">Copaige</seg>     28.9.16 <lb/><lb/> D Tomat, a capa,   I hope you have not thought it ill<lb/>of me that I did not write before now. I have not<lb/>written to any of my imprisoned comrades for the<lb/>good reason that I could not write as I wished &amp;<lb/>say what I would like but as by now the friends<lb/>who flocked to show sympathy must be easing off<lb/>in their eager anxiousness to be doing something and<lb/>writing sympathy to you all. I am just writing to<lb/>say that there is nothing to say that I can<lb/>write. Individually the boys are all good in<lb/>health &amp; if sick at heart yet hopeful. We could<lb/>do with some of you home if only to give you a<lb/>piece of our minds. A few of that training school<lb/>of January are in Cork at work including Wall<lb/>Driscoll &amp; Mullane. A group of the city lads assembled<lb/>on Ballingeary last Saturday and had a noisy time.<lb/>I had a fortnight there during summer during which<lb/>Applebee was so busy looking after me that he could not<lb/>see some companions who would have interested him<lb/>more. The Gaelic League promises great but we<lb/>lack direction &amp; guidance with the result that there<lb/>is likely to be a waste of energy. Conscription 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3487_img_2895_2"/>
             rumours are in the air also. I hope it will not materialise<lb/>if only to make the slackers fight on some side.  How are you in Reading. Too much of it<lb/>I Suppose. I see you read my notes in J.P. Like so<lb/>much in this letter the boss had ordered me to write no<lb/>more politics. I wish I were able to say write it<lb/>yourself to —. But the prefominant partner holds<lb/>the <seg type="unclear">Kudos</seg>. Ref to Milroy &amp; Capt OF. not<lb/>forgetting T.MJ and any of the others that I knew.  Father Tom Roche is in Dartmoor &amp; Portland<lb/>lately to see Tom Huner &amp; De Valera. All<lb/>fairly good. Not with any other prisoners, McNeill<lb/>has some <seg type="unclear"></seg>   to study &amp; Irish Books are<lb/>allowed to any looking for them. Beazley most stubborn<lb/>wants no favours. Tom Lynch is going to see<lb/>Diarmuid this week endo.   Everyone is waiting for Griffiths history of the<lb/>Volunteers &amp; the Rising. Tell him be thinking over<lb/>if for even the Board of Eire are talking of<lb/>his ability in that connection.  I hope that such excellent company is<lb/>sufficient to overcome such wretched environment<lb/>and that the peace flutter means the coming of<lb/>that stray cluer so that we may have you all<lb/>come back to Eire before very long.  Yours disgruntled as ever<lb/>Tadhg Barry 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>