<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0787">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Arthur Munro to North Circular Laundry, 17 November 1915.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Arthur Munro</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles Arthur Munro (1869 - 1952) to North Circular Laundry concerning a collapsed wall. This letter is part of a series of correspondence regarding the collapse of a shared wall between the neighbouring laundry and prison. Munro wished to inquire after the manager&#39;s plans to rebuild the wall as it does not form part of the prison&#39;s original structure.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/2892/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/787</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0487">Charles Arthur Munro</persName>
              <date>1915-11-17T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1165">Mountjoy Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0323">North Circular Laundry, North Circular Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0787_img_2325_1"  type="Letter"  url="3b4c2bb3a69afb5c058d63ea33b3653e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0787_img_2325_1"/>
              COPY.   His Majesty's Prison  Mountjoy.    17th November, 1915   Sir   With reference to the wall recently blown down which <lb/>separates your property from the Prison grounds, as this wall <lb/>was not erected by the Prisons Department and does not form <lb/>part of any of the buildings, I would be obliged by your <lb/>letting me know what steps you propose to take in reference to <lb/>the re—building of same and removal of debris.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant   (Sd)  C. A. Munro,  Governor.   The Manager,  North Circular Laundry,  N. C. Road,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>