<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5580">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Monteith to Roger Casement, 11 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Monteith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Robert Monteith (1880-1956) to Sir Roger Casement (1865-1916). Monteith was the commander of the Irish Brigade, appointed by Casement. The letter contains refers to a letter that had gone &#39;astray&#39; and news of two potential recruits. Monteith writes that he does not have a &#39;general pass&#39; and asks if he can get one to make moving around easier. He also mentions that he has received a new uniform, although he does not have permission from the authorities to wear it. 

This letter is taken from a collection of letters, poems, articles and other documents of Roger Casement and his family covering his career in the British Diplomatic Service as well as his activities in the Irish Revolutionary movement, 1889-1945. Sir Roger Casement was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. Casement believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany. He spent eighteen months in Germany, arriving first as an envoy of Irish-American leaders, attempting to encourage Germany to support Irish separatist aspirations by providing arms. Casement succeeded in securing limited German support but his attempt to form a brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps to fight against Britain was largely unsuccessful.  When it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sir Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15; Ms. 13,085/24 </collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5580</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0377">Robert Monteith</persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5580_img_675_1"  type="Letter"  url="c47bb34f1ed6beb58c1c682f9ad6c789.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5580_img_675_2"  type="Letter"  url="cc8a216f54ae4f2209ee6fe85c71da11.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5580_img_675_1"/>
             R in B Nov 12/15   Limburg   10.xi.15.   Dear Sir Roger   I am indeed sorry about that <lb/> letter of mine going astray. I will take good <lb/> care in future to address my letters as per <lb/> note heading -   Two more men are being sent on <lb/> to Zossen, I don't expect they will leave <lb/> here before Friday next-   Is it possible to obtain a <lb/> general pass for me from the Foreign <lb/> Office? The people here were surprised <lb/> that I had not one in my possession <lb/> I had to get a special pass to go to <lb/>Frankfurt &amp; Zerhussen has been stopped <lb/> in the street to explain who I was, and <lb/> what my business was - of course a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5580_img_675_2"/>
            <lb/>pass will not prevent my being stopped but it will <lb/> simplify matters for me a great deal -   My uniform is now ready, but the <lb/>camp authorities have had no notification <lb/> from the War Office that I have any permission <lb/> or right to wear it - can you get the <lb/> War Office to notify them? You see in the <lb/> correspondence with the War Office I am shown <lb/> as <hi rend="underline">Mr.</hi>Monteith &amp; we can't blame the people <lb/> here - Any old rank will do, I can <lb/>carry on just as well with cloth shoulder <lb/> straps as with gold ones - I may say I have <lb/> only heard indirectly of the uniform question <lb/> but I know that it was intended I should <lb/> hear of it -   Keogh arrived yesterday morning. <lb/> I think he will be of good use to us -   Faithfully Yrs   R.Monteith 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>