<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3992">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Art Ó Briain, 12 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter (unsigned) addressed to &#39;A Chara&#39;, presumably to Art Ó Briain (1872-1949).

The writer refers to men he had visited in Wandsworth and to letters from prisoners transferred from Wandsworth prison to Frongoch, and to the &#39;Ladies Committee&#39;.  He transcribes letters from prisoners J E Lyons (see MS 8434 / 23-4) and James Daly (MS 8434 / 23-5) to Miss Coates and refers to other letters, including one from a young timid Dublin man who hadn&#39;t had a visit until the previous week.

Art Ó Briain (1872-1949) was Honorary Secretary of The Irish National Relief Fund which was set up to provide assistance to the dependents of those executed in 1916, those sentenced to prison and to the prisoners themselves.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Art Ó Briain papers, c. 1900-c.1945, Ó Briain’s work for Irish political prisoners (1916-21), MS 8434 /23-4 and 5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3992</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0640">Frongoch, North Wales (South Camp), United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1063">Art Ó Briain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1356">London, England, United Kingdon</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3992_img_3379_1"  type="Letter"  url="2173394c4bb104bcda9b756f6cdfd449.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3992_img_3379_2"  type="Letter"  url="f745cfa599a0d5de31082792eeecef7c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3992_img_3379_3"  type="Letter"  url="d60f6cae73b6261a0f8a4625f089bac1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3992_img_3379_1"/>
             1  Frongoch Sth Camp    12/7/16.    A cara  <!-- the Irish word for \'friend\' used as a salutation -->  As the Ladies Com. does not<lb/>appear to be meeting I send the<lb/>copy of a letter from Frongoch.<lb/>I have received several mostly from<lb/>the poor citizen army men whom I<lb/>visited at Wandsworth.  The Censor had quite washed out two<lb/>lines of one letter from a Lewes friend<lb/>- teacher of Irish at Rockwell Coll: but<lb/>one sentence was camp practically<lb/>under our own control.  However the letter of one old man<lb/>whose son was with him at Wands<hi rend="superscript">wth</hi><lb/>is full of details from the Camp.<lb/>(which I had asked him to supply.)  5/7/'16   Dear Miss <seg type="unclear">Coales</seg><lb/>We arrived here on<lb/>the 26th and I take the opportunity<lb/>of thanking you for your kindness<lb/>to us during our stay in Wandsworth<lb/>which helped to brighten our<lb/>lot very much while there.  The prisoners here are separated<lb/>into two camps. North and South<lb/>I am in the S<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Camp where there 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3992_img_3379_2"/>
             2.<lb/>are about 600 men. We are in huts about<lb/>30 in each which are well lighted,<lb/>ventilated and clean. We take our<lb/>meals in huts preserved for the<lb/>purpose. Our own men manage<lb/>the camp, keep order, cook clean<lb/>etc.  The supply of rations is fair, the<lb/>bread and meat being fresh<lb/>and the tea of good quality.  There is very little margarine or<lb/>butter, no cheese, or jam. There is<lb/>a canteen where these things can<lb/>be bought, but as there are a<lb/>number of men who have no money<lb/>they have to do without them and<lb/>also without cigarettes, tobacco<lb/>and matches. If you could do<lb/>anything for us in this matter<lb/>you would confer a great benefit<lb/>on us. Thanking you again.  Yours faithfully  JE Lyons  This letter as all others took a<lb/>week to reach me.  Another letter of a young Dublin lad<lb/>whom my mother found and had never had<lb/>a visit until the last week. He was very timid 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3992_img_3379_3"/>
             3.  and almost in tears as no one had claimed<lb/>him in the visiting rooom.  Upper Camp   29/6/16.    Dear Miss Coales,   I am writing to let you  know  I am<lb/>going on well and I hope you are<lb/>in the best of health.  All the Wandsworth boys here send<lb/>you their best thanks for your<lb/>kindness to them and send also<lb/><seg type="del">the</seg>to all the ladies.  We are well treated and we<lb/>have grand scenery and country<lb/>air.  When you write don't forget to<lb/>put my number on the letter. It<lb/>is 1107. We rise at 6.30 and go<lb/>to bed at 9.45.  We have a canteen here and<lb/>we can buy anything we want.<lb/>We play football all day and smoke.<lb/>We are having a jolly time. In our<lb/>hut we sing and dance.  All the boys here are in great<lb/>spirit and plenty of fun. I will<lb/>not say any more for the present<lb/>Hoping to hear from you soon.   Yours truly <lb/>James Daly 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>