<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0167">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sister M. Marcella to Anna O'Rahilly, 20 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. Marcella</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Sister M. Marcella to Anna O&#39;Rahilly, the sister of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) The letter discusses two of Anna&#39;s pupils and their success in their exams, most notably Irish. The letter goes on to discuss the death of Anna&#39;s brother Michael. It also discusses Nancy, Michael&#39;s wife, stating that the author prays for her daily. Michael &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill (1867-1945) and Bulmer Hobson (1883-1969) who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/185/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/167</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1138">M. Marcella</persName>
              <date>1916-07-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0178">St. Mary&#39;s, 81 Haddington Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0167_img_1301_1"  type="Letter"  url="2dee970b063f0e7082ef60e7910898a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0167_img_1301_2"  type="Letter"  url="cbaa401236c7011eeb071243d9f6dbae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0167_img_1301_3"  type="Letter"  url="dc9ee8697bc39c0f4a6be97dc3ca6c4c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0167_img_1301_4"  type="Letter"  url="61106b4aacfa2f0c8eab190abfd58b50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0167_img_1301_5"  type="Letter"  url="2dee970b063f0e7082ef60e7910898a2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0167_img_1301_1"/>
                Sisters of the Holy Faith,  St. Mary's, 81, Haddington Road,  Dublin.    July 20th 1916   My dear Miss O'Rahilly   You will be delighted <lb/> to hear that your two <lb/> pupils passed the <lb/> Matriculation success- <lb/> fully and got Certifi- <lb/> cates for Irish, Latin <lb/> French Mathematics <lb/> and English. Many <lb/> thanks for all the the concluding paragraph of this letter is in the top left hand corner of this page and has been transcribed at the end (page 4)   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0167_img_1301_2"/>
              <lb/>trouble you have taken <lb/>with them. I really do <lb/>not know how you <lb/>managed to get them <lb/> up, in Irish in one <lb/>year. We are all very <lb/>very grateful to you. <lb/>I did not forget you <lb/>during the Retreat. <lb/> I never forget your <lb/>dear, noble-hearted <lb/> Brother R.I.P. whom <lb/>our dear Lord has <lb/>taken to himself. <lb/>Our loss is indeed  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0167_img_1301_3"/>
              <lb/>his gain. I enclose <lb/>a little badge for the <lb/>dear little baby. I will <lb/>depend on you to give <lb/> me the pleasure of seeing <lb/>it. I would also <lb/>like to have the honour of <lb/>Consecrating it to our <lb/>Blessed Lady and the <lb/>Sacred Heart unless <lb/>Mrs. O'Rahilly has <lb/>other arrangements. <lb/>Please tell her that <lb/> I pray for her every <lb/>day. She is one of  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0167_img_1301_4"/>
              <lb/>Gods Chosen Ones since <lb/>she has got so much of <lb/>His Cross. I feel that <lb/>the Sacred Heart will <lb/>bless and sustain her <lb/>under It. May our dear <lb/> Lord comfort her in her <lb/>heavy trial under which <lb/>she has been so good <lb/>and resigned. I hope <lb/>you are enjoying a well <lb/> earned rest. I am in <lb/>Glasnevin yet, but will <lb/>go away after a few day <lb/>until the 21st of August <lb/> when school will re open here. the concluding paragraph of this letter is contained in the top left hand corner of page one and is transcribed below   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0167_img_1301_5"/>
              Good bye now and <lb/>take care of your <lb/>dear self and <lb/>come back quite <lb/>strong. <seg type="closer"> With best love I am Yours affectionately  Sr M Marcella </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>