<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3126">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Patrick McCurtin SJ to Fr Thomas V Nolan SJ, 10 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick McCurtin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter concerns the possible purchase of a property adjacent to St Aloysius&#39; College, &#39;Wyalla&#39; and the benefit it would be to the school. It ends describing the reaction to the Dublin Rising in Australia. 

Fr Patrick McCurtin SJ was Rector of St Aloysius&#39; College, a Jesuit day school for boys at, Milsons Point, Sydney, Australia. Born on 1st February 1865 in Tipperary, he was educated at Rockwell College before entering the Jesuits in 1883. He died on 16th July 1938 at Melbourne. 

The first two Irish Jesuits, Frs. William Lentaigne and William Kelly, set foot in Melbourne, Australia on 21st September 1865. In 1901, the Austrian and Irish Missions amalgamated and Australia was created a Vice-Province in 1931 and a Province in 1950.  Irish Jesuits worked mainly as missionaries, and educators in the urban communities of eastern Australia. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/MSSN/AUST</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3126</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0464">Patrick McCurtin</persName>
              <date>1915-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2131">St Aloysius&#39; College, Milsons Point, Sydney, Australia</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1453">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1938</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3126_img_2543_1"  type="Letter"  url="9de695419236c980c314e54e28966a6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3126_img_2543_2"  type="Letter"  url="2803dfae5e86de2d7abe0013a2f11c02.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3126_img_2543_3"  type="Letter"  url="2a08649a3fcdd151ce713a1b89a7f042.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3126_img_2543_4"  type="Letter"  url="3d6df9b3f83aea44a92b8c3d6e4ec8f8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3126_img_2543_1"/>
             TEL. NORTH SYDNEY 58. <lb/> ST. ALOYSIUS' COLLEGE, S.J., <lb/>MILSON'S POINT, <lb/>SYDNEY.     May 10 1916     My dear Father Provincial P.C.  <lb/>When Fr. Superior was <lb/>going on to Brisbane to-day he <lb/>asked me to send Your Reverence <lb/>this enclosed letter and plan, about <lb/>this property adjoining our recent ac — <lb/>quisition, "Wyalla".   There is no intention or request <lb/>that the College should secure <lb/>"Ardnours" — but from its position one <lb/>can easily see that some hold over <lb/>it by the Society would be an advan 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3126_img_2543_2"/>
             tage. The erection of a terrace of houses, <lb/>or flats would be a great draw— <lb/>back.   What F. Ryan wishes to do is this — <lb/>that he should be empowered to in— <lb/>vest <seg type="unclear">cannot read</seg> money in "Ardnours", if <lb/>by renting it he could secure the <lb/>   money in 'Ardnours', <hi rend="underline">if</hi> <lb/>by granting it he could secure his <lb/>interest. The prices offered are <lb/>£6,000 down, and the   <lb/>on   at 6%. The full <lb/>price is £4000.    I think his price will come <lb/>much lower than £4,000 — <lb/>and in a letter I wrote recently <lb/>to his agents, I don't think that we 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3126_img_2543_3"/>
             could not write me on any re— <lb/>quisitions unless the selling <lb/>price of 'Ardnous' came to £3000 <lb/>or lower.   If F. Ryan could secure <lb/>it in some way, it would be <lb/>a quiet matter. Already the <lb/>securing of 'Wyalla' has left St. <lb/>Aloysius' in a strong position — <lb/>and it has come when most <lb/><seg type="unclear">undid</seg>. Yesterday and to—day there <lb/>were 170 boys actually in class. <lb/>Some of them sitting in chairs around <lb/>the walls of class—rooms: some <lb/>squatting on the floor. We hope to 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3126_img_2543_4"/>
             be in   of 'Wyalla' within <lb/>a week from to—day.   Our deepest sympathy goes to poor <lb/>old Dublin — as during the last <lb/>two or three weeks our papers have <lb/>been full of the dreadful happenings <lb/>in Ireland. At first the feeling was one <lb/>of anger with Sinn Feiners — but <lb/>there is now a swing to the other <lb/>side, owing to the <seg type="unclear">hurting</seg> of so <lb/>many — a treatment so different to <lb/>that of the S. African <seg type="unclear">rebels</seg>.   Yours, my dear Father, <lb/>very sincerely and respectfully <lb/>in the <lb/><seg type="unclear">P. McCurtin, S. J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>