<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3935">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Laurence J. Ginnell, 27 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,612/18-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3935</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-02-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1462">Laurence J. Ginnell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3935_img_3310_1"  type="Letter"  url="80bf4bc9308735d4b1e2ebc9ef2caa2b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3935_img_3310_1"/>
             11, Grosvenor Place,<lb/>Rathmines, Dublin.   27-11-16.   Dear Mr. Ginnell,   Many thanks for the question re the stopped cables. As we<lb/>cannot draw them without particulars, perhaps you would now be good<lb/>enough to ask why they stopped a cable sent by me on  Jan. 8th , addre—<lb/>ssed to Ford Peace Crusade, The Hague, Holland, in these terms:<lb/>Dublin Public Meeting convened by Irish Women's Franchise League<lb/>endorsed your mission; and whether they propose to return me the<lb/>money paid for the <sic>despatch</sic> of this cable.     I am glad to know that you are coming over to speak at the Anti-<lb/>Taxation Meeting on Tuesday. There is a good committee in charge<lb/>of the meeting, and I believe it will be the starting point of an<lb/>All-Ireland agitation, —not for restitution or adjustments or<lb/>set-offs, but for Fiscal Independence.         Meeting arranged for next Tuesday. At present politics have gone<lb/>back to the pre-Davitt days, — a Constitutional movement which is<lb/><sic>sunk</sic> in Whiggery and useless, while all the real <seg type="unclear">Nationalism</seg> of the<lb/>country is diverted into the physical force movement. That is a<lb/>dangerous position; the Taxation question seems to offer the best<lb/>prospect of creating a new, militant, aggressive, movement not com-<lb/>mitted to physical force.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>