<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5539">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 27 January, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
May continues her plans to get away. Her neighbour is thinking of enlisting in the British army.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5539</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-01-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5539_img_635_1"  type="Letter"  url="8217b7616d79f3bfd90a445dea851b78.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5539_img_635_2"  type="Letter"  url="93de032a9ebcdee520acbe324e56041e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5539_img_635_3"  type="Letter"  url="226b1caf54d7714e9b59e89d471e1faa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5539_img_635_4"  type="Letter"  url="f9aab1002ee6683e99d9f79e521d18d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5539_img_635_5"  type="Letter"  url="e2b2c40325acc8a91e8d6503bb694a9b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5539_img_635_1"/>
             Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea   27. Jan    My dearest James,   Was delighted<lb/>to get you letter this morn<lb/>You are very good to him 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5539_img_635_2"/>
             of writing so often.  Mother is coming<lb/>today she has written to say<lb/>so but sent a wire also it<lb/>took a start out of us thought<lb/>she was lost or something<lb/>wrong, is the first thing<lb/>the sight of wire puts into<lb/>our heads  Well for <hi rend="underline">sure </hi>&amp; for <hi rend="underline">certain</hi><lb/>we are going on Sat mid-day<lb/>train from Castletown<lb/>you may tell your (<hi rend="underline">our</hi>)<lb/>Mother so &amp; also tell her<lb/>Mrs S- will not write<lb/>to her when I'm writing<lb/>&amp; not to be depending on<lb/>her for butter that she has 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5539_img_635_3"/>
            them from mere fear I <lb/> hope she won't any way <lb/>they are nasty without <lb/>being dangerous of course <lb/>Laddie Jim &amp; Edgar have <lb/>had them &amp; colds before that <lb/>so every thing happened <lb/>while Mother was away. <lb/>Jack Nolan knows nothing
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5539_img_635_4"/>
             not <hi rend="underline">enough for herself.</hi><lb/>I am very glad we are<lb/>getting off on Sat late<lb/>train &amp; all we could not<lb/>manage first. The mumps<lb/>are improved today I expect<lb/>by tomorrow or Sat at least<lb/>I'll be able to eat something<lb/>Mrs S; is afraid today she<lb/>is getting them she might get 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5539_img_635_5"/>
             but I think he can be<lb/>justly suspected of having<lb/>just an outline of peoples<lb/>minds Poor Jack he is thinking<lb/>of listing not to save his<lb/>king &amp; country but to save<lb/>his wife &amp; family from starving<lb/>I expect. - he getting a bit<lb/>anxious about Johnnie's long   holiday nothing much<lb/> <seg type="unclear">-pers</seg> him he has near<lb/>given up hopes of any<lb/>one thinking of me seems<lb/>to think I ought to be gone<lb/>by that I must be grown<lb/>up &amp; for some time <hi rend="underline">too</hi><lb/>I will not write any more<lb/>now so keep this love<lb/>warm till Sat   <lb/> Your ever loving <lb/> May     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>