<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4015">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to Alice Katherine Wynne</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>&#39;On His Majesty&#39;s Service&#39; is crossed off the envelope.
The letter discusses the work which Charles had to carry out. He says. &#34;One advantage of the rain...keeps down the smell...several dead men have been dug up&#34;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin </repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/809</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4015</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-10-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0807">Glendalough, Co. Wicklow.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4015_img_340_1"  type="Letter"  url="475e3cfe029b80e154d0b5d4a5b9ffca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4015_img_340_2"  type="Letter"  url="da8ce0e4eda2e7ac7632d6f6d3c4a4ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4015_img_340_3"  type="Envelope"  url="61a69102e99b709833510cf288d29b33.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4015_img_340_4"  type="Envelope"  url="141d7b0702f52cab8ba0d9acdc7b4571.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4015_img_340_1"/>
             29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Oct 16   Dear Mother <lb/><lb/> Now I end this for the present<lb/><sic>I</sic> sorry it didn't go before but: there<lb/>were no facilities for letters over there.<lb/>I have now returned it was delightful<lb/>getting the post on arrival will write soon. C.W.W.   Your letter which I got on Thursday certainly<lb/>brought the war nearer to me than anything yet.<lb/>Still it's the same for everyone; everyone has got<lb/>his bit. The first thing that struck me when I got<lb/>out here was how extraordinarily cheerful and how<lb/>decent and friendly everyone is. Everyone has a smile<lb/>no matter what happens. And the minute you<lb/>meet anyone it's as if you knew him for years.<lb/>One always manages a bit of fun— Its the people<lb/>at home it's worst for— How they stand it<lb/>I don't know. There's many hard blows have been<lb/>given and many more will come. One can<lb/>only trust that all will work for good in the end. And<lb/>certainly already a lot of good must have been done.<lb/>The men are wonderful — always ready for a joke<lb/>no matter what happens — It's splendid. The job<lb/>I'm on now isn't very amusing though I suppose it's<lb/>nothing to what the chaps have in the front line—<lb/>There's a working party supplied by various batteries to<lb/>clean up and build a trench on the ridge— Each battery<lb/>in turn provides an Officer for three days— I'm on<lb/>it now and am glad my time finishes tomorrow<lb/>The mud is awful. This morning it rained steadily<lb/>till we had to <seg type="unclear">chuck</seg> work. One advantage of the rain<lb/>it keeps down the smell. Several dead men<lb/>have been dug up. Anyway it will be splendid when 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4015_img_340_2"/>
            the job is done and it was really cruel <lb/> coming along the trench before and when it's <lb/> finished it will be all boarded with <seg type="del">cl</seg>wire <lb/> netting along the sides and stays every yard with <lb/> smaller ones in between to prevent the sides falling <lb/> in. It ought to last some time — though really I don't <lb/> know whether anything will hold out long against <lb/> the rain. <seg type="del">Will</seg> We are billeted just beside where <lb/> I was with the advance party and I am sleeping <lb/> in the same place as before — very comfortable <lb/> with a nice stove. We start out at 8 .0 and work <lb/> till 3.0. when we come home &amp; have dinner and <lb/> are finished for the day — a fairly long spell but <lb/> much better than the way they did it before when <lb/> they came all the way down for dinner and <lb/> then all the way back again; another party came <lb/> in last night which brings the total to nearly 120. <lb/> So if only the weather takes up we ought to be able <lb/> to get on well with the work. There's another <lb/> Officer on another job here. So I'm not alone of an <lb/>evening. But still I shall be remarkably glad when <lb/> I get back to the battery again. I shall then I expect take <lb/> my turn of duty with the rest as the telephone system <lb/> is pretty will fixed and won't want much attention <lb/> in a place like this.The day seems to have taken up a bit <lb/> now (3.30 pm) it has stopped raining and isn't looking so bad. <lb/> I suppose one can't expect much more decent weather <lb/> now. I am grand myself as I hope all are at home. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4015_img_340_3"/>
             <seg type="del"><hi rend="underline">On His Majesty's Service</hi></seg>   Oct 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916  <lb/> Mrs. Wynne<lb/>The Cottage<lb/>Glendalough<lb/>Co Wicklow<lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> <lb/><lb/> CW<hi rend="underline">Wynne</hi>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4015_img_340_4"/>
            <!-- Back of envelope blank -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>