<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0823">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward J. Gavegan of the Irish Relief Fund Bazaar Committee, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward J. Gavegan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward J. Gavegan of the Irish Relief Fund Bazaar Committee to various individuals inviting them to become Patrons of the bazaar. The proceeds of the Bazaar will support those affected by the Easter uprising.Edward J. Gavegan (b. 1863) was a prominent Irish-American who lived in Manhattan, New York. He was a lawyer and Justice of New York Supreme Court between 1910-33. He also acted as the Grand Marshal of the New York St. Patrick&#39;s Day parade.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>American Irish Historical Society</repository>
                  <collection>AIHS4106c, AIHS4106c</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/823</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1485">Edward J. Gavegan</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0335">New York, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Irish Relief Fund Bazaar</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName >None</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0823_img_2365_1"  type="Letter"  url="a21cf1439dcf67220bc172c73ec1068c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0823_img_2365_1"/>
                October 7, 1916.   Dear Sir:   You are cordially invited to become on of the patrons<lb/> of the Irish Relief Fund Bazaar, which opens on next Saturday<lb/> at Madison Square Garden.  The purpose of this great demonstration is to raise the largest<lb/> possible fund for the relief of the thousands of sufferers, who<lb/> were reduced to want as a consequence of the Easter uprising<lb/> in Dublin and other parts of Ireland.  Despite reports to the contrary, which have been widely<lb/> and industriously circulated, there still remains a large amount of <lb/> suffering to be relieved, Nothing can more plainly indicate this<lb/> than the recent exchange of cablegrams between Archbishop Duhig<lb/> of Brisbane, Australia, and Rev. Richard Bowden of the Dublin<lb/> Pro-Cathedral, as follow:    'To Rev. R. Bowden, Dublin -- Cabled Bank of Ireland<lb/> £450, from Irish sympathisers, Queensland, including<lb/> £250 from Queensland Irish Association, London ' Times'<lb/> cabled newspapers here-- ' No distress in Dublin.'<lb/> Cable M'Donald full reply.--- Archbishop Duhig, Chairman; <lb/> Frank M'Donald, Treasurer; P.J. Stephens, Secretary.' <lb/> The reply of thanks from Father Bowden stated:<lb/> ' Further help badly needed. 1,200 families on<lb/> our books alone.'  We feel sure that you will be entirely willing to become a Patron<lb/> to so worthy a cause, and are accordingly adding your name to the <lb/> list. Should it happen, however, that for any reason you would prefer<lb/> that your name be not included , your are requested to so advise us<lb/> on the enclosed stamped return envelope. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely,  <hi rend="underline">Edward J <seg type="unclear">Gavegan.</seg></hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>