<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0136">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. Guinell to Mary Ellen O'Rahilly, 9 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A. Guinell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Mary Ellen (‘Nell’) O’Rahilly concerning the death of her brother Michael. The author of this letter expresses her sympathy for Nell and Michael&#39;s family but notes that this is what he would have wanted. While expressing sympathy for the plight of Ireland&#39;s men the writer acknowledges that it is the wives, mothers and sister of those men who suffer most. The author then requests that Nell send on &#39;relics&#39; of Michael and any other photographs, that she can lay her hands on, of the leaders of the Rising. Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated. Nell was also involved in the Nationalist movement as a member of Cumann na mBan and was imprisoned after the Rising for her role.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/121/004/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/136</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0204">A. Guinell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0415">51 Queen&#39;s Road, Richmond, Surrey, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Ellen O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0136_img_1233_1"  type="Letter"  url="8af9a0e2f14e4a9be5851ed890b708a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0136_img_1233_2"  type="Letter"  url="758fbef3455b68ff7fc1da77986f1721.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0136_img_1233_3"  type="Letter"  url="8af9a0e2f14e4a9be5851ed890b708a2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0136_img_1233_1"/>
                51, Queen's Road,  Richmond,  Surrey.    9th June '16   Dear Mrs. Humphreys,   My husband asks me to acknowledge<lb/> &amp; thank you for your letter of 5th June.<lb/> Needless to say we were <hi rend="underline">delighted</hi> to hear<lb/> your good news. Long may he live!  Your sister-in-law must try to be as <lb/> brave as she can &amp; to remember that <hi rend="underline">he</hi><lb/> would not have had it otherwise &amp; that  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0136_img_1233_2"/>
              if Ireland exacts much from her men, she<lb/> often expects more from the wives, mothers<lb/> &amp; sisters of her dearest &amp; best. Enclosed<lb/> are some questions. He has not got a copy of <lb/> the questions about the watch, chain &amp;<lb/> ring. Would Madame please let him know<lb/> if the articles have been returned.  You will not forget, I hope, to get any<lb/> 'relics' you can for us - &amp; also we want<lb/> a photograph of you know whom &amp;<lb/> also, if possible of P.H.P. &amp; any others you can<lb/> lay your hands on.  If we are in Dublin we shall certainly<lb/> call. With all good wishes to Madame &amp; the final piece of this letter is contained in the top right corner of the first page and is transcribed here   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0136_img_1233_3"/>
              yourself from us both. <seg type="closer"> I remain,<lb/> Yours sincerely <lb/> A. Guinell </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>