<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3924">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Dr Catherine Maguire, 24 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,612/18-19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3924</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1165">Francis Sheehy Skeffington </persName>
              <date>1916-01-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1248">11 Grosvenor Place ,Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Catherine Maguire </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3924_img_3300_1"  type="Letter"  url="7db24f8b5189a7fcf9322fba0ea21bc4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3924_img_3300_1"/>
             11, Grosvenor place, <lb/>Rathmines, Dublin.   24 — I<seg type="del">I</seg>. — 16.   Dear Dr. Maguire,   You were kind enough, in September 1914, to sign for me a bank <lb/>guarantee for £100 for the IRISH CITIZEN, jointly with Lady Ernestine <lb/>Hunt and Captain White. Owing to the continued drain on the paper, <lb/>I have been unable to pay this off; nor will the National Bank press <lb/>for repayment so long as I meet the interest regularly. Now, howev- <lb/>er, Lady Ernestine Hunt, for personal reasons, wishes to withdraw her <lb/>name from the guarantee; with the result that the bank will call up <lb/>the guarantee unless they are satisfied that you and Captain White <lb/>are prepared to be jointly responsible for the amount, without Lady <lb/>Ernestine's concurrence. May I ask if you will be good enough to <lb/>let me have an intimation to this effect?   I have now stopped the drain on the paper by making it a monthly <lb/>and will not attempt to resume weekly publication until the entire <lb/>debt, including this guarantee, has been paid off.   I note that "Votes for Women" has also been compelled to become <lb/>a monthly; so it is not surprising that, with our more restricted <lb/>field, the IRISH CITIZEN should also have had to shorten sail.   With regrets for having to trouble you, and many thanks for your <lb/>assistance in keeping the paper going, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>