<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1194">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr John Fitzgibbon to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, circa 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Fitzgibbon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Fitzgibbon (1882-1918) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Fr. Keary&#39;s injury and the anxiety surrounding the next big push. Fr John &#39;Jack&#39; Fitzgibbon SJ was ordained a priest on 31st July 1915. His father, John Fitzgibbon, was a successful draper and Member of Parliament from 1910-1918. Fr Fitzgibbon served in the 6th Division of the British Army, having enlisted shortly after the death of his brother at Gallipoli. He was promoted to senior chaplain in 1917, and in the same year he was gassed at Loos on 5th September and awarded the military cross. Fr Fitzgibbon was killed in action by a shell on the 18th September 1918, and is buried at Trefcon, St. Quentin, Picardie.Father Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/18, IJA/CHPI/21/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1194</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0632">John Fitzgibbon</persName>
              <date>1918</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1194_img_3877_1"  type="Letter"  url="de8693d3a83ca4a42c09f5d2cd208e40.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1194_img_3877_1"/>
               (1918)    Dear Fr Provincial   We are still in the <lb/>land of the living anxiously awaiting <lb/>the next big move. It is a trying <lb/>time, for although there is little <lb/>fighting, we are being very heavily <lb/>shelled &amp; all movements in daylight <lb/>are impossible - then at night continual <lb/>air raids not only with bombs but <lb/>machine guns. A few weeks ago <lb/>our advanced dressing station was blown <lb/>in &amp; the medical officer mortally wounded, <lb/>a few days later the one where Fr Keary <lb/>was, was also blown in - but thank God <lb/>both of us escaped uninjured, though <lb/>the Medical officer &amp; some men were <lb/>killed. The Yanks are all around <lb/>us now &amp; last Sunday I had <lb/>hundreds of them at Mass &amp; Benediction <lb/>is an old form, some miles behind. <lb/>The Benediction started at 7 o.c &amp; between <lb/>confession &amp; Holy Communion I was not <lb/>finished until after 10. oc &amp; then I had <lb/>an hours trek back to my little grey <lb/>home'. There seems no chance of leave <lb/>in our Division so we must carry on <lb/>with very best wishes &amp; a little request <lb/>for a <seg type="unclear">moment</seg> in Your Holy Sacrifice &amp; prayer. <seg type="closer"> I remain <lb/>Your obedient child  Jack Fitzgibbon sj. </seg> PS. <lb/>And for Fr. Farley  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>