<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3034">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from W.G. Wakley to Robert Chalmers, 19 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.G. Wakley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from W.G. Wakley, Secretary of The Incorporated Law Society of Ireland, to the Under Secretary of Dublin Castle enclosing a memorandum regarding the suggested legislation for the government of Ireland and its impact on the Incorporated Law Society of Ireland and the solicitors&#39; profession.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5618-12565-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3034</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0243">W.G. Wakley</persName>
              <date>1916-07-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1338">Incorporated Law Society of Ireland, Solicitors Buildings, Four Courts, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0887">The Under Secretary's Office, Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3034_img_2433_1"  type="Letter"  url="35f98cfe9e9e1840c86a97111de8004c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3034_img_2433_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="378050b847936b2d993c7a79bdc8baa7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3034_img_2433_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="e5971c374842a2e2d5b8513b1953ddcf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3034_img_2433_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="bd7f92bdffea24a50e78443f735e41a3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3034_img_2433_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="360150b346ea5101fad97350f82664bb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3034_img_2433_1"/>
             Telephone N<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">o</hi>.</hi> <lb/>2607 <lb/>Registered <lb/>Telegraphic Address <lb/>"Law Society Dublin"   The INCORPORATED LAW SOCIETY OF IRELAND, <lb/>SOLICITORS BUILDINGS, FOUR COURTS, <lb/>DUBLIN.   19th. July, 1916.   Dear Sir,   I am directed by the Council to send you enclosed memorandum <lb/>relative to the suggested legislation for the government of Ireland as <lb/>affecting this Society and the Solicitors' profession.   Faithfully yours,   <hi rend="underline">W.G. Wakely</hi>  <lb/>Secretary.  Right Hon. The Under Secretary for Ireland, <lb/>Dublin Castle, <lb/>D u b l i n. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3034_img_2433_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">The Incorporated Law Society of Ireland.</hi>  Memorandum relative to the suggested Legislation for the <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Government of Ireland.</hi>  <lb/>THE INCORPORATED LAW SOCIETY OF IRELAND.  The Incorporated Law Society of Ireland was founded by the Royal <lb/>Charter of 5th April 1852. Its membership consists of "persons being <lb/>" Attorneys or Solicitors practising in our Courts of Justice within that <lb/>" part of our said United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland called <lb/>" Ireland, or who shall have voluntarily retired from practice."   By Supplemental Charter of 14th December, 1888, it is (<seg type="foreign">inter alia</seg>) <lb/>provided that five members of the Northern Law Society and five <lb/> members of the Southern Law Association and a member from each of <lb/> the four Provinces be members of the Council of the Society, in addition to <lb/> the thirty-one ordinary members provided for by the Original Charter.   By Statute 29 and 30 Victoria, cap. 84, the Incorporated Law <lb/> Society was made the Registrar of Solicitors in Ireland. This Act was <lb/> repealed by the Solicitors (Ireland) Act, 1898, 61 and 62 Victoria, <lb/> cap. 17, which re-enacted the provision of the previous Act making the <lb/> Society the Registrar. Every practising Solicitor in Ireland must, by <lb/> the Statute, obtain each year a certificate from the Society as the <lb/> Registrar, enabling him, upon its being stamped, to practise his profession <lb/> and the Statute requires that each Solicitor shall pay to the Society a <lb/> fee of five shillings for such annual certificate.   The Society is, by the above Statutes, made the educational and <lb/>examining body for the admission of Solicitors in Ireland, and the <lb/>Statutes require that every person seeking to become a Solicitor in <lb/>Ireland shall pay to the Society certain prescribed fees.   By the Act of 1898 a Committee of the Council is appointed to <lb/> hear and report upon disciplinary applications against Irish Solicitors. <lb/> The Society is the custodian of the Roll of Solicitors in Ireland.   The Incorporated Law Society of Ireland respectfully submit that <lb/>the status of the Society, as the governing and educational body of the <lb/>Solicitors' profession in Ireland, should not be affected or altered by the <lb/>contemplated legislation and that the Society should continue to exercise <lb/>its statutable functions over the Solicitors practising in every part of <lb/>Ireland.   Should it, however, be determined by Parliament that there shall <lb/>be set up a separate governing body of the Solicitors' profession for the <lb/>Counties of Antrim, Armagh, Down, Fermanagh, Londonderry and
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3034_img_2433_3"/>
            Tyrone and the Cities of Belfast and Londonderry and that the <lb/>Incorporated Law Society of Ireland should be thus compulsorily deprived <lb/>of a portion of its statutable rights and privileges, it is submitted that <lb/>the Society should be compensated for the loss of revenue when it will <lb/>suffer as a consequence, and in support of this claim, the following facts <lb/> are submitted: —    The income of the Incorporated Law Society of Ireland is mainly <lb/>derived from —  <lb/>(1) Members' subscriptions. <lb/>(2) Examination fees. <lb/>(3) The 5/- annual certificate fee from all practising Solicitors. <lb/>(4) The Solicitors' admission fees. <lb/>(5) A grant in aid from Parliament in respect of disciplinary <lb/>proceedings, varying in amount from £300 to £500 <lb/> per annum.  The present number of members of the Society resident in the <lb/>Counties and Cities to be excluded is 129 out of a total membership of <lb/>828. The number of practising Solicitors resident in the Counties and <lb/>Cities to be excluded is 441 out of a total number in Ireland of 1,528.   The average annual loss of income to the Society under the foregoing <lb/>heads, consequent upon the cessation of the jurisdiction of the Society <lb/>over the Counties and Cities to be excluded, would be about —   <lb/>(1) Subscriptions .. £100 <lb/>(2) Examination fees .. £400 <lb/>(3) Certificate fees .. £110 <lb/>(4) Admission fees .. £130  This means the loss of £740 per annum out if a total average annual <lb/> income of £3,300.   The exclusion of the six Counties and two Cities would not mean <lb/> that the Society could, as a consequence, reduce its expenditure. The <lb/>existing educational staff — consisting of two Professors and three Ex- <lb/>aminers — would have to be continued to be employed. The Secretarial <lb/> staff, consisting of a Secretary, Librarian and three Clerks would still <lb/> be necessary.   The Society is in the exceptional position in Ireland of being a <lb/>Voluntary Society, unconnected with the Government, with powers and <lb/>duties cast upon it by Statute which it exercises over the whole Solicitors' <lb/>profession in Ireland, and it has been possessed of such statutable <lb/>jurisdiction for the past fifty years.   It is submitted that, if the Society is now to be deprived of some of <lb/> its statutable jurisdiction and of a portion of its revenue, it would be <lb/> entitled to compensation from the State in respect of that portion of its <lb/> annual income of which it would be compulsorily deprived. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3034_img_2433_4"/>
             The Society desire further to submit that it would be inequitable <lb/>to deprive Irish Solicitors whose names are now on the Roll of Solicitors, <lb/>or any apprentice to an Irish Solicitor, at present serving under Identures <lb/>of Apprenticeship, when admitted, of their right to practise in every part <lb/>of Ireland. The Solicitor has been admitted a Solicitor of the Supreme <lb/>Court in Ireland, with a statutable right to practise everywhere in Ireland, <lb/>and he has paid his stamp duties to the Crown, and his fees, on the faith <lb/>of a Statute giving him such a right. The apprentice has paid his stamp <lb/>duties and fees on the faith of a Statute providing that he shall acquire <lb/>such right, upon serving his apprenticeship, and passing his examinations <lb/>and being admitted as required by the Statute.   It is submitted that, so far as the rights and privileges of the <lb/>Solicitors' profession in Ireland are concerned, there should be no <lb/>provision passed into law whereby two branches of the Solicitors' pro- <lb/>fession should in future exist in Ireland, the one for twenty-six Counties <lb/> the other for the remaining six Counties.   There are in the City of Dublin a number of practising Solicitors <lb/>who would be particularly affected by the establishment of a separate <lb/>Solicitors' profession for the Counties of Antrim, Armagh, Down, <lb/>Fermanagh, Londonderry and Tyrone, and the Cities of Belfast and <lb/>Londonderry, i.e., those Dublin Solicitors who at present act as "Dublin <lb/>Agents" of Solicitors who practise in those six Counties and two Cities.   These Solicitors would be compulsorily deprived of their salaries <lb/>and emoluments as such Agents, and some of them would be left <lb/>without employment. Should the intended legislation have the effect <lb/>of making their services as Town Agents unnecessary it is submitted <lb/>that they are deserving of generous consideration at the hands of the <lb/>State.   SOLICITORS' BUILDINGS, FOUR COURTS, <lb/>DUBLIN,   5th July, 1916. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3034_img_2433_5"/>
            The <hi rend="underline">Incorporated Law Society</hi> of Ireland.  <hi rend="underline">5th day of July, 1916.</hi>  Memorandum  RELATIVE TO THE SUGGESTED <lb/>LEGISLATION FOR THE <lb/>GOVERNMENT OF <lb/>IRELAND.   SOLICITORS' BUILDINGS, FOUR COURTS, <lb/>DUBLIN. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>