<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2626">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Auntie D, 3 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her Auntie D written on December 3rd 1915. Celia writes to her aunt describing her work at the Voluntary Aid Detachment. Celia has finished her 6 months in VAD and plans to sign up again. She writes of how excited she was about a new nurse in her ward who comes from America. They have three male patients in the ward that suffer from nerve shock. 

Celia Duffin, born in 1888, was one of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She attended the Cheltenham Ladies College. She served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#34;Escape Poem&#34; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell &amp; Co. Ltd in 1929. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/C/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2626</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Auntie D</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2626_img_2051_1"  type="Letter"  url="728b79205b85f7865ef7853afbca6535.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2626_img_2051_2"  type="Letter"  url="418eae2342b5194862601dc854398be6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2626_img_2051_3"  type="Letter"  url="f2d78270e13a9b89b04bce2bba3da7c0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2626_img_2051_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/C   Dec. 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>/15    Dear Auntie D.   I enclose the only copy of the magazine<lb/>I can get as the first number is out of<lb/>print and the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> not published yet, I<lb/>will post you a copy when it comes out.  Please thank Aunties B &amp; E. for the nice<lb/><seg type="unclear">squares</seg>, I have collected quite a large<lb/>number now and they are so useful. I<lb/>should like to write a line to the<lb/>old lady who knitted the ones you<lb/>enclosed but can't quite make out<lb/>whether her name is <seg type="unclear">How</seg> or Horn.  I have just finished my 6 months here<lb/>now, so will soon have to sign on again.<lb/>Some of the V.A.D's are leaving but I<lb/>think the greater number will stay. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2626_img_2051_2"/>
            I am still in the same ward, but have <lb/>a new staff nurse now who comes from <lb/>America and is consequently full of new <lb/>ideas. She has been doing laboratory <lb/>work for some time and is very ready to <lb/>teach us which is different from some <lb/>of the nurses who don't bother to explain <lb/>anything. We have two or three <lb/>poor fellows suffering from nerve shock at <lb/>present, rather difficult patients to <lb/>nurse. They are very nice men and <lb/>quite sensible, but one thinks that <lb/>he is dumb and another that he is deaf, <lb/>although there is nothing really wrong <lb/>with their organs, and will be all right <lb/>when they have had a little rest. <lb/>Sister sent the deaf one to the concert <lb/>last night and he went very meekly <lb/>although he hears nothing.  I am hoping to see Dorothy in her way through <lb/>London, I am having a day off on <lb/>Tuesday, so hope she will come then.   I liked Auntie B's <seg type="unclear">cuttings</seg>, it was <lb/>good of her to send them, I suppose <lb/>the war must change them, but <lb/><seg type="del">they</seg> the ones who have been out always <lb/>seem to be nicer than the recruits we <lb/>get in the wards sometimes. It seems <lb/>to make them more thoughtful and <lb/>gentle instead of making them harder.   Here is quite a nice little chapel <lb/>attached to the hospital and we sometimes <lb/>get permission to go in the mornings if <lb/>we are not too busy in the wards.   I want to thank you all ever so <lb/>much for the Xmas money mamma has <lb/>forwarded to me. I don't think we really <lb/>ought to have any Christmas presents <lb/>this year, it is too good of you yo give it.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2626_img_2051_3"/>
             It is splendid about Sam, Aunt Margaret<lb/>must be pleased.  I hope you aren't working too hard at<lb/>the old S.T.S.F.A. I do think you have done<lb/>more than your share of it, and that<lb/>somebody else should take your place now<lb/>and let you have a rest.  It will be funny having Xmas here in—<lb/>stead of at home. Some of the nurses are<lb/>getting up theatricals and singing for the<lb/>patients and staff.  Please thank Auntie <seg type="unclear">E.</seg> for her nice letter<lb/>and best love to all you dear aunts,<lb/>I should like to pop in and pay you a visit.  Ever your loving niece<lb/>Celia   I enclose 7<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> stamps and keep<lb/>4<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> for the next copy.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>