<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1336">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 13 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) expressing his love for May.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1336</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1661">National Health Insurance Commission, Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1336_img_665_1"  type="Letter"  url="f5f4ba27ba6555319e11eeb9717e0403.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1336_img_665_2"  type="Letter"  url="3aea242b7b85d2252071659049f656d4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1336_img_665_1"/>
              Easter. I芒聙聶m sure you will all be <lb/>busy in the next four weeks and I <lb/>wouldn芒聙聶t like to be keeping you <lb/>from your work, entertaining a silly <lb/>love芒聙聰sick ass like me so I won芒聙聶t <lb/>speak about it anymore unless you <lb/>do it beforehand. Glad to hear <lb/>Christy is improving so much. <lb/>I suppose Kerrigan was only making <lb/>a big fellow of himself by making <lb/>him out to be so bad. Hope <lb/>everyone at home is well also at <lb/>Lockardstown I am writing to Mrs <lb/>S. today. Bad job about Johnnie. <lb/>Ask him can I help him at all <lb/>when you see him. Give my regards <lb/>to everyone. I send you my <lb/>warmest and sincerest love <lb/>and kiss your dear sweet <lb/>face and hands a thousand <lb/>times. <lb/>your happy husband to be <lb/>James    NATIONAL HEALTH COMMISSION (IRELAND),  PEMBROKE HOUSE,  UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN.    13th March, 1916.   My dearest love,   I was delighted to see by your letter of yesterday that <lb/>you were pleased with the watch and with my taste in the selection. <lb/>As a matter of fact my one regret in the matter is that I couldn芒聙聶t afford <lb/>to buy you one much more in keeping with my love for you. As regards <lb/>my taste being better in the watch than in the wife, I wish to remark <lb/>(as Bret Harte would say) that anyone could get that same watch or <lb/>a better one any day in the week for a few pounds whereas there is only <lb/>one May Fay and money couldn芒聙聶t buy her. She was fool enough to sell <lb/>herself (or rather give herself away) without properly realising her own value. <lb/>That芒聙聶s why I shall always be inclined to reproach myself for taking you at a <lb/>mean disadvantage because you were too innocent to value yourself enough and <lb/>foolish enough to value me too highly. However as I have already said <lb/>in my last letter I do love and honour you to the best of my poor power <lb/>for your dear goodness and sweetness and with God芒聙聶s help I芒聙聶ll try to manage <lb/>so that you may never too much regret confiding in me. I need hardly <lb/>say how much I feel proud and glad and flattered to see from your letters <lb/>and your manner to me that you do think of me and that you do love <lb/>me  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1336_img_665_2"/>
              me 芒聙聰 perhaps even a good deal. I can never understand why it should <lb/>be so but I hug myself with pleasure that it is so.  I shall be looking forward with great interest to your letter <lb/>of to芒聙聰morrow morning (I hope) with a full and true account of what <lb/>happened at the Kelly芒聙聶s party on Sunday. I am quite sure you will be <lb/>able to keep your end up with Mrs Duffy. When you put on that consequential <lb/>air of yours, it requires quite a lot of courage I should say to resist it. In <lb/>my case anyhow I find it very difficult to resist you at any time but <lb/>I think the emotion produced is not fear so much as something very different. <lb/>I always want to take you in my arms and smother you with kisses. <lb/>By the way talking of kisses I must say that I have formed a very high opinion <lb/>of the intelligence and good sense of Father Flynn, your recent confessor, <lb/>and I feel quite grateful to him for making your tender conscience easy <lb/>on that score. The prospect sounds so promising and <hi rend="underline">appetising</hi> that I <lb/>feel almost inclined to swoop down on you some weekend soon and take <lb/>advantage of the greater generosity which I presume you are now prepared to <lb/>show me. To tell the honest truth, I芒聙聶m beginning to feel the want of you more <lb/>and more every day and <hi rend="underline">worse</hi> and <hi rend="underline">worse</hi> so that I very much doubt if I <lb/>shall be able to hang on till Easter without seeing and kissing your dear <lb/>face again and hearing your voice. So don芒聙聶t be surprised if you hear of <lb/>my arrival in the country about the end of the month. Seriously however, <lb/>if you wouldn芒聙聶t like me to come 芒聙聰 I mean if you think it would be better <lb/>for me not to come, I will wait and possess my soul in patience until  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>