<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3107">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 2 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Peter Mooney was born 5 February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne, Co Meath. Orphaned at age 7, he and his sister Katie (b. 1884) were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. 

He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This  letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Mooney Family Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3107</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1915-11-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1889">Ballincollig, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1461">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1970</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3107_img_2514_1"  type="Letter"  url="1107fb9538ae21a652511e8e784169bd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3107_img_2514_2"  type="Letter"  url="2dd18cb2a90a646e5a3e67c2c41567dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3107_img_2514_3"  type="Letter"  url="21d47f0e7144fc666ea05dca796d7eab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3107_img_2514_4"  type="Letter"  url="0b9da14e22f3486f9dbff8d559c1cab4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3107_img_2514_1"/>
             Nov 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1915   Dear Katie   I was glad to <lb/>receive your letter this <lb/>morning. I also got one <lb/>from John Farrell &amp; James <lb/>Reilly. It does me good <lb/>to know that they think <lb/>of me. As I lie in bed <lb/>at night I think of those <lb/>at home. My arm went <lb/>on all right and I will <lb/>not have to be done <lb/>again. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3107_img_2514_2"/>
             2) <lb/>When you are writing <lb/>again send me on some <lb/>corn plaster as I will <lb/>want some now. Tell <lb/>the Priests at the Station <lb/>that I was asking for <lb/>them. I am getting more <lb/>used to life here every <lb/>day. It will come very <lb/>easy when we get over <lb/>the drill. John Farrell <lb/>says he does not like <lb/>going over to Caulstown <lb/>as he thinks he should <lb/>see me. Keep Poor old <lb/>Barry well fed I know <lb/>he can eat a lot  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3107_img_2514_3"/>
             3) <lb/>We will have a good time <lb/>all to-gether when I get <lb/>home at Christmas. Tell <lb/>all the lads that I expect <lb/>to have a good time with <lb/>them on St. Stephens Night. <lb/>I hope they keep hurling <lb/>every Sunday in the field. <lb/>I am glad that <sic>Charly</sic> <lb/>is minding the Horses <lb/> &amp; Greyhounds so well.    Tell him I will not forget <lb/>to him. Tell him to keep <lb/>the place nice &amp; clean that <lb/>I said it. I did not <lb/>write to Tommy yet
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3107_img_2514_4"/>
            but will soon. I have an <lb/>awful lot of writing to do. <lb/>I will write to all in turns. <lb/>Has Paddy learned to ride <lb/>the <sic>Bycycle</sic> yet I hope <lb/>he has. Tell Mary &amp; Joe <lb/>Fitzpatrick that I was <lb/>asking for them. I am <lb/>sure you are getting on well <lb/>without me now. Do not <lb/>fret for me. You make <lb/>me happy when I know <lb/>that you are  all  happy &amp; well.    Good Bye &amp; God Bless you all   Your Fond Brother   Peter Mooney 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>