<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1534">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff to Lady Clonbrock, 12 August, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs. Arthur Goff</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff, honorary secretary of the Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation, to Augustine Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Mrs. Goff had a similar role to Lady Clonbrock in the Irish Women&#39;s Association, formed in London in the Spring of 1915 for the purpose of providing food and comforts for prisoners of war belonging to Irish Regiments. 
Mrs. Goff supplies parcels to Royal Dublin Fusiliers POWs in Bulgaria. Here she is writing about a Connaught Ranger she has been looking after at the request of his wife. Mrs. Goff is asking Lady Clonbrock if she may continue supplying this prisoner.
A note on the back of the letter, apparently written by Lady Clonbrock, indicates that she has written to the IWA to clear the request.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1534</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1236">Mrs. Arthur Goff</persName>
              <date>1916-08-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0673">Belfort House, Dundrum, Co. Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1534_img_1002_1"  type="Letter"  url="7277bf4b1407f0824ce96738b5c0b3ca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1534_img_1002_2"  type="Letter"  url="e82c8f5a79b634248ee59e09c2c46d70.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1534_img_1002_1"/>
              Hon. Sec., <lb/>MRS ARTHUR GOFF, <lb/>Belfort House, Dundrum, <lb/>Co.Dublin.   Aug 12 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>19   Dundrum, <lb/>Co. Dublin.   Dear Lady Clonbrock   I have been intending to write to you for some <lb/>time past <seg type="unclear">re</seg> the enclosed post-cards but have <lb/>been so pressed with work.   Mrs Andrews hearing that I had undertaken <lb/>the oul fun in Bulgaria came &amp; asked me <lb/>to send parcels to her husband also. So I have <lb/>been doing so since the middle of June.   She Subscribes herself 2/- a week.   I dont know what arrangements you have <lb/>about the Connaught-Rangers in Bulgaria <lb/>but if you will allow me I will be glad to <hi rend="underline">keep</hi> <lb/>on this man especially as his wife wishes it.   Sincerely yours   Elli Marie Goff   4922 <seg type="unclear">P</seg>. G. Andrews <lb/><seg type="unclear">P.A.W. 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> C. R</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Zalar Bagardyk</seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1534_img_1002_2"/>
             Wrote to I.W.A. to ask if <lb/>Pte. G. Andrews <lb/>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>C.R. Bulgaria <lb/>may be   <lb/><seg type="unclear">S</seg> Mrs. Goff  <lb/> not once
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>