<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0290">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Phillip Miles to Robert Chalmers, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Phillip Miles</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from William Phillip Miles (b. 1878) to Robert Chalmers. In the letter Miles notes a forthcoming re-arrangement of staff in the Dublin administration offices. He goes on to apply for any position which may be suitable for a man with a special education for figures. Miles also provides a brief description of himself, stating that he is working for the Earl of Dudley, William Humble Ward (1867-1932). Miles states he is unsuitable for military duty due to a slight lameness. Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>National Archive of Ireland-Chief Secretary&#39;s Office-Registered Papers, NAI/CSO/RP/1916/5611/8356/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/290</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0118">William Phillip Miles</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0355">183 Henwick Road, Worcester, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0890">Dublin Castle</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0290_img_1493_1"  type="Letter"  url="3efad5ffb304f5816839ee945a7dbe67.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0290_img_1493_1"/>
              Ackn <seg type="unclear">&amp; state</seg> that<lb/> no <seg type="unclear">rearragts</seg> are in contemplation<lb/> which would be likely to meet his case    183. Henwick Road  Worcester, England.    13th. May, 1916.    Sir Robert Chalmers,  Dublin Castle.   Sir,   During the forthcoming re-arrangement of the staffs<lb/> of the Administrative Offices of the Irish Government<lb/> Departments, may I most respectfully request that the following<lb/> application for appointment to one of the suitable vacancies <lb/>may receive your favorable consideration.  I bet to make application for appointment to a vacancy<lb/> in any office in which a good all round clerk, with a<lb/> special qualification for figures, is required.  I am of Irish extraction, 38 years of age, married, total<lb/> abstainer, of good education &amp; appearance &amp; certified<lb/> medically unfit for military service owing to a slight<lb/> lameness.  I am in the employ of the Earl of Dudley at his<lb/> Estate Office at Great Witley, near Worcester. His Lordship would, if desired, support my application.  I shall be glad to forward testimonials &amp; to give<lb/> all necessary detailed particulars respecting myself at your<lb/> request. <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir,<lb/> Your obedient servant,  W. P. Miles. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>