<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5252">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Victoria Mary Tyrrell 21, March, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell has recently arrived at the front and mentions having attended a Y.M.C.A. concert.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5252</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1632">Royal Irish Rifles, 8th Infantry Base Depot, Havre, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5252_img_None_1"  url="daacbfc64059e3bcdaf46bbdbd0372df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5252_img_None_2"  url="e794fafa5a2b0a88f2ff1b31448f0546.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5252_img_None_3"  url="57c5bbdbe325515f872a145927c5ba58.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5252_img_0_1"/>
              Roy. Ir. Rifles<lb/>8<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Inft. Base<lb/>Defot<lb/>Havre    Tuesday March 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>    My dearest Minnie   The above is my address<lb/>for the present and any letter so<lb/>addressed will find me. We<lb/>got here today and may be here<lb/>any length of time. We are bound<lb/>for the first  Batt.  I think but don't<lb/>know. We went on board at<lb/>Southampton at 10 P.M. and got<lb/>a berth and went to bed. I slept 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5252_img_0_2"/>
             above Healy and assured him<lb/>if I said Look out I meant<lb/>Look out. However no need as<lb/>crossing was very smooth. We<lb/>did not leave till 6 A.M. and<lb/>got in at 1 P.M. We had<lb/>great fun making the Wales<lb/>understand us. However, in the<lb/>end &amp; we got something like<lb/>snail sausage which was no<lb/>nice. We are in a huge camp<lb/>here outside Havre and have<lb/>quite a nice mess and nice little<lb/>canvas tents which hold two and<lb/>I am with another R.I. Rifleman  from 4th Bn who seems very nice  It is now 9 P.M. and we<lb/>have just been to a Y.M.C.A.<lb/>concert which was splendid. We<lb/>are very comfortable here. Far<lb/>better than I thought.  The post goes out at noon<lb/>every day so this won't go<lb/>till tomorrow.  We had very smooth crossings<lb/>both times. We have got all our<lb/>baggage with us so far and<lb/>no objection to weight.  My name on bottom left<lb/>corner of both letters and envelope is       
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5252_img_0_3"/>
             for benefit of the censor.  No news and I will write<lb/>often as letters don't need stamps   With best love<lb/>Your most affec brother<lb/>Willie 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>