<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1204">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr William Keary to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 6 October 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W. Keary</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr William Keary (1881-1958) to Fr Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the news Fr John Fitzgibbon&#39;s death. Fr. Thomas V Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/30, IJA/CHPI/21/30</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1204</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0303">W. Keary</persName>
              <date>1918-10-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1204_img_3888_1"  type="Letter"  url="eaf38a68d2092411f2402647b4433f32.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1204_img_3888_1"/>
                Sunday 6-10-18    Dear Fr. Provinical P.C. <lb/>Many thanks for your kind letter. <lb/>I was on leave when Fr. Fitzgibbon was killed, and <lb/>when I returned I found that his effects had <lb/>all been sent to his <hi rend="underline">home</hi> address (to his father). <lb/>He was so much loved and respected that great <lb/>care was taken that <hi rend="underline">all</hi> (clothes, altar-kit, etc.) was sent. <lb/>It must indeed be a great loss to your Reverence; <lb/>for I cannot tell you what a loss he is to me. <lb/>Apart from out intimate friendship, he was such a <lb/>splendid organiser, had so tactful a <hi rend="underline">way</hi>, and was so <lb/>zealous and hardworking; and yet was so kindly and <lb/>encouraging to us younger Chaplains that I feel quite <lb/>'at sea' without him. May he rest in peace.I have <lb/>said 4 <seg type="unclear">Masses</seg> for his soul, and hope to say another soon. <lb/>Mass is a sore treat in the rough and tumble life <lb/>we are leading during the present advance. <seg type="closer"> Yours very respectfully in Christ,  W. Keary S.J.   16 Field Ambulance,  B.E.F.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>