<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5747">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 15 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
This letter is some banter between the couple</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5747</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-04-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5747_img_847_1"  type="Letter"  url="2fab88e108d759e7f391d3ca0fcdac4c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5747_img_847_2"  type="Letter"  url="45082380d2ca4098cf63c7850634b857.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5747_img_847_3"  type="Letter"  url="f3c620fb34e269da66585629601c8460.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5747_img_847_1"/>
             15 April, 1916.   My Dearest Love,   I was delighted to get your <lb/>letter today but you needn't have <sic>apologised</sic> <lb/>for writing on Thursday. I hadn't the last <lb/>hope of a letter yesterday morning so I wasn't <lb/>disappointed (blessed are they that expect nothing) <lb/>as I know very well that the chances were <lb/>very much against you being able either <lb/>to write or to post even if you cared <lb/>with. I'm sorry to hear that Mrs Seery <lb/>was nasty to my little girl the other evening. <lb/>I’m sure she was a bit worrying all right and 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5747_img_847_2"/>
             I know very well that her jokes cut pretty deeply<lb/>at times if you mind her but I hope you<lb/>won’t pay too much attention to what she says<lb/>as her bark is always worse than her bite. I<lb/>must face her whatever happens when I go<lb/>down about the best man as I can’t put it<lb/>off any longer. I hope she will take it reasonable<lb/>anyway. I was sorry to see that you take<lb/>me so seriously to heart although of course it<lb/>flatters me very much. I thought I had enough<lb/>on my conscience when I diddled you into<lb/>agreeing to marry me but if I have in<lb/>addition the load on my conscience of<lb/>making you give up all your prayers and<lb/>other good works I don’t know what will<lb/>become of me. I hope it won’t be quite so<lb/>bad as that and that you will be content<lb/>to go and do the stations with me on Good<lb/>Friday and be good and loving and sweet<lb/>afterwards as you always otherwise are. Sometimes<lb/>I don’t know when you talk that way whether<lb/>you are joking or not or whether you really do<lb/>scruple being fond of me or kissing me with<lb/>the freedom and frankness which is only reasonable<lb/>in the case of us two. I don’t see what harm<lb/>you do even if you did think of me and<lb/>love me on Good Friday as well as on any other<lb/>day. So far as I am concerned my conscience<lb/>is not only quite clear in loving and thinking<lb/>about you but I know and am convinced as 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5747_img_847_3"/>
             never was of anything before that my only<lb/>hope of salvation lies in loving you and thinking<lb/>of you always. I am always a better and a<lb/>cleaner man when I think of you and I<lb/>intend to cling to that last straw like the<lb/>drowning man. In view of what I say, I<lb/>imagine it will be easy enough for you<lb/>to boss me even without the poker but I hope<lb/>you will not be too severe although I’d<lb/>certainly advise you to be firm. Moll &amp; Nora<lb/>got back all right but they didn’t have much<lb/>news for us. Things here are very quiet<lb/>and nothing at all interesting happening. Give<lb/>my regards to all and with my warmest<lb/>and deepest love to my dear and darling.   Always your loving &amp; devoted<lb/>James   <hi rend="underline"></hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>