<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1450">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Scott Alexander to Augustine Birrell, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Scott Alexander</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Scott Alexander to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), the Chief Secretary for Ireland. Alexander is offering his skills to the British Government. He claims to be a powerful speaker and holds the ability to entice people to sign up for the British Army.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/4172</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1450</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1415">Scott Alexander</persName>
              <date>1916-03-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1353">24 Buckingham Street, Strand, W.C., London, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1868">House of Commons, London S.W., United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1450_img_879_1"  type="NULL"  url="6d07f422810d299b7ca859de3a202040.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1450_img_879_2"  type="NULL"  url="04f95ad725d9da3e11e544414561036f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1450_img_879_1"/>
                24, Buckingham Street,  Strand. W.C.    3rd March 1916.    Mr. Birbell.  Chief Secretary of State for Ireland.  House of Commons. S.W.   Sir,   I wish to place my services at the <lb/>disposal of the Government.   For the last 25 years I have been <lb/>controlling large bodies of people, as <lb/>organiser of Exhibitions, Fetes, Theatrical <lb/>and Variety Companies &amp;c. &amp;c. so am used to <lb/>vast crowds of people, keeping them in order <lb/>addressing them &amp;c.   My business has taken me through nearly <lb/>every town and village in Great Britain and <lb/>Ireland as well as in S.Africa and Australia.   I have been (till last Saturday) running <lb/>some important Theatrical Ventures, but <lb/>owing to the calling up of the young men, <hi rend="underline">both Artistes and Audience</hi> I felt that my brains <lb/>may be better employed in the service of my <lb/>Country, where men with experience such as <lb/>mine are rare, and might put to a more <lb/>useful purpose during the Crisis.   My age is 46: my father was a distinguished <lb/>Commander in the Royal Navy, who won the <lb/>Legion of Honour during the Crimean War.   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1450_img_879_2"/>
              During the early stages of this war, <lb/>I gave recruiting speeches at various Theatres. <lb/>At the Hippodrome, Stoke-on-Trent, I succeeded <lb/>in getting 13 members of the audience to come <lb/>on to the stage and enlist, whilst many others <lb/>went to the Town Hall the following morning <lb/>and enlisted also.   I was a powerful speaker, a skilled organiser <lb/>and possess a thorough knowledge of the <lb/>British Temperament.   If you can make any use of my services, <lb/>I will be glad of an early reply.  <seg type="closer"> Your truly  Scott Alexander </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>