<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1460">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Éamon de Valera to Jack, 9 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Éamon de Valera</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Éamon de Valera (1882-1975). This letter was written after his dearth sentence had been relayed to him but before it was commuted. He is writing to an unidentified family friend advising him that he believes he will be executed - something he would find easier, were it not for his &#39;poor wife and helpless little ones&#39;. He asks Jack to help his wife with decisions relating to the children in later life.Éamon de Valera had joined the Irish Volunteers in 1913 and was adjutant to Thomas MacDonagh (1878-1916), Dublin Brigade commandant. He went on to command forces at Bolands Mill during the Rising and was the most senior participant to escape execution. De Valera would go on to become one of the most influential figures in Ireland&#39;s 20th century.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/539/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1460</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0274">Éamon de Valera</persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Jack</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1460_img_910_1"  type="Letter"  url="97c194aa1186eedf0cecd6454fd80e8f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1460_img_910_1"/>
                Kilmainham Prison    May 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   My dear Jack,   I am to be shot for my part in <lb/> the Rebellion.  It would be easy to die but for <lb/> the poor wife left with her helpless <lb/> little ones.  Should you find it possible in <lb/> later years to advise her as to what <lb/> she <sic>shd.</sic> do with the children I <lb/> know you will do it.  Remember me to your mother, <lb/><seg type="unclear">Sherwin</seg> &amp; the others. Pray for me. <seg type="closer"> Dev. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>