<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5219">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A.B. Browne to Ellen Jnr Daly, 11 April 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A B Browne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/9/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5219</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0697">A B Browne</persName>
              <date>1923-04-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1792">21 Castle Street, Tralee, Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Jnr Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5219_img_None_1"  url="5a1ae96fc5f6196a9b557b7dcbef0294.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5219_img_None_2"  url="6c4eeb3ad3ab444c73569844bf1b1a7a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5219_img_0_1"/>
              11th April 1923   Ellie<seg type="unclear">.</seg> Just after Con leaving  on Tuesday evg. I had a letter from Tom. You will  be pleased to hear . He's very well.  T G  and   you  are all his  trouble . How  you  are taking  Charlie's RIP death. and asked  me as a favour   to tell him. So I wrote a long letter and parcel  to him.  You  will have a letter from him Next <hi rend="underline"></hi>Week.  So Cheer Up. &amp; also told him if he would like  to get Charlie's last letters. May would give me  a copy of them to send them on.or May can do it  herself. I have no account of Willie . The two                   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5219_img_0_2"/>
             were always with me. I often think. How changed  everything is for us all. But may he first <hi rend="superscript"></hi>not.  When I used to be above in the kitchen and the Boys  helping me to get steak for the dinner as they used  to be hungry after school. <seg type="unclear"></seg> Ellie i have no   more news to-day.  The children have gone back to school.  With foremost love to May and girls and not forgetting  Con's &amp; <seg type="unclear">fru</seg> our share.   Truly Sincerly  <seg type="unclear"></seg>   A B Browne  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>