<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5928">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John J. O'Leary of the Irish Relief Fund Bazaar, 4 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John J. Murphy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John J. O&#39;Leary of the Irish Relief Fund Bazaar&#39;s asking for contributions for the upcoming bazaar. The proceeds from which would go to the families of the men who were executed, imprisoned or deported since the Easter week rebellion.John J. O&#39;Leary was President of the committee of the Irish Relief Fund Bazaar.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>American Irish Historical Society</repository>
                  <collection>AIHS4106b, AIHS4106b</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5928</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1409">John J. Murphy</persName>
              <date>1916-10-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0335">New York, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5928_img_2364_1"  type="Letter"  url="8c65dcc6e5b857fc900882f1eacd5e58.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5928_img_2364_1"/>
                October 4, 1916   Dear Sir:   We respectfully beg to call your attention to the<lb/> IRISH RELIEF FUND BAZAAR, which is to be held at Madison Square<lb/> Garden, New York City, October 14th to 22nd.  The entire proceeds of that Bazaar, without the de-<lb/> duction of a single dollar for expenses, will be devoted to the<lb/> immediate relief of the destitute dependents of the men executed,<lb/> imprisoned or deported since the Easter week rebellion of the <lb/> Irish people.  The necessity of such relief appears clearly from the<lb/> excerpts from the report of John J. Murphy, Commissioner of the<lb/> American Relief Committee, who has just returned from Ireland,<lb/> and which we beg to enclose.  We feel that the American people, who have never<lb/> yet turned a deaf ear to an appeal in behalf of the unfortunate,<lb/> will not fail to heed this urgent call.  May we, therefore, ask you to aid this Bazaar by a <lb/> contribution, as you prefer, in money or goods, which can be<lb/> disposed of at the Bazaar.  Checks can be made payable to Thomas Hughes Kelly,<lb/> for which please find addresses envelope enclosed.  Goods can be sent to Headquarters of the Bazaar at<lb/> 1482 Broadway. <seg type="closer"> Very truly yours,  John J O'Leary  PRESIDENT OF BAZAAR<lb/> Hon. Henry J Murphy,<lb/> Henry von Schuckmann,<lb/> CHAIRMEN OF COMMITTEE ON DONATIONS </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>