<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5177">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Daly to May Daly, 12 April 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Daly  </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/6/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5177</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1009">Susan Daly  </persName>
              <date>1923-04-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2040">Hillford Avenue, Lexlip, Kildare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">May Daly  </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5177_img_None_1"  url="627cc500e6bb402e2c567edf93255cdd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5177_img_None_2"  url="040066e6cf2ff414123c0090c4f09279.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5177_img_None_3"  url="e6622ab44146bee31de84bd8cf04f423.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5177_img_None_4"  url="9dfc068e33bbef390f6fc4acd934caac.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5177_img_0_1"/>
              Do you get 'Eire' at all<lb/>lately if not I will<lb/>keep the copies for you   Leixlip:<lb/> Thursday.   P41/6/2/3  <seg type="foreign"> A Mháire a chroodhe </seg>  I have let<lb/>your letter go so long without<lb/>answering that you must<lb/>think I was not going to write<lb/>to you at all. Did my mother<lb/>get the card I sent from<lb/><seg type="unclear">Lucan</seg> on Thurs. I had a great<lb/>drive to Skerries that evening. it<lb/>is 19 miles from Dublin. The<lb/>hotel is the best in Skerries and<lb/>it was in the hall there that 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5177_img_0_2"/>
             2  Harry Boland was murdered.<lb/>They went to live there on Tues.<lb/>I hadn't a chance of writing<lb/>since. I went in to O'Mahony's<lb/>Sunday evening and went in<lb/>to college Mon. evening after<lb/>calling to Dunleary to see S.O. Brien.<lb/>I saw Jim Larkin coming off<lb/>the boat. He is a fine looking<lb/>man and I believe that he has<lb/>got a large part of Labour <seg type="unclear">with</seg><lb/>him and it is likely that there<lb/>will be a split between himself<lb/>and Johnson. I got over the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5177_img_0_3"/>
             3  exams alright but I didn't get<lb/>off till yesterday evening<lb/>and I must go back for good<lb/>on Sunday. I called on Nora<lb/>Ring yesterday and Margaret<lb/>Galvin and I spent a few hours<lb/>there. They have a flat in<lb/>Harcourt St. but the <seg type="unclear">mother</seg><lb/>was out looking for a house<lb/>and so I didnt meet her. Nora<lb/>and Jenny are both very nice<lb/>girls. I had a letter from Mollie<lb/>a few days ago and one from<lb/>M. <seg type="unclear">Corkery</seg> yesterday. Did I say 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5177_img_0_4"/>
             in my last letter that I had a letter<lb/>from Josie? How is everybody at<lb/>home. when writing again give<lb/>me all the news. I don't know<lb/>how many have asked <seg type="unclear">mem </seg><lb/>cards of Charlie. Today Moll <seg type="unclear">O Brien</seg><lb/>wrote and asked for one and<lb/>Sr. Colmcille in Omagh. Jenny Galvin's<lb/>sister also wants one. Florrie is to<lb/>type more copies of his letters. Florrie<lb/>has this week off as she is not<lb/>very well. Now I must write to Tom<lb/>and Willie. I got <seg type="unclear">Willie's letter</seg> from<lb/>Charlie and am sending it to him.<lb/>I must tell Tom that I cannot 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>