<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2237">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Vernon, 15 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924), to Vernon. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland. 
The letter concerns a case regarding the Lendrums on the Colebrooke estate. The letter then discusses the matter of Home Rule, stating that James Craig (1871-1940) and Edward Carson (1854-1935), Unionist leader, informed him that any opposition to the six county scheme i.e. the partition of Ireland, would be met with alienation by other British parties. The letter also discusses John Redmond (1856-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, and his view that the scheme is only temporary for the war period, however Montgomery also notes Carson&#39;s determination that the six counties are excluded from Irish Home Rule. The letter also comments on the exclusion of Donegal, Cavan and Monaghan from the scheme, going on to comment on Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), prime minister, and his ability as leader.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingbourne Papers, D/627/429/32</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2237</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Vernon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2237_img_1681_1"  type="Letter"  url="9a3b2e716f08c967710e7201fb53be0f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2237_img_1681_2"  type="Letter"  url="40ce791491d59191e282a2ea1ca3b269.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2237_img_1681_3"  type="Letter"  url="2501d001d0d3ee8b540e90dc41346ab5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2237_img_1681_1"/>
            Copy  13th June, 1916.   My dear Vernon,   Many thanks for your letter and for the nomination for <lb/>Miss Lendrum. I troubled you in this matter after George Brooke <lb/>had written to say he did not think he could do anything. I <lb/>had applied to him first, as these Lendrums were tenants on the <lb/>Colebrooke estate, and George Brooke always professes to take an <lb/>interest in the pit from which he was digged. George Brooke, <lb/>however, told me last Thursday that he had  had  a form sent to Miss <lb/>Lendrum. I am writing to Lendrum to tell him if his daughter <lb/>receives two forms to fill that she should fill them both, and <lb/>in sending the second explain that she is the same person as <lb/>sent the first. I hope this will not create any inconvenience.   We had a choice of evils before us at Belfast yesterday. <lb/>I think we choose the least. If the information given us in <lb/>private by Carson and Craig as to the condition of public opinion <lb/>including Unionist opinion in England  is correct  it is clear that whatever <lb/>party first placed difficulties in the way of this preposterous <lb/>settlement would alienate the sympathy of all parties in Great <lb/>Britain. We did the best we could; but as Redmond says he <lb/>understands the proposal to be for a temporary arrangement during <lb/>the war, and Carson says he will have nothing to say to it unless <lb/>it is understood that the six counties are permanently excluded <lb/>from the provisions of the Home Rule Act, I do not see how the <lb/>negotiations are to go on; and we may perhaps be made responsible.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2237_img_1681_2"/>
            <lb/>for their rejection after all. I am afraid the Nationalists <lb/>and Radicals are much clevere r  than we are. The case of Cavan, <lb/>Donegal &amp; Monaghan is a difficult and distressing one. <lb/>Your protest is very well worded. I hope the action of the <lb/>representatives of the six counties in taking the responsibility <lb/>for an arrangement leaving them outside the excluded Ulster will <lb/>not be very bitterly resented. What you have lost or given up <lb/>is a big thing as regards sentiment, but in substance it was <lb/>really not worth twopence. We could have done nothing for you, <lb/>even before the war upset all our calculations. It was well <lb/>known that General Richardson held that if it came to fighting <lb/>the first thing he would have to do would be to withdraw all <lb/>the Covenanters from these three counties within the borders <lb/>of the six.   The choice we had was really between all Ireland being placed <lb/>under a Home Rule Parliament, or all Ireland minus six counties <lb/>and I believe, odious as the position is, that we <sic>choose</sic> right. <lb/>What is difficult to understand is (1) how the American pressure <lb/>to which the Cabinet has unanimously yielded can be strong enough <lb/>to justify their action, and (2) how it is possible that the <lb/>sort of Home Rule it is proposed to give can satisfy the feeling <lb/>that is at the back of this pressure.   If the country was under the government of a great man <lb/>instead of an Asquith some other way would surely have been found <lb/>to meet the American and other pressure: as it is Carson, who is
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2237_img_1681_3"/>
            <lb/>not the man to be frightened by bug bears seems to regard the <lb/>forces at the back of Lloyd George's proposal to be for the <lb/>moment irresistible.   I am sure you know how deeply we sympathise with you <lb/>about your sailor boy. I would have written had I not felt <lb/>that letters of condolence are terribly futile things under <lb/>such circumstances.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>