<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4223">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 15 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968).  Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/62</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4223</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4223_img_3593_1"  type="Letter"  url="a727609cc20ccb664e4ef57331880b9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4223_img_3593_2"  type="Letter"  url="c5e35e6461c175afb164c7f226ea5ba6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4223_img_3593_3"  type="Letter"  url="b6d434aead4f41f3778d3d4911381466.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4223_img_3593_4"  type="NULL"  url="945d65f0a71d68375e458097eeeff433.JPG"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4223_img_3593_5"  type="NULL"  url="05698427d1a7f8cf8d1146f8620d9907.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4223_img_3593_6"  type="NULL"  url="b095144a01386307267780c54cf85b55.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4223_img_3593_1"/>
             15 Nov   My dear pr.   Only time for a few lines as I <lb/> have been out all day with the bombers. On <lb/> my return I found Gen' Bols &amp; Col Hudson waiting <lb/> to see 'me'. Both very friendly &amp; as usual for <lb/> the time I at any rate ( &amp; I think they also) <lb/> forgot the difference in our respective ranks, &amp; had a nice <seg type="unclear">buck</seg>. We shall stop here <hi rend="superscript">at x</hi> another week <lb/> &amp; then remain in sight of our church spires <lb/> or towns. I won't say which for fear of giving <lb/> our position away!   I wish I could be with you tomorrow but
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4223_img_3593_2"/>
            know the p r will make a wise decision.   I do not think the Comforts Commitee sounds much <lb/> of a success at present but if the p r takes it up know <lb/> it will get a better chance especially if Mrs B works <lb/> with her. On the other hand if you get a good <lb/> offer of work which will not take too much out <lb/> of you &amp; is really helpful to the nation I shall <lb/> not be surprised if you take this. I won't advise <lb/> either way as it is unsafe to do so from this <lb/> distance.    I like to see the various big doctors chasing <lb/> the p v !, but grow anxious sometimes lest they <lb/> use her for experimental purposes not to her own <lb/> good.   I am more than ever convinced that my plan
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4223_img_3593_3"/>
            is the right one for the Comforts Committee i e <lb/>to help the men to buy what they want &amp; not <lb/> to give them presents. We are to get <seg type="del">a</seg> plumpuddings <lb/> from the Daily News ! ! ! which has a fund for <lb/> the purpose for the army. This I cannot look upon <lb/> as disinterested on their part, &amp; in any case I think <lb/> our men can eat them with a quiet conscience.    No letter since the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which came <lb/>last night I am glad to get this, but look <lb/> forward to a bumper soon. By the way the <lb/> mail seems to be a very uncertain one so <lb/> you may expect big delays sometimes, even <lb/> if I am good in writing.   As regards funds I find that my messbill has
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4223_img_3593_4"/>
            every prospect of being by especially as it is won in <lb/>the porting system with £180 cook. I very much resent <lb/>this as I should like to feel I was doing all I could <lb/>to save for the loans. I wish our people would realise <lb/>this more, but the Govt don't put an example &amp; the <lb/>people have no guides.    Rubber has bounced up again I see &amp; this should <lb/>materially increase our income this year, but the reason <lb/>is done to the sudden demand for rubber trench boots <lb/>which will not last after the war, &amp; we must look <lb/>to a drop of another £1000 then. I sometimes wonder <lb/>if I am justified in not taking a chance of returning <lb/>to the army &amp; its pay, but it does mean as <lb/>much humiliation in store in future that I do <lb/>not want to do it unless the little pr feels that <lb/>she could not manage if things got very bad <lb/>later. Our right course now is to try &amp; help the
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4223_img_3593_5"/>
            loans to our <seg type="del">0</seg>utmost extent, so that as soon as <lb/> the terms are mentioned I hope you will <lb/> send out the pass book to me , but it won't be <lb/> much use doing so till we know your future <lb/> life.   If you wish to furnish a flat I am quite <lb/> agreeable to this, but may very possibly look on <lb/> that as a capital investment &amp; sell out to <lb/> meet it. I do not want to lessen or loan <lb/> contributions, tho' there is no hurry about it. <lb/>The pinch won't be felt till next year, &amp; I am <lb/> not sure it is not better for them who are willing <lb/> to subscribe , to hold back till then so that the screw
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4223_img_3593_6"/>
            may now be put on the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>.   Best of love. Have to <seg type="unclear">censor</seg>for <lb/> the mind     Wilfrid BSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>