<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3910">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J., 16 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-85-100</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3910</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-04-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1820">8th Royal Irish Fusiliers, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3910_img_3287_1"  type="Letter"  url="8fd6618794d30199f92ccffeaf0c88cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3910_img_3287_2"  type="Letter"  url="d3d607f7f75e9423f0cb5c1c02479a22.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3910_img_3287_1"/>
             Two lessons from experience at the Front   8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> R. Irish Fusiliers   16/4/16   My dear Child ,  I am beginning this letter this morning <lb/>how or when I shall finish it (or where!). At least let <lb/>me wish  you  every   grace &amp;   from our <lb/>Risen Lord, one being that you may more deeply <lb/> realise the meaning hidden in the words, "Ought <lb/>not Christ to <hi rend="underline">have suffered</hi> these things and so <lb/>enter into His glory." You have a good deal to <lb/>learn just now, dear child, bu it is all for Him, <lb/>He wishes it and so I leave you a happy man <lb/>though the tears may flow.   I have seen very clearly since I came out here <lb/>that Jesus wanted to teach me one lesson at <lb/>least ( I have written it also for you on the card), <lb/>and I think the "want of absolute submission to His Will" has <lb/>been the cause of much I have suffered. He asked me to <lb/>make the sacrifice of my life but I was unwilling. Not <lb/>indeed that in any sense I fear death (would not Heaven <lb/>be a welcome exchange?) but knowing what I do about <lb/>the state of the world, the millions to be saved, and how <lb/>little He is known or loved or thought about, I felt <lb/>it hard, very hard, to leave all that work there and go <lb/>to enjoy the happiness of His company. Then, too, my
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3910_img_3287_2"/>
            <lb/>mind is full of plans for His glory, and, <lb/>perhaps more than that, I know well that I have <lb/>not "done the work He gave me to do," that is I <lb/>have never fully lived the life He has so often <lb/>asked for and made clearly known to me because <lb/>I was too <seg type="unclear">arrogant</seg> and cowardly. That life, to <lb/>put it in a word, was to be one in which I <lb/>should "refuse Him no sacrifice He asked." You know <lb/>Jesus, my child, and that He is not afraid to <hi rend="underline">ask</hi>! <lb/>However grace has won the day and I think I can <lb/>say with truth that I have now no choice or will <lb/>except him — I have told Him he may <seg type="unclear">may</seg> do just as <lb/>He pleases with me and take all, even my life <lb/>This has brought great peace and a sense of great <lb/>security in the midst of <seg type="unclear">danger</seg> since I know I am <lb/>in He's hands. <seg type="unclear">In</seg> return He has made me see <lb/> that without this absolute abandonment to His pleasure, <lb/>without the breaking of one's own will a life of <lb/>contemplation as His <seg type="unclear">Victim</seg> is a farce. The <lb/> "perfect renunciation" may be easy but "without murmur <lb/> or complaint" is the real test of the true lover.   Another lesson I have learned<seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg>the powerful <lb/>weapon we have in prayer and how much His <lb/>Interests may be helped on at any moment of the <lb/>day, easily &amp; sincerely, Oh, how much we could all do <lb/>for Him and his Interests and how  many poor souls would be <lb/>saved daily if we only fill in the chinks of our <lb/>full lives with little aspirations. <lb/>No chance of writing more <hi rend="underline">underlined text</hi>off to the  for 16 days. <lb/>God bless you always.   From yours affectionately <seg type="unclear">in</seg> Him    W.D. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>