<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2995">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Countess Constance Markievicz to Madeleine ffrench-Mullen, 12 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Constance Markievicz</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Countess Constance Markievicz (1868-1927) to Madeleine ffrench-Mullen (1880-1944). Markievicz was a militant republican, a labour activist,  a suffragist and a politician. She was an executive member of the radical women&#39;s nationalist movement Inghinidhe na hÉireann, the nationalist Boy Scouts movement Na Fianna Éireann, the Irish Neutrality League, and the revolutionary socialist movement the Citizen Army. During Easter Week of 1916, Markievicz served as second-in-command of the St. Stephen&#39;s Green Citizen Army garrison. In 1918, she became the first woman to be elected to the British parliament, and in 1919, she became the second woman  in Europe to serve as a cabinet minister.

Madeleine ffrench-Mullen was a labour activist, a nationalist, and a life-long advocate on behalf of the poor. An early member of Inghinidhe na hÉireann, she was active in their campaign to provide school dinners for children. She served in the soup kitchen of Liberty Hall during the 1913 Lockout, served during Easter Week on the first aid staff of the Irish Citizen Army, and was afterwards interned in Kilmainham Gaol. In 1919, along with her lifelong friend Dr Kathleen Lynn (1874-1955), she co-founded Teach Ultain, the first hospital for young children in Ireland.

In this letter, Markievicz thanks ffrench-Mullen for a recent present, tells her that Mrs Clarke is doing wonderfully despite her poor health, and sends her love to Kathleen and Emer. She sends her thanks for cigarettes sent by Emer, and assures ffrench-Mullen that she (Markievicz) is doing well, having gained some weight and benefited from her &#34;enforced rest&#34;. Markievicz asserts that &#34;right must triumph in the end&#34;, and sends her love to &#34;you and yours and my soldier girls&#34;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Military Archives of Ireland, Br Allen Collection, Kathleen Lynn Collection, IE/AL/KL/1/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2995</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1231">Constance Markievicz</persName>
              <date>1916-08-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1064">Holloway Jail, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Madeleine ffrench-Mullen</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2995_img_2398_1"  type="Letter"  url="e6ec200d13c71e4a720def1a00d32125.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2995_img_2398_2"  type="Letter"  url="52534e1f0e29d00d318badcdb0332ba1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2995_img_2398_1"/>
             Holloway Jail  <hi rend="underline"> Aug.12 </hi>  My Dear Madeline  I loved your <lb/>present, &amp; it arrived up to date. Very<lb/>many thanks for it. We are <seg type="unclear">getting</seg><lb/> along all right, thanks for the many<lb/>parcels we recieve, &amp; are quite cheerful.<lb/> Mrs. Clarke is wonderful, with her bad<lb/> health, its marvellous how she sticks it<lb/>out at all. Give Kathleen &amp; Emer my<lb/>love &amp;thank Emer for fags she sent<lb/> me. I hope K. is well; I heard that she<lb/>was back from her holiday, but not<lb/>going about much. I am all right again
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2995_img_2398_2"/>
            <lb/>gone up in weight &amp;all the better for<lb/>my enforced rest! One feels too all<lb/>the time that God is good &amp; right<lb/> must triumph in the end, &amp; the<lb/>knowledge that we are much  use<lb/> here than anywhere else is most con<lb/>-soling. I could not write you before, so I<lb/>must answer letters   in their<lb/>turn as they come, 3 is such a small<lb/>allowance,&amp; our paper is so small - much<lb/> smaller than the mens of course!   Now goodbye much love to you &amp;yours<lb/> &amp; my Soldier girls (Rosie etc).       Constance de Markievicz   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>