<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0769">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 18 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968) In this letter, Spender goes into great detail describing the internal politics of the general staff with whom he works.Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/351</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/769</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0769_img_2300_1"  type="Letter"  url="33805ac6c92f73d635b0a4b44796b7cf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0769_img_2300_2"  type="Letter"  url="6368f9d4aa1c3559026c35c30e33ab37.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0769_img_2300_3"  type="Letter"  url="9706a30974739036475426f57c2c6c14.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0769_img_2300_4"  type="Letter"  url="f035c368110020d4e104a81580751236.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0769_img_2300_1"/>
                18 July   My Pr   Just back from a ride <lb/> on Fanny in which I went <lb/>wrong but quite enjoyed. <lb/>Sometimes I think she enjoys <lb/>a scamper with the bw as <lb/>as much as the pr. I won't say <lb/>which he best approves as <lb/>his companion ! No letter <lb/>last night but I did not expect <lb/>one on a Monday especially as <lb/>I was already one up.  I have no news yet of Reg <lb/>but may hear something <lb/> about him at the base if <lb/>he does not come up at once. <lb/>Nor have I any news of my <lb/>going to the 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which may not take place as we have <lb/>just changed our corps - for the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0769_img_2300_2"/>
              <lb/>9th time, I believe; since we <lb/>came out. I don't know our <lb/>new staff at all but wish <lb/>we had gone to the next corps <lb/>where I know all of them.  The Army Commander is <lb/>due here this morning, but <lb/>I don't expect I shall see <lb/>him, which is perhaps just <lb/>as well under the circumstance.    Farnham has had a <seg type="unclear">man</seg><lb/>from his regiment asking <lb/>for his early return. I know <lb/>he much regrets leaving us <lb/>now, &amp; his friendship with the GOC is a factor <lb/>which we shall greatly miss. <lb/><seg type="unclear">And</seg> his views were generally <lb/>sound on Ulster matters, &amp; I <lb/>doubt if Sanderson will show <lb/>the same tact from what I have <lb/>heard of him  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0769_img_2300_3"/>
              Gen' Powell &amp; Sir G both <lb/>wrote to the G asking him to <lb/>put their congratulations in <lb/>orders - the former several pages!  I must say I sympathize <lb/>with the G in this, &amp; I think <lb/>he is right in declining. It is a <lb/>little lacking in tact like the <lb/>publication of his &amp; my letters <lb/>without authority. Sir G also <lb/>published a UVF order with the <lb/>G's &amp; the former, who is very <lb/>bitter at the desertion of his <lb/>county - not unnaturally - &amp; <lb/>who wishes he had never <lb/>touched the UVF now is quite <lb/>furious. I think he is justified <lb/>&amp; that Sir G ought to have <lb/>realize this. I am writing a <lb/>line of caution to Sir G. Col <lb/>J.C would never have made <lb/>these mistakes. We get news <lb/>papers the same evening as  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0769_img_2300_4"/>
              <lb/>they are published now, &amp; letters <lb/>come with them but my <lb/><seg type="unclear">arrows</seg> are likely to be very <lb/>much delayed if I go to the <lb/>24 Div to help. I know their <lb/>GSO2 &amp; A man quite well <lb/>we are old pals so that it <lb/>won't be quite 'going among <lb/>strangers' not as if I were <lb/>leaving the Division altogether <lb/>as I expect it will be only for <lb/>3 weeks when the Div may <lb/> join me again. Still even <lb/>this is unpleasant as one's <lb/>position away from one's <lb/>own men is quite different, <lb/>as you will understand.  I don't like to hear of your <lb/>long office hours. Please feed <lb/>yourself well. You will need it <lb/>with this extra work now on. <seg type="closer"> Your bw  WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>