<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1340">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Louis Hahn to Roger Casement, 19 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A. Hahn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Corporal Louis Hahn to Roger Casement (1864-1916). Hahn&#39;s letter reports on the activities of the Irish Brigade in early November 1915 and refers specifically to a number of men found guilty of drunkenness. The Irish Brigade had been set up by Casement from Irish prisoners in German prisoner of war camps with the intention of assisting the fight for Irish freedom. The venture was ultimately unsuccessful.This letter is taken from a collection of letters, poems, articles and other documents of Roger Casement and his family covering his career in the British Diplomatic Service as well as his activities in the Irish Revolutionary movement, 1889-1945. Sir Roger Casement was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. Casement believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany. He spent eighteen months in Germany, arriving first as an envoy of Irish-American leaders, attempting to encourage Germany to support Irish separatist aspirations by providing arms. Casement succeeded in securing limited German support but his attempt to form a brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps to fight against Britain was largely unsuccessful. When it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sir Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, Ms. 13,085 /24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1340</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1416">A. Hahn</persName>
              <date>1915-11-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0605">Zossen, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0915">Berlin, Germany </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1340_img_677_1"  type="Letter"  url="cb27ad6ca5182f44bd9b2465066cf1bb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1340_img_677_2"  type="Letter"  url="2dc52fc9b4bec57f237409bbb4425da6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1340_img_677_1"/>
              R. in Berlin <hi rend="underline">19 Nov. 1915</hi>    Zossen,    15th November 1915.  <lb/>To <lb/>Sir Roger Casement.  Dear Sir,   I beg to forward you a report concerning <lb/> the affairs of the brigade for the last fortnight.   I am very sorry to say that this report will necessarily be a bad one for there have been cases of <sic>drunkness</sic> and gross insubordination.   In mine and Q.M. Sgt.Quinlisk's and Sgt.Dowling's <lb/>opinion these men, being aware of the fact that the brigade <lb/> may be for active service in the near future, are striving <lb/> by their bad conduct to remain in Germany and so <lb/> escape being sent out.  The names of the men guilty of those offences are : <lb/>Karpl. O'Mahoney (drunkenness and absence) <lb/>Private Ryan <lb/> ' Sweeney P. (drunkenness) <lb/> ' Holohan ( ' ) <lb/> ' Branden (insubordination) <lb/> ' McGrath T ( ' ) <lb/> ' McDonagh ( ' ) <lb/> ' Keogh.  At the same time that I furnish you with this <lb/> report, Herr General Schneider will also be furnished with a copy <lb/>of the same.  As I know that Herr General Schneider fully com <lb/>plies with all your orders which are transmitted through the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1340_img_677_2"/>
              <lb/>Kriegsministerium I would ask you to forward an <lb/>order through the Kriegsministerium requesting the <lb/>removal of these men. If they are allowed to <lb/>remain here their conduct and example will <lb/>be most detrimental to the moral and discipline <lb/>of the remainder of the men.  Hoping to have a communication soon from you re this matter I am <seg type="closer"> Very respectfully yours!  L Hahn, <lb/>Unteroffizier. <lb/>P.S. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Hon</seg> General Schneider has taken immediate action <lb/> about this matter by communicating with the Gefangener- <lb/> Inspection Berlin regarding immediate removal of <lb/> these men.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>