<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0051">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Circular Letter from Frank O'Donnell to the Secretary of each registered Company (National Volunteers) in Kerry, 18 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frank O&#39;Donnell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent from Frank Hugh O&#39;Donnell (1846-1916) to the Honorary Secretary of the Kerry County Board of the National Volunteers. The letter refers to recent arrests and the failure of some arresting officers to distinguish between Sinn Féiners and National Volunteers (Redmondites). Certain National Volunteers have been selected to verify the statements of those who claim not to have participated in the &#39;recent disturbances&#39; (the Easter Rising). Local Districts should adopt a similar procedure. The letter goes on to say that the surrender of arms and ammunition only applies to Sinn Féiners, Irish Volunteers, and Irish Citizens Army members, but that National Volunteers should cooperate with the authorities in this matter, and it stipulates how arms should be stored. Finally the writer asks for a report on the attitudes of National Volunteers to the recent &#39;lamentable occurrences&#39;.Frank &#39;Francis&#39; Hugh O&#39;Donnell was an Irish nationalist and politican. In 1877, O’Donnell secured election to the House of Commons as MP for Dungarven, County Waterford. O’Donnell clashed with Parnell for leadership of the Home Rule party, eventually abandoning the Irish Parliamentary Party to co-found the National Democratic League and serve as its president 1904–6. Opposing the service of Irishmen on the British side in the South Africa war, he wrote an anti-recruiting pamphlet for the Irish National Club.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Frank O&#39;Donnell Collection BMH CD/52/2/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/51</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0030">Frank O&#39;Donnell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0308">45, Moyderwell, Tralee, Co.Kerry.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0051_img_1099_1"  type="Letter"  url="aa2d81f8bfd317bfe9fefe1917eb9d7d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0051_img_1099_1"/>
                45 Moyderwell, Tralee.    18th May 1916  <lb/>URGENT.  Dear Sir   I have received the following recommendations from <lb/> Headquarters of the National Volunteers, with directions to have them <lb/> issued immediately to the various Registered Companies in the County:  (1) MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL VOLUNTEERS.  Some members of the National Volunteers have been put under <lb/>arrest by the Military within the past few days. Possibly under <lb/> the circumstances this was unavoidable and apparently some Military <lb/>Officers have failed to discriminate between what are termed Sinn <lb/> Finers and National Volunteers (under the leadership <sic>pf</sic> Mr John <lb/> Redmond M. P.).Representations on this important matter have been <lb/> made from this Office (Headquarters) to His Excellency the Lord <lb/> Lieutenant and these have been conveyed by His Excellency to the <lb/> Commander-in-Chief, Dublin, who has, through his Chief of Staff, expressed <lb/>a desire to facilitate certain Officers of the National Volunteers <lb/> nominated by Headquarters to verify otherwise the statements of <lb/>person sunder arrest who claim to have been members of the National <lb/> Volunteers and who have taken no part in the recent disturbances.  If any such arrests have been made within your District <lb/> immediate steps similar to those taken in Dublin should be taken to <lb/> obtain their release. Officers verifying the statements of persons <lb/> under arrest who claim to be National Volunteers, should be cautioned <lb/>to exercise great care and to deal only with cases of bona fide <lb/> National Volunteers who have not been concerned in the recent disturb- <lb/>ances. They should not interfere in the case of any other person.  (2) ARMS AND AMMUNITION.  As the Proclamation requiring the surrender of Arms and <lb/> Ammunition refers only to members of the the Sinn Fein Irish Volunteers <lb/> and of the Citizen Army, it is not necessary for National Volunteers <lb/> to deliver up their arms, but they should notify the local police of any <lb/>arms and ammunition in their possession.   Where the arms of the Company of the Battalion are kept at <lb/>Headqs., or such other place as ordered by the Company or Battalion <lb/> the arms and ammunition are to notify the local police whilst retaining <lb/>possession of the Arms and Ammunition.   If, however, the military or police demand possession no <lb/>opposition should be offered but a receipt singed by an Officer or <lb/> Sergeant of Police for the Arms or Ammunition taken.'  I hope, therefore, that you will act without delay on these <lb/> instructions and let me know what you ave done in the matter.  I would also be obliged if you would let me have a general <lb/> report, for the information of Headquarters, a to the attitude of <lb/>the National Volunteers in your District during the recent lamentable <lb/> occurrences.   Trusting you will NOT FAIL to send this information as <lb/>early as possible. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  Frank O'Donnell <lb/>Hon. Sec. Kerry Co. Board, Nat. Vol.   To the Secretary,  Each Registered Co. in Kerry.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>