<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1510">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington to John Dillon, 4 November 1917.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter written by Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington (1877-1946) to John Dillon (1851-1927). Mrs. Sheehy-Skeffington wants Dillon to press for publication of the evidence. She says that about a third of the property uplifted in the raids on her home by Bowen-Colthurst’s men has been returned and she lists, as best she can, what is still missing. Her solicitor has put in a claim for compensation and there has been a payment which was less than the claim. She comments that all of this is trivial compared with ‘the bigger question’ and asks when the report is likely to be debated (in the House).Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full detail emerged. John Dillon was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. Dillon issued a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs. Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, Ms. 6837/33/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1510</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0722">Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-11-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1322">43 Moyne Road, Ranelagh, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1480">2 North Gt. Georges Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1510_img_968_1"  type="Letter"  url="352d46c2f8a72e713a2ad36720672d70.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1510_img_968_2"  type="Letter"  url="01571260834c18115ddc524203243f31.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1510_img_968_3"  type="Envelope"  url="3a8bc301c48b6a722023043bae169002.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1510_img_968_4"  type="Envelope"  url="f906e6fe9c7837d14a48c8b9313b9811.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1510_img_968_1"/>
                4 Mar. 1916    43 Moyne Rd  Ranelagh   Dear Mr. Dillon,   I note Mr. <seg type="unclear">Asquith's</seg> reply to Mr. O'Brien <lb/> re publication of evidence of report when latter <lb/> asked question on your behalf. I suppose you will <lb/> press the matter, as the evidence &amp; various <lb/> documents bearing on the case should have <lb/> the fullest publicity. I know the matter is safe <lb/> in your hands. The evidence will be valuable for debate.   You asked me to inform you re property papers <lb/> taken from my house by Capt. Colthurst &amp; his party. <lb/> About one-third of the papers &amp; other documents <lb/> have been returned since, but much of the <lb/> property <hi rend="underline">( 2 large trunks, attache case, portfolios, <lb/> stock of household linen etc) have never been <lb/> returned : I understand the Royal Irish Rifles <lb/> took with them to Victoria Barracks, Belfast <lb/> much <seg type="unclear">passable</seg> books </hi> from houses raided &amp; <lb/>it is probable that the <hi rend="underline">authorities have never <lb/> thought of searching there. </hi>  My solicitor put in a claim for compensation <lb/>for such of my goods as could be estimated  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1510_img_968_2"/>
              in terms of money: the sum was <hi rend="underline">Â£49</hi> odd. I <lb/>received last week order <hi rend="underline">for Â£44</hi> - I suppose <lb/> the assessor feels it his duty not to award <lb/>the full claim. Mine was a perfectly honest <lb/> estimate &amp; was, if anything, un der stated.   Quantities of private letters of my own, letters <lb/>from my husband to me before our marriage, <lb/>manuscripts of his, including articles for press,  poems  &amp; <lb/> an unfinished play on which he had been working <lb/> for a couple of years) &amp; various other documents <lb/> of literary value, several educational books <lb/> (scraps, pictures, etc)  of my own, necessary for my work &amp; now difficult <lb/> to replace owing to war conditions, have not been <lb/>restored, as well as many private relics &amp; <lb/>souvenirs of <hi rend="underline">my husband which were very <lb/> precious to me </hi><seg type="del"> have never been returned</seg>: on <lb/> such things no money value can be put <lb/> &amp; it would mean a great deal to me if they <lb/> could be traced &amp; restored. <hi rend="underline">Lieutenant Morris <lb/> stated in his evidence at inquiry that Capt. <lb/> Colthurst has passed round to him &amp; other <lb/> officers a number of papers found in my </hi><lb/>house - <hi rend="underline">apparently as curiosities.</hi>  Of course, I do not consider any questions re property <lb/> as anything but trivial, compared with the bigger <lb/> question &amp; merely forward these details at your request.   I shall be glad to know when it is likely that the <lb/> report will be debated.  <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely,  H.S. Skeffington Sheehy </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1510_img_968_3"/>
                John Dillon Esq M.P.  2 North St George St   <hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi>    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1510_img_968_4"/>
                Blank back of envelope   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>