<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1560">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Moynihan to John Moynihan, 18 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Moynihan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from John Moynihan (d. 1946) of Tralee, County Kerry, to his brother Michael Moynihan (d. 1918). Maurice had joined the Civil Service Rifles, a unit of the British Terrritorial Army, before the outbreak of the Great War. In June 1916 he volunteered for foreign service and was sent to France as a private in the London Regiment. In 1917 he received a commission in the 8th (Irish) Battalion of the King&#39;s Liverpool Regiment and was killed in action in June 1918.
Maurice thanks John for all his help in sending him books. He comments in detail on the political situation in Ireland and states that there is no hope for a settlement of the Irish question while the war is still on. He also writes that Ireland is in a better position than many other counties and had suffered little from the war.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Michael Moynihan Papers, P57/198(1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1560</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1459">Michael Moynihan</persName>
              <date>1916-09-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1368">John Moynihan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1918</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1560_img_1028_1"  type="Letter"  url="e678d0609edf6a6ddae9ae51f683f4f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1560_img_1028_2"  type="Letter"  url="130883a61b9aab22453128c27db40963.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1560_img_1028_3"  type="Letter"  url="1c5e217897517d3dbf7981c1d8ca2699.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1560_img_1028_4"  type="Letter"  url="7b7b249784ca7bff028fa5775f56f6e4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1560_img_1028_1"/>
             P57/198 1  BE. F.     18 Sep 1916       Dear John,     Thanks for the trouble you<lb/>have taken over those two books,<lb/>Faust and the monograph on<lb/>Balzac. They have both come,<lb/>and are welcome additions to<lb/>my library. As regards your<lb/>suggestion about starting a deposit<lb/>to <seg type="unclear"></seg> , I think you had<lb/>better leave it alone, as I have<lb/>quite enough literature now to<lb/>carry me on for an indefinite<lb/>period.   I am afraid that no<lb/>re-arrangements that can take<lb/>place in Irish politics will lead<lb/>to any fruitful result while<lb/>the war lasts. Until normal<lb/>political conditions are restored in<lb/>Great Britain, it is vain to hope<lb/>for any tangible gain from 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1560_img_1028_2"/>
            Irish agitation. There is no means <lb/> by which any movement of Irish <lb/> opinion can reflect themselves <lb/> at the polls, still less in Parliament <lb/> itself. The policy of inaction <lb/> adopted by the Government, which, <lb/> it must be admitted has its <lb/> justification, in the force of <lb/> circumstances, can only be met <lb/> by a corresponding policy of <lb/> waiting, on the part of the <lb/> Irish People. They have really <lb/> lost nothing by the failure of <lb/> the attempt at a temporary <lb/> settlement, and they should not <lb/> be led by their chagrin at <lb/> that failure to beat their heads <lb/> against a stone wall, before peace <lb/> reopens the door to free <lb/> discussion and rational <lb/> negotiation. And in this <lb/> interim period it must not be 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1560_img_1028_3"/>
             P57/198 2   forgotten that even under a<lb/>semi - hostile military regime,<lb/>they suffer far less inconvenience<lb/>than the inhabitants of belligerent<lb/>countries on the continent have<lb/>to put up with from their own<lb/>war administration. Apart<lb/>from the suppression of opinion,<lb/>there is no restriction in Ireland<lb/>of the free exercise of ordinary<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg> The citizen of<lb/>Ireland is far better off than<lb/>the citizen of independent Greece.<lb/>And the war which has brought<lb/>desolation and ruin to so many<lb/>of the   parts of Europe,<lb/>has, in Ireland, brought, if<lb/>anything, increased prosperity.     I hope that Sir G.<lb/>Munro's forecast may prove<lb/>correct. But the length of<lb/>time that now separates us<lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1560_img_1028_4"/>
            from winter is hardly <lb/> sufficient to justify undue <lb/> optimism on that point. <lb/> M. Moynihan.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>