<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4832">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eamonn O’Modhráin to Mary Moran, 6 December 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eamonn O’Modhráin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O’Modhráin Collection</repository>
                  <collection>PC_Doyle_1920-12-06</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4832</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1186">Eamonn O’Modhráin</persName>
              <date>1920-12-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1165">Mountjoy Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Moran</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0189">Curragh, Kildare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1955</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4832_img_None_1"  url="9ef8c7f66a4282270cc91ad68617ccb2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4832_img_None_2"  url="1f448b46cdfb855fd6191cf79898b715.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4832_img_0_1"/>
              Let know<lb/>had Treasa<lb/>To pay or had<lb/>letter. I had<lb/>no stamp    Mountjoy Prison,<lb/>Dublin    6.XII.20    Dearest Mother   I hope you are keeping<lb/>well and not overworking yoruself or<lb/>worrying, there is no necessity to worry<lb/>about me anyhow as I am having an<lb/>A.1 time. I wrote to Treasa on Saturday<lb/>as I wanted her to send me in some<lb/>things and as we can only write one<lb/>letter per week I could not write you<lb/>earlier. We however receive all latters<lb/>that come to us. One visit per week is all that<lb/>is allowed the hours are 11am to 1pm and<lb/>2.30 to 4.30 pm any day, Saturdays<lb/>included, no visits are allowed on Sunday.<lb/>Now you are not on any account to come<lb/>up specially to see me you have enough<lb/>on hands. How is Lewie? Is he still<lb/>in Beresford Bks? Has a summary<lb/>of evidence been taken yet or do the mean 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4832_img_0_2"/>
             to try him on such a ridiculous charge?<lb/>The possession of newspapers which can<lb/>be bought in any newsagent weekly.<lb/>I trust that everything is goin on<lb/>well and that Denis is still with you<lb/>but for him I don't know how you would<lb/>carry on I hope he will be able to remain<lb/>I let Treawsa know that I want here<lb/>better let her manage it at this end<lb/>than be sending parcels from home. If <lb/>however, any friends have books to send<lb/>I will be most grateful for them but the<lb/>chances are they will never be returned<lb/>books here are common property. Will<lb/>you square expenses with Treasa.<lb/>We are having a series of lectures here<lb/>......<seg type="del">.       .</seg>......<lb/>They are quite interesting.<lb/>With best wishes to yourself, Denis<lb/>Fionnuala and all friends, not forgetting<lb/>Maggie   As ever    Eamonn     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>