<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4163">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 10 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/53</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4163</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4163_img_3536_1"  type="Letter"  url="64cfcc19597bebdf3c75593c07e47818.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4163_img_3536_2"  type="Letter"  url="ea59013a925037d7b530d1243ebbef60.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4163_img_3536_1"/>
             10. Nov 15   This must be on business   In regard to the Margate Ho I am glad you wrote to Ev. <lb/>In such matters involving a loss of rent of £15 yearly (is reduction of <lb/>1/3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>) I should most certainly not have taken action myself without <lb/>consultation of Ev &amp; Rex, &amp; also when a decision is reached I should <lb/><hi rend="underline">notify <seg type="unclear">Mab</seg></hi>, so that she may be prepared for further diminutions <lb/> of rent.   My own view is that we should get Mr Bayley to <lb/>bargain for rather more eg £45 at any rate, but be prepared to <lb/>accept £40 if necessary. The fact that the tenant goes in without <lb/>requiring dilapidations to be done up is a saving of at least £10-0-0 <lb/>&amp; tho' Margate may become more popular after the war, the <lb/>Germans will see that house rents do not rise at present. There <lb/>is also the fact that houses deteriorate in the winter if unoccupied <lb/>However Ev will give his advice with which I will agree.   Many thanks for the N Hummock extracts which will be <lb/>quite useful to me when I get the <seg type="del">not</seg> record of the meeting. <lb/>This is often sent by forwarding a  financial  newspaper &amp; I shall be glad <lb/>if you will send it on. In fact if you do not mind buying <lb/>one I should like a Financier sent to me once once a month <seg type="del">either</seg> <lb/> <seg type="del">a Tuesday or</seg> a Friday's for choice.   Yes quite a good pr in accumulating £70 in October, <lb/>but I can't quite tell what this really means till I see the pass <lb/>book, as Oct is a good month &amp; I do not know if any calls have
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4163_img_3536_2"/>
            <lb/>been deducted or insurance paid etc in it. Morrows then was no <lb/>rent and both our exes will be lower without hours &amp; wages.    I am quite sure however in spite of this qualified praise that the <lb/>pr has been very good, &amp; as long as she does not think that she <lb/>is rolling in money when the balance goes up. According to our agree- <lb/>ment of not touching our pay there is still I think £150 or £200 to <lb/>be invested this year out of our temporary savings. This I would like <lb/>put in the next war loan issue if it is available, &amp; if you do not <lb/>incur any capital expenditure such as home furniture which I am <lb/>quite ready to agree to.   This month &amp; December are both good months &amp; also the first <lb/>15 days of January after which then are 2 lean months till the 20 March <lb/>I think.   If you have not returned my pass book yet you might send it to <lb/>me, but if you have I will wait till the beginning of December to <lb/>see how a pr manages affairs! I do not want her to stint <lb/>herself &amp; she knows it, &amp; I know she won't do a wild Xmas <lb/>best in spite of the fact that Rubber is still bouncing.   I fancy that according to our original agreement that if rubber <lb/>went up over 2/6 the surplus was to be given to a motor may <lb/>almost prove near a possibility &amp; that if the war continues £50 <lb/>may be available, but after the war I expect a pretty big <lb/>slump in prices as all the motors now being used at the front <lb/>will stop, &amp; rich people with motors will be far fewer. I wonder <lb/>Germany has not got her substitutes yet. She still may &amp; then it <lb/>will be a case of a very poor mangey bw &amp; rather a thin pr ! <lb/>Shan't we hate the Bosches?   you don't loan the pass book about I hope   WSP 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>