<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2967">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 15 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lillian in which he briefly touches on many subjects: a misinterpreted letter, an appointment of Lillian&#39;s, a flat to which Lillian has recently moved, the purchase of Christmas presents, financial matters, holiday leave, and a recent ride to the front with &#34;the General&#34;, which ended in both Spender and his companion getting lost.

This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Captain Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968).. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.

Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914, and served as an officer of the Ulster Division until 1916. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund during the war, and a member of the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/105</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2967</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2967_img_2372_1"  type="Letter"  url="d38cf2001e7815d47d9bbdc2f0332cb9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2967_img_2372_2"  type="Letter"  url="94ba5b7369de201e6e2076487a9def86.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2967_img_2372_1"/>
             I may be home on leave fairly early in January 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or so as Genl going on 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>   R very seldom goes with the Genl. I wonder <lb/>if anything has happened.   My Dear PR   You will see by the enclosed that there has been a bit of <lb/>a bother! Apparently I read Hugh's letter wrongly, but didn't it <lb/>read that way? Anyway I have gone out of my way to write <lb/>as nice a reply as I can &amp; there the matter must end. <lb/>2 letters today as I hoped nice but not much news. No I <lb/>can't think why you should not like Sunday morning. Oh yes <lb/>of course it means your getting up earlier both yourself &amp; the bw <lb/>when there. Just back from a hard ride with the General. <lb/>looking at the bombers who were good. He afterwards went on <lb/>to look at something else &amp; asked me if a village was B &amp; <lb/>having a map said no it is Y &amp; we ought to go to our <lb/>right. However he was not going to be corrected &amp; galloped <lb/>straight on when my cap conveniently came off so as he <lb/>had 2 ADCs with him I fell out &amp; came home. I wonder <lb/>where he fetched up. Any how I think it was tactful of <lb/>me not to stop &amp; crow silently later, but he may take it <lb/>differently of course.   You will I hope have settled on your habitation, this <lb/>sounds better for a <seg type="unclear">r</seg> than a mansion, especially when you <lb/>haven't <seg type="unclear">been</seg> settled whether it is to be a flat or a maisonette. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2967_img_2372_2"/>
             I was in at lunch. Genl <lb/>not quite sure how to take <lb/>my disappearance. He got there but like this, &amp; all the <lb/>time going hard so he was back to a very late lunch. <lb/>Your LXV111 letter posted 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp;  2 also on 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  got here first post 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Wednesday. <lb/>Do exactly what you think fit for the youngsters, I <lb/>don't mind their getting Xmas presents now, but preferably <lb/>something that will outlast the Xmas holidays.    Yes if Mater should read my letters what would <lb/>she think a pr!!   <seg type="unclear">Killinhall</seg> div rather disappointing tho' it <seg type="unclear">earnings</seg> are <lb/> good, but it is putting by more that half for eventualities which <lb/>shows what they expect. I think it is probably wise. I should <lb/>like to se the report on the meeting if it reaches you.   Genl talks of taking leave early in January so you <lb/> may  have the chance of seeing him soon. Don't growl at <lb/>him! A pr's growl might really be terrifying as a <lb/>poor rabbit-kicked bw ( this corresponds to henpecked) knows so <lb/>well.   Your poor bw who is very jealous of the <lb/>2 uncles.   Wilfred BS   We must settle the leave when it comes. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>