<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0567">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward Marsh to Lord Wimborne, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Howard Marsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter as written by Sir Howard Marsh (1872 – 1953). Marsh was a civil servant and patron of the arts. In 1915 Marsh became the assistant private secretary to Prime Minister H. H. Asquith, in which position he served until the fall of Asquith&#39;s government in December 1916. When Churchill returned to government as Minister of Munitions in 1916, Marsh joined him there as private secretary. Although Marsh enjoyed a distinguished career as a civil servant, he never attained the highest eminence and he is to be remembered, in Churchill&#39;s words, as ‘a deeply instructed champion of the arts’.The letter was sent to Lord Wimborne (1873 – 1979). Sir Ivor Churchill Guest was lord lieutenant of Ireland from 1915 to 1918. From the beginning of 1916 Wimborne began agitating for measures to be taken against the Irish Volunteers, but was constantly dissuaded by Birrell and Nathan. However, Wimborne&#39;s early recommendations for action reflected favourably on him after the 1916 Rising.This letter refers to the appointment of Viscount Massereene and Ferrard, Algernon Skeffington (1872 -1952), as His Majesty’s Lieutenant for County Antrim. From 1914 until 1918 Skeffington served as an officer with the North Irish Horse in World War I. He would occupy the position of Lord Lieutenant and Custos Rotulorum of County Antrim from 1916 until 1938.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-8420, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-8420</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/567</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0132">Edward Howard Marsh</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0852">10 Downing Street, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0567_img_1959_1"  type="Letter"  url="6e14b1ea21a445520bc62a5528bce21e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0567_img_1959_1"/>
                10 Downing Street,  Whitehall SW    16th May 1916.   My Lord,   The King having been graciously pleased to direct that <lb/>Viscount Massereene and Ferrard should be appointed His <lb/>Majesty's Lieutenant for the County Antrim, I have to <lb/>request that the necessary steps may be taken to give <lb/>effect to His Majesty's commands.  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant.   E Marsh <lb/>for the Prime Minister    HIs Excellency,  The Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>