<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1121">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 1 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from May Fay (1897-1976) to James Finn (1877-1922) regarding her everyday activities and preparations for their upcoming marriage. May also briefly mentions reading the published correspondence between Sir General John Maxwell (1859-1929) and the Bishop of Limerick, Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), regarding the British administration&#39;s treatment of the Easter Rising rebels.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. After James&#39; death May held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1121</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0149">Tgherstown, Ballinea, Mullingar, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1121_img_353_1"  type="NULL"  url="095b434981dfbb7a6eab806fe4002ad4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1121_img_353_2"  type="NULL"  url="4e0e8276eae14aa8a5da2ea8275c0792.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1121_img_353_1"/>
                Togherstown  Ballinea  Mullingar  Co W Meath    1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June 1916   My dearest James   I got your letter this morn also card to fit ring <lb/>and a paper I think addressed by your Mother we were very <lb/>glad to get it and see Dr Dwyer’s letters to Maxwell <lb/>I wonder they got on papers at all they were very good. <lb/>We are having awful weather <sic>hear</sic> at present <sic>quiet</sic> cold <lb/>as well as wet. I hope they are trying to <hi rend="underline">spit up</hi> all the <lb/>bad weather before we go off.  Christy is gone to M.Gar to day &amp; will take home <lb/>all my dress etc. nearly, so they won’t be late at that <lb/>rate. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Seery was called over to Balrath last night, <lb/>the boss there was at death’s door with drink but is slowly <lb/>recovering M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Kiernan had got word from Gertie Duffy <lb/>saying if she went to Dublin with her to see the Doctors <lb/>she would pay her expenses for one day. I believe she is <lb/>very delicate (Gertie) but does not think it, like every one <lb/>of her said complaint, people all pity John the take in <lb/>he got but I think one is as much to be pitied as the other  I am returning the ring card size <hi rend="underline">T</hi> is my size. <lb/>About your present I will look at some things in  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1121_img_353_2"/>
              Mullingar if I don’t get something I think you would <lb/>like I will wait till we go to Cork won’t that be <lb/>all right.  Well Christy has not gone to Mullingar at all, <lb/>there were arrangements made to drive the filly <lb/>&amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> S pressed her <hi rend="underline">car</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">son,</hi> also when Christy <lb/>went down he asked the loan of the <hi rend="underline">bit</hi> from <hi rend="underline">Tom,</hi><lb/>he got it and threw it on the ground to him <lb/>&amp; they were all giving him short answers, he that <lb/>so seldom goes near them so he did not go, with the <lb/>going on they had he’d be late for Mass there. <lb/>The whole cause of the general bad humour was a letter <lb/>Johnnie had got saying that firm was not going <lb/>to be opened <seg type="del">at all</seg> for the present  &amp; they therefore did not require <lb/>him it was hard of course after such long <lb/>wait for both parties but I can’t understand them <lb/>showing temper to Christy that would give them the <lb/>house from over his head.  I am sure tho’ like ourselves you will be disappointed <lb/>for Johnnies job,  I have no more news now dearest James. I hope you <lb/>will get to make out this, I would not be half as mad if it were <lb/>to myself it was done because I have the “<hi rend="underline">gift</hi> of the <hi rend="underline">gab</hi>” <seg type="closer"> warmest love from your loving  May </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>