<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5957">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert A. Johnson, Royal Mint, to Edward Carter Preston, 1 February 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert A. Johnson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Liverpool Record Office</repository>
                  <collection>Edward Carter Preston Collection, 730 PRE 4/7/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5957</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0328">Robert A. Johnson</persName>
              <date>1923-02-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Carter Preston</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1699">Liverpool, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5957_img_None_1"  url="phpI2BJ9S.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5957_img_None_2"  url="phpzCWwx8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5957_img_0_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">730 PRE 4/7/4</seg>   1st February, 1923    Dear Carter Preston,   Yours of the 31st ult. re Great Seal for  Northern Ireland. The instructions are the Royal Arms  with a scocheon of the arms of Ulster, which are a golden  shield with a red cross. We do not know at present whether  the harp of Ireland is to come out of the Royal Arms or  not, but unless and until an order to that effect is  received, of course it remains in.  It is not essential that the scocheon should be  above the Royal Arms, that is rather a matter for the  artist to decide, but no doubt our heraldic experts would  claim that it should be shown like the old shields of  Pretence were, i.e. tacked on to the middle of the Royal  Arms, and therefore obliterating part of them.  As regards the King's clothing, I do not  suppose His Majesty would care to appear naked on  horseback, but, for the rest, we should like the artist  to show him as he thinks he would appear best. Personally  I cannot imagine anything more awful than the portrait  of His Majestsy in naval uniform, on the deck of a naval  battleship  Carter Preston Esq.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5957_img_0_2"/>
             battleship, as it appears on the present Counterseal to<lb/>the Great Seal for England, and I am sure my Committee<lb/>agree with me. As to what the King's own views may be,<lb/>we shall only know thta when he has seen the artists'<lb/>models. My own view is that he would probably not be<lb/>appropiate as a Roman senator, or an ancient Briton, and<lb/>thta the safest plan would be to put him in military<lb/>uniform, carefully disguised by a cloak with a cocked hat,<lb/>which, like the monument to the Prince Consort in Holborn,<lb/>he might be holding in his right hand. However, as I say,<lb/>this is just the sort of point on which we invite the artist's<lb/>ideas.   Believe me,    Yours sincerely,<lb/>Robert A. Johnson.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>