<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0256">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Anderson to Sir Matthew Nathan, 20 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Anderson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Anderson (b.1860), the honorary secretary of the Irish Association of Volunteer Training Corps, to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). Anderson writes that he is enclosing a letter from John Bristow, the Commandant of the Belfast Volunteer Defence Corps, giving particulars of the duty which his corps has been doing at the request of the Military Authorities in Belfast.Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. The IAVTC were a corps consisting of men who were over age or engaged in important occupations and therefore could not enlist for wartime service when war broke out in 1914. This was a volunteering training militia that came to be known by the nickname &#39;Gorgeous Wrecks&#39; due to the G.R. armbands they wore symbolizing Georgius Rex.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7964/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/256</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0902">Robert Anderson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0481">18 South Frederick Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0256_img_1440_1"  type="Letter"  url="395d3baa5f64eea24b762d07217eb5af.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0256_img_1440_1"/>
               18 SOUTH FREDERICK STREET.  DUBLIN.   20th April, 1916  Sir,   With reference to my letter of the 15th instant, I<lb/>now beg to enclose copy of a letter received to-day from Mr.<lb/>John Bristow, Commandant of the Belfast Volunteer Defence<lb/>Corps, giving particulars of the duty which his Corps has<lb/>been doing at the request of the Military Authorities in<lb/>Belfast.  As stated at our interview to-day, I will mention<lb/>the matters discussed between us to the meeting of the<lb/>executive Committee which takes place this afternoon and<lb/>will communicate with you as soon as possible thereafter. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,  R. <hi rend="underline">Anderson</hi>  Hon. Secretary.   Lt. Colonel,  The Right Honourable Sir Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G.  Under Secretary for Ireland,  Chief Secretary's Office,  DUBLIN CASTLE.  </seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>