<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5941">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eamonn O'Modhrain to Mary Moran, 3 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin (1881-1954) to his mother, Mary Moran, requesting items to be sent to him in Frongoch and reassuring her that he is getting on alright. According to Eamonn the prisoners are able to attend mass and confessions and are being entertained by lectures, concerts, football and physical drills among other activities. Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin was a member of the Irish Volunteers and took part in the Easter Rising alongside his brother Louis. He was arrested and incarcerated in both Wakefield and Frongoch prison. After his release Eamonn would go on to command the 6th Battalion of the Carlow Brigade during the Irish War of Independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O&#39;Modhráin Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5941</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1527">Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1077">South Camp, Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Moran</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1401">Rose Villa, Ballysax, The Curragh, Co. Kildare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5941_img_333_1"  type="Letter"  url="45b2d964963521f6807161c402c52fe8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5941_img_333_2"  type="Letter"  url="85a24d3082101d2811d04578b7f37d9d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5941_img_333_3"  type="Envelope"  url="36547776ddd89e1b0067c57c4764f4c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5941_img_333_4"  type="Letter"  url="4da9c282978b0cf2c8741430f5801b26.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5941_img_333_1"/>
                290. Ed. Moran, Irish Prisoner of War  South Camp, Frongoch, N. Wales.    3.VII.16   My Dearest Mother   Your letter &amp; Norman's came <lb/> Sat. and Maire's yesterday. I was very glad to <lb/> get them and to learn that all are well, let you <lb/> all write often. We have Mass, confession &amp; Holy <lb/> Comm. every Sunday. Don't send papers, 'Ind' comes <lb/> every day now, send some books, Irish &amp; English. <lb/> As weather is wet I will want a coat &amp; vest, rough <lb/> tweed, good clothes no use here, they will want to be <lb/> larger than last measurement, also putties like <lb/> knickers and a portmanteau, not too big, suit case  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5941_img_333_2"/>
              would do. I hope visiting time will be extended before <lb/> Tess &amp; Una come and that Maire can arrange to <lb/>come also. Glad to know all well in Enniscorthy <lb/> Would you ask Maire to spend some of her holidays <lb/> with you. Better buy cake now for delivery in <lb/>Nov., Cotton or Linseed, whichever better <seg type="unclear">so far,</seg><lb/> 2Â½ or 3 tons. I charged Casey 30/= for ten acres, <lb/> his own stuff. Let Lewie charge current prices <lb/> for materials. We are not having a bad time here <lb/>lectures, concerts, Irish classes, football, physical <lb/> drill, &amp;c had a march into country today. With <lb/> best love to all, particularly the children <seg type="closer"> Eamonn. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5941_img_333_3"/>
                Mrs. Moran  Rose Villa  Ballysax  The Curragh  Co. Kildare  Ire.    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5941_img_333_4"/>
                290, Edward Moran  Irish Prisoner of War  South Camp, Frongoch    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>