<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1241">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 13 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) recounting his feelings when proposing to May. James cannot quite believe that May has accepted him and vows to do his duty by her.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, 1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1241</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-01-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0831"> 39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1241_img_430_1"  type="Letter"  url="187255e2701520a54438a65f11dfa821.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1241_img_430_2"  type="Letter"  url="30ecb0c2f2de3ea9ea43ba9f2324aaf0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1241_img_430_3"  type="Letter"  url="805f69f9ff3b54e3fa462b547d608357.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1241_img_430_1"/>
                39, Belgrave Square,  Rathmines,  Dublin.    13th January 1916   My dearest May,   I got back safe and <lb/>sound although I don't feel quite <lb/>so cheerful as I did in the <lb/>country. I always feel like that <lb/>but I had more reason, I suppose, <lb/>this time than ever before.  I remember now that on <lb/>Monday when I spoke to you I <lb/>was so intent on asking you to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1241_img_430_2"/>
              marry me that I quite overlooked <lb/>in the excitement telling you that <lb/>I loved you very dearly. I hope <lb/>you didn't need me to tell you that <lb/>anyhow in order to believe it of <lb/>me. I can hardly yet think that <lb/>the converse is true. That you have <lb/>any special regard for me — it <lb/>seems somehow too good to be <lb/>true but I hope with God's help <lb/>that it may come true any how. <lb/>As I told you already I could never <lb/>bring myself to believe that any <cb/> good girl could trust herself to <lb/>me and in your case it seemed <lb/>impossible but I suppose the reason <lb/>is that the Lord is always a thousand <lb/>times better to us than we <lb/>deserve. With His help I will try to <lb/>be better in the future than I <lb/>have been in the <seg type="unclear">past</seg> and maybe <lb/>in the end with you to help me <lb/>I'll turn out something better than <lb/>the rotter I know myself to be. <lb/>This is a queer sort of letter to <lb/>write to you, you will think, but <lb/>perhaps you will be able to read  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1241_img_430_3"/>
              between the lines that I love you <lb/>whatever comes and that if the <lb/>Lord spares me I will try and do <lb/>my duty by you.  Mrs. Seery showed you my <lb/>mother's letter, I presume. You will <lb/>see that she is as pleased as can be with <lb/>events. Indeed I think she has always <lb/>wished that I might be lucky enough <lb/>to get you. Now that the 100 <lb/>to 1 chance has come off, we are <lb/>both naturally delighted.  No news here since I went away. <lb/>Am back in harness tomorrow but will <lb/>take a few days off when you come up <lb/>which I hope will be soon. Give my regards to <lb/>everyone and with dearest love for yourself. <seg type="closer"> Yours forever  James. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>