<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0720">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John George Lambton to Lady Londonderry, 21 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Lambton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence belonging to Lady Londonderry, a large proportion of which concerns Sir Edward Carson and opposition to the Third Home Rule Bill. Lady Londonderry was a prominent figure in politics and high­ society from 1890 until 1919. Her correspondence includes many important figures in literature, the arts, the military, law and the church.The author of the letter is John Lambton, 3rd Earl of Durham and Lord Lieutenant of that county from 1884 until a few months before his death in 1928. Among other positions, Lambton was a Knight of the Garter, a member of the Privy Council, and Lord High Steward to the King.This particular letter discusses various aspects of country life, including the rearing of horses, the trouble of petrol shortages, and the workings of politics.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Theresa, D2846/2/21-12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/720</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0335">John Lambton</persName>
              <date>1916-02-21T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0957">Lambton Castle, County Durham, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Theresa Talbot</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0720_img_2224_1"  type="Letter"  url="00669416dc63cca875e8562067575bbb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0720_img_2224_2"  type="Letter"  url="8fda7bd2f1b6e3b1ba01e3c17f3d00c5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0720_img_2224_3"  type="Letter"  url="c6bce5bc3980595c71f97c5e9ad9f69b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0720_img_2224_1"/>
                LAMBTON CASTLE,  FENCE HOUSES.    21 Feb. 1916.   My Dear Lady Londonderry,   I am very glad to hear <lb/> that the foal is satisfactory, <lb/> and I shall hope for a <lb/> flashing Corcyra colt next <lb/>year. The difficulty about <lb/>coming to see you is my <lb/> lack of chauffeurs &amp; petrol.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0720_img_2224_2"/>
              We have only one man to <lb/>do all out jobs.   Poor Ridley is a great loss. <lb/> He was the only active young <lb/>peer we had up here, and <lb/>would have been very useful <lb/> in the future. when Charlie's <lb/> military duties are over I <lb/> am looking forward to <cb/> his presence in the north as <lb/>I foresee troubles in which <lb/> we can act together,( if I am <lb/> not suffering from senility!) <lb/> and the fact that he has <lb/>fought by the side of the <lb/> working classes will <lb/> enhance his position .    I believe Edith, if I may <lb/> call her so for short!  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0720_img_2224_3"/>
              is to be approached today <lb/> at the Executive meeting <lb/> of the Women's' etc. etc.: <lb/> about joining . I hope she <lb/>will be able to. N.E. wind <lb/> this afternoon which I never <lb/> like â especially as it suits <lb/> the cursed Germans.  <seg type="closer"> Ever yours  Durham </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>