<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3486">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Dillon to John Redmond, 19 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Dillon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Dillon (1851-1927) to John Redmond (1856-1918). Dillon writes to Redmond to discuss party issues, including a conversation he had with Joe Devlin MP (1871-1934) on the situation in Belfast. 

John Redmond  was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. John Dillon was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. Dillon issued a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 where he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Dillon would succeed John Redmond as leader of the Home Rule party in 1918. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 15,182/23/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3486</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1834">2 North Great George&#39;s Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_1"  type="Letter"  url="09bcaf26c4f26fd428dfad0ccb454af6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_2"  type="Letter"  url="06047cc7a79487cbc23dc1eec4a2229d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_3"  type="Letter"  url="67aa059bda01f68df2f02bd94a25c34e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_4"  type="Letter"  url="e2cd115362787ea64e49ab6d6ae71ec2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_5"  type="Letter"  url="d6fae82063fd8c80b70abe4cde8f4294.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_6"  type="Letter"  url="6ef608a9f3e26d68367ae9ec6c988508.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3486_img_2894_7"  type="Letter"  url="01da0eea0d2472c3016c2bda36cc8ecd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_1"/>
             2, NORTH G<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">T</hi></hi> GEORGE'S STREET, <lb/>DUBLIN.   Monday 19 June 1916   My dear Redmond   I have just had a <lb/>long battle with Devlin over <lb/>the telephone. He give a <lb/>most cheering account <lb/>the situation in Belfast. <lb/>The account in the Independent <lb/>of the meeting - 5am <lb/>outrageous travesty. I <seg type="del">was</seg>  was 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_2"/>
            an immense success and <lb/>practically unanimous. <lb/>I expect you will have an <lb/>account for Hannah. <lb/>Devlin's very <seg type="unclear">strongest</seg> <lb/>opinion that you &amp; I <lb/>should go in to Belfast <lb/>on Wednesday evening — <lb/> or at latest by the early <lb/>train on Thursday morning. <lb/>He thinkks it will be of the <lb/>utmost importance to <lb/>be there to interview important
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_3"/>
            people during Thursday.   Let me know what you <lb/>decide to do.   D is making arrangments <lb/>to <seg type="unclear">lessen</seg> the six <lb/>Counties.   On the other hand <lb/><seg type="unclear">Megher</seg> writes that the <lb/>Irish are working <lb/>hard answering against <lb/>the proposal.   A special messenger <lb/>brought me a letter from
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_4"/>
             George yesterday - telling me <lb/>that now <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the <lb/>Unionist Ministers have gone <lb/>into revolt. Bonar Law's <lb/>attitude is not known as <lb/>he's away in Paris.   I am strongly of opinion <lb/>that some money should <lb/>be spent in enabling <lb/>the Fiennan in   <lb/>for the next few days.   Fallon who had a <lb/><hi rend="underline">most</hi> successful meeting
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_5"/>
             of the South Monaghan <lb/>Executive. The longest <lb/>that had been held for <lb/>a long time - and quite <lb/><seg type="unclear">unanimous</seg> — tell me <lb/>that Murphy has <lb/>several agents distributing <lb/>the Independant in <lb/>Ulster.   But for the abominable
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_6"/>
            printing. The Freeman <lb/>of Saturday and <lb/>today are quite good <lb/>campaign douments <lb/>I am taking some <lb/>steps on my own <lb/>responsibility to circulate <lb/>it — This will of <lb/>course cost something.   I shall write tonight <lb/>or tomorrow morning
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3486_img_2894_7"/>
            about the overdraft.   Yours Sincerely   <hi rend="underline">John Dillon</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>