<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4196">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Shaw to James Shaw, 15 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Samuel Shaw to his father, James Shaw, regarding the conclusion of the war and the future of Home Rule. Samuel writes that he expects the war to be over in the coming spring. He also writes about Ireland&#39;s exemption from the conscription bill and his belief that Home Rule has been knocked on the head forever. Samuel believes that Ulster&#39;s effort in the war will make Home Rule a thing of the past.

Samuel Henry Shaw (1896-1967) was a sergeant with the 10th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers. He volunteered for active service in September 1914. Before enlisting Samuel was a member of the Portstewart Company, Coleraine Battalion, North Derry Regiment, Ulster Volunteer Force. Samuel served in France, and was wounded during the Battle of the Somme in July 1916 and again in early 1917 and in 1918. Before the war he was employed as a ironmonger&#39;s assistant. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4196</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0493">Samuel Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-01-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1967</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4196_img_3568_1"  type="Letter"  url="4f620ff2f217bb1bf0c9334a071b99f2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4196_img_3568_2"  type="Letter"  url="a26438d4a667ef0e90e69bd728536c92.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4196_img_3568_3"  type="Letter"  url="2a334945dc7e4e69810d9983cdbc43e5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4196_img_3568_1"/>
             Same Address   15—1—16   My Dear <lb/>Dad,   I received your letter <lb/>All right. You wanted to know <lb/>if we were in the <seg type="unclear">fun</seg> in Xmas <lb/>day but I'm sorry to say we <lb/>were not, it was the Division <lb/>that relieved us. I am glad <lb/>to know that all the boys <lb/>went to sea together. They <lb/>will always be <seg type="del">to</seg> able to <lb/>chum it the same as we
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4196_img_3568_2"/>
             P.S. Hope you are all in the <lb/>best of health &amp; spirits, <lb/>the boys were asking for <lb/>you. <lb/>Sammie  <lb/>out here. There is one thing <lb/>we may all look forward <lb/><sic>too</sic>, that is the war will <lb/>be over this spring. We <lb/>will put them back into <lb/>their own country quicker <lb/>than they left it. You said <lb/>in your letter that Ireland <lb/>was not included in the <lb/>conscription bill, but as far <lb/>as Home Rule goes its kno— <lb/>cked on the head for ever.   When the Tommies out here <lb/>see what Ulster has done <lb/>for Briton they say that
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4196_img_3568_3"/>
            Home Rule is and will al— <lb/>ways be a thing of the <lb/>past. Tell mother not <lb/>to send me any more parcels <lb/>as were getting pretty decent <lb/>grub now/. When this is <lb/>over we will get a family <lb/>photo taken with Willie <lb/>and me in the uniform.   I think this is all. <lb/>With the best of love to <lb/>yourself, mother &amp; all <lb/>the children.   Your Loving Son   Sammie. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>