<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0666">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Tate to his father Alec C Tate, 29 September, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Tate</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Alec C Tate served with the British army in India before he married Milicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. James spent the majority of the war in India during which time the Indian Expeditionary Force was dispatched to Mesopotamia. This letter is part of a collection that he wrote to his parents detailing his movements and his day to day experience. James&#39; letter to his father begins by saying he is glad to hear how he has improved. He talks of how they have a peaceful if somewhat boring existence, and how they long to see the inside of a house. He tells him of how his new bomb idea was rejected and the disappointment he felt after all the work he put into it. He informs his father that he has not made a will and should anything happen to him his father must make arrangements with what to do with what little is left of his property.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>The Tate Papers, D2859/4/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/666</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0347">James Tate</persName>
              <date>1916-09-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alec C Tate </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2074">Glenlua, Ballycastle, Co. Antrim, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0666_img_2159_1"  type="Letter"  url="732ade4a46ca0e4b616a7eae0e2ce857.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0666_img_2159_2"  type="Letter"  url="dfc3fbaee9d26f36548a75b6518415d4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0666_img_2159_3"  type="Letter"  url="1b5c7ed7dd1e0f4415351484981e696e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0666_img_2159_1"/>
                Mesoptamia Expd. Force.    29/9/16    I am very glad to hear that you are getting <lb/>on so well &amp; that you are able to be about &amp; go <lb/> to town again. I am also very glad to hear that <lb/>Baby is improving under the new treatment. <lb/> I must have been very dull for you being kept <lb/> in the house for so long. We find it just the other <lb/> way — very dull not having seen a house for so long. <lb/> So much so that the S &amp; T man built a hut for <lb/>himself but it was not a success as the sandflies <lb/>got in in such numbers that he now sleeps outside. <lb/> There is nothing doing here at all &amp; we live a <lb/>very peaceable existence except for odd arab thieves <lb/> who come along at night. At first they made rather <lb/>a good thing out of the camps but now the sepoys <lb/> are getting very much alive and we are being <lb/> troubled less and less. About a fortnight ago they <lb/> killed one &amp; wounded a second at a camp near here <lb/>since when there have been no more thieves. <lb/> I wish we had stuff to make illuminating grenades <lb/>as we used to in Princes Coy in Pindi. I tried to <lb/> get some but failed. I had a long letter from Prince <lb/>some time ago. He said that simla had not accepted <seg type="del">an</seg> the <lb/> new bomb he invented &amp; on which I worked as they already  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0666_img_2159_2"/>
              had fixed a type but they thanked him very much as also <lb/>did the G.O.C. Pindi Division. So all our work was no good. <lb/> He also said that he had sorted out my kit and left it for <lb/>Billy who was coming to Pindi soon &amp; would take it away. <lb/> It was very good of him to take such a lot of trouble. <lb/> I have made no will so if anything happens to me &amp; I get <lb/> killed — which seems very improbable — you will have to arrange <lb/>what is to be done with my property. I have got a case which <lb/>I left in the workshops in Dowlaishwarem, it contains clothes &amp; picture <lb/>frames &amp; some books all of very little value especially as I had <lb/> a letter from De Bras the workshop supdt who said that he thought <lb/>the white ants had got it! The rest of my kit <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>. I sold all <lb/>the chairs &amp; plates etc. before I left Dowlaishwarem. The kit is <lb/>officially in charge of the Executive Engineer Godavii Eastern Division <lb/>Dowlaishwarem. The rest of my kit, except what I have got out here <lb/> is with Billy &amp; also consists of clothes books photographs etc. <lb/> All the money I possess is with the Cox &amp; Co Rawalpindi who have got <lb/>a power of Attorney. They have also got my United Cities Service <lb/>Shares which I told them to sell if they could get a price <lb/>for them — I forget what price — E. Haser. the manager of Cox &amp; Co <lb/>Rawalpindi is a friend of mine &amp; would I am sure do anything for <lb/>you or find out anything. I have left two bills one for about Rs14-0-0 <lb/> with King &amp; Co Bombay for getting off my kit when I landed in 1914 <lb/> they looked after it so well that one bag was cut open &amp; about <lb/>Rs10-0-0 of stuff extracted so I don't intend to pay them. I tried <lb/>to make them pay me &amp; they would not so I think it may  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0666_img_2159_3"/>
              be left at that. The other is for about Rs 50-0-0 from Ranken <lb/>Tailor Rawalpindi it is for a cawapore Topee &amp; a Blue Forage cap <lb/>for which the right price is about Rs 30-0-0 So I am going to <lb/>write to him about it. Except fot these I have left no bills in <lb/>India. I have not <seg type="del">had</seg> bought anything from shops at home since I came <lb/>out but am now sending my watch to S.D. Neills to get mended <lb/> which will mean a bill with them.  I am afraid I have saved no money during the time I was <lb/>in India &amp; have sold shares to the value of about £45-0-0 <lb/>but I hope to here as there is absolutely nothing to spend <lb/> money on &amp; no way except mess bills &amp; sending to India &amp; home <lb/> for parcels also my combined civil furlough &amp; military pay comes <lb/>to 19.7-0-0 odd &amp;416-0-0 so I hope to save at least Rx400 <lb/>a month.  I think I told you that I saw Joe Sparrow out here. <lb/>He is very well &amp; had dinner several times in out mess. <lb/> He seems to have got a very good job now though he <lb/> is only a 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Lt. and I think likes it.  I hope mother is well &amp; also Phil &amp; Ander &amp; that Baby <lb/>is continuing to improve. <seg type="closer"> From your loving son <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Jimmy</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>