<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3960">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frongoch to Laurence J. Ginnell, 8 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from a group of Irish prisoners in Frongoch to Laurence Ginnell. The representatives want Ginnell to raise questions in parliament regarding the administration of a scheme in the camp whereby prisoners are entitled to a rebate of a percentage of what they have spent in the canteen. 

Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; because of the revolutionary nature of the inmates.

Laurence Ginnell (1852 – 1923) was an Irish nationalist politician, lawyer, and member of parliament. He initially ran as a member of the Irish Parliamentary Party, but, from 1910 onward he ran as an Independent Nationalist.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Art Ó Briain Papers, Collection List No. 150; Ms 8429/19-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3960</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1003">Frongach Prison, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1007">Laurence Ginnell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3960_img_3335_1"  type="Letter"  url="fcfcbfbf6f9fff1830ff378ffd1c8f4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3960_img_3335_2"  type="Letter"  url="d9ca2385e1f6e33e29759ee8fa293884.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3960_img_3335_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">9/10/16 Q.F.B 10/10/16.</hi>   Irish Prisoners,<lb/>Internment Camp,<lb/>Frongoch, <lb/> 9th October 1916.   To<lb/>Laurence J. Ginnell, Esq., B.A., B.L., M.P.   Sir,   We the undersigned being the duly elected Leaders of<lb/>the above Camp would feel very much indebted to you if you could<lb/>see your way to having the following questions asked in Parliament,<lb/>at the earliest convenience:-  (1) What is the percentage of the rebate allowed to the<lb/>Irish prisoners in Frongoch on their purchases in the Camp<lb/>Canteen? Is the percentage of the rebate allowed supposed to be<lb/>fixed at 10%? And if so, are the Camp Leaders or Prisoners'<lb/>Auditor allowed to see the Canteen a/c each month. If not, why<lb/>not, considering that it is solely the Prisoners' money that is<lb/>being dealt with? (3) How are the Prisoners to know that they<lb/>are receiving a rebate of 10% other than the system of merely<lb/>letting the Leaders know that they can draw on the Canteen Fund<lb/>up to £10 per month (4) Is it fact that when there were 1,800<lb/>prisoners in the Camp in July they were only allowed £4:10:0 while<lb/>with an average of 900 men in August they received £10 and with<lb/>545 men in Sept. they also received £10 (5) Why are not the<lb/>Camp Leaders allowed to purchase such goods as they think most<lb/>suitable for the prisoners in the way of food, tobacco, cigarettes,<lb/>etc., considering that it is solely the Prisoners' money?  P.S. We would be glad if you would make inquiries into<lb/>the alleged connection of the Adjutant of this Camp— Lieut. J.T.<lb/>Burns (who has charge of the Canteen Fund) with the officer of<lb/>that name connected with the Lipton scandal some few years ago. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3960_img_3335_2"/>
             There are strong rumours concerning this; and certainly the<lb/>Adjutant is obviously an officer of much service and experience<lb/>for a mere Lieutenant. If this alleged connection is correct<lb/>it may have a pertinent bearing on the above questions.   Signed(5)    12/10/16    To A Byrne Esq.   We have been informed by the Adjutant on yesterday, 11th<lb/>inst. that we may draw in the Canteen a/c up to £25 for this<lb/>month, but we are not allowed to check accounts.  (2) 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>