<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3891">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 6 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Marie Martin, the foundress of the Medical Missionaries of Mary to her mother Mary Martin. Written from the Western Front. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary </repository>
                  <collection>BF129</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3891</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1540">Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1575">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3891_img_327_1"  type="NULL"  url="38e653583ebc9be0c872b5b71f398b07.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3891_img_327_2"  type="NULL"  url="001736f573177a776a4125566899a931.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3891_img_327_3"  type="NULL"  url="58e58c7ed527d87d5f2c3bd189c775b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3891_img_327_4"  type="NULL"  url="1f0c2129e1959a9c251447eae7704f40.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3891_img_327_5"  type="NULL"  url="8de279189a9b4f21a7bc2423464186b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3891_img_327_6"  type="NULL"  url="1055337b0e185b313eea09974887664e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3891_img_327_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">6th Feb. 1916</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   A thousand thanks for <lb/> your very nice letter which dated from 20th of Febr &amp; <lb/> the enclosed from Colonel <seg type="unclear">Pose</seg> It was such <lb/> a pleasure to hear he has done so <lb/> well but I was very disappointed he <lb/> was not able to give us more <lb/> satisfactory news. I hope when you get <lb/> Major <seg type="unclear">Whyte's</seg> letter then we'll have more news <lb/> on it. I sincerely hope you are keeping <lb/> very well and not worrying too much. It <lb/> is really terrible the length of time we <lb/> we have to wait for news.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3891_img_327_2"/>
            trench boots in fact the men said <lb/> it was very hard in the distance <lb/> to recognise him as an officer, he always <lb/> used to say 'What's good enough for the <lb/> men is good enough for me to get <lb/> on with' he seems to have been very <lb/> popular. I would like to meet one of his <lb/> own company - Of course this man knew <lb/> all our family History as he comes from <lb/> George's St. Aunt Agnes sent me a cheque of <lb/>£3.00 out of P Rangis fund to buy things <lb/> for the P. men there are only about <seg type="unclear">5</seg> or <lb/> 6 just now but of course   just more any <lb/>day.   We have been having a rather hot time <lb/> lately. Marion has been in rather a   <lb/> and everyone has been been getting into trouble <lb/> the fact of the matter is no one has <lb/> anything to do we have about 205 <seg type="unclear">workers</seg> <lb/>of 1,200 &amp; a staff twice the size we <lb/> started with so you can imagine how <lb/> things are going, we are all frightfully <lb/> unsettle as no one knows what is going <lb/> to happen to us either. There are so many <lb/> Rumours one does not know what to believe <lb/> but something is going to happen as I am <lb/> just warning you in case you get a cable
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3891_img_327_3"/>
            saying I am sent off to Mesopotamia or <lb/> some such place or perhaps home. one <lb/> rumour is that most of us shall be sent <lb/> straight home but I personally think <lb/> it will be those whose time is up in <lb/> about 6 weeks. You see they are closing <lb/> most of the Forts as Hospitals &amp; put troops <lb/> in them so really no one knows what is <lb/> happening, by the way if I get a choice or chance <lb/> of refusing. Have you any <lb/> object to me going to Mesopotamia, <lb/> India or Africa as these are the places <lb/> mention that we might be sent to yet. <lb/> I personally think it will only be the <lb/> trained sisters who are sent out so far <lb/> a field any how it is just as well you <lb/> should know worst in case of anything <lb/> happening. I shall of course cable as soon as <lb/> we hear definitely. Of course 0 have to delay <lb/> here &amp; if the worst should happen I can <lb/> always consult him. I know what the <lb/> answer will be, I imagine if we are sent <lb/> on further it will mean signing on for <lb/> another six months as they would never send <lb/> us out for 11 weeks so if you would rather <lb/> I did not go further just let me know
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3891_img_327_4"/>
            as I can always get work at home <lb/> &amp; perhaps get out to France for the <lb/> summer. It is miserable here at present <lb/> &amp; we are all fed up being so slack. <lb/>Well I must tell you about my first <lb/>serious row with Matron on Friday. We <lb/>went to a Concert in the Recreation Room <lb/> <hi rend="underline">St.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Georges</hi> &amp; having the evening off from 5 <lb/> <seg type="unclear">O'clock</seg> we had something in our rooms before <lb/>we went down &amp; made up or minds to <lb/>set it out about 20 others came including <lb/>Matron &amp; after she had been there a little <lb/>longer then 1/2 hour she with her very few <lb/>followers got up &amp; went to dinner but <lb/> most of us remained on although the <lb/>Concert was rotten just as it was over. <lb/>Matron arrived back &amp; had a good <lb/>look all round to see who was there, her <lb/>face was white with anger &amp; called me <lb/> &amp; asked me if I had permission to <lb/>remain away from dinner. I said "No <lb/>Matron" Then "Come to my office tomorrow <lb/>morning. I wish to see you all". so up we <lb/>came feeling very naughty!! another <lb/>V.A.S asked me to go &amp; see her up in <lb/> her room for which I had to go through
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3891_img_327_5"/>
            the tent &amp; just as I was walking <lb/>up the stairs I met M who said <lb/>"What are you doing in the tent at <lb/> this hour of the night. So I explained <lb/>to her but I think she thought I <lb/> was stealing the Breakfast Breads, go <lb/> back to your quarters at once, then <lb/>she started giving me what of &amp; said <lb/>I was selfish &amp; broke a great breach <lb/>of Etiquette in not get up &amp; going out <lb/>when she went out, considering I have <lb/>been to a great number of concerts &amp; <lb/> always stayed away from dinner.) <seg type="unclear">Later</seg> <lb/>then she went on to tell me how <lb/> surprised she was at me   Any how things seems to have blown <lb/>away &amp; she seems just as nice as she <lb/>ever was. I may tell you up <lb/>to that I was one of her favourites <lb/> but that it <seg type="unclear">was</seg>   I do not <lb/>care, very much. Aunt Lily has <lb/>just arrived to spend the afternoon <lb/>so will have to end. she saw <lb/>Matron but was not smitten, we <lb/>have just had tea &amp; I have been <lb/>confined to Barracks today as
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3891_img_327_6"/>
            I have had my <seg type="del">second</seg> 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> dose of <lb/>inoculation for Paratyphoid. Just have <lb/>got leave to go out with her <lb/> for drive to Blue Sisters. I am <lb/> feeling alright so far    A Lily sends her very best love <lb/>to all &amp; is looking fairly well. I <lb/>think she would be better with <lb/>more work to do. as it is very <lb/> trying Killing time.   Well I shall end this &amp; write soon <lb/>again as she is waiting for <lb/>me.   Very best of love to you Dearest <lb/>Mother &amp; all at home.   Your most loving &amp; <lb/> grateful daughter   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>   Excuse Scribble 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>