<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5653">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Captain Black, DDOS Cork District to Royal Hospital Kilmainham, 23 February 1916. </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Captain Black </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A series of letters between the Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Dublin and the Chief Crown Solicitor, Dublin Castle concerning an injury sustained by Patrick Sheehan while he was working as a casual labourer employed by the Forage Department to handle hay, oats and straw. The series of letters concerns possible compensation as this was an injury sustained at work. 

This letter is from Captain Black explaining how Patrick Sheehan slipped while carrying sacks and dislocated his ankle. Cpt. Black then advised Patrick Sheehan to put his claim in writing.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_3785_9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5653</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1284">Captain Black </persName>
              <date>1916-02-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0808">6 Lapp&#39;s Quay, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0388">Royal Hospital, Kilmainham, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5653_img_746_1"  type="Letter"  url="a8b339b60b303d4fa4bc06afc1628e06.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5653_img_746_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Subject. Injury of Patrick Sheehan.</hi>   23/2/16.   6, Lapp's Quay, <lb/>Cork.   A.A.O., Ireland, <lb/>Royal Hospital, <lb/>Kilmainham.   1. I attach letter from Mr. Patrick Sheehan who, while <lb/>employed in carrying oats to Messrs Beamish and Craw- <lb/>fords Store, slipped with a bundle of empty sacks and <lb/>injured his ankle. He called here yesterday on crutches <lb/>and I asked him to put his claim in writing.   The favour of your instructions is requested please.   J. Black  <lb/>Captain A.S.C., <lb/>D.D.O.S. Cork District. <lb/>M.C.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>