<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1272">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Caldwell, Head Constable, Liverpool, to the Officer Commanding the Irish National Volunteers, Dublin, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Caldwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter from Francis Caldwell to the Officer commanding the Irish National Volunteers encloses a police report referring to and describing an alleged deserter, Joseph Egan, under the Military Service Act. Also enclosed is the response from Patrick J Reddy of the Irish National Volunteers, declaring no knowledge of the individual in question. Francis Caldwell (c.1860-1934) was the Head Constable of Liverpool at the time of writing this letter. He died at 74 as a decorated officer. The Military Service Act introduced conscription on 27 January 1916. It made men aged between 19 and 41, who had lived in Britain since August 1915 and had no dependent children enlist for general service with the British Armed Forces. The men now came under the controls specified in the Army Act.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NLI10561/2/2a</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1272</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0109">Francis Caldwell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1699">Liverpool, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Officer Commanding the Irish National Volunteers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1272_img_464_1"  type="Letter"  url="94f596b20e253361fc2c3a4ba3dff0a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1272_img_464_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="fe0609086758ef2dcc6b13632fb3b5ef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1272_img_464_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="71e6a9f583ddda77e1b05d44e7f196f3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1272_img_464_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">Telephone No. 8300 Central.</hi><hi rend="underline">Telegrams: 'Devoir, Liverpool.'</hi>   Please address your letter <lb/> THE HEAD CONSTABLE, <lb/> and in your reply quote No. Your reference No.     Central Police Office,  LIVERPOOL    31 March 1916.    I beg to send the attached copy of <sic>Police Report</sic> for your information.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  FRANCIS CALDWELL, <lb/> Head Constable.  </seg> The Officer Commanding. <lb/> Irish National Volunteers. <lb/> Dublin   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1272_img_464_2"/>
              'H'.    General Enquiry Office 29 3 16.  P.C. 151 'H' Constantine.  Inspector on duty.    Mar 10    Alleged deserter under the Military <lb/> Service Act. <lb/>  I beg to report that at <sic>6-25.pm.today</sic> Mr <lb/> Thomas Dickson, Special Constable. (E. Division) called <lb/> at this Office and stated that a <sic>Man</sic>, named Joseph E- <lb/><sic>gan,residing</sic> in Almond <sic>Street,No</sic> not known, had <sic>abscon</sic><sic>ded</sic> to Ireland after having been served with his pap- ers to attend for Military duties <sic>.Complt</sic> states that <lb/> accused is believed to be in Dublin at a Camp of the <lb/> Irish National Volunteers, he is described as follows, <lb/> 29 to <sic>33yrs,5ft</sic> 7 <hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi>',dark hair and heavy moustache; <lb/> usually dresses very respectably, speaks with a broad <lb/> Irish accent and up to 18th inst he was employed at <lb/> Messrs Stonier &amp; <sic>Co.78 Lord Street,when</sic> he left re- <lb/> marking to a friend that things were getting too hot. <lb/>  Constantine   P.C.151'H'.   Submitted Ch. Sup of H. C. O.    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1272_img_464_3"/>
              ÓGLÁIGH TÍORAMHLA NA H-ÉIREANN, — IRISH NATIONAL VOLUNTEERS.  Left-hand side of page    TELEPHONE 4598 DUBLIN,  TELEGRAMS: 'VOLUNTEERS.  Ref. No. <hi rend="underline"> 155 </hi>  COMMUNICATIONS TO BE  ADDRESSED TO  THE INSPECTOR GENERAL  Inspector General's Office,  44, Parnell Square,  Dublin.    Date, <hi rend="underline">3rd. April 1916.</hi>   The Head Constable, <lb/> Central Police Office <lb/> Liverpool . <lb/> Sir,    The Inspector General is in receipt of your memorandum of the <lb/> 31st March re Joseph Egan and begs to inform you that the National <lb/> Volunteers have at present no Camp in the City or County of Dublin.   We do not know anything of the man referred to. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/> Sir, <lb/> Your obedient servant,   Patrick J.Reddy <lb/> Secretary to the Inspector General. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>