<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2238">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Willis, 15 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to a Mr Willis. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter discusses the six county scheme i.e. the exclusion of six Ulster counties from Home Rule, and the possibility of negotiations ending if Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), prime minister, stated the proposal is only provisional until the war is over. The exclusion of Protestants in the south of Ireland from the six counties is also discussed, of which Mongomery states it is better that the six counties help those who have been exuded rather than all of them are subject to an Irish parliament.  Montgomery then contemplates a vote which may be taken by the Irish Unionist Alliance, which he believes is a stab in the back of Edward Carson (1854-1935), Unionist leader. Montgomery then states that he will be pleased to see the attempts of David Lloyd George MP (1863-1945) at finding common ground fail.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2238</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2238_img_1682_1"  type="Letter"  url="393f2f954a1887b3af8ca23c3ef676fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2238_img_1682_2"  type="Letter"  url="3c5ac23428d30bb56a55d9dc2e1a003d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2238_img_1682_1"/>
            Copy  15th June, 1916.   My dear Willis,   Till we see whether Asquith's announcement that Lloyd <lb/>George's proposal is a "provisional" one puts an end to <lb/>negotiations or not, the position is hardly worth arguing <lb/>about; but I write a line to say that I totally disagree with <lb/>you as to our having "absolutely protected our own interests," <lb/>as I think the suggested six County Province, though easier <lb/>to defend than the whole Province, will be an exceedingly <lb/>uncomfortable salient to live in; but if anything comes of <lb/>the scheme, we shall be in a better position to help our <lb/>friends standing, as it were, on dry land ourselves, than <lb/>if we were all drowned together under an Irish Parliament.   The question of the exclusion of Ulster was, I think, <lb/>very thoroughly considered by Unionists, North and South, <lb/>before the war, and I was under the impression that all Unionists <lb/>whose opinions were worth anything, were agreed that Ulster <lb/>Unionists were serving the interests of Southern Unionists as <lb/>well as their own in insisting upon exclusion. I do not think <lb/>the I.U.A. is at all likely to pass such a silly resolution as <lb/>you suggest. It would strengthen the hands of the more selfish <lb/>members of the Ulster community in devoting themselves altogether <lb/>to the safeguarding of their own interests and neglecting those <lb/>of Unionists outside their borders; a line the majority of us <lb/>have never hitherto taken; but we should all bitterly resent <lb/>such a stab in the back to Carson at a time when he is doing
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2238_img_1682_2"/>
            his best to get the best available terms for all Unionists <lb/>North and South. We do not see what use we could be either <lb/>to you or to ourselves in a permanent minority in a Dublin <lb/>Parliament. I am altogether against schemes to strengthen <lb/>one rebel faction against another; but for many reasons I <lb/>should be well pleased to see Lloyd George's <sic>eirenicon</sic> rejected <lb/>by a Nationalist Convention. Barring a few Belfast men of <lb/>business, nobody <hi rend="underline">likes</hi>the position as we are now in; but I hold <lb/>that we chose the least of the evil alternatives with which <lb/>we were faced, in the interest of Southern Unionists as <lb/>well as in our own.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>