<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2646">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maria Duffin to Celia Duffin, 9 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

This letters, from Maria to her daughter Celia, is filled with  news of family and friends.  She mentions that Terry has arrived. They have visited Wolfhill. She also writes that Aunt Elizabeth is dying.  

She writes they met Mrs Lee Dawne after her return from Siberia. She notes that Mrs Dawne is very thin as she had to march 20 miles a day, suffered cold and hunger, as well as the hardships of a retreating army, including witnessing dead men along the route who had perished from hunger and cold</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/A/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2646</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2646_img_2071_1"  type="Letter"  url="5aa50099cbf1234be53a9b7304f76223.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2646_img_2071_2"  type="Letter"  url="44dad75047da560632543a2c8b289bbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2646_img_2071_3"  type="Letter"  url="414e00e88dbaad7fed55825ff2ed3477.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2646_img_2071_4"  type="Letter"  url="6353ba5b7ca292d98a20182ed39b3739.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2646_img_2071_5"  type="Letter"  url="9b278be2ade3757a89c173f80eb01e84.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2646_img_2071_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/A   Jan. 9<hi rend="superscript">:</hi> 1916    DUNOWEN,<lb/>BELFAST.    Dearest Celia.   Terry arrived this<lb/>morning, looking very well.<lb/>He wired &amp; telephoned to you<lb/>to meet him for lunch. but<lb/>had no reply. I suppose you<lb/>had gone to   <seg type="unclear">Boad</seg>.   He will be in London on<lb/>next Friday again: perhaps<lb/>you could arrange to meet<lb/>someway. It is a joy to<lb/>have him for a few days.  We were at Wolfhill yester—<lb/>day: we went for a walk,<lb/>but the usual rain came<lb/>on. They are feeling very<lb/>dreary. Naturally and I 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2646_img_2071_2"/>
             am sorry for both.  Old Aunt Elizabeth is dying,<lb/>I had post a card from<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Morris and she gave no<lb/>particulars, but said she<lb/>was unconscious and slept<lb/>most of the time. Under the<lb/>circumstances, I saw no good<lb/>in going. but told her to<lb/>inform Aunt E's  . if<lb/>she was in correspondence<lb/>with them. I have heard no<lb/>more and suppose she may<lb/>linger for a day or two, poor<lb/>old lady!   We were at a musical at home<lb/>at M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi>   on Thursday:<lb/>the usual   people. M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi><lb/>P. Cott. Higgins had a solemn<lb/>colloquy with me about      <lb/>Dorothy. He was afraid we<lb/>might think they had spread<lb/>the news of her engagement.<lb/>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> <seg type="unclear">Horburgh</seg> had spoken to<lb/>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi> Cadell, so it was all out<lb/>and I had to make the best<lb/>of it and say there never<lb/>had been a real engagement.<lb/> but it is very awkward.<lb/>J. has a very stiff neck.<lb/>got. I suppose. by coming<lb/>out of very hot rooms at<lb/>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi> B's and going on with<lb/>me to the adults tea party<lb/>at the <seg type="unclear"></seg> However, it<lb/>is better today. No letter<lb/>yet from Emma. It is a<lb/>fortnight since we had<lb/>one. but M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi> Finlay had     
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2646_img_2071_3"/>
             heard and the Floyd Campbells<lb/>had an acknowledgment of<lb/>some sweets, so I suppose she<lb/>is all right.  We met M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi> Lee Dawne after<lb/>her Serbian adventures. She<lb/>is very thin and had to<lb/>march 20 miles a day and<lb/>suffered cold &amp; hunger. and<lb/>all the hardships of a retreating<lb/>army. but is very cheery<lb/>about it all. Dead men &amp;<lb/>horses all along the route.<lb/>who perished from hunger<lb/>&amp; cold. I am glad Dorothy<lb/>was not with her. Mrs<lb/>Calwell and others are<lb/>Aurthian <seg type="unclear"></seg>  employed.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2646_img_2071_4"/>
             D2109/10/1/A  2  DUNOWEN, BELFAST.  as nurses.  I have written to engage<lb/>a young cook who turned<lb/>up and hope to get her<lb/>settled in soon, but she is<lb/>reported noisy. and has not<lb/>been in good places. They<lb/>are very scarce, and I want<lb/>a cheap one. there times.<lb/>I suppose you are just<lb/>plodding along, I fear having<lb/>a dull monotonous time,<lb/>Dorothy is swithering as to what<lb/>to do. Colonel <seg type="unclear">Damet</seg> has<lb/>just informed her that no<lb/>V.A.Ds get paid anything 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2646_img_2071_5"/>
             until after three years full<lb/>training! Such is<lb/>the knowledge he possesses!<lb/>and he says he has V.A.Ds<lb/>in Hospitals under him,<lb/>which. I presume. are military!  Ruth went back last Tuesday.<lb/>and comes over today for tea.<lb/>after lunching at Hopefield.<lb/>She thought Effe very<lb/>normal. When she saw her.<lb/>but was convinced she needed<lb/>a change. She was. evidently.<lb/>badly managed in the first<lb/>nursing Have and suffered<lb/>in consequence.  I hope you got Emma's present<lb/>all right.  Goodbye now darling. much<lb/>love. Is there no chance of<lb/>your getting any leave?<lb/>It seems hard after seven<lb/>long months.  Your loving   Mammy.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>