<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6343">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Máire Ní Dhonnghaile to Ellen Daly, 20 June 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Máire Ní Dhonnghaile</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/4/6/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6343</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0652">Máire Ní Dhonnghaile</persName>
              <date>1923-06-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0949">Labby, Draperstown, Derry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6343_img_None_1"  url="55c316ea7ddd5eea20087bddb180d870.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6343_img_None_2"  url="928d6ed131f7fdbf03d1ccc3f3b78f3c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6343_img_None_3"  url="c06979c4288ffcd91fbc9b2372de9a50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6343_img_None_4"  url="2c6faf097fa9db2e8e0f7c2474819200.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6343_img_0_1"/>
             P41/4/6/15   Labby<lb/>Draperstown<lb/>Co Derry    20.6.23 <lb/><lb/> Dear Mrs Daly,     <lb/>I received your<lb/>letter allright yesterday &amp; I wish<lb/>to thank you for the photo and<lb/>the letters enclosed. The photo<lb/>is a very good one, and the<lb/>letters are beautiful, although<lb/>sad. They are the works of a<lb/>saint. Dear Mrs Daly dont<lb/>mourn for Charlie as he is in<lb/>Heaven, in Pearse's Brigade,<lb/>rather be proud you had a<lb/>son to die for Ireland.  We are sorry to hear of 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6343_img_0_2"/>
             your other boys being in jail<lb/>but we trust they will be<lb/>released soon. My brother Joe<lb/>done 8 months in Derry prison.<lb/>He was sentenced to 6 mts but was<lb/>kept for 2 months longer, that<lb/>is the sort of justice <seg type="del">l</seg> we get<lb/>up here. I know a man<lb/>Jim Kelly of Straw, Draperstown,<lb/>a relation of the late Dr Ferran<lb/>who is on Craigs prison ship<lb/>the Argenta for the last 13<lb/>months without any charge being<lb/>preferred against him &amp; the<lb/>question is when they will<lb/>be released. But bad as the<lb/>specials are they would not<lb/>shoot anyone for carrying a<lb/>revolver, but the F.S.is setting<lb/>them a good example 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6343_img_0_3"/>
             I see times are still unsettled<lb/>down South . To tell the<lb/>truth, I dont read the papers<lb/>we get up here, as they just<lb/>give the F.S. side of things,<lb/>and therefore are not to be<lb/>credited. So I am a bit<lb/>ignorant of the situation in<lb/>Southern Ireland.  In a sense we have peace<lb/>up here, but what prospects?<lb/>We are getting leave to live,<lb/>nothing more. We dare not<lb/>have a dance or party because<lb/>of Curfew. We were all curfewed<lb/>at a party in Mrs Kelly's Labby<lb/>on the 8<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> of April I hid upstairs<lb/>&amp; they did not find <hi rend="superscript">me</hi> but they got<lb/>my name aftterwards, We were<lb/>just <seg type="del">find</seg> fined in 2/6 &amp; costs 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6343_img_0_4"/>
             The crops up here are not very<lb/>promising especially the oat crop<lb/>which has come abraird, to<lb/>disappear again, There is no price<lb/>for produce, eggs 1/ per doz. butter<lb/>10d per pound &amp; in April you could<lb/>get a load of potatoes from big<lb/>farmers for 9d as there was no sale,<lb/>for them, and they wanted their fields<lb/>cleared for ploughing. So that<lb/>is of some prosperity for Ulster.  I think I will finish up now.<lb/>I enclose <seg type="del">o</seg> a memoriam card. It is<lb/>not a very good one, but we must<lb/>take what we get. Best Wishes<lb/>from   Yours Sincerely    <seg type="foreign">Maire Ni Dhonnghaile</seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>