<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2607">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B.J. Collingwood to Edward O’Farrell, 2 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>B.J. Collingwood </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from B.J Collingwood, Professor of Pathology and Bacteriology at University College Dublin, to Sir. Edward O’Farrell (c. 1857-1926), the assistant under-secretary, Dublin Castle.

As a person licensed to carry out experiments on animals, Collingwood  was obliged to furnish an annual Return of Experiments. In this letter he is submits his Return together with an apology for its lateness due to work pressures.

Enclosed is a letter from Edward O’Farrell to B.J. Collingwood, dated 22 February 1916, in which the Return of Experiments is requested.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5781</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2607</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1545">B.J. Collingwood </persName>
              <date>1916-04-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0877">Adelaide House, Earlsfort Terrace, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2607_img_2031_1"  type="Letter"  url="c8e84349a8a31bfd8152eca7178f9b30.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2607_img_2031_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="9496008ff64093dcb297114a0d894eb7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2607_img_2031_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="7311c1cf23d5b3b8300cf5ceb11082db.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2607_img_2031_1"/>
             Adelaide House <lb/>Carlsfort Terrace <lb/>Dublin   Ap 2 1916   Dear Sir,   I am very sorry that by an <lb/>oversight I have ommitted to send <lb/>this earlier. I have been <lb/>completed overwhelmed with <lb/>work at University &amp; also from <lb/>Military.   faithfully yrs   B. Hollingwood 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2607_img_2031_2"/>
             2654  <lb/><hi rend="underline">IMMEDIATE.</hi>  Dublin Castle,   22nd February 1916   Sir,   I am directed by the Chief Secretary to request that you will state on <lb/>the enclosed form :—   (1) The number of experiments on living animals performed by you in <lb/>the year ended 31st December ;ast, under licence granted to you <lb/>under the Act 39 and 40 Vic, cap. 77, or any special certificate <lb/>you may have held during that year:   (2) The general purpose of the experiments; and   (3) The number of those experiments in which there was reason to <lb/>believe that any appreciable pain was inflicted, specifying the <lb/>kind of animal used and stating in general terms the nature of <lb/>the experiment occasioned pain.   All experiments under Certificate C must be performed with anaesthetics, <lb/>and it should be stated in your Return that the animals used were killed before <lb/>recovery from anaethesia.   I have also to request that you will furnish in Table 4 of the form <lb/>enclosed a complete list of any writings based upon the experimental work which <lb/>you may have published during the past year, giving the full title of each <lb/>paper with an exact reference to any periodical in which it may have appeared, <lb/>and the name of any Society to which it may have been communicated, and <lb/>that if you have not already done so, you will forward copies of such papers <lb/>for the information of the Chief Secretary.   As it is desirable that the preparation of the Parliamentary Return <lb/>relating to Experiments on Living Animals should be undertaken at once, you <lb/>Return should be furnished within one week.   Your licence under the Act <seg type="del">will</seg> expire d  on the 28th <seg type="del">instant</seg>  Feb,1915, . <seg type="del">If you desire <lb/>its renewal an application to that effect should be made stating the grounds. <lb/>The licence should at the same time be forwarded.</seg>   I am, <lb/>SIR, <lb/>Your obedient Servant   E O'Connell   B.J Collingwood, Esqr MD, <lb/>Adelaide House <lb/>Earlsfort Terrace, <lb/>Dublin 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2607_img_2031_3"/>
            <!-- <lb/>RETURN of Experiments performed in the Year 1915 by the holder of <lb/>Licence No. 89 <lb/>TABLE 1. — NUMBER OF EXPERIMENTS. <lb/>Under Under Certificates <lb/>Licence alone Under Certificates <lb/> A. B. C. D. E.+A. EE.+B. F. <lb/>None None <lb/> <hi rend="underline"> </hi> <lb/>TABLE 2. — GENERAL PURPOSE OF EXPERIMENTS. <lb/>Number of Physiological. Number of Pathological. Number of Therapeutical. <lb/> None None None <lb/> <hi rend="underline"> </hi> <lb/>TABLE 3. — PARTICULARS OF EXPERIMENTS. <lb/>Number Animals used <lb/>of and Object. General Nature. <lb/>experiments. number. <lb/> <hi rend="underline"> </hi> <lb/>TABLE 4. — LIST OF WRITINGS BASED UPON EXPERIMENTAL WORK PUBLISHED DURING <lb/>THE YEAR. <lb/> Exact reference to Periodicals Name of Society to which <lb/>Full title of Paper. in which is was <lb/> it appeared. communicated. <lb/> <hi rend="underline"> </hi> <lb/>Signature, B.J Collingwood <lb/> Date, April 2 1916   (1.18) <lb/>(4003.) Wt.7455—66.2.125.3/14.A.T.&amp;Co, Ltd.  -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>