<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4160">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 10 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/52</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4160</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4160_img_3533_1"  type="Letter"  url="8fa954221810d0b30cfb64edb60c1b49.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4160_img_3533_2"  type="Letter"  url="f77c565418f3eb0979081b2cca991c32.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4160_img_3533_1"/>
             10 Nov   My pv.   I will try one more letter to Rugby but afterwards until <lb/>Saturday I will send them to 29.   What will Mater think of your daily post ! ! I know <lb/>she will want to hear "all the news."   It is a wet day &amp; so I mind the loss that Richardson has <lb/>gone off for a long tour investigating a serious charge against the <lb/>misuse of the post — luckily not by one of your own Ulster men <lb/>but by one of the new people attached to us.   I do not think that our <seg type="unclear">morphia magnate</seg>will come out <lb/>after all &amp; for once justice may be done though I shall be much <lb/>surprised if he does not get a brigade at home in consequence! I <lb/>would bet odds on something of this sort.   I told you I think that <seg type="unclear">M'Carmmon's</seg>battalion had been trans- <lb/>ferred to the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div as a Reserve. He is awfully upset &amp;I find it <lb/>difficult to forgive Gen Powell's <sic>obtinacy</sic>in  Craig's &amp;my advice <lb/>to apply for this battalion for our Div<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>. In the more latter days <lb/>he would I feel have taken this advice, but at that time he was <lb/>very much the autocrat, as you may remember.   How is your cold? I do hope gone. Mine has practically <lb/>&amp; in any case it won't do for you to take it to Mater's. She <lb/>will probably insist on rubbing you with her rings on , a performance <lb/>which I remember even now with some terror ! I <seg type="unclear">am just the</seg>  <lb/> <seg type="del">good</seg> too much butter &amp; new French bread perhaps but I hope <lb/>my tabloids will put this right. The Gen' is distinctly that way
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4160_img_3533_2"/>
            &amp;at meals is very trying sometimes bursting out into a wild <lb/>tirade suddenly about the food or waiting. Thank Heavens Farnham <lb/>is responsible for the mess,&amp; in consequence it does not react on <lb/>him as it <seg type="del">does</seg> would on any one else who has less intime, or a mere <lb/>Commoner ! a very important point. I was next to him last <lb/>night &amp; continued my conversation with  during this outburst <lb/>on purpose — it was a one sided converstion &amp; I am not sure whether <lb/>it was approved.  was strong on mixing the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>&amp;36 Div' <lb/>but I think I convinced him that he would be making a dangerous <lb/>experiment. I asked him what he thought would be the result if some of <lb/>one Div<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> (e g the guns) shot at some of the other, which must often <lb/>happen especially at night, or some shot near them, or if one was <lb/>a little late in supporting the other,  through no fault perhaps, ..., can't you imagine !   This thoughtlessness is so typically the English point of view.   Have you read Miss Bates' article in the Nov Nat' Review on <lb/>Carson &amp; Ulster. It is very good tho' a little flattering in style. You might <lb/>write our joint congratulations if you have time Send it c/o him at the <lb/>Ulster club if you wish.   I will close now as I think you are rather a spoilt <lb/>p r , but you pass on the spoiling too   Ever your b w    W.BSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>