<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4462">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Campbell to Matthew Nathan, 6 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Campbell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from Henry Campbell to Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), Under-Secretary for Ireland. The letter states that an enclosed letter to the censor has also been sent to the Chief Secretary (Augustine Birrell).  In the enclosed letter, Henry Campbell states that the letters coming to his office have been opened and that he does not know why the censor is suspicious of him.  He claims his innocence and says that opening his letters is an insult.  An enclosed report outlines the detail of an interview with Henry Campbell in which he expressed that Sinn Fein &#34;was becoming very dangerous and foretold rioting in Dublin&#34;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_491_1_1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4462</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1011">Henry Campbell</persName>
              <date>1916-01-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4462_img_381_1"  type="Letter"  url="dcbf89568aa874aee40930b4e3558d33.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4462_img_381_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="ea2e94847aa301a8fe4f7b595d4b7294.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4462_img_381_3"  type="Letter"  url="d70290331459c9e3ea9d42b3a5364a98.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4462_img_381_1"/>
             The Town Clerk's Office,<lb/>City Hall,<lb/>Dublin   4th Jany. 1916.    Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G.,<lb/>Under Secretary for Ireland    Sir,   I think it right to send you a copy of a letter which<lb/>I have to-day addressed to the Censor. I have also addressed<lb/>a copy to the Chief Secretary.<lb/>I have the honour to be,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your Obedient Servant,<lb/> Henry Campbell <lb/>Town Clerk.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4462_img_381_2"/>
             The Town Clerk's Office<lb/>City Hall,<lb/>Dublin   14th.  Jany. , 1916    To The Censor,<lb/>C/O the Secretary,<lb/>General Post Office, DUBLIN.    Sir,   I notice that some of the letters coming to me officially,<lb/>as Town Clark of Dublin, at my office in the City Hall, have<lb/>been opened by you. I do not know what has created in your<lb/>mind, or in the mind of any other Government official, a sus-<lb/>picion in this crisis with regard to me. A suspicion there<lb/>must be, and an infernally ill-founded one; for, be it known to<lb/>you, whoever you are, and to every person connected with the<lb/>government of the Empire, that I am as loyal a subject as you<lb/>or any of them are; and that I take this opportunity— the only<lb/>one so far available to me— of resenting this insult. It is<lb/>all the greater insult to me to think that a letter coming from<lb/>Cavendish Place, in the City of Dublin, should be opened. So<lb/>far as I am concerned, the Government and all its officials can<lb/>examine into my conduct; and I think that it will be found to<lb/>be on a much higher level, so far as the Empire and Government<lb/>affairs are concerned, that that of some of those who are draw-<lb/>ing big salaries from the Government.  I am sending a copy of this letter to the Chief Secretary<lb/>to the Lord Lieutenant.   I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient servant,   HENRY CAMPBELL, <lb/>Town Clerk. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4462_img_381_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Memorandum of Interview.</hi>  THE TOWN CLERK, Dublin, (Mr Henry Campbell)<lb/>came to see me this afternoon on the subject of his<lb/>letter of the 4th January forwarding a copy of one<lb/>he had addressed on the same day to the Censor at<lb/>Dublin. He had been unwell yesterday and was<lb/>unable to come and see me as I had asked him to do.  He had seen Mr. MacMahon this morning and had<lb/>given him the various covers to which he had referred<lb/>in his letter. He appeared to recognize that<lb/>there <seg type="del">w</seg> c ould be no official censorship of his letters<lb/>and, was anxious that the persons who had been tamper-<lb/>ing with his correspondence should be detected.  He spoke at some length on the subject of<lb/>Sinn Fein persons in the Government service referring<lb/>to men recently taken on by the Registrar-General.  He did not now require any reply to his letter<lb/>of the 4th January.  I asked Mr. Campbell what he thought of the<lb/>prospects of the election for the Mayoralty, and<lb/>he had little doubt but that Councillor Gallagher<lb/>would be re-elected and that matters between the<lb/>Government and the Dublin Corporation would go on<lb/>in the same smooth way during the coming as they<lb/>had done during the past year. He did not think<lb/>that the Labour and Sinn Fein Parties combined<lb/>would be able to determine the election. He<lb/>thought, however, that the latter Party was becoming<lb/>very dangerous and foretold rioting in Dublin.   DUBLIN CASTLE,    6th January, 1916.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>