<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0357">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Irish Prisoners, Frongoch to T. M. Healy Esq., KC, MP, 10 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by a group of Irish prisoners in Frongoch to Timothy Healy. In this letter the prisoners quote a letter previously read to them which remitted the punishment of prisoners for refusing to preform fatigue duty.The letter also refers to a hunger strike, in protest of such punishment, that has since ceased. Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; because of the revolutionary nature of the inmates.Timothy Michael &#39;Tim&#39; Healy (1855–1931) was an Irish journalist, author, barrister and an Irish Parliamentary Party MP. He was one of the few King&#39;s Counsel who represented Irish prisoners detained at Frongoch Internment Camp after the Easter Rising in 1916. Among the signatories to this letter are Michael Staines, Thomas Sinnott and Richard Mulcahy.Staines (1885 - 1955) was a member of the Irish Republican Brotherhood and served as Quartermaster in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was elected Head Leader by his peers.Sinnott (1893 - 1965) was the Officer Commanding Wexford Brigade, 1916. After the rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was a Room Leader.Richard Mulcahy (1886 - 1971) fought with Thomas Ashe in Ashbourne during the Easter Rising. After the Rising, he was detained in Frongoch where he was also a Room Leader</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD 45/4/9/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/357</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0137">Frongoch Internment Camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">T. M. Healy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0357_img_1595_1"  type="Letter"  url="4b58ed6ba37fa03e1be16398f1682344.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0357_img_1595_2"  type="Letter"  url="5b3886a18cf738fdcb19e082a27f63d2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0357_img_1595_1"/>
                10th Oct 1916.   Sir,   This morning about 10.30 a.m. the Camp Leaders were<lb/> brought before the Commandant and the following letter read<lb/> to them:-  Home Office,<lb/> Whitehall. 9th Oct. 1916 313106<lb/> Sir,  I am directed by the Secretary of State to say that<lb/> he has had under his consideration the case of the prisoners<lb/> now under punishment for refusing to perform <seg type="unclear">fatigue</seg> duty<lb/> ordered by you (removal of rubbish from the Guard's quarters)<lb/> and it appears to him that they have now been sufficiently<lb/> punished for this offence. He has therefore decided to remit<lb/> the remainder of the punishment and also for the future to<lb/> relieve them from this particular duty, which he understands<lb/> from you, can be properly performed by the Guard.  In announcing this decision to the prisoners the<lb/> Secretary of State desires that you should make it clear that<lb/> in his opinion you were right in requiring them to perform this duty and right in punishing those who refused,<lb/> but the matter being a trifling one he does not desire to<lb/> carry the matter further.  I am, Sir,<lb/> Your obedient servant,<lb/>(Sgd) M.L. Waller.<lb/> The Commandant,<lb/>Prisoners of War Camp,<lb/>Frongoch.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0357_img_1595_2"/>
              As a result of the above letter all the prisoners<lb/> confined in the North Camp are being brought back to-day,<lb/> except the eight prisoners whose case has been dealt with<lb/> in Paras. dated 4th and 5th Oct. of our previous letter to<lb/> you dated Frongoch 8th Oct.  We have only quite recently heard that two other<lb/> prisoners (H. Wilson and M. Kent) who were of the above<lb/> fatigueparty, were also undergoing a hunger strike in the <lb/> North Camp since last Thursday, they contending that the<lb/> stoppage of their letters was also inflicting a punishment<lb/> on their people at home. In deference to the earnest wishes <lb/> of the Catholic Chaplain here these two prisoners above mentioned<lb/> consented to take their meals this morning. <seg type="closer"> We desire to remain, Sir, <lb/> Your Obedient Servants, <lb/> M.S. Head Leader <lb/> No. 1 Room Leader<lb/> No. 3 ' '<lb/> No. 4 ' '</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>