<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5710">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
In this letter James speaks of the wedding plans, the choice of dress and some loving banter. He recounts how there was Volunteer activity in Dublin the night before, shots fired in Grafton Street.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5710</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2081">Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5710_img_812_1"  type="Letter"  url="f0ca4d11a5f052a218e51fbb28e15c05.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5710_img_812_2"  type="Letter"  url="8e3dda0d624e28c7114b5a24768d451a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5710_img_812_1"/>
              office in Grafton Street. I<lb/>don’t know what is going to be<lb/>the end of it all but I hope for<lb/>the best. No other news here I<lb/>think. Mrs Ross of Longford was<lb/>up seeing us yesterday evening and<lb/>I believe there was something between<lb/>the brother James Fitzpatrick and<lb/>Miss Dooner of Longford but it’s all<lb/>off now she tells me. Mother and<lb/>everyone here well as usual. Give<lb/>my regards to your mother and<lb/>all and with my warmest and<lb/>fondest love and kisses to yourself. <lb/>  Always your loving<lb/>James     National Health Commission (Ireland),<lb/>Pembroke House,<lb/>Upper Mount Street,<lb/>Dublin.    31st March 1916     My dearest May,    Thanks very much for your loving letter to-day which has<lb/>brightened the whole day for me. I am glad that you are thinking of<lb/>the 1st June as a settled date even <sic>although</sic> you haven’t made up your<lb/>mind finally on the point. Personally I think it’s all tommy rot about<lb/>bad luck and so on if the date is deferred or if the day is wet or if<lb/>you’re married in May and so on. A great deal of the luck depends on<lb/>people themselves and although I don’t deserve anything in that way I am hoping<lb/>that I may dodge the bad luck under your tender and sheltering wing.<lb/>I hardly imagine that you will have the bad luck anyhow for you don’t deserve it<lb/>so I ought to be quite safe as long as I hang on to your petticoat. So far as<lb/>I’m concerned I’m prepared to chance my arm if you made up your mind to<lb/>go off immediately after Easter and I’m leaving all decisions of that nature to<lb/>you, especially now that I know you’re such an “ancient piece of goods”<lb/>and such an” ould granny”. So I’ll hug the prospect of the 1st of June<lb/>to my heart and keep my love hot and my heart up with the hope of 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5710_img_812_2"/>
             of my dream coming true. I hope your dream anyhow won’t come true. I'm<lb/>very, very fond of you right enough but I doubt if I could endure being a<lb/>guest at your wedding to somebody else, however much I might wish you<lb/>luck and happiness. I expect you must have been thinking about what I<lb/>told you when I was down and dreamt about it. About the white silk<lb/>I do hope you will decide on it. I’d love to see my darling girl in white silk<lb/>for I’m sure she would look glorious in it. I’m afraid though if you looked too<lb/>well the morning of our marriage that I’d be nearly afraid to touch you and<lb/>then what would I do? Jennie wouldn’t be vexed at you for liking to look<lb/>your best on the most important day of your life, indeed she’d probably be more<lb/>vexed if she thought you had put the idea of the white silk out of your<lb/>head on her account. In any case you can bring it with you on your honeymoon<lb/>and put it on for her and she can pluck you to pieces for all I care.<lb/>I’ll be tired of you by then! I hope you will continue to remember me<lb/>in your prayers as I want them all very badly indeed. I’m trying to pull<lb/>myself together so as to be a little better worthy of you and the struggle is<lb/>a hard one. I doubt sometimes whether I’ll ever be any use to you or any<lb/>one else and upon my word the more I think of it the more I realise what a<lb/>very unwise and innocent girl you are ever to agree to chance yourself with<lb/>this miserable son of a gun. Talking about guns, the Volunteers held a big meeting<lb/>in town last night to protest against the deportations of Volunteers organisers<lb/>and there was a row afterwards with the police in which revolvers were freely used.<lb/>No one luckily was hurt but there were a lot of shots fired passing the Recruiting 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>