<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0587">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to Peter Quinn, 10 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Andrew Philip Magill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from A.P. Magill (1871-1941) in which he advises Fr. Quinn that a permit has been granted to hold a Nationalist demonstration.The complete correspondence is available here. It begins on 4 August 1916 in a letter from Fr. Quinn Mr. Asquith, Prime Minister. He wrote directly to the P.M. as the new chief secretary had not yet taken up duty. He had applied to the R.I.C. County Inspector for permission to hold a nationalist demonstration but hasn&#39;t received a reply and he fears that the application will be refused on the grounds that the demonstration is likely to lead to disturbances. This, he strongly refutes, indicating that the fears of the R.I.C are groundless due to the location chosen. The motivation for the rally is to help keep the local youth from following ‘courses’ other than the campaign for Home Rule.Magill served as Private Secretary to a number of Chief Secretaries for Ireland, to the Reverend Peter Quinn, Parish Priest of Coalisland, County Tyrone.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13804</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/587</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date>1916-08-10T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Peter Quinn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1101">Parochial House, Coalisland, County Tyrone</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0587_img_1990_1"  type="Letter"  url="a0b316c330a07dd3b95e9967b293a17c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0587_img_1990_2"  type="Letter"  url="c8f333063f0c6cc089f54c358212e26e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0587_img_1990_3"  type="Letter"  url="f1c7829cc75427244aaf68a1467b8e19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0587_img_1990_4"  type="Letter"  url="5a3b55c67731ed4e6ad042a1e83dfc6c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0587_img_1990_5"  type="Letter"  url="85fd80032e4490be65d967d7eb139f16.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0587_img_1990_6"  type="Letter"  url="8009187047adeba2548a40e4bf84038a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0587_img_1990_1"/>
                10th August, 1916.   Dear Sir,   With reference to your letter of the <lb/>4th instant, which has been forwarded to the <lb/>Chief Secretary, I am desired by him to state <lb/>that he understands directions have already <lb/>been given that a permit may be granted for <lb/>the holding of the meeting to which you refer <lb/>under proper restrictions. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,   A.P.M.   The Rev. Peter Quinn, P.P.,  Parochial House,  Coalisland,  Co. Tyrone.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0587_img_1990_2"/>
              <hi rend="underline">POST OFFICE TELEGRAPHS</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">MESSAGE RECEIVED IN THE IRISH OFFICE.</hi>  Date Aug 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>1916    Handed in at Dublin Castle   at . Received here at 5.16pm  From Brennan To Magill   Your telegram of today re Father Quinn's application <lb/>to Prime Minister about Stewartstown meeting.  In accordance with Chief Secretarys minute of <lb/>yesterday the Inspector General has been informed <lb/>that a permit may be granted on condition that <lb/>Bands and Banners are eliminated and that there <lb/>should be no organised processions to or from the <lb/>field and no excursion trains.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0587_img_1990_3"/>
                AUG 9 16   WIRED AT 12.14pm <lb/><hi rend="underline">Wire</hi> Under Secretary,   The Revd. P. Quinn <lb/>P.P. writes to the P.M. re <lb/>proposed meeting at Stewartstown <lb/>on 15 inst. As his letter is <lb/>dated 4 inst. I <sic>wd</sic> like to <lb/>send him reply today. Will <lb/>you kindly suggest reply. The <lb/>file is with you. <seg type="closer"> Magill. </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0587_img_1990_4"/>
              Irish Office    Parochial House  Coalisland  Co. Tyrone    4<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Aug 1916  <lb/>To/ <lb/>The Right â Honourable <lb/>Mr. Asquith, Primeminister  Right Honourable Sir   I beg to inform <lb/>you that I have applied to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><lb/>Miller County Inspector R.I.C. for <lb/>County Tyrone for a 'permit' to hold <lb/>an openâair Nationalist demonstration <lb/>in this parish of Stewartstown on the <lb/>15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst &amp; that though it is a week <lb/>since I made this application I have <lb/>not yet received any definite reply.  I have reasons for believing that the <lb/>Police Authorities will most likely <lb/>refuse my request on the grounds that  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0587_img_1990_5"/>
               (2)  they fear opposition &amp; disturbance from <lb/>the Orangemen of the neighbourhood.  Now I wish to assure you that their <lb/>fears are groundless as we have been <lb/>most careful to select for our place <lb/>of meeting a locality entirely Catholic <lb/>&amp; Nationalist &amp; one in which we have <lb/>had large demonstrations before that <lb/>there never was the least attempt at <lb/>disturbance. Our motives for holding <lb/>this demonstration are of the purest <lb/>kind, &amp; are mainly to keep our young <lb/>men from falling into the hands of leaders <lb/>who would commit them to other courses.  We the Nationalists of Co. Tyrone feel <lb/>very acutely the great Constitutional <lb/>Grievance with which we are threatened <lb/>by exclusion from the benefits of a Home <lb/>Rule Parliament notwithstanding the fact <lb/> that we are 55 per cent of the population <lb/>&amp; have for years past returned three out of <lb/>four members of the County as Home Rulers.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0587_img_1990_6"/>
               (3)  Is it not then more desirable <lb/>&amp; safer to have our grievances ven <lb/>tilated in the open &amp; thus offer <lb/>a safety-valve for our wounded feelings <lb/>than to have them find vent in the <lb/>halls of some Secret Society?  I do not wish to make my appeal <lb/>longer &amp; I am very sorry to have to <lb/>trouble you amidst your heavy <sic>burthens</sic><lb/>&amp; cares in these awful times, but as <lb/>the new Chief Secretary has not as yet <lb/>taken up his duties I felt obliged <lb/>to do soâ <seg type="closer"> I remain <lb/>Right Honourable Sir <lb/>Yours respectfully   Peter Quinn P.P. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>