<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0415">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Madge Calnan to James Ryan, 17 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Madge Calnan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Madge Calnan to James Ryan (1891-1970). She refers to a misunderstanding in a previous letter. She writes to James about news in University College Dublin and the exams that are going on. She also mentions a picnic organised that day in Tallaght for the Irish Relief Fund. The letter ends with a reference to buttons from the uniform of another arrested rebel, which Madge wants as a souvenir of the Rising.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch, and was released in August 1916. Ryan later became a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/20 (1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/415</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1385">Madge Calnan</persName>
              <date>1916-06-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1497">Loreto Hall, 77 Stephen&#39;s Green</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1797">Stafford Prison, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0415_img_171_1"  type="Letter"  url="2507cdaebc0c5dd489705b2028b6ea2b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0415_img_171_2"  type="Letter"  url="7dccdcec1a879aae0731d875529835eb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0415_img_171_3"  type="Letter"  url="06aa17c9826a1cda6e568202238d5882.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0415_img_171_4"  type="Letter"  url="0269da79478ddd74e7f7b2dc394ad8c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0415_img_171_5"  type="Letter"  url="8e2f37fe2d9c566b20417e294cef60a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0415_img_171_1"/>
                Loreto Hall,  77 Stephens Green.    17-6-'16   Dear Jim   Thanks ever so <lb/>much for your lovely long <lb/>letter. It was very good <lb/> of you to write again, but I <lb/> have a crow to pluck with <lb/>you. If you were annoyed <lb/> at my having thought that <lb/> the Gaelic excursion was <lb/>put off on your account, I <lb/>was doubly annoyed at <lb/> the way you read it. What <lb/>I meant was how could <lb/>the college run an Irish <lb/> excursion this year when <lb/>the people who generally do <lb/> so are away, and that <lb/> we would not enjoy it <lb/>under such circumstances. <lb/> So now I hope you are <lb/> not annoyed any more, <lb/>for I am not, because I  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0415_img_171_2"/>
              think you will forgive the <lb/> loose phraseology of my <lb/> last letter. I heard that <lb/> Min has gone to Stafford, <lb/> her visit will be a great <lb/> pleasure for you and of <lb/>course she will give you all <lb/> the news.   Exams are in full <lb/> swing now. They began on <lb/> Wednesday last. The pass <lb/> degree students are getting <lb/> very nice papers. My <lb/> exam is not coming up <lb/> till Thursday next, when I <lb/> am doing pass history so <lb/> don't forget the prayers that <lb/> day. I really mean that.   There is a great picnic <lb/> in aid of the Irish <lb/> Relief fund on today to <lb/> Tallaght. Want of time <lb/> is keeping me at home and <lb/> I think it is the same <lb/> with a lot of others. Everybody  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0415_img_171_3"/>
              is rushed to death now making <lb/> up for lost time. Yesterday I <lb/> stole a book out of National <lb/> Library and when I went in <lb/> this morning at about 11 o'clock, <lb/>the man accosted me with <lb/> 'What did you do with Lodge's <lb/> history, which you took out <lb/> yesterday'. I had to confess <lb/>my guilt, whereon Monsieur <lb/>the librarian delivered me a <lb/> lecture as long as today &amp; <lb/> tomorrow, so you may bet I <lb/> won't try that trick again.   I have just heard there <lb/> is a 'National Student' <lb/> coming out today. I'll <lb/>send it on to brighten up <lb/> your hearts when I get it. <lb/> I do not know who is acting <lb/> editor for Eimear O'Duffy <lb/> but I think it is James <lb/> Anthony M! How is Des <lb/>Ryan? Give him my love. <lb/>I began a letter to him but <lb/> I couldn't find anything to <lb/> say and as two or three  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0415_img_171_4"/>
              other girls were writing to him <lb/>I said I would put it off <lb/> for while. Frank Murray <lb/> did his Latin exam, I believe. <lb/> You know he is doing Hons <lb/>Degree in Sept and had <lb/> to take pass Latin. Everybody <lb/> though he would not do it <lb/>till next year as he did not <lb/>come back to College.   I am going home I <lb/>think on Friday next. Mother <lb/> Eucharia refuses to keep <lb/> anybody on who has done <lb/> her exam. So write to me <lb/> soon or if you have not <lb/> written before then, get my <lb/>home address from Dan.   You seem to have a <lb/>rather good time now. It is <lb/>grand that there are so <lb/> many College <seg type="del">girls going</seg> boys <lb/>there. Excuse this blot but <lb/>Eileen McGrane is trying to <lb/>persuade me to go to <lb/> picnic today and I don't <lb/> know I am writing. <lb/>Eileen is only one going  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0415_img_171_5"/>
              from here. I think Anita <lb/> Connolly has not written to <lb/>you yet. At present she is <lb/>a fixture in National Library <lb/> trying to stuff in a year's <lb/> work into a few days, as <lb/> indeed the most of us are. <lb/>She says she will write to <lb/> you in a few days and <lb/> Maureen says the same. <lb/> Both send all sorts of <lb/>nice messages.  <seg type="closer"> Goodbye with best wishes <lb/> Yrs very sincerely   <hi rend="underline">Madge Calnan</hi> </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S.Write soon and give <lb/>us all the news. Dan has <lb/> not sent me on buttons, but <lb/> I suppose he will soon. You are <lb/>very good  to get them  and when I get rich <lb/> I am going to get one of them <lb/> dipped in gold &amp; made into <lb/> a brooch for myself. <lb/><hi rend="underline">M.</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>