<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0048">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. E.F. Murnane to George Gavan Duffy, 2 August 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr E.F. Murnane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Fr Murnane on the eve of Roger Casement&#39;s execution. He describes how Casement is facing death bravely &#39;with the added courage and confidence of a good Catholic&#39;. Murnane describes Casement&#39;s message to all who supported him and writes that Casement has prayed for all those who tried to help him, in particular Mr. &amp;amp; Mrs. Gavan Duffy. Fr. Murnane also encloses a letter from Casement to Mrs. Gavan Duffy, which, he says, she will treasure. This letter has not survived.George Gavan Duffy, (1882-1951), was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement (1864-1916) at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising.Sir Roger Casement was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. Casement believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany, and when it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD/45/2/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/48</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0626">Fr E.F. Murnane</persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0292">The Presbytery, Dockhead, Bermondsey, London S.E., England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0048_img_1093_1"  type="Letter"  url="633139c21bdd86c3e2565a0ae6a82f6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0048_img_1093_2"  type="Letter"  url="2293f7831fdf31c26723d91d3eb409e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0048_img_1093_3"  type="Letter"  url="b1b0875cb21e6552ea1431218c9c0e39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0048_img_1093_4"  type="Letter"  url="d99e13ca31927b90274ea9020e607deb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0048_img_1093_5"  type="Letter"  url="d36841c280848064fffff519904f3823.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0048_img_1093_1"/>
              I am enclosing a letter for M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi><lb/>Gavan Duffy. It might fall into <lb/> unworthy hands or those who <lb/> would not value it. She will <lb/>treasure it.    The Presbytery,  Dockhead,  Bermonsey S.E.    Aug 2. 1916   My dear Gavan   I found your telegram <lb/>on my return from him. And <lb/> our last interview will ever <lb/> remain in my mind and <lb/>heart. He faced death like <lb/>a gallant Irish gentleman <lb/> with the added courage <lb/> and confidence of a good <lb/> Catholic. He talked freely of <lb/> his death and was looking <lb/> forward to his Confession <lb/> tonight and his first Holy <lb/> Communion tomorrow morning  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0048_img_1093_2"/>
              He sent  grateful  messages to all who <lb/>prayed for him and loved <lb/>him. That I was to tell all <lb/>that he died for Ireland <lb/> and that he wished  them  to know <lb/>that, he had no bitterness <lb/>in his heart for anyone <lb/>and that he felt that he <lb/> was being put to death, not <lb/>for the principles he held <lb/>but because he was Roger <lb/>Casement (I think I lost a <lb/> few words here) He was <lb/>wonderful, the peace, the <lb/>tranquillity the courage <lb/>with which he faced death <lb/> and talked of it - it was <lb/>like the last hours of some <lb/>glorious martyr. And I  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0048_img_1093_3"/>
              reminded him of Our Lord's <lb/>words 'He that shall <lb/>lose his life for me, shall <lb/>find it' and that he was <lb/> one more added to the <lb/>glorious roll of Irish Martyrs. <lb/>He bowed his head and <lb/>made the sign of the <lb/> Cross as I blessed him <lb/>and bade him Goodbye <lb/>till we meet him in <lb/>Heaven. He hears Mass <lb/> and makes his first <lb/>&amp; last Communion at <lb/> 7 ocl. He had many prayers  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0048_img_1093_4"/>
              <lb/>and tears at our Devotions <lb/> this Evg. and will have <lb/>Masses and Communions <lb/> tomorrow morning.   And he will reward  by his prayers in heaven  you <lb/>who have fought so <lb/>bravely and ably to save <lb/> him and all who tried <lb/>to help him. My heart <lb/>is divided between joy <lb/>and sorrow. With a <lb/>blessing to you and <lb/> Mrs. Gavan Duffy and <lb/>the Children <seg type="closer"> Ever Yours Sincerely <lb/> E.F.Murnane  I have many letters to write in <lb/>his name. </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0048_img_1093_5"/>
              I owe K. £3.6.0 <lb/>F.Murnane 2/8/1916  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>