<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1158">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 19 September 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s trip in Africa.Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/16, IJA/CHPI/54/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1158</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1917-09-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0786">Bombay, India </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1158_img_3835_1"  type="Letter"  url="36e75709007cb93774df2322fb84de1b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1158_img_3835_1"/>
                19 Sept. 1917   Dear Father Provincial, P.C.   Your letter with status news reached <lb/>me on my return from a trip to the east coast <lb/>of Africa. I was very interested in the various changes. <lb/>F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>O'Mahony who had also been 'Africking' and myself <lb/>were amused at F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Richard O'Reilly appearing on the <lb/>list in large capitals. He looked like the General <lb/>in a Catalogue. I hope the <seg type="unclear">tertianship</seg> will not <lb/>be moved from Tullabeg now that it has dropped <lb/>for one year. Of course a Chaplain has really made <lb/>his <seg type="unclear">tertianship,</seg> but still I have very pleasant memories <lb/>of 'the bog', and if Superiors don't hold the same views <lb/>about military life as a preparation for the last vows, <lb/>as I do, then Tullabey would be my preference.  I am keeping quite well, though I don't imagine I <lb/>have as many pounds <seg type="unclear">avoirdupois</seg> to carry about as I <lb/>has when I left Ireland â not that I ever had many  I should be glad if your Reverence would ask <lb/>whoever is preparing the 1918 Ords, to send me a copy, <lb/>and the little compenduim for the <seg type="unclear">Breviary;</seg> a catalogue <lb/>of the Province would also be very acceptable.  I have sent my Mass a/c to F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley. I suppose <lb/>the delay in notification does not matter. Unless something <lb/>extraordinary turns up, I ought to be able to say Mass every <lb/>day, now that the Monsoon is nearly over.  <seg type="closer"> I commend myself to your Reverences Masses and prayers.  Frances M.Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>