<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0653">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from W.A.F. Barry to Sir Matthew Nathan, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.A.F. Barry</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Application letter from W.A.F. Barry to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) concerning the position of Crown Solictor for Kings County. In the 1911 census, W.A.F. Barry is listed as 18 years of age and working as a solicitor apprentice.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary’s Office Registered papers, CSO-RP-1916-5615-10272</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/653</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1092">W.A.F. Barry</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0914">John&#39;s Place, Birr, Offaly, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0653_img_2128_1"  type="Letter"  url="19744bbcf13c345cb5bac06d839ec1f2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0653_img_2128_1"/>
                John's Place  Birr    18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916   Sir,   I have the honor to ask you to submit my name <lb/>as a candidate for the office of Crown Solicitor for the <lb/>King's County vacated by the recent death of my father, <lb/>Mr. Richard Fitzwilliam Barry L.L.B., after about twenty <lb/>years service.  I served my apprenticeship under my father at Birr; <lb/>since my admission as a solicitor my father and I <lb/>carried on the civil business of the office together <lb/>and I have assisted him in his official work as <lb/>Crown Solicitor; and I may mention that since my <lb/>father's health first began to fail namely about <lb/>eighteen months ago I have had the main share <lb/>in carrying on the office work in connection with <lb/>his position as Crown Solicitor.  I trust that these facts will weigh in my favor in <lb/>the consideration of my fitness for the position. <seg type="closer"> I have the honor to be <lb/>Sir <lb/>Your obedient servant  <hi rend="underline">W. A. F. Barry</hi>   The Under Secretary  <hi rend="underline">Dublin Castle</hi>  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>