<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2920">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Max Green, Chairman of the General Prisons Board, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was addressed to Max S. Green (1865 - 1922), the chairman of the General Prisons Board. The letter relates to a series of correspondence regarding the collapse of a shared wall between the neighbouring laundry and prison. According to this letter the wall belongs to the laundry and as an addition the author has enclosed a report concerning the rol the prison&#39;s ivy played in undermining the wall&#39;s structure. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/2892/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2920</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0327">Max Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2920_img_2329_1"  type="Letter"  url="9d13ee81f812d66627dbf0076a6414ad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2920_img_2329_1"/>
             23 NOV 1915<lb/>GENERAL<lb/>PRISONS BOARD.  For Chairman<lb/>M<lb/>23.11.15   H. M. PRISON<lb/>MOUNTJOY    22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> November 1915   With reference to my report of<lb/>14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. as to wall having been<lb/>blown down I beg to further report<lb/>that on learning from the Clerk of<lb/>Works that there was some doubt<lb/>as to whether this wall ever was<lb/>built by the Prisons Department<lb/>or formed part of their property. I<lb/>wrote to the Manager of the N. C. Laundry<lb/>as per copy of letter attached. From<lb/>letter received in reply (attached) it<lb/>will be seen that the Manager thinks<lb/>That the wall belongs to the Laundry<lb/>&amp; has as stated begun removing the<lb/>stones &amp; debris. As regards the suggestion<lb/>that the ivy on our side of the wall<lb/>was instrumental in causing the<lb/>damage I attach report from the<lb/>Foreman of Works on this subject.<lb/>Pending instructions from the<lb/>Board I have not replied to this<lb/>letter which also it will be seen<lb/>contains a suggestion for opening<lb/>negotiations as to the purchase or<lb/>renting by the Board of the ground<lb/>adjoining wall.   Maxwell<lb/>Green <lb/><lb/> The Chairman<lb/>General Prisons Board<lb/>Dublin Castle  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>