<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3990">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J E Lyons to Miss Coates, 5 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J E Lyons</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Transcription of a letter from a prisoner recently transferred (on the 26th June) from Wandsworth prison to Frongoch and thanking Miss Coates of the Ladies Committee for visits to Wandsworth. The letter refers to the North and South camps at Frongoch, the number of men in the south camp (approximately 600) and the number in each hut (30).  It refers to the conditions, the management of the camps and the availability of supplies and requests assistance for prisoners who have no money to purchase cigarettes etc. 

The JE Lyons letter has been transcribed and sent with an introduction and postscript referring to other letters, (presumably to Art Ó Briain)

According to the 1936 Roll of Honour John E Lyons served at the Four Courts Garrison during the Rising.

From the Art Ó Briain Papers held in the National Library of Ireland.   NLI records indicate that MS 8434 /23 is a collection (13 items) of letters from prisoners in Frongoch and Reading jails.

Art Ó Briain (1872-1949) was Honorary Secretary of The Irish National Relief Fund which was set up to provide assistance to the dependents of those executed in 1916, those sentenced to prison and to the prisoners themselves.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Art Ó Briain papers, c. 1900-c.1945, Ó Briain’s work for Irish political prisoners (1916-21), MS 8434 / 23-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3990</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0988">J E Lyons</persName>
              <date>1916-07-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1238">Frongoch, North Wales (South Camp)</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Miss Coates</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3990_img_3377_1"  type="Letter"  url="fd5abb7871a7a81e3163ed7ad81f753b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3990_img_3377_2"  type="Letter"  url="0b4bf603679330be4cd6e7f6939dd2f4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3990_img_3377_1"/>
              <seg type="unclear">Frongoch. Sth Camp</seg>    12/7/16    <seg type="foreign">A cara</seg>.   as the ladies com: does not<lb/>appear to be meeting I send the<lb/>copy of a letter from Frongock.<lb/>I have received several mostly from<lb/>the poor citizen army men whom I<lb/>visited at Wandsworth.  The Censor had quite washed out two<lb/>lines of one letter from a <seg type="unclear">Lewes</seg> friend<lb/>- teacher of Irish at Rockwell Coll: but<lb/>one sentence was camp practically<lb/>under our own control.  However the letter of one old man<lb/>whose son was with him at Wands<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">wth</hi></hi><hi rend="underline"></hi><lb/>is full of details from the camp.<lb/>(which I had asked him to supply).  5/7/16.    Dear Miss Coales,   We arrived here on<lb/>the 26th and I take the opportunity<lb/>of thanking you for your kindness<lb/>to us during our stay in Wandsworth<lb/>which helped to brighten our<lb/>lot very much while there.  The prisoners here are separated<lb/>into two camps. North and South  I am int he 8<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Camp where there 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3990_img_3377_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline">2.</hi>  are about 600 men. We are in huts about<lb/>30 in each which are well lighted,<lb/>ventilated and clean. We take our<lb/>meals in huts preserved for the<lb/>purpose. Our own men manage<lb/>the camp, keep order, cook clean etc  The supply of rations is fair, the<lb/>bread and meat being fresh<lb/>and the tea of good quality.<lb/>There is very little margarine or<lb/>butter, no cheese, or jam. There is<lb/>a canteen where these things can<lb/>be brought, but as there are a<lb/>number of men who have no money<lb/>they have to do without them and <lb/>also without cigarettes, tobacco<lb/>and matches. If you could do<lb/>anything for us in this matter<lb/>you would confer a great benefit<lb/>on us. Thanking you again.   Yours faithfully    J. E Lyons.   This letter as all others took a<lb/>week to reach me.  Another letter of a young Dublin lad<lb/>whom my mother found and had never had<lb/>a visit until the last week. He was very timid 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>