<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1528">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. Costello C.C. to Nancy O'Rahilly, 23 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. Costello C.C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter of condolence to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). The writer expresses deepest sympathy and says that The O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s name is a household word in his area. He assures her that &#39;that spot in Moore St.&#39; (where her husband died) will be a place of pilgrimage for generations to come.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/42</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1528</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0688">M. Costello C.C.</persName>
              <date>1916-05-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0834">Ballinskelligs, Caherciveen, Co. Kerry, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1528_img_989_1"  type="Letter"  url="a3f669d73d8248eedce7e48f2a412271.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1528_img_989_2"  type="Letter"  url="480d29ca296c4dd94e8d41bbf5fe3b4b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1528_img_989_1"/>
                <seg type="unclear">Ballinaskillys</seg>  Caherciveen    <hi rend="underline">May 23rd 1916</hi>   Dear Mrs Rahilly,   I am at a great <lb/>loss to express how deeply I feel <lb/>for you in your most sad <lb/>bereavement.   I did not know your husband <lb/>personally - his name is a <lb/>household word here among <lb/>the people of <seg type="unclear">BallinasKillys</seg><lb/>where the sad news of his tragic <lb/>end was received with deep regret.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1528_img_989_2"/>
              My stay in Dublin in February <lb/>was limited to two days, and it <lb/>was too late when I got your kind <lb/>invitation to call <seg type="unclear"> on you at H.O.</seg><lb/>Mrs <seg type="unclear">J</seg> writes to say she would <lb/>like to see Dublin in its <seg type="unclear">destruction</seg><lb/>for my part I would not.  There is much I regret but <lb/>not all. Depend upon it that <lb/>spot in Moores it will be a <lb/>place of pilgrimage for generations <lb/>not yet born. <seg type="closer"> With Sincerest Sympathy.  <hi rend="underline">M Costello C.C</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>