<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4317">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from G.L. Moore to Edward Carson, 6 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>G.L. Moore</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from G.L. Moore to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4317</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0536">G.L. Moore</persName>
              <date>1916-06-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0532">6 Bedford Place, London, W.C., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_1"  type="Letter"  url="0a3c6203fb900337add53b7e1fd25f8b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_2"  type="Letter"  url="7f2756c06b21b4d9798139e7f1814839.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_3"  type="Letter"  url="92d293defa8245b4417b088360368eea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_4"  type="Letter"  url="9d34e31a9c8e7f1d75f1a96dfb08e02e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_5"  type="Letter"  url="d8f5e320a7099285b56f510c21b2123d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_6"  type="Letter"  url="4e2df3f63d2c04aea3bef8a419fb6c16.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4317_img_3678_7"  type="Letter"  url="4f4e4bc90433122b3a6f4171bb517d7c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_1"/>
              Keep Moore 42<lb/>D1507/A/17/9    6 Bedford Peace<lb/>London W.C.    6t<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> June '16    Dear Sir Edward,   Since seeing you<lb/>off last night I have<lb/>been thinking (as, indeed,<lb/>I <hi rend="underline">always</hi> am) of the very<lb/>serious Irish Problem. Is<lb/>it going to be solved?<lb/>&amp; now? I am wondering<lb/>how you are all getting<lb/>on at the Council to-day.<lb/>I am looking forward to<lb/>the report (if any) in to-<lb/>morrow's Papers here, &amp;<lb/>the fuller account in the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_2"/>
             —2—  <lb/>local papers arriving here<lb/>the following day. Surely<lb/>the Exclusion of six<lb/>Counties is not feasible!<lb/>My heart w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 'bleed' if<lb/>Fermanagh were not ex-<lb/>cluded! I think of what<lb/>is emblazoned on our Flags!<lb/><hi rend="underline">Enniskillen </hi>etc etc. It<lb/>w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be an abandonment<lb/>and a betrayal of the<lb/>loyal &amp; historic! <hi rend="underline">I</hi> feel<lb/>that I could never hold<lb/>up my head if loyalists<lb/>such as these were dragooned<lb/>into submission to a<lb/>Dublin Parliament.    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_3"/>
             -3-   43   Stand <hi rend="underline">firm</hi> for the total<lb/>Exclusion of Ulster as the<lb/>minimum. And stand<lb/><hi rend="underline">firm</hi> also for no patched<lb/>up peace — no truce —<lb/>no arrangement during<lb/>the continuance of the<lb/>war with Germany. Let<lb/>there be no peace where<lb/>there is no peace. Better<lb/><seg type="del">be</seg> a thousand times be<lb/>as we are than accept<lb/>something to satisfy &amp;<lb/>gain renown for M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><lb/>The People. Does <hi rend="underline">he </hi>care<lb/>for England? Does he<lb/>care for the pockets of<lb/>the British people? 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_4"/>
             — 4 —   44   If a settlement c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be<lb/>effected to gain him<lb/>honour &amp; renown he<lb/>w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> sacrifice the <seg type="del">pocke</seg><lb/>pockets of the people<lb/>— he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> bleed them dry —<lb/>Ay! he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> tax to the<lb/>tune of £ 1,000,000 if<lb/>only he c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> gain his point!<lb/>You will not trust him!<lb/>And you remember Redmond's<lb/>words years ago Trust<lb/>me; don't trust Asquith<lb/>You will not trust any<lb/>of them! A nice trio !  God be with you —<lb/>especially at this great<lb/>crisis. Your burden<lb/>of responsibility is, indeed,  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_5"/>
             — 5 —   D1507/A/17/9 45   <lb/>great; but we shall all<lb/>help you to bear it,<lb/>&amp; lessen it.  Victory must be<lb/>ours! We are a minority.<lb/>But one, with God on<lb/>our side, is a Majority!  I have copied a few<lb/>lines of Longfellow on<lb/>last page. No doubt<lb/>they are already known<lb/>to you. They appear<lb/>to me so <hi rend="underline">apropos</hi> that<lb/>I make bold to<lb/>refresh your memory.  I hope you &amp;<lb/>Lady Carson had a<lb/>pleasant crossing. 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_6"/>
             With kind regards <lb/>to you both. <lb/>Cordially yours <lb/><hi rend="underline">G.L.Moore</hi>  Sir E. Carson P.C. 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4317_img_3678_7"/>
             Sail on, O Ship of State! <lb/>Sail on, O Union, strong &amp; great! <lb/>Humanity with all its fears, <lb/>With all the hopes of future years, <lb/>Is hanging breathless on thy fate!  <hi rend="underline">Longfellow</hi>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>