<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3035">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to W.G. Wakely, 21 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Acknowledgement of receipt of letter (dated 19 July 1916) from W.G. Wakely, Secretary of the Incorporated Law Society of Ireland, from the office of the Under Secretary of Dublin Castle. The letter of 19 July enclosed a memorandum regarding the suggested legislation for the Government of Ireland and the impact on the solicitors&#39; profession.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5618-12565-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3035</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0684">M </persName>
              <date>1916-07-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0887">The Under Secretary&#39;s Office, Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">W.G. Wakely</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1934">Incorporated Law Society of Ireland, Solicitor Buildings, Four Courts, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3035_img_2434_1"  type="Letter"  url="321ca69305da6c707bd665186dee2c50.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3035_img_2434_1"/>
             DUBLIN CASTLE,   21st July, 1916.   Dear Sir,   I am desired by the Under Secretary <lb/> to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of <lb/>the 19th instant enclosing a memorandum rela- <lb/>tive to the suggested legislation for the <lb/> Government of Ireland.   Yours faithfully,   J.S.   The Secretary, <lb/>Incorporated Law Society of Ireland, <lb/>Solicitors Buildings, <lb/>Four Courts, <lb/>Dublin. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>