<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0025">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Amelia Jephson to Nancy O'Rahilly, 14 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Amelia Jephson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Amelia Jephson to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961) on the 14th of June 1916. The writer apologises for the long lapse of time before writing and asks for a memento of her &#39;wonderful &amp;amp; heroic husband&#39;. She did not hear of the memorial Mass in time - otherwise she would have been there. She proposes that she and Nancy do Lough Derg together. Finally, the writer indicates that she could visit Nancy. in conjunction to her regular visits to Lansdowne Road to see her ailing motherNancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at its founding in 1914. She was the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916), who was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/51</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/25</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1199">Amelia Jephson</persName>
              <date>1916-06-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1688">45 Albert Road, Glenageary, Co. Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0025_img_1055_1"  type="Letter"  url="94087ae76b93b76cfe43e8a1bbc0d6f9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0025_img_1055_2"  type="Letter"  url="8f3bcebf927e9bb9051fa97693eb86ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0025_img_1055_3"  type="Letter"  url="b2823720bc76bc67bc75c71ea79d7022.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0025_img_1055_1"/>
                45 Albert Road  Glenageary    14th June/16   Dear Mrs. O'Rahilly   It is only now - after this <lb/>long lapse of time - that I <lb/>can bring myself to try and <lb/>tell you how I have felt and <lb/>prayed for you ever since <lb/>I knew that a mere letter <lb/> of sympathy could only be <lb/> poor comfort in such trouble  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0025_img_1055_2"/>
              <lb/>as yours. To say nothing <lb/>of your irreparable loss <lb/> the anxieties of Easter <lb/>Week must have been <lb/>appalling, but please God <lb/>you will soon have a great â <lb/>if not <hi rend="underline">the</hi> greatest â consolation.   Perhaps some time, later <lb/> on, you could find me some <lb/> small memento â a prayer book <lb/> or any little belonging of <lb/>your wonderful &amp; heroic <lb/> husband â that is if you <cb/><lb/>can spare it to one with <lb/> so small a claim as I have.   I wish I had known of <lb/>the Requiem at Donnybrook. <lb/> I only heard of it yesterday <lb/> or I should have been present, <lb/> but indeed I suppose it is <lb/>he who is praying for us <lb/>in poor distracted Ireland.   I am waiting a few years <lb/>for L. Derg, so we may do it <lb/>together again.   I suppose you would not  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0025_img_1055_3"/>
              <lb/>care to see me (?) but I am <lb/>very often in your neighbourhood <lb/> I go up constantly to <lb/>Lansdowne Road as my mother <lb/>has been laid up for the past <lb/>2 months with phlebitis. <lb/>Thank God she is now getting <lb/>better and will soon I hope <lb/> be able to get away for a <lb/>change.  <seg type="closer"> With renewed &amp; deepest <lb/>sympathy <lb/>I remain dear Mrs O'Rahilly <lb/>Yrs ever most sincerely   Amelia Jephson </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>