<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5528">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Monteith to Roger Casement, 5 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Monteith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Monteith (1880-1956) to Roger Casement (1864-1916) from Limberg, where there was a prisoner of war camp holding a large number of Irish POWs. Monteith was the Commander of the Irish Brigade, appointed by Casement. 
Casement spent eighteen months in total in Germany attempting to secure German support for an uprising in Ireland and raising an ultimately unsuccessful brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps. By April 1916, he had become become disillusioned with German assistance and marginalized from the plans for the Rising. He believed there should be no rising without sufficient German support and when he realised that it was going ahead with only a small supply of German arms, he travelled to Ireland to prevent it from taking place. The Germans supplied a submarine to transport Casement, Monteith and Sergeant Beverly (Daniel Bailey) to Ireland but Casement and Beverly were captured after they landed in Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Casement was hanged for treason in London in August 1916.
This letter details Monteith&#39;s work in attempting to recruit Irish POW&#39;s to the Irish Brigade. It mentions meetings he has had, including one with the commandant of the POW camp who  who has provided a room for Monteith to interview potential recruits.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sir Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15; Ms. 13,085/24/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5528</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0377">Robert Monteith</persName>
              <date>1915-11-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5528_img_624_1"  type="Letter"  url="bbecddb1f1ec2db4a5caa145043f5c24.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5528_img_624_2"  type="Letter"  url="04e2bdef5fe21093b76e6d5097287be4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5528_img_624_1"/>
             Recd. <lb/>only 8.11.15 <lb/>9p.m.   Limburg.   5.XI.15   Dear Sir Roger.   I have received your letter, parcel &amp; <lb/> newspapers, many thanks. I will put them to the <lb/> best possible use —    One man was sent on to Zossen <lb/> yesterday, he is of the right sort —    I called on F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Berkessel on Sunday <lb/> last &amp; had a long chat with him, he is such <lb/> a lovable man, he promised to see me <lb/> in Limburg on Tuesday, but was unable to come, <lb/> however as I was leaving the hotel last night <lb/> to pay a visit to F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crotty I met F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Berkessel <lb/> at the door, he came with me and we <lb/> spent a couple of pleasant hours with <lb/>F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Crotty —    In my previous letter I omitted to <lb/> tell you that on our arrival at Limburg the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5528_img_624_2"/>
            Commondant had a vehicle to take us to the <lb/> camp — he has done everything to meet our <lb/> requirements in the way of rooms for interviewing <lb/> the men, passes for camp and town, greatcoats <lb/> belts and side arms for the N.C.O.<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> and he had already <lb/> made arrangements for hotel accommodation for the <lb/> whole party. I explained that it was my <lb/> wish to put the Government to as little expense <lb/> as possible &amp; would prefer to pay my hotel bill - <lb/> he was quite agreeable —   I am altogether in agreement with you as <lb/> to the future of the Brigade &amp; will start in to <lb/> get them fit on my return, but I would like <lb/> to see every man in this camp before leaving.   Faithfully yours   <hi rend="underline">R.Monteith</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>