<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3566">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Evelyn Sharp to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 11 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Evelyn Sharp</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Evelyn Sharp (1869–1955) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), Evelyn offers her condolences regarding the tragic death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. Evelyn conveys the extent to which Francis&#39; death is a loss to their cause and Ireland as well as a personal one, and offers her assistance to Hanna in any way that it would be necessary. She writes that the women of the United Suffragists are similarly moved in response to the tragedy and then praises how quickly the whole affair was brought to light. She finishes by assuring Hanna that she need not respond unless there is anything she would like the United Suffragists to do.

Evelyn Sharp was a key member in the Women&#39;s Social and Political Union and the United Suffragists, two militant suffragist organizations, the latter of which Evelyn helped to form. She was the editor of Votes For Women during the First World War.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-29</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3566</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0979">Evelyn Sharp</persName>
              <date>1916-05-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0939">12 John Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1955</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3566_img_2969_1"  type="Letter"  url="03473ebc3f5b393d0e7a410e364a8cde.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3566_img_2969_2"  type="Letter"  url="9a347a0606b9c24eddd358104f2a7aaf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3566_img_2969_1"/>
             TELEPHONE,<lb/>HOLBORN 5724.   May 11: 1916:    16 John Street<lb/>38, Douchty Street,<lb/>Bedford Row W. C.   Dear Mrs Sheehy Skeffington,  I do not know how to write to you<lb/>in your great sorrow. You will hear from<lb/>many who know you and knew your splendid<lb/>husband much better personally than myself,<lb/>but I cannot refrain from sending you a<lb/>few words to tell you how outraged I feel at<lb/>his tragic fate and how deeply sympathetic<lb/>with you. The loss to our own cause is irrepa—<lb/>—rable, as it is to Ireland and to humanity,<lb/>But his soul will go marching on: no one who<lb/>even met him once for 5 minutes, as I did, can<lb/>doubt that for a moment. You poor dear woman!<lb/>Let me know if there is anything more we can 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3566_img_2969_2"/>
             do over here. At two United Suffragists' meetings<lb/>this week, we told the audience what had happened,<lb/>and they were profoundly moved, knowing<lb/>how much you and your husband had done<lb/>for our Cause. Mr. Nevinson has been splendid:<lb/>I think it is very largely owing to his untiring efforts<lb/>that the affair was bought to light so<lb/>promptly in Parliament. Do not dream of<lb/>answering this unless there is anything we can<lb/>do for you over here— Mr. Laurence and Mr<lb/>Lansbury have been working hard too.  Yours with warmed—sympathy   Evelyn Sharp  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>