<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1300">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Delaney to Alice Stopford Green, 29 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Delaney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Joseph Delaney to Alice Stopford Green (1847-1929). It was sent from Maryborough (now Portlaoise) in Queen&#39;s County (now Laois). A campaign was launched featuring many prominent figures such as W.B. Yeats and George Bernard Shaw to secure a reprieve for Casement but he was hanged on 3 August 1916. Delaney was a supporter of the campaign and the letter refers to signatures for a petition.Alice Stopford Green was an Irish historian and nationalist. While not a supporter of armed rebellion, her house provided a space for leading nationalists to meet. Stopford Green had collaborated with Roger Casement on Congo Reform and, after the Easter Rising in 1916, she tried to save him from execution</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, List no. A15, Ms. 13,088 /9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1300</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1481">Joseph Delaney</persName>
              <date>1916-07-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0572">Greenview, The Ridge, Maryborough, Queen&#39;s County.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1300_img_519_1"  type="Letter"  url="26078b24b5ffbe9314e13252fa77b3af.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1300_img_519_1"/>
                Greenview,  The Ridge,  Maryboro,  Queens Co    July 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 16   Mrs.Stopford Green  Dear Madam   I enclose you the <lb/> petition signed by <lb/> 15 ratepayers and <lb/> myself, and I wish <lb/> the cause every success <lb/> as I am sure everyone <lb/> in Ireland and America <lb/> does today. <seg type="closer"> Faithfully Yours  Joseph Delaney. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>