<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4311">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of a letter from John Crozier to Edward Carson, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Baptist Crozier</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Copy of a letter from John Baptist Crozier (1853–1920) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Crozier was a Church of Ireland clergyman who served as Archbishop of Armagh and Primate of All Ireland from 1911–1920.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4311</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1356">John Baptist Crozier</persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1920</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4311_img_3672_1"  type="Letter"  url="9e46049cabed25ec3f1643ca9f22b8d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4311_img_3672_2"  type="Letter"  url="8f810fdcb97335901a51083d3fd579bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4311_img_3672_3"  type="Letter"  url="fcff1bc5454c49873858bd3358353c50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4311_img_3672_4"  type="Letter"  url="085789f3407ef6ee883daf74266fa347.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4311_img_3672_1"/>
             D1507/A/16/12   Dr Croziers memo<lb/>sent to Sir Edward May 7th 1916<lb/>&amp; forwarded to Mr Asquith P.M.    Page 1 of 2   Original letters &amp; mem  <lb/>with  <lb/>1934     Nothing but the keenest sense of duty would induce me to write<lb/>to you on this matter, and the fear that men who do not know the<lb/>North of Ireland may make a terrible blunder at this serious<lb/>crisis in our National life.  (1) There is more than a rumour that a proposal will be made<lb/>to disarm the Ulster Volunteers.  (2) As one who knows Ireland <hi rend="underline">thoroughly</hi>I would say that<lb/>when the Rebellion broke out in Dublin, Meath, Wexford, Galway and<lb/>elsewhere; the Loyalists of Ireland knew that if it succeeded, it<lb/>would be a Revolution — and in the lonely Northern outposts — in<lb/>Cavan, <seg type="del">Tywne</seg>  Tyrone  Monaghan and elsewhere the fears of the Loyalists were<lb/>allayed by the knowledge that their fellow Loyalists in Belfast <seg type="del">St</seg><lb/>were armed and would come to their aid.  (3) And an attempted disarmament now would spread terror<lb/>amongst these scattered Loyal folk — whose only fault is their<lb/>loyalty!  (4) Large numbers of these people have nobly given their sons<lb/>and brothers to the service of the King — and this in spite of the<lb/>knowledge that others all around them equally fit for service had<lb/>no intention of offering themselves.  (5) Again everyone who is in touch with Irish life knows<lb/>that before very long the extreme section of the Nationalist party<lb/>will be fully armed again and it is not, I suppose, intended that<lb/>(as in the case of a previous Rebellion in Ireland) the Loyalists<lb/>should be left <hi rend="underline">unarmed</hi> To the vengeance of others.  (6) The Ulster men have covered themselves with glory by<lb/>their calmness and readiness to help the Government in this crisis, 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4311_img_3672_2"/>
             D1507/A/16/12   Page 2 of 2   <lb/>2  <lb/>crisis, and this calmness is chiefly due to the fact that they trust<lb/>their leaders and are under splendid control.  (7) To attempt to disarm them now would be so flagrantly<lb/>unjust that I think no power in earth could prevent a rising and<lb/>a general strike in Belfast — an awful alternative for every reason;<lb/>and a red ruin to the Muniment works and shipping industry.  (8) Lastly, though I could say much more, it would be looked<lb/>upon by our great Ulster Division serving in France as a hideous<lb/>travesty of Justice. They have left their wives and children<lb/>trusting to the faith of their comrades who stay behind to look after<lb/>and protect them; they never relied in help or kindness or protection<lb/>from Mr. Birrell and those with him — they relied on the fact that<lb/>they left behind them men who would sacrifice their lives in their<lb/>defence.  This war in Ireland has stir<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>ed these men to the depth of their<lb/>hearts. They have seen now, what they <hi rend="underline">knew</hi> long ago, the imminent<lb/>danger Ireland was in because of England's extremity. To disturb<lb/>now the only confidence of these men at the front, would be to run a<lb/>risk no sane man ought to dare to face. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4311_img_3672_3"/>
             [This and the next page are copies of the 2 previous pages.] 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4311_img_3672_4"/>
             [This and the previous page are copies of the first 2 pages.] 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>