<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2917">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from North Circular Laundry to Charles Arthur Munro, 18 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Arthur Munro</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from North Circular Laundry to Charles Arthur Munro (1869 - 1952) concerning a collapsed wall. This letter is part of a series of correspondence regarding the collapse of a shared wall between the neighbouring laundry and prison. According to the laundry the collapse of the wall was actually the result of the prison&#39;s ivy plant against the wall which proved to heavy for the structure. The author requests that Munro look into previous complaints made in order to find a solution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/2892/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2917</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0487">Charles Arthur Munro</persName>
              <date>1915-11-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0836">North Circular Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0487">Charles Arthur Munro</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1165">Mountjoy Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2917_img_2326_1"  type="Letter"  url="3ab5fa0ea90b1f4590973739a121b928.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2917_img_2326_1"/>
            N. C. LAUNDRY Ltd.  NORTH CIRCULAR ROAD, (TOP OF BERKLEY STREET), DUBLIN,   Nov 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915   C. Munro Esq <lb/>Governor <lb/>Mountjoy Prison   Dear Sir   We are in receipt of yours 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>re our wall and in reply have to say <lb/>we had arranged and did start men <lb/>removing the stones &amp;c. this morning <lb/>We have taken advice on this matter <lb/>and have been informed that it was <lb/>the very heavy mass of ivy &amp;c which <lb/>had been planted and allowed to grow <lb/>against and on our wall by your people <lb/>which caused to a great degree the <lb/>damage to the wall and so left it <lb/>more easily blown down and we would <lb/>be glad to know what Prison Board <lb/>are willing to do about this.   <hi rend="underline">Some time ago we suggested that <lb/>Prison Board might purchase or rent <lb/>the portion of ground squaring your <lb/>ground. Perhaps this would be a good <lb/>time to revive this. We are open still</hi> <lb/>to treat about the matter.   Awaiting reply we are <lb/>Yours faithfully   <seg type="unclear"><hi rend="underline">N.C. Laundry</hi></seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>