<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0213">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James R. Martin to Robert Chalmers, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James R. Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from High Sheriff of County Galway, James R. Martin, to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858–1938), the under-secretary of Ireland. Martin writes about the Rising in county Galway, claiming that the requests for compensation are false claims. He reports that Sinn Fein sympathisers willingly assisted the rebels and are now seeking to be refunded by the crown.The high sheriff of County Galway was the sovereign&#39;s judicial representative in County Galway. Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7940/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/213</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0088">James R. Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1862">Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0213_img_1360_1"  type="Letter"  url="cbe468aef807f6d2b8771e8aba563214.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0213_img_1360_2"  type="Letter"  url="1b32b1679169ef1886d5897c8742080e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0213_img_1360_3"  type="Letter"  url="1ded451a5e7b873adeffac95e7b66fd3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0213_img_1360_1"/>
              Spoke to NJ <lb/>1. Ack. <lb/>11. Send extract <lb/> [ ] to CDB <lb/>111.See file he claims for compensation    Rockmore, Athenry  Co. Galway    9 May 1916    The Under Secretary  The Castle Dublin   Dear Sir   I would like to be allowed to express an <lb/> opinion in the question of compensation for <lb/> injuries sustained in this county &amp; the <lb/> recent Sinn Fein rising. Many claims <lb/> will be, &amp; I think have been put in by people <lb/> who were thoroughly in sympathy with <lb/> the rebels &amp; now make exorbitant claims <lb/> for articles that they gave them of their <lb/>own free will. Speaking broadly all <lb/> the people in this locality were in sympathy <lb/> with the rebels  Also people who were not in sympathy  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0213_img_1360_2"/>
              <lb/>with them &amp; have sustained injuries are <lb/>putting in exorbitant claims. I take from <lb/> the 'Galway Express' of the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> with three <lb/>claims one for Â£160 one for Â£288.8.0 <lb/> &amp; one for Â£50 &amp; my belief is that these <lb/> amounts are enormously in excess of the <lb/> value of the damage sustained.    If I may be allowed to further express an <lb/> opinion as to this county, for which I am <lb/> responsible, I would like to say that the <lb/> leaders of this rising  in Co. Galway  several of whom have <lb/> not as yet been apprehended, are all men <lb/> well known to the police, and have for <lb/> years kept this County in a state of disturbance <lb/> &amp; have been at the bottom of all outrages, <lb/> &amp; are the recipients of German money. <lb/> It is their constant endeavour to keep the <lb/> County disturbed as if it becomes peaceful <lb/> their occupation &amp; means of living are gone to <lb/> great extent, owning to them for many years  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0213_img_1360_3"/>
              <lb/> No one in this County has been able to embark <lb/> on any kind of business without first finding <lb/> an answer to the question; 'If this business <lb/> is successful shall I be allowed to carry it on'.   I need hardly point out the advantage of <lb/> putting such disturbers of the public peace <lb/> in a position in which they will be no longer <lb/> harmful.   I may perhaps also draw your attention <lb/> to another point some of the men who have <lb/> turned out as rebels, some of which are not <lb/> yet apprehended, have received from the <lb/> conjested district board excellent farms in <lb/> the vicinity of Athenry, &amp; no doubt elsewhere, <lb/> &amp; grants of money to build houses. Some <lb/> have received these things quite recently. It <lb/> is obviously not right that these men should <lb/> be allowed to retain these farms or pass <lb/> them on to their friends &amp; relations. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  James R. Martin <lb/> High Sheriff for the County Galway </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>