<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1309">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman, 2 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Martin Mahoney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman. The letter refers to debt collection to meet parish outlays.Mahoney, a parish priest in Minnesota, edited the Catholic weekly &#39;Manifestos&#39;. John Sweetman (1844-1936) was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. Sweetman was a founding member of the Sinn Féin party in 1904, its first vice-president (1906–7), and second president (1908–10). Sweetman&#39;s clericalist Catholicism and his political and social conservatism led him to denounce any form of ‘class politics’, for him nationalism would make Ireland prosperous, by cultivating ‘national feeling’. This line of thought left him open to criticism from the more left-wing and republican members of the Sinn Féin movement.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Collection, Collection List 154, MS. 47,604/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1309</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0410">Fr. Martin Mahoney</persName>
              <date>1915-12-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1659">Mendota, Minnesota, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1309_img_56_1"  type="Letter"  url="5377538ff6b227d57da85bf434a2bf65.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1309_img_56_2"  type="Letter"  url="5377538ff6b227d57da85bf434a2bf65.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1309_img_56_1"/>
                Mendota Minn    Dec 2nd, 1915   Dear Sir:   With the report of last Easter collection, I am enclosâ <lb/> ing the little envelope for the Fall collection which ought to come <lb/> in next Sunday. This Fall collection serves to meet two of the <lb/> largest Parish outlays, the Seminary assessment and the Fuel, both <lb/> of which used to be, and are yet in many places two distinct collâ <lb/> ections, sometimes kept up for several Sundays. What an awful <lb/> punishment it would be of my desire to spare people that unpleasant <lb/> music, if one were to confine himself for this one Fall collectâ <lb/> ion to only such an offering as he felt bound to make for each <lb/> of these old style levies. This is a good occasion for a worthy <lb/> thanksoffering to the Lord for the bounties of this year.  <seg type="closer"> Sincerely,  Martin Mahoney. </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1309_img_56_2"/>
              Easter 1915 Collection  $5.00 James Scott  3.00 D. Tousignant.  2.00 J.J Beaudette, Arhtur Bernier, Ed Dupuis, Jos Fee, Mrs Pat <lb/> Fee, James McCarthy &amp; Family, Wm Perron.   1.50 Nick Welch,   J   &amp; Mrs Shields.   1.00 Alex  , Fred  , M. Barry, L. P.  caudet,  einier, <lb/> Frank Bouthilet, Fred. Bouthilet, Mrs Anne Burns, Chas Burns <lb/><seg type="unclear">Geo Burns</seg>, Hugh Burns, James Burns, M. Burns, Wm Callahan <lb/> Alex Chandelain. Desire Chaudelain, Louis Chaudelain, <lb/> D. Coffee, Thos. Connolly, Jno Cunningham, N. Cunningham, <lb/> Jas Fee, Wm Fee, Mrs T. Fisher L. Gosselin, M. Haggerty, <lb/> Jno Kearns, . Kester, Jos, Labbey, Thos Labbey, J.H. Liebel <lb/> Eug Lemay, J. Lemay, J. . Lemay, J.J. Lemay, Rbr Levendre, <lb/> J. . Levendre, F. McCarthy, M. O'Connor, W.W. O'Neill, Adolard <lb/> Perron,   Perron, Jos Quigley,  <lb/> N. Ried, H.   Shields, Lillian Shields, M/ Shields, Jas Slator <lb/> Chas Small,  Small, Mrs L. St   Chas Sodersrom, <lb/> Felix  , Matt Walsh, T. Walsh, Gus Weber, L. Weber, <lb/> Mrs Weber.   .75 T.F. Eagan, Mrs Fred Leclure  .50 Matt D  , James Burns, Julia  , E. Clemens, <lb/> Felix Deslandier, M. Downin, Ed Dunns Jr., Stet   Dunuis <lb/> F. Fournier, Louis Fisher, P. Hurley, Mrs F Kaufhold, <lb/> M. <seg type="unclear">Leuer</seg>, Emmanuel Letencre, K. Lonendre, Mrs. Miller, <lb/> P. Mooney,   O'Neill, Xy Perron, Omar Perron, R. Reid, <lb/> ,Mrs Thos Ryan, (R.I.P.),  Shields, J.J. Slater, <lb/> Thomas Slater, V. Tousinant,  Vainencourt, Emily Weber, <lb/> Mary Weber, J. Williams P. Williams.   .25 Jos.  , Paul  , Francis Dean, Carroll Callahan, <lb/> Hugh Callahan, Omar Desleurier, Joe Fec  ,  . Leahey, <lb/> Chas  , Jno Slater.   Plate $4.02 Total $120.27  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>