<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1353">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mabel FitzGerald, 24 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mabel FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). In the letter, she points out the Desmond was a non-combatant and had been in prison until shortly before the Rising and so could have had no part in the planning of the rebellion. She also requests political prisoner status for those sentenced to penal servitude.Desmond FitzGerald had served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.Mabel was particularly active in attempting to secure the release of her husband, who had not taken an active part in the actual fighting.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1582/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1353</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-05-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0584">2 Loretto Villas, Bray, Co. Wicklow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1353_img_704_1"  type="Letter"  url="4f6c687be1c40a5dcfe8a864a87946ea.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1353_img_704_1"/>
                2 Loretto Villas,  Bray.    24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, 1916.   Dear Sir,   My husband, Mr.Desmond Fitzgerald, was tried by Field <lb/> General Court Martial on Tuesday, 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, and sentenced to 20 <lb/> years penal servitude. The sentence was confirmed on 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, <lb/>10 years being remitted.  Mr.Fitzgerald held no rank whatever in the Volunteers <lb/> and though in the G.P.O. during the Rebellion was there as a non-combatant. <lb/> He was neither trained nor equipped to fight and merely <lb/> helped in the distribution of food and in Red Cross work.<lb/> At his trial Lieut.King, one of the British Officer prisoners <seg type="unclear">i</seg><lb/> in the G.P.O. made a written deposition stating that my husband <lb/> wore civilian clothes and was not to his knowledge engaged in <lb/> the fighting at all, and that he treated him while a prisoner <lb/> with great kindness and consideration.  I understand from my husband that the only evidence <seg type="unclear">a</seg><lb/> against him was his own statement <seg type="del">that</seg>which he made voluntarily <lb/> that <seg type="del">t</seg> he was in the Post Office and that he performed certain <lb/> non-combatant duties there. He was arrested at home on Wed. <lb/> 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May.  As Mr.Fitzgerald was in Mountjoy Prison from October <lb/> last till within three weeks of the Rebellion on a sentence of <lb/> six months for a Nationalist speech he had made here at Bray it <lb/> is obvious that he would have had no share in plans for the Rebellion.  As, therefore, he was neither responsible for it, nor <lb/> took a prominent <seg type="del">XXXX</seg> or even a belligerent part in it, his <lb/> sentence is quite disproportionately severe even among sentences <lb/> which are all harsh, and I shall be grateful if you will bear the <lb/> above facts in mind and if opportunity arises will press his <lb/> claim to a proper trial with a view to revision of the sentence in <lb/> in accordance with the evidence, or will take whatever other <lb/> action you think suitable, recognising however that my husband <lb/> while welcoming inquiry into his case, does not in any wise disassociate <lb/> himself from his friends whom circumstances placed in <lb/> the position of combatants. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  Mabel W.Fitzgerald </seg>  P.S. It would give great satisfaction generally in Ireland <seg type="unclear">f</seg><lb/> if conditions of political imprisonment could be obtained for <lb/> the prisoners sentenced to terms of Penal Servitude; at least <lb/> they might be permitted to keep their own clothes.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>