<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4327">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Somerset Francis Saunderson to Edward Carson, 17 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Somerset Francis Saunderson </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Somerset Francis Saunderson (1868-1927) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Saunderson was the first born son of Edward James Saunderson, leader of the Irish Unionist Party for much of its existence. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4327</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0834">Somerset Francis Saunderson </persName>
              <date>1916-06-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0498">5, Wilton Place, S.W., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4327_img_3687_1"  type="Letter"  url="bcf020038c69afa37a889c1d6491aa9b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4327_img_3687_2"  type="Letter"  url="75a75e88a7f52a73b8cdc0ed56e0b792.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4327_img_3687_1"/>
             TEL. 1808 VICTORIA   June 17. 16.   5, WILTON PLACE, <lb/>S.W.   My dear Carson,   Thanks for your letter. The whole <lb/>situation is very distressing, with the <lb/>one bright side that you can discontinue <lb/>the negotiations &amp; refuse to have <lb/>a Home Rule parliament put into <lb/>operation during the war, &amp; it cannot <lb/>be done as we have the support <lb/>of the Unionist members of the <lb/>Coalition. The knowledge that this <lb/>nightmare is past will have a <lb/>great effect in France among <lb/>our men at the front.   There is one thing I very earnestly
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4327_img_3687_2"/>
            implore you to do &amp; that is <lb/>to fix up a meeting with Walter. <lb/>He will be in London on Monday.   I humbly suggest that, in the <lb/>interests of Ulster &amp; the loyalists all over <lb/>Ireland when the war comes to <sic>a</sic> end, <lb/>it is of the first importance to clear <lb/>up the mis-understandings which have <lb/>arisen, before the question is raised in <lb/>the H. of C.   I have been deeply into the matter <lb/>since I saw you last &amp; am convinced <lb/>that if there has been any betrayal or <lb/>trickery it has not been on the part <lb/>of the Unionist members of the govt <lb/>or at any rate of the majority of them. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>