<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5900">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Florence to Lady Clonbrock, 28 November 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Florence</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent to Lady Clonbrock, Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), &#39;Tweety&#39;, (1839-1928), wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock, (1834-1917).
Lady Clonbrock was one of a number of mainly well-to-do ladies who were members of the Irish Women&#39;s Association formed to provide food and comforts for prisoners of War (WW1) belonging to Irish Regiments. 
HMS Hampshire, on a mission to Russia, was sunk on 1 May 1916 west of the Orkneys. It was thought that there was little hope of survivors, and among those believed to be lost was Horatio Herbert Kitchener (1850-1916), referred to in this letter as Ld. K.
The writer refers to the Hampshire incident and to a letter related to is which has been circulated.
The writer goes on to describe bomb attacks on London in terms of the excitement it caused and the damage it did.
Finally she refers to her &#39;General&#39; as having been through the &#39;Beaumont Hamel Push&#39; (Battle of the Somme, 1 July, 1916) and &#39;thoroughly enjoyed it!&#39;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5900</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0278">Florence</persName>
              <date>1916-11-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1019">Officers&#39; Families Fund, Lansdowne House, Berkeley Square W., London, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5900_img_995_1"  type="Letter"  url="4625ef66d53e9b5e0900326e58b6e1a5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5900_img_995_2"  type="Letter"  url="8c271b16ff702cdd732178f6b7ae2086.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5900_img_995_1"/>
             Lansdowne House, <lb/>Berkeley Square, <lb/>w.   <hi rend="underline">Nov. 28th 1916</hi>   My dearest Tweety   I've never had a moment <lb/>to write till now. We are so amused <lb/> at Sybils story having reached Ireland. <lb/>It is true she heard <hi rend="underline">of</hi>the letter but never <lb/> actually saw it! Since then we have heard <lb/>of several other prisoners of war on the <lb/> Hampshire - but not one mentions L<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. K. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Personally</hi>I always say he's alive!! but <lb/>that is all I can tell you, it created a great <lb/>excitement at the time, and the King was <lb/> told abt. it — but the actual letter was never <lb/> forthcoming! I'll let you know if I ever hear <lb/>of anything exciting. Meanwhile we are full <lb/>of excitement at this moment. We all heard <lb/>5 distinct crashes at 11-30 this <seg type="unclear">morn &amp;</seg> <lb/>we went out to luncheon we hear 5 bombs <lb/>were dropped in Belgravia at that time in  Goodbye for now. I love getting a letter  Fancy dear At. Georgey &amp; Granny if they had lived in these days!!! ?Yours affec   Florence ?Cockran? 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5900_img_995_2"/>
            broad day light &amp; brilliant sunshine - 44 <lb/>Belgrave Sq. was hit, 13 Lowndes Square the <lb/>bomb went right thru the house to the kitchen <lb/>Several people were taken into St Georges Hospital <lb/>&amp; one bomb demolished a bakers shop near <lb/>Harrods and also part of Victoria Station!! <lb/> So the whole of London is wildly excited but no <lb/>panic - <hi rend="underline">"Isn't it amusing"</hi>? is what most people <lb/>say!!! I can't say I think it is at all amusing ?   We have just taken 44 Pont St for the <lb/> winter and have come up today.! the <lb/>girls are thrilled as they always longed <lb/> to be "in a raid"!! I think everything is <lb/> too dreadful just now, but mercifully one <lb/> never has a moment to think ! We are so busy here - &amp; get more &amp; more so every <lb/>moment! — Cecy lunched with Bea today <lb/>&amp; had heard all those bombs all round <lb/> her! Maud &amp; I heard them and <lb/>said oh! its only <hi rend="underline">practising</hi> in St. James' Park. <lb/>Well I must get back to work - My "General" <lb/>was all thru that Beaumont Hamel. Push <lb/>&amp; appears to have thoroughly enjoyed it! <lb/>He said the 10 days passed like lightening"!!! <lb/>&amp; they were just going back &amp; rest this week —   Goodbye for now. I love getting a letter. I for Lacey dear <lb/>at Grocery &amp; Grocery <lb/>if they had <lb/>hired me here <lb/><seg type="unclear">dogs!!!</seg>   <seg type="unclear">With ever affec.</seg>    <hi rend="underline">Florence <seg type="unclear">Jordan</seg></hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>