<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0470">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick H. O'Brien to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, 20 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Hugh Aloysius O&#39;Brien</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Patrick Hugh Aloysius O&#39;Brien to Lord Wimborne (Ivor Churchill Guest) (1873 -1939), Lord Lieutenant of Ireland from 1915 to 1918. O&#39;Brien writes to apply for the vacant post of Clerk of Crown and Peace for County Westmeath. He outlines his career in the legal profession and his recruiting activities for the British Army and Navy. O&#39;Brien states that he will provide testimonials from a number of military men and Government officials. Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/10466</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/470</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0747">Patrick Hugh Aloysius O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date>1916-06-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1987">Strabane, County Tyrone, Ireland. </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0470_img_1817_1"  type="Letter"  url="3d3711316b8e1e5fb616dee782885b98.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0470_img_1817_2"  type="Letter"  url="13db0c59e8c2f33183eeb602465174b9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0470_img_1817_1"/>
                Strabane  Co. Tyrone    20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. June 1916    To His Excellency  The Lord Lieutenant General  and General Governor of   Ireland   May it Please Your Excellency   I take <lb/> the liberty of asking you for the <lb/> position of Clerk of the Crown &amp; <lb/> Peace for the County of Westmeath <lb/> rendered vacant by the death <lb/> of Mr PR Kelly  I am fully quali- <lb/>fied for the position being a <lb/> practising solicitor of over twenty <lb/> two years standing, having been  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0470_img_1817_2"/>
              admitted to the profession in <lb/> February 1894.  I have rendered <lb/> valuable public services <lb/> during my life to members <lb/> of His Majesty's Governments in <lb/> Ireland and have taken a <lb/> very active and prominent  part <lb/> in Recruiting both for the Army <lb/> and Navy, besides acting as <lb/> Secretary of our local Recruiting <lb/> Committee  I am well known to <lb/> several military men and <lb/> Government Officials from <lb/> whom and other persons I hope <lb/> to furnish your Excellency with <lb/> testimonials in a few days  I am a Roman Catholic <lb/> aged about forty seven <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be <lb/> Your Excellencys <lb/> Humble &amp; obedient servant  Patrick H. O'Brien </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>