<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0116">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to Mary Martin, 17 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892–1975) to her mother Mary Martin. Marie begins that she will write a long letter, as she has a whole day off. She expresses joy at her opportunity to rest and outlines her plan for the day, which include going to town. She writes what has happened where she is, including an evacuation. Mary describes her patients as Ulster men, describing one soldier who believed Ulster was the only place in Ireland one could live in safety, going on to claim the men had great pride in being the Ulster Division. She asks her mother to thank her sister Beatrice (b. 1898) for her letter. She is glad Laurence John &#39;Jack&#39; is going back to Townside as it will worry her mother less, assuring her that he will work hard as he is young. Marie was a born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the outbreak of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Medical Missionaries of Mary, B/F/1/61/1916/09/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/116</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-09-17</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1575">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_1"  type="Letter"  url="6ec58bb1335376d0fdb96c90c5c7e3b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_2"  type="Letter"  url="db468069c6a88de4d9ef047395d7fc94.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_3"  type="Letter"  url="135c31a9135027648347ef9c6426b469.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_4"  type="Letter"  url="c56a31891d49e1d5ef4b0616d9099105.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_5"  type="Letter"  url="cc3b7a7d213f729c1437375e45d69cf8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_6"  type="Letter"  url="272d26156400d88e432c1b55cae38b49.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0116_img_1199_7"  type="Letter"  url="97c0a04a0f37cfc4bd1bda11bf91c798.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">17-9-16</hi>   My very dearest Mother   I am now going to write you <lb/><sic>areal</sic> long letter telling you all the <lb/>news I can find, my last letters <lb/>have been very sketchy &amp; written <lb/>in a great hurry. <sic>Iwill</sic> start off <lb/>by <sic>tell</sic> you a very good bit of <lb/>news, <sic>Ihave</sic> a whole day off &amp; have <lb/>just enjoyed my breakfast in bed <lb/>consisting of Toast, bacon &amp; <seg type="unclear">fried</seg><lb/>Tomatoes, I am just delighted at <lb/>having a rest as I just felt I <lb/>wanted a day off so am taking <lb/>it very quietly &amp; staying in bed <lb/>til 10.30 &amp; then go in to town by <lb/>the 11.45 train &amp; have a look about <lb/>town as <sic>Ihave</sic> not been in for  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_2"/>
              over a month.  We have had an enormous evacuation <lb/>these last two <sic>day</sic> &amp; the Hospital is <lb/>practically cleared, my two tents <lb/>are empty for how long no one <lb/>knows they are <seg type="unclear">evidently expecting</seg><lb/>another big rush, I am so pleased getting <lb/>this day before we start again although <lb/><sic>Iwas</sic> very sorry <sic>loosing</sic> all my Gas <lb/>Poisoning <sic>patient</sic>, it was so interesting <lb/>&amp; I was just beginning to under <lb/>stand &amp; learn all about the effect of <lb/>the Gas on the heart etc, however it <lb/>is a great consolation to know they <lb/>have all gone to England but I <lb/>doubt they will get anything like the <lb/>treatment they were getting here as <lb/>our M. O. has made a special study <lb/>of it &amp; was just getting to the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_3"/>
              bottom of it, when all his cases <lb/>have been sent to Eng: it is a <lb/>great pity he is not in charge of <lb/>a big Hospital at home which has <lb/> nothing but G. Cases â.  Well you will be interested to <lb/>hear my last lot of patients <lb/>were all Ulsterman â my 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> was <lb/>a <sic>Srg.th</sic> out of the <sic>Innis</sic> Fus: <sic>a</sic><lb/>absolute terror, who ran Dublin &amp; <lb/>the South down &amp; called them all <lb/>traitors etc &amp; that <sic>ofcourse</sic> Ulster was <lb/>the only place in Ireland one could <lb/>live in safety &amp; that it was the <lb/>only place in Ireland one could <lb/>get work &amp; live on the pay &amp; as for <lb/>the Irish Reg: none of them had <lb/>to go through what the Ulsters <lb/>had etc, <sic>oh</sic> there used to be  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_4"/>
              terrible arguments, I only know he <lb/>was the ruination of the ward, he <lb/>had a different complaint every <lb/>morning for the Medical O. the last <lb/>one a <sic>stygh</sic> on the eye which finished <lb/>him &amp; was sent down to C.C. <lb/>then the next lot that came in <lb/>were really belonging to the Ulster <lb/>division, what a nice lot of men &amp; <lb/>they seemed such a superior <lb/>class &amp; very proud of being in <lb/>the Ulster division, they have all <lb/>been very lucky &amp; got home, having <lb/>been gassed by our own Gas <lb/>It has been terrible cold here these <lb/>last few days, we cannot bear to <lb/>think of the winter, it is so  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_5"/>
              exposed &amp; the gales from the Sea <lb/>are terrible.  Please thank Bee probably Marie's 17 year old sister Beatrice a 1000 times <lb/>for her long &amp; cheery letter it <lb/>did me a lot of good, <sic>Iam</sic><lb/>longing to see her with her <lb/>hair up I am sure she looks <lb/>very attractive tell her my com- <lb/>plexion is the envy of all the <lb/><sic>french</sic> people here, I do not know <lb/>what they would think of hers <lb/>&amp; Violets probably Marie's 19 year old sister , at present the skin is <lb/>peeling off mine with the sun <lb/>&amp; cold winds.  When <sic>Iwrote</sic> asking you for a <lb/>cake, it was just our mess <lb/>had got to a terrible state, we  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_6"/>
              had had no<seg type="del">t</seg> butter for breakfast <lb/>&amp; had been having vile stuff &amp; they <lb/><sic>they</sic> had been giving us tinned <lb/>meat so often &amp; bully beef but <lb/>things are looking brighter <lb/>again &amp; we have been having <lb/>fresh meat &amp; good butter these <lb/><sic>lastfew</sic><sic>day</sic>, <sic>ofcourse</sic> every thing <lb/>is so dear &amp; hard to get  How are all the <sic>invalidis</sic><sic>Ihope</sic><lb/>poor Ritchie most likely Marie's 13 year old brother is better &amp; that he will <lb/>be the last to get it, I am glad <lb/>to hear Jack is going back to <lb/>Downside probably the Catholic co-educational boarding school in Somerset England , it will be less <sic>ofa</sic><lb/>worry for you &amp; am sure he <lb/>will work just as well, it does <lb/>seem hard having to send him  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0116_img_1199_7"/>
              from home so young but am sure <lb/>he will <sic>geton</sic> well &amp; the life might <lb/><seg type="del">t</seg> suit him very well if he is <lb/>strong enough. What is the latest <lb/>news of Tommy, <sic>Iam</sic> longing <lb/>for news <sic>ofhim</sic>.  Well <sic>Imust</sic> close now &amp; shall write <lb/>very soon again, I am <lb/>hoping to hear from you to-night <lb/>With my very fondest love to <lb/>every one at home also all <lb/>the relations. <seg type="closer"> Your most loving &amp; grateful <lb/>daughter.  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>