<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3040">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jim Fitzhenry to Bridgit Fitzhenry, 24 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Fitzhenry</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Fitzhenry (1887-1917)  to his sister Bridgit Fitzhenry. He asks her to thank their aunt for a parcel she sent him. 

Fitzhenry was born in New Ross, Wexford, He had a sister, Bridgit who was born in c. 1853. He may also have had a brother called Edward who was born in 1883. In the 1911 census he is listed as unmarried, boarding with George and Margaret Woodward and their two sons, at 24 Derlwyn Street, Phillipstown. James is a colliery timberman, working underground. He enlisted in the army in Newport on 3rd September 1914. 

His enlistment papers show his address recorded as Glenview Villa, New Tredegar. He became a in the Royal Field Artillery and on 17th May 1915  (no  13140,). He was assigned to the 5th Reserve Brigade, Royal Field Artillery. Through 1915 and into 1916 he was moved to the 4th reserve Battery, 64th Brigade and 65th Brigade until the 30th August 1916 when he was assigned to the 62nd Brigade. He died in 1917 in action. 

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Wexford County Archive</repository>
                  <collection>The Gunner James Fitzhenry Collection, Wexford County Archive, WXCA/P177/6/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3040</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1002">James Fitzhenry</persName>
              <date>1916-08-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Bridgit Fitzhenry</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0921">Wexford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3040_img_2439_1"  type="Letter"  url="eebe80b23784a2da4f833c4d722cfe7c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3040_img_2439_2"  type="Letter"  url="663590a0099b8be2c9978b94bff72226.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3040_img_2439_3"  type="Letter"  url="f91c498822a9fac9cc625f2c6074ae9d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3040_img_2439_4"  type="Photograph"  url="6114e3d579b812379fbab2ea56007f10.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3040_img_2439_5"  type="Photograph"  url="d44cd90640d7879df9cd9ef9b51d7a79.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3040_img_2439_6"  type="Photograph"  url="7ce61c30fea33686c6358a451be260e6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3040_img_2439_1"/>
             24/8/16   France   My Dear Sister   Just a few lines to <lb/> let you know I am <lb/>in the best of health <lb/>  few lines <lb/>will find you all <lb/>right. I had a letter <lb/>from K Ahearn a few <lb/>days back . She told <lb/>me <seg type="unclear">Wins</seg> husband is <lb/>in Hospital some <lb/>where in France
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3040_img_2439_2"/>
            She don't know if she <lb/>is coming to Paris or <lb/>not. She mentioned some <lb/>thing about having been <lb/>offered a place. She wishes <lb/>to be <sic>rembered</sic> to you. <lb/>Well Dear Sister &amp; home <lb/>not much to say at <lb/>present. Every thing as <lb/>usual. By the way I <lb/>received Writing Paper <lb/>safe. With thanks for <lb/>same &amp; also Auntys letter. <lb/>With your Photo . I think <lb/>it is a fairly good one <lb/> of you. thanks very much <lb/>for it. Give my love to <lb/>May Cullen when you <lb/>write to her — bye the <lb/>way I had a letter from <lb/>S McCarthy She has had a <lb/>letter from May Nolan <lb/>and she was asking for <lb/>me. I am pleased to hear <lb/>she is getting on well. <lb/>Tell Bridie I wish to be <lb/><sic>rembered</sic> to her
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3040_img_2439_3"/>
            We are having fine weather <lb/>in so far hope it is <lb/>keeping so will you <lb/>give my best love to <lb/>Aunt &amp; Uncle glad to <lb/>hear Uncle is feeling <lb/> . I will write to <lb/>Aunt before end of week. <lb/><sic>Rember</sic> me to Jim also <lb/>Be good you &amp; God <lb/>Bless you all     Your loving Brother  <lb/>Jim xxxx  Ps ask May Cullen why <lb/>she don't drop me a line <lb/>&amp; let me know how she getting on 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3040_img_2439_4"/>
            <!-- photograph -->
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3040_img_2439_5"/>
            <!-- Photograph -->
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3040_img_2439_6"/>
            <!-- Photograph -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>