<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0308">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Casement Relief Petition Committee to Herbert Henry Asquith, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the Casement Relief Petition sent to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), British prime minister, from the Casement Relief Petition Committee. They are sending signatures including 18 Bishops and Archbishops, 2 Peers, 26 MPs and 253 Representatives of Universities. These are all &#39;people of note&#39; and claim to be looking at the situation without being influenced by the popular opinion and outcry. Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) had been arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Though Casement had not been intimately involved in the planning of the Easter Rising and had travelled to Ireland from Germany to try and prevent it taking place, believing it should not happen without sufficient German support, he had been sentenced to death for treason. The signatories believed that enough blood had been spilt in Ireland and that nothing good will come from the execution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, Ms. 13,088/9/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/308</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1266">44, Parnell Square, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0665">10 Downing Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0308_img_1530_1"  type="Letter"  url="2000bc21384afdbc3912f37adb03fb92.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0308_img_1530_1"/>
              Copy<lb/> to Mrs. Green<lb/> 36 Grosvenor Rd <lb/> Westminster<lb/> London    44, Parnell Square,  Dublin,    31st. July, 1916.    Rt. Hon. H.H. Asquith M.P.  Prime Minister.   Sir,    In continuation of our previous letters enclosing forms of<lb/> petition, we now enclose a few more making in all<lb/> 18 Bishops &amp; Archbishops,  2 Peers  26 M.Ps. &amp; 253 others,<lb/> Representatives of Universities &amp; other learned bodies.   You may see that only men of character &amp; position &amp;<lb/> learning have been asked to sign. This committee has not sought great<lb/> numbers of signatures: it has tried to show the Government<lb/> that men of weight &amp; position, men &amp; women representing the<lb/> learned classes, not influenced by popular emotions, having gravely<lb/> considered the situation, deliberately advise the Government against<lb/> the execution of Roger Casement. Those who have signed have long &amp;<lb/> intimate knowledge of the people &amp; their history; they represent<lb/> many shades of opinion &amp; are united only on this point : that<lb/> enough blood has been shed in Ireland &amp; that it is in the interests<lb/> of Ireland &amp; the Empire that mercy should be shown.   The members of this committee, who are mostly unconnected<lb/> with politics, feel in addition that great dangers are to feared if<lb/> their advice is not followed, but they do not wish to insist on<lb/> this more than is absolutely necessary in order that their views <lb/> shall be known to the Government.   We understand that some thousands of other petitions have<lb/> been sent in by other bodies, but this committee has studiously<lb/> avoided any popular agitation in view of the excited state of opinion<lb/> in Ireland &amp; the signatures have been collected as privately as possible.    We strongly urge the Government not to imagine because there<lb/> has not been a great popular outcry that a strong and intense feeling <lb/> does not exist. Hundreds of thousands of signatures could be obtained<lb/> with the greatest ease, but for the sake of the peace of the Country <lb/> we have deliberately refrained from demonstration or public appeals.<lb/> This ought to render our appeal all the stronger. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully, </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>