<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1024">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Gerard Crofts to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 10 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Gerard B. Crofts</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Gerard Crofts (1889-1934) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) enclosing four tickets and apologizing for the delay in return. Gerard Crofts was known for writing and performing Republican songs and frequently sang at concerts and made gramophone recordings. He joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914 and during the 1916 uprising was serving at the General Post Office in Dublin. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47, ms 33,604/17-12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1024</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1432">Gerard B. Crofts</persName>
              <date>1916-03-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1488">82 Camden Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1024_img_2936_1"  type="Letter"  url="71333c9adc3a7bcb84e69f50a6683840.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1024_img_2936_1"/>
                82 Camden St.  Dublin    10/3/16   Dear Mrs Skeffington   Enclosed kindly find <lb/>four tickets returned.  I sold only two &amp; paid <lb/>a lady, (think was <lb/>last week) in the rooms <lb/>in Westmoreland Street, <lb/>apologising for delay <lb/>in the fixing up of this <lb/>matter. <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/><seg type="foreign">do chara</seg>  G.B. Crofts </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>