<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1052">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Captain Wilfrid Spender to Sir George William Hacket Pain, 5 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Copy of a letter from Captain Wilfrid Spender (1876-1960) to General George William Hacket Pain (1855-1924) offering an account of the deeds of the 108th Infantry Brigade during the initial days of the Battle of the Somme. Spender provides a bleak account of the men&#39;s advance from the trenches and despairs over the unfortunate loss of life, particularly in relation to certain officers such as Captain James Davidson (1877-1916). Prevalent throughout the letter is a sense of Ulster pride. Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Sir George William Hackett Pain was working with the Ulster Volunteers prior to the outbreak of war in 1914. Pain immediately re-enlisted and raised the 108th Infantry Brigade, as part of the 36th (Ulster) Division, by recruiting the Ulster Volunteers. Pain commanded the 108th in France for two years before returning to Ireland to command the Northern Ireland district.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-7, Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1052</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1461">Wilfrid Bliss Spender </persName>
              <date>1916-07-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir George William Hacket Pain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1052_img_3141_1"  type="Letter"  url="f9c097169aa423918ddea3b22b2102f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1052_img_3141_2"  type="Letter"  url="d9988657f38b874af9bf350df6b77a93.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1052_img_3141_1"/>
              Copy of letter from Captain Spender) <lb/><hi rend="underline">to General Hacket Pain.)</hi>    5th July, 1916.   My dear General :-   I know I ought to send you and Sir George an <lb/>account of the wonderful deeds of the Division, which you and he <lb/>raised, but it is not easy.  <lb/> I was in a forward observation post, and could <lb/>therefore see better than anyone else, and I am a very proud, but a <lb/>very sad man in being associated with such splendid men. I honestly <lb/>believe that in the history of mankind no more wonderful feat has <lb/>been done than their attack. <lb/> Our attack was on both sides of a river up a steep <lb/>valley, one flank having to deploy in a wood on the slopes of a hill. <lb/>It had been a wood, but it is now a mass of debris. The wood was <lb/>enfiladed by the enemy's guns on the one side, and by a village on the <lb/>other.  <lb/> Our total front to attack was 3,000, with an unfordable <lb/>river in it. <lb/> The men lost very heavily in the Assembly Trenches <lb/>from intense bombardment, and two Companies of the 10th R.I.R. , <lb/>were reduced to 2 Platoons before they left the awful wood of death. <lb/> The place was covered with smoke and explosions of <lb/>heavy shells, and I felt that no attack was possible, but suddenly, <lb/>out of the clouds, I saw men advancing as if on Parade, quite slowly. <lb/>It seemed impossible, and yet they went on; stormed on the left by <lb/>high explosive and shrapnel, and on the right by enfilade machine <lb/>gun-fire. <lb/> Suddenly they charged, and when I could next see <seg type="del">througg</seg><lb/>through the clouds at the slope (less than a mile away) I saw that we <lb/>had taken the front Trench, and in another minute the B line trench <lb/>followed, as our men shouting: 'Remember the Boyne', and 'No surrender', <lb/>got through - God knows how. <lb/> As they advanced, the fire of the Guns became more and <lb/>more enfilade, but nothing could stop their steady progress. Platoons <lb/>in 'Artillery formation', but very much reduced, pushed on to the 3rd <lb/>Line. This fell in a few minutes. <lb/> Between the 3rd and 4th Lines was a bigger interval, <lb/>and a Parallelogram Redoubt, with a net-work of Trenches, flanked it <lb/>on the right. I saw our men form up towards it, with Artillery <lb/>pounding them in their rear. They took the Redoubt, and the 4th line, <lb/>and were busy consolidating, though pounded on every side, so that it <lb/>looked as if no human being could live. <lb/> The orders had been for the Divisions on our right and <lb/>left to advance with us, and the tragedy was that they were not  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1052_img_3141_2"/>
              able to take even the 1st trenches of the Germans, so that <lb/>our men were in a long narrow salient. <lb/> The 3rd Brigade was to take the last and the 5th line of <lb/>Defence. How they got up to the 4th line through the open zone, <lb/>I do not know, nor whether it was intended that they should not <lb/>attack. Anyhow, our men, who were determined to make the name <lb/>of Ulster ring throughout the world, and not let the Regular <lb/>Division on our left - one with a very big name - beat them, <lb/>(alas there was no chance of their doing so) went straight ahead <lb/>in little parties, and got into the enemy last line. <lb/> No supports could reach them, nor ammunition be sent up. <lb/>How long they stayed, I do not know. Some bodies for 36 hours. <lb/>we had to fall back, and when relieved, handed our part of the <lb/>first two, and a bit of the 3rd line, to the Troops who relieved <lb/>us. <lb/> One of the Brigades sent forward a relieving Party, <lb/>organised by Crozier (who was not allowed to go himself) and sent <lb/>Woods who behaved most gallantly) -- a splendid thing for worn out <lb/>men. <lb/> I cant write more now of the deeds of Heroism I saw, or know <lb/>of - my eyes were a little bothered by the Gas-shells, but some <lb/>day I will try and do so. <lb/> All who watched were amazed, and I hope the Ulster name will <lb/>ring even in the deaf ears of the 'Wait and Sees'. <lb/> The General has refused to mention any special Battalion <lb/>when all the twelve did so well. He now knows he has commanded <lb/>the best troops in the world, and confesses it. <lb/> We hope to get back a large number of wounded later, to <lb/>give a stiffening of 50% to the newcomers; but we can only <lb/>honour and imitate. We cannot replace men like Davidson <lb/>(Machine Gun Commander) who fought his Gun with his leg off. <lb/>Craig who directed movements while unable to move himself, and <lb/>who lies a pr<seg type="del">e</seg>isoner. Bell ,and a host of others, including <lb/>gallant Colonel Bernard, shot getting his men out of the trenches. <lb/> It was rather a bad time, being practically safe oneself, <lb/>watching others in the Battle, and unable to help. <lb/><seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely, </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>