<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5212">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M Buckley to Cornelius Daly, 19 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M Buckley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/8/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5212</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0791">M Buckley</persName>
              <date>1923-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0963">Clashatlea, Ballymcelligott </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Cornelius Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5212_img_None_1"  url="722d44e6f16bd027f286c54addbe0abe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5212_img_None_2"  url="ac881bc8730a57e0d585988b47008eaa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5212_img_None_3"  url="3506196a0e1994b8516712cea6d4ff1c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5212_img_0_1"/>
             P4118/14   Clashatlea<lb/>Ballymeelligott    March 19th 1923    Dear Con   It is with feelings of Sorrow that I learned of<lb/>the appalling catastrophy <seg type="del">with</seg>  which  has befallen you<lb/>by the cowardly, and brutal murder, of your son<lb/>Charlie; Anyone who had known Charlie as I had<lb/>known him, could not but <seg type="del">feelin</seg> feel terribly  shocked  by the<lb/>terrible news. I should have gone &amp; sympathised<lb/>with you before now, but the fact is I could not on<lb/>any account bear meeting you, as I know you must<lb/>be terrily upset by this act of low crawling<lb/><seg type="del">try </seg>tyrants, calling themselves an Irish Goverment  Charlie was the only officer in the<lb/>Firies Battalion, 'while he was adjutant thereof'<lb/>who ever took any pains from organising the<lb/>Companies of the Batt and keeping them in<lb/>working order. In 1918 when I was on command<lb/>of 'A' Company if I had any difficulties with the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5212_img_0_2"/>
             men I had only to aquaint him of it and<lb/>it was righted immediately. When Charlie was Adjutant<lb/>he would not laugh at questions I would ask at<lb/>meetings, as the adjutant we had <seg type="del">b</seg> previous to<lb/>the truce in 1921 had done, Charlie took a<lb/>special interest in placing every company large<lb/>or small in their proper places &amp; he thought just<lb/>as much of the poor as he did of the rich, but it<lb/>was not so with some of the fellows that took his<lb/>place after.  Isn't it a heartrendering thing to think that after<lb/>all this is done, that there are <seg type="del">are</seg> are neighbours of<lb/>some murdered men, doing their endeavours<lb/>to get into the Civic Guards &amp; other positions offered<lb/>by the Free State So called Government who are doing<lb/>their best trying to murder all the good men so that<lb/>when this thing ends, there will be on one to<lb/>reorganise the country. I have said <seg type="del">qit</seg> quiet enough<lb/>the matter is not very interesting for long gossip<lb/> I remain your friend M Buckley     
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5212_img_0_3"/>
             P.S.<lb/>I hope the other two boys are keeping<lb/>in good health and spirits.   M.B.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>