<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0536">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Connolly to Miss Carney, 27 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Connolly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from James Connolly (1868-1916) to Miss Carney acknowledging his regret at hearing of the fire in her premises in Belfast and the destruction of union goods. His writes of his intention to visit her to discuss new premises.James Connolly was an active trade union and socialist organiser and commandant of the Irish Citizen Army. In 1916 he joined the military committee (later Military Council) of the Irish Republican Brotherhood and became intimately involved in the planning and execution of the Easter Rising. He was a signatory of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic and commander in chief of the rebel forces in Dublin during the Rising. He was executed on 12 May.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Allen Library, Br. Allen Collection, IE/AL/1916/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/536</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1403">James Connolly</persName>
              <date>1916-01-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1603">Irish Transport and General Workers Union, Liberty Hall, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Miss Carney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0050">Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0536_img_1915_1"  type="Letter"  url="3d4946ba066ca312828fb6f358b2c34f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0536_img_1915_2"  type="Letter"  url="77df521e31f89e7961693a4b859dd543.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0536_img_1915_1"/>
             EACH FOR ALL. IRISH TRANSPORT ALL FOR EACH.<lb/><lb/>FOR PROGRESS<lb/><lb/>GENERAL WORKERS UNION  General Workers Union   James Larkin,<lb/>General Secretary <lb/>   Head Offices: LIBERTY HALL,<lb/>                              BERESFORD PLACE, DUBLIN              January 27 1916           Dear Miss Carney    I regret very much to learn<lb/>about the fire in your premises, and<lb/>hope the goods of the Union destroyed were<lb/>not of much significance. I shall try and<lb/>visit Belfast in the course of the coming<lb/>week to consult with you about new<lb/>premises. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly  <lb/>James Connolly </seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0536_img_1915_2"/>
               Indonta  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>