<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5406">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Brother Ignatius of De La Salle Training College in Waterford to Martin Kennedy in New York, 19 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Brother Ignatius</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Martin Kennedy, who was born in Tullaroan, Co Kilkenny in 1891, had emigrated to New York in 1915 and was teaching in Westchester, New York. This letter accompanied the return of a form required by the New York City School system to outline applicants&#39; educational background. The envelope was opened and resealed by the censor. Martin Kennedy left New York in December 1916, then spent six months teaching at Jefferson College in Louisiana, then travelled through South America, spending three months at the Eagle Ironworks in Peru, a year at the Chile Exploration Company, and then several years teaching in Buenos Aires. He eventually wound up spending several decades as a Spanish teacher in New York City. He died in 1983. The photograph is from 1928.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Bowden Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection, Martin Kennedy Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5406</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0441">Brother Ignatius</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1923">De La Salle Training College, Waterford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Martin Kennedy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1235">New York City, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5406_img_469_1"  type="Letter"  url="7693533872a5394c28174e14fd82f4ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5406_img_469_2"  type="Envelope"  url="1786210ad373df86ac0fbc84a3d46a1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5406_img_469_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="f880483e45130773351a55b11bf46e37.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5406_img_469_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="e4d77f4158fcb9ad043ea8e2863549df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5406_img_469_5"  type="Photograph"  url="5a2f956b830a281c2e141ce95e21ff30.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5406_img_469_1"/>
             DE LA SALLE TRAINING COLLEGE <lb/>WATERFORD   19-5-16   Dear Martin   There has been <lb/>considerable delay in letters <lb/>over here owing to trouble <lb/>in the Country, hence delay <lb/>in returning form.   I hope you are very well. <lb/>Wishing you success.   Yours sincerely   B. Ignatius 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5406_img_469_2"/>
             Kindly return <lb/>to M.Kennedy <lb/>apt.21, <lb/>1284 Amsterdam Ave., <lb/><hi rend="underline">N.Y. City</hi>   Mr. Martin Kennedy <lb/>c/o J.Nolan <lb/>307 West 118<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Street <lb/>New York City <lb/>U.S.A. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5406_img_469_3"/>
             DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION <lb/>THE CITY OF NEW YORK <lb/>Office of the City Superintendent of Schools <lb/><hi rend="underline">Information Respecting Technical and</hi> <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Professional Education</hi>   To Superintendents and Principals:   For the information of the Board of Examiners you are respectfully requested to fill out one of <lb/> the following blanks regarding the applicant whose name appears on the reverse of this sheet.   WILLIAM H.MAXWELL  <lb/>City Superintendent of Schools.  I hereby certify that the statement made on the reverse of this sheet by the applicant whose <lb/> name there appears is correct respecting work done by him (or her) under my supervision. The <lb/> courses described were terminated by succeccful examinations, except as noted under "Remarks".  REMARKS <lb/>Name <hi rend="underline">B.Ignatius P.Flood</hi> <lb/>Present (or former) title <hi rend="underline">Principal</hi> <lb/>Institution <hi rend="underline">De La Salle Training College, Waterford,</hi> <lb/>Ireland.  N.B. Where college or university courses were counted toward the granting of a recognized collegi- <lb/>ate degree, that fact should be so certified under "remarks." 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5406_img_469_4"/>
            
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5406_img_469_5"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>