<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0836">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr Kathleen Lynn to the Deputy Adjutant General at Parkgate, 26 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Lynn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Dr. Kathleen Lynn (1874-1955) to the Deputy Adjutant General at Parkgate. In this letter, written from Mountjoy Prison, Dublin, Dr. Lynn requests the return of her surgical instruments, fur coat, hat, parcel of clothing and a pair of shoes which she left in the dressing room of Liberty Hall on Monday 24 April, 1916.Dr Kathleen Lynn was a medical practitioner, a suffragist, a nationalist, and a revolutionary. Lynn was Chief Medical Officer of the Irish Citizen Army during Easter 1916, and was a part of the City Hall garrison, of which she took command after the death of Seán Connolly.. After independence, Lynn played a major role in improving public health including the eradication of tuberculosis in Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br. Allen Collection, IE/AL/KL/1/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/836</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1086">Kathleen Lynn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1627">Mountjoy Prison, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1242">Parkgate, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0836_img_2389_1"  type="Letter"  url="39f3068ede1454d39f11d265033337e3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0836_img_2389_2"  type="Letter"  url="4d282fd06aa7908263aea2f536233fe9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0836_img_2389_1"/>
              1006<lb/> Dr. K Lynn    Mountjoy Fl Prison    26.5.16    To the Deputy Adjutant  General,  Parkgate  <hi rend="underline">Dublin.</hi>   Dear Sir   I hear my letter <lb/> to the Provost Marshall<lb/> re property taken <lb/> from me in Ship St <lb/> barracks has been<lb/> referred to you. <lb/> I have further to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0836_img_2389_2"/>
              request that my<lb/> surgical instruments,<lb/> fur coat  hat , parcel con-<lb/> taining clothing &amp; a<lb/> pair of shoes which<lb/> I left in the dressing<lb/> room, 18. Beresford<lb/> Place (Liberty Hall) on<lb/> Monday April 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May<lb/> be returned to me! <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  K. Lynn </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>