<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3636">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from E.J. Kelly to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>E.J. Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from E.J. Kelly to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) expressing sympathy regarding the murder of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. Kelly writes that no words can convey the indignation that is felt in London and Dublin in response to his death.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/2-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3636</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0906">E.J. Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0105">12 Brighton Vale, Monkstown, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3636_img_3033_1"  type="Letter"  url="b88a9bf22a4c94ae7014d9fbe4503fe0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3636_img_3033_1"/>
             12 Brighton Vale,<lb/>Monxstown,  13.5.16  <lb/> My dear Hannah, <lb/>I want to tell you first, how<lb/>much I sympathise with you in your loss,<lb/>and also, how much I admire the manner<lb/>in which your poor husband met his end.<lb/>You know as well as I do that no words<lb/>of mine can convey to you the indignation<lb/>that is felt both here and in London, at<lb/>the way he was done to death; and that<lb/>that indignation is shared alike by friend<lb/>+ foe; by those of whom he may have fallen<lb/>a little foul of, as well as by those who<lb/>agreed with him.   With sincerest sympathy,<lb/>always yours sincerely<lb/>E.J. Kelly  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>