<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4352">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Travers R. Blackley to Edward Carson, 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Travers R. Blackley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Travers R. Buckley to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4352</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1559">Travers R. Blackley</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0996">Drumbar,  Co. Cavan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4352_img_3709_1"  type="Letter"  url="f6f922f7899824f182446bc8ddcde748.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4352_img_3709_2"  type="Letter"  url="48225a2d6b932fd44ff349b8794e6ae6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4352_img_3709_3"  type="Letter"  url="ee8a1dc365f16ae23e7698be66dc2c79.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4352_img_3709_4"  type="Letter"  url="e537f11f7de611a087f1c9fd7233faae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4352_img_3709_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="20641aa0725dfc39abbc404f024adbc0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4352_img_3709_1"/>
              D1507/A/18/13    29    PAGE 1 OF 4    Drumbar,<lb/>C A V A N.    11th July, 1916.    Dear Sir,   Enclose I send you letter from Major Somerset<lb/>Saunderson, resolution, and authority to publish.  But for Assizes coming on and my meeting here<lb/>to—morrow at 12 o'clock to pass resolution. I would have gone<lb/>over to see you at Monaghan, but time is of vital importance<lb/>and I rang up Mr Knight this morning and he advised me to send<lb/>all on to you, and to write and ask you to summon your<lb/>Delegated by wire and pass the resolution and send it direct<lb/>to Major Saunderson,<lb/>5 Wilton Place,<lb/>LONDON. S.W,<!-- both address lines are indented -->  The reasons for passing it are:—<lb/>  <!-- the opening inverted commas are handwritten and the (I) is more like an old capital letter I -->(I) A large number of English Unionist Party are opposed to<lb/>the introduction of Home Rule during the war. Five Unionist<lb/>Members of the Government are also opposed to it but remain in<lb/>office because they think it very ill advised to break up the<lb/>Government during the present offensive in France. If we do<lb/>nothing Ulster stands for Home Rule now and as such will be a<lb/>grave source of weakness to our friends in England.<lb/>(2) We declare our opinion and leave it to the six Counties<lb/>to take what course they like. We commit them to nothing;<lb/>they must judge what course of action their honour demands.<lb/>We know our plain duty and act accordingly.<lb/>(3) If we do nothing it would be a policy of letting things<lb/>slide, when by acting we can influence the course of events in<lb/>the right direction, and possibly help largely to prevent the<lb/>breaking up of the Unionist Party in England. It is essential<lb/>for our own future after the War that the Unionist Party<lb/>should remain a living powerful force.  The above are reasons put forward for passing resolution,<lb/>and Major Saunderson is acting under advice and it is of vital<lb/>importance that <hi rend="underline">that resolution should be in his hands on<lb/>Friday</hi><!-- the word friday is indented on the last line of the page --> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4352_img_3709_2"/>
              D1507/A/18/13    30    PAGE 2 OF 4   <lb/><hi rend="underline">Friday. </hi>May I ask you to leave no stone unturned to obtain<lb/>this for him, and I would be grateful for a line or 'phone from<lb/>you to say you have done so. My number is II <!-- this number if more like capital letter I -->Cavan, but I<lb/>shall be at Court House all Thursday and Friday as Sub—Sheriff.  <lb/>Yours faithfully <lb/>TRAVERS R. BLACKLEY. <!-- there is a broker underline centred across part of the page -->  To Unionist Delegates of County Monaghan.<lb/>Letter by Captain Somerset Saunderson.<!-- this line is centred across the page -->  You will remember that after the meeting of the Unionist<lb/>Council in Belfast on June 12th., we left with feelings of<lb/>dismay and a sense that we had been sold and betrayed by our<lb/>leaders in the Coalition Government which we were told had<lb/>unanimously approved of Mr Lloyd George's proposals; one of<lb/>those proposals being that a Home Rule Parliament should<lb/>forthwith be set up in Dublin.  The delegates of the counties of Cavan, Donegal and<lb/>Monaghan looked on this proposal as a gross breach of the<lb/>pledge under which the men of the Ulster Division had gone to<lb/>the Front, and we would not have considered its acceptance but<lb/>that we were assured that the Government were unanimously of<lb/>the opinion that the proposals should be accepted for grave<lb/>reasons of Imperial necessity in connection with the successful<lb/>conduct of the war arising out of our relations with America.  Being utterly at a loss to understand the view of our<lb/>Leaders in the Coalition, on my return to London I made<lb/>enquiries, and found to my surprise that Mr Lloyd George's<lb/>proposals had never been before the Cabinet nor had our<lb/>relations with America in this connection,and furthermore that<lb/>some members of the Government could see no reason connected<lb/>with the conduct of the War for experimenting with a Home Rule<lb/>Parliament in the present condition of Ireland and as a sequel<lb/>to a dangerous rebellion. <!-- There is the number one displayed as a capital letter I at the bottom right hand corner of this page -->
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4352_img_3709_3"/>
              D1507/A/18/13    31    PAGE 3 OF 4   I forthwith informed Sir Edward Carson by letter, of what<lb/>I had learnt, being convinced that he would immediately<lb/>discontinue negotiations on the basis of a setting up of a<lb/>Home Rule Parliament during the War, but he was unwilling to<lb/>accept my information as accurate.  I then took the earliest opportunity of seeing Sir Edward<lb/>and told him that I was assured of the truth of the inform—<lb/>ation I had received and must take complete freedom to do all<lb/>in my power to upset the proposal. That I felt in honour<lb/>bound to do so as a duty to the men serving at the Front.  I may say that I hve left no stone unturned to<lb/>accomplish this object. Time was too short to ask for your<lb/>authority but I am convinced that I have acted in strict<lb/>accordance with your views and with those of Lord Farnham who<lb/>is with the Ulster Division at the Front.  The Irish Unionist Alliance were kind enough to invite me<lb/>to join their Deputation in London and I gave them a complete<lb/>account of our proceedings in Belfast and they are now aware<lb/>of the reasons and pressure which made us take the course we<lb/>did.  But that course has had the unfortunate result of making<lb/>it appear that the Ulster Unionists have accepted the principle<lb/>of Home Rule; and the Prime Minister himself in our interview<lb/>with them and Mr Lloyd George used that as an argument to<lb/>induce the Unionists of the S. &amp; W. of Ireland to do the same.  But what I have since learned, as above stated (and which<lb/>has been borne out by the statements of Lord Selbourne and<lb/>Lord Landsdowne in the House of Lords) proves conclusively that<lb/><!-- the next 3 lines are typed in single line spacing -->the grounds on which the Ulster Unionist Council came to its<lb/>decision of June 12th., were based on misconception and that that<lb/>decision cannot stand and I am strongly of the opinion that<lb/>the Unionist Committees of the three Counties Cavan, Donegal<lb/>and Monaghan should meet at the earliest possible moment and<lb/>pass a resolution to that effect and forward it to Sir Eddward<lb/>Carson for communication to Ulster Unionist Council.  For the rest of the Ulster Unionist Council naturally I<lb/>cannot<!-- this word is indented on the last line of page --> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4352_img_3709_4"/>
              D1507/A/18/13    PAGE 4 OF 4    32   cannot speak, but having been associated with them for some<lb/>years until it is proved to me I will not believe that they<lb/>will allow their names to be handed down to future<lb/>generations as men who just so as to make a bargain in their<lb/>own favour were willing to throw all their pledges to the<lb/>winds and give assent to the betrayal of a sacred trust, the<lb/>duty they own to the memory of those who have died for them<lb/>and those who are still left to fight for the Empire. <!-- there is a broken horizontal line centred across part of the page -->  RESOLVED :—  That we, the Delegates of the County of<lb/>to the Ulster Unionist Council, now knowing that it was upon<lb/>an entire misconception of fact that we agreed to abide by<lb/>the decision of the remaining six Counties (which authorised<lb/>Sir Edward Carson to continue negotiations with Mr Lloud<lb/>George upon a basis involving the setting up of a Home Rule<lb/>Parliament in Dublin during the War) hereby declare that our<lb/>consent is cancelled and we ask Sir Edward Carson to place<lb/>this declaration before the Ulster Unionist Council.<lb/><!-- There is a horizontal broken line centred across part of the page --><lb/><!-- There is a horizontal broken line at the left hand side of the page -->1916.   Dear Sir,   We have received and considered your letter dated<lb/>June 10th, 1916, and have to—day passed a resolution of which<lb/>we enclose a copy herewith.  We have no objection to this correspondence being<lb/>given to the press.  Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Capt. Somerset Saunderson,<lb/>5 Wilton Place, S.W. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4352_img_3709_5"/>
            <!-- This page of the letter is handwritten --><!-- The next 2 lines are centred -->  D1507/A/18/13    33   Copy Resolution<lb/>passed by Co Monaghan delegates 13<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>July 1916 <!-- above is followed by an unbroken horizontal line centred across part of the page -->  That having ready Major Somerset Saunderson's<lb/>letter of 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916 and Mr. Blackley's letter of 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July<lb/>we are unanimously of opinion that we see no cause to<lb/>change the decision we (along with the representatives of<lb/>Cavan and Donegal) have already arrived at and that<lb/>our confidence in Sir Edward Carson remains unabated  <lb/>Signed<lb/>M.E. Knight<lb/>E. J. Richardson Major<lb/>William Black.<lb/>Thos. W. Hanna<lb/>Thompson Brown<lb/>Robert Doogan<lb/> Martin. <!-- All above signatures are indented to the right hand side of the page -->  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>