<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2986">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Kathleen O'Connell from Pádraig </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Pádraig [?]</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Kathleen O&#39;Connell from Pádraig [?]. She is in America at the time and he fills her in on the events of the Easter Rising, and the fates of different people who were involved. He comments on the large number of young women who took part in the Rising and are now imprisoned in Kilmainham and Mountjoy prisons. He mentions the current censorship of all letters to and from America.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Kathleen O&#39;Connell Collection, UCD, Collection List P155/111/001</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2986</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0802">Pádraig [?]</persName>
              <date>1916-05-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1886">Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Caitlín (Kathleen O&#39;Connell)</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1864">America</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_1"  type="Letter"  url="b0e4f83bf2d9107f9ab47d3ecaad12ef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_2"  type="Letter"  url="6e242c69012d74bdc5a8f93f420efced.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_3"  type="Letter"  url="e170c59614edc53288bc2c13c2c81b49.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_4"  type="Letter"  url="44175dc76b7fbef36abbf3eb33123d23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_5"  type="Letter"  url="7c63ee460ffbf3a21fa3af55169c2508.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_6"  type="Letter"  url="e5f61ba8d140441c330408b1323f6dc0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_7"  type="Letter"  url="c679053e2b456b5a104b7b43c6ed72e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2986_img_239_8"  type="Letter"  url="312b764f63a1f2cfd1847f2d11564d21.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_1"/>
             Contae Ciarraighe   <hi rend="underline">31/V/16</hi>   <seg type="foreign">A Chaitlin, a chara dhil</seg>,   Your letter <lb/>delayed owing to censorship, reached <lb/>me a week later than it should <lb/>in the ordinary course. I immediately wrote <lb/>the" Cork Free Press" and the "Cork <lb/>Examiner" people, and asked them <lb/>to forward you the papers extending <lb/>over the period of the rebellion, which <lb/>will give you all the news, if they <lb/>reach you which is doubtful. <lb/>I have had acknowledgements from <lb/>the newspaper people stating that they <lb/>forwarded the newspapers in due course. <lb/>Ireland is under martial law at <lb/>present and a strict censorship is <lb/>kept on all letters, even letters from <lb/>point to point in Ireland. Letters <lb/>to America come in for special <lb/>attention, hence the newspaper reports <lb/>are the only things available for information
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_2"/>
            at present.   I think you met a good many <lb/>of the men who were mixed up in the <lb/>business the time you were  up  in Dundalk <lb/>at the Oireachtas. Of these the best <lb/>known would be P.H. <sic>Pierce</sic> who was <lb/>shot by sentence of court marshal, Seán <lb/>McDermott who was also shot, Major <lb/>John McBride, Ditto, The O'Rahilly <lb/>who was killed in action at the <lb/>Post Office, Thomas Clarke who was shot. <lb/>There were in all 15 shot by sentence <lb/>of court marshal and about 100 <lb/>sentenced to penal servitude. Of the <lb/>latter were Tom Ashe, Diarmuid Lynch, <lb/>Fionán Lynch (Fr. John Lynch's brother <lb/>of Killmakerin). Ashe was sentenced <lb/>to penal servitude for life and Lynch <lb/>(Diarmuid) got 10 years. He was <lb/>I believe sentenced to be hanged, but <lb/>the American Authorities intervened <lb/>and his sentence was commuted to <lb/>10 years. Fionán Lynch got 10
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_3"/>
            years also. There are about 2000 <lb/>deported to England awaiting trial <lb/>including Arthur Griffith. John <lb/>McNeill has been tried and found <lb/>guilty but has not been sentenced <lb/>so far. I think he is likely to get <lb/>off lightly for at the last moment <lb/>he issued an order to all his <lb/>followers prohibiting them from taking <lb/>part in parades or anything else on <lb/>that day. This order kept the <lb/>Country out of reach from Dublin, <lb/>absolutely quiet, and prevented the <lb/>trouble from spreading. We haven't <lb/>got the rights or wrongs of the thing <lb/>yet but it would appear that McNeill <lb/>was against the rising and certainly <lb/>his order prevented the Rebellion from <lb/>being on a much larger scale.   Sean T. O'C. is a prisoner awaiting <lb/>trial and wounded I believe.   Kerry kept very quiet during <lb/>the business. The volunteers in this County <lb/>looked upon McNeill as their chief and <lb/>they acted on his order. That accounts
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_4"/>
            for good many of them being out of jail <lb/>today probably.   The newspapers state that the <lb/>Government had made arrangements to <lb/>suppress the Irish volunteer organisation <lb/>on the day in which it broke forth. One <lb/>hundred of the leaders were to be arrested <lb/>and deported and all were to be disarmed. <lb/>You will be interested to hear that the <lb/>National volunteers (Mr Redmond's volunteers) <lb/>loyally assisted the military in various <lb/>parts of the country in putting down the <lb/>Rebellion. So that when you hear over <lb/>there that we are a <sic>rebelly</sic> lot, you'll be <lb/>able to realise that we are not all as black as <lb/>we are painted. The "Kilkenny <lb/>Journal" in a burst of indignation informed <lb/>the world that Mr Redmond's volunteers <lb/>in that town paraded the streets, headed <lb/>by a piper's band to celebrate the shooting <lb/>of the first batch of rebels, who were shot <lb/>by order of court marshal. What a <lb/>satisfaction it must be to Mr Redmond <lb/>today to realise that the sentiments of <lb/>loyalty which he implanted so carefully in <lb/>the breasts of his followers has borne <lb/>such good fruit. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_5"/>
             Pierce Beasley got 3 years.   It was a sad business all round <lb/>but I believe the rebels did terrible <lb/>havoc among the military too. They <lb/>fought with tremendous bravery and <lb/>even Mr Asquith paid a tribute to <lb/>"their bravery and to their "clean fighting" <lb/>in the English House of Commons. One <lb/>thing is to be placed to their credit, <lb/>all declare and that is that they <lb/>knew how to fight and <hi rend="underline">they knew <lb/>how to die</hi>. The last words of <lb/><sic>Pierce</sic> as he faced the guns were:- "Ireland <lb/>is unconquered and unconquerable" and <lb/>he was singing "A Nation Once Again" <lb/>as he fell. They all refused to have <lb/>their eyes bandaged saying that they <lb/>wished to face their executioners. Rebels <lb/>against the Crown and Constitution <lb/>of course, but brave men all. The <lb/>firing party paid them that tribute. <lb/>Isn't it sad to think of such men <lb/>under the sod, instead of leading <lb/>their men against the common foe in <lb/>France and Flanders. If they had <lb/>taken Mr Redmond's advice they might
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_6"/>
            have been starred as Victoria Cross <lb/>heroes in England's Roll of Honour.   Curiously enough there appears to <lb/>have been a large number of Irish <lb/>girls involved in the Rebellion. They <lb/>fought with the men, many of them <lb/>sniping away with rifles and doing <lb/>serious damage by all accounts. <lb/>I read an article written by an <lb/>English Red Cross nurse, who <lb/>was all through the business in <lb/>the London 'Daily Express' a few <lb/>days ago. She paid a wonderful <lb/>tribute to the bravery of the girls <lb/>and stated that they acted as <lb/>messengers in many cases, going <lb/>into the zone of fire with the <lb/>utmost nonchalance. It was a <lb/>question of honour with them she <lb/>states to carry through their orders <lb/>or to be shot. She was present on <lb/>one occasion when a volunteer Captain <lb/>asked for a volunteer to carry a message <lb/>to one of his colleagues. The carrying <lb/>of the message necessitated a journey
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_7"/>
            through an area swept by machine gun <lb/>fire but the whole twenty girls sprang <lb/>towards him and clamoured to be left <lb/>go on the errand - each one of them. Eventually <lb/>a well-known authoress was selected <lb/>and she set off after calmly saying <lb/>"good-bye" to the others. She got back <lb/>safely I am glad to say. One would <lb/>feel sorry to think of such a woman <lb/>being shot.   There are about 70 girls imprisoned <lb/>in Kilmainham Jail according to the <lb/>press and about 30 in Mountjoy. <lb/>It is thought however, that they will <lb/>be all released immediately.     I suppose the American papers <lb/>have by this time the romantic marriage <lb/>of Joseph Plunkett, son of Count <lb/>Plunkett, who was shot by order of <lb/>Court martial. He was engaged to <lb/>be married to the daughter of a <lb/>Dublin solicitor, a Miss Gifford. <lb/>She desired to be his bride, so they <lb/>were married in prison the night <lb/>before his Execution at midnight and <lb/> he was shot the next morning. She <lb/>was bride and widow within the 24
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2986_img_239_8"/>
            hours. Miss Gifford's sister was <lb/>married to Thomas McDonagh the <lb/>poet, who was also shot by order of <lb/>Court martial. So that the two sisters <lb/>gave their all.   I think you were present last <lb/>year at O'Donovan Rossa's funeral <lb/>when <sic>Pierce</sic> delivered the funeral oration <lb/>over his grave. There were few more <lb/>eloquent speakers than he. How <lb/>curiously apt are the words in which <lb/>he wound up his speech, nowadays, <lb/>"The fools, the fools, do they seek to <lb/>destroy our Nationality, while they leave <lb/>us the graves of our dead"    I suppose his own grave will <lb/>now become an inspiration for Young <lb/>Ireland, <seg type="unclear">ensuring</seg> the struggle goes on from <lb/>generation to generation with passionate <lb/>devotion and willing self sacrifice on the <lb/>one side, and ineptitude and stupidity <lb/>and callous indifference on the other.    "Thou art not Conquered yet Dear Land."   With very kind regards <lb/>Your Sincere friend   <hi rend="underline">Padraig</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>