<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3006">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Christmas Card to the Ceannt family, [December 1915]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This Christmas card is from the family papers of Éamonn Ceannt (1881-1916). Ceannt was one of the leaders of the Easter Rising and a signatory of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic. During the Rising he commanded the garrison in the South Dublin Union. Following the surrender he was tried by court-martial and sentenced to death. He was executed on 8 May 1916.

On the front of the Christmas card, there is a sketch of soldiers marching under an Irish tricolour flag. Below this, there is a printed poem in Irish by Patrick Pearse. Inside the card, there is a handwritten message wishing &#34;a very happy Xmas&#34; to Eamonn, his son Rónán, and Fanny, who is Eamonn&#39;s wife Áine, christened Frances. There is also a second printed poem, in English by James Clarence Mangan.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Brother Allen Collection, IE/AL/CC/1/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3006</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">Irish</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1915-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Eamonn, Fanny, and Rónán Ceannt</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3006_img_2408_1"  type="Letter"  url="40d8cc9c4c3edc199c3b4e421a46d318.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3006_img_2408_2"  type="Letter"  url="82a1e12fd28b216d51c3e9030e59124e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3006_img_2408_1"/>
            <seg type="foreign"> "A buidhe le Dia na Bfeart go bfeiceam, <lb/>muna mbimid beo 'na dhiadh acht seachtmhain <lb/>Ghrainne Mhaol is míle gaisgidheach <lb/>Ag fogairt fáin as Ghallaibh!"  <lb/>Pádraic Mac Piarais</seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3006_img_2408_2"/>
             Wishing Eamonn, Tommy &amp; Rónán <lb/>a very Happy Xmas from  Joe &amp; Gerard   <hi rend="underline">Xmas 1915,</hi>   May God send you a bright and <lb/>happy Christmas.   Yes, up! and let your weapons be <lb/>Sharp steel and self-reliance ! <lb/>Why waste your burning energy <lb/>In void and vain defiance, <lb/>And phrases fierce but fugitive ? <lb/>'Tis deeds, not words, that I weigh — <lb/>Your swords and guns alone can give <lb/>To Freedom's course a highway!  <lb/>JAMES CLARENCE MANGAN.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>