<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0236">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David G. Curtin to Lord Wimborne, 25 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David G. Curtain</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Mr. David C. Curtain to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Churchill Guest (1873–1939), Lord Wimborne. In the letter Curtain suggests that Wimborne should settle the lease for a former soldier Timothy Murphy, so that in showing this sign of good faith he would be able to recruit Murphy&#39;s neighbours.Lord Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5344/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/236</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1424">David G. Curtain</persName>
              <date>1916-03-25T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0664">Rockchapel, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0236_img_1408_1"  type="Letter"  url="89675dd81ba4176803a8b27a5fa80ca2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0236_img_1408_2"  type="Letter"  url="c542f5df22cf4300bfe32201fa4360bf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0236_img_1408_3"  type="Letter"  url="5efe2e03a60a14c1928a37f4997526f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0236_img_1408_4"  type="Letter"  url="f264b808d51436b3ea7addca9292ec2c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0236_img_1408_1"/>
              Please reply <lb/> as I have <lb/>more to say <lb/> next time <lb/>excuse <lb/>scribble    Rockchapel    25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 16   To his Excellency the Lord Lieutenant   My lord my name is <lb/> Mr.  David C. Curtin, D.C. <lb/>Rockchapel Co Cork <lb/><hi rend="underline">so much for an introduction</hi>  My Lord <lb/>enclosed is <lb/> a letter from the son <lb/>of an evicted tenant <lb/>the evicted tenant's name <lb/>is Timothy Murphy Esq <lb/>Cooleykerane Millstreet  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0236_img_1408_2"/>
              To begin with Millstreet District is <lb/> the hotbed of Sinn Feinners I asked <lb/>several of them why not go to the front <lb/> they replied look at the evicted tenants <lb/> and others groaning under rackrents <lb/> and if we recruit maybe when we are <lb/> dying in France for the Flag that <lb/> same flag may throw down our <lb/> father's house at home for being <lb/> unable to pay a rackrent.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0236_img_1408_3"/>
              Now I would call your <lb/>Special attention to this <lb/>particular case and to <lb/>the underlined sentence <lb/> of this letter which <lb/>shows the ultimatum <lb/>and bitterness of the <lb/>agent though there are <lb/>a 1000 Murphys at least <lb/>in the army a Father <lb/>Murphy's photo is in <lb/>the Examiner of 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi><lb/>an army Chaplain. <lb/> Then in God's name this <lb/> Holy Season of lent  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0236_img_1408_4"/>
              <lb/> according to the agents letter where he <lb/> says he will not relet the land to <lb/> Murphy must the Murphy family go to <lb/> the Giants Causeway for a home like <lb/> the wild geese. I would suggest  re  value <lb/> this land and settle the lease or send <lb/> down M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Loughlin to hold a war meeting <lb/> and I will attend myself. then when the <lb/> land is settled the government will get men <lb/> and I will go out myself.  I conclude with the best <lb/> wishes from <seg type="unclear">me</seg>.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>