<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0478">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Pat S. Higgins to the Under-Secretary, 13 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick S. Higgins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Patrick S. Higgins, Acting Town Clerk, Waterford, to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), Under-Secretary for Ireland, submitting an application for the reimbursement of court expenses incurred by the Corporation for the year to 31 March 1916.Sir Robert Chalmers was appointed Under-Secretary of Ireland in 1916, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/12088</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/478</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1162">Patrick S. Higgins</persName>
              <date>1916-07-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1014">Town Clerk&#39;s Office, Town Hall, Waterford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0478_img_1837_1"  type="Letter"  url="3f5f5e58864765c4c0341327925eeb63.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0478_img_1837_1"/>
                Town Clerks Office  Town Hall  Waterford    13th July, 1916   Sir,   I beg to forward, for the purpose of <lb/>recoupment, the accompanying Statement showing the <lb/>amounts advanced by the Corporation during the <lb/>financial year ended the 31 st March, 1916, in respect <lb/>of expenses of Prosecutors and Witnesses, together <lb/>with Petty Sessions Certificates, Paying Orders <lb/>issued by the Cerk of the Crown and Peace and the <lb/>certificates of the Crown Solicitor.  I am to request you to be good enough to <lb/>return me the documents when no longer <sic>requrred</sic> and <lb/>to acknowledge their receipt. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  Pat S Higgins <lb/>Acting Town Clerk.   The Under Secretary,  The Castle, DUBLIN.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>