<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4233">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, circa November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/70</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4233</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4233_img_3601_1"  type="Letter"  url="f1b7010fc770b401850c1fc353c9f02a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4233_img_3601_1"/>
             No mail tonight when I particularly wanted it as the motor has <lb/> broken down near a place to which Douglas was being conveyed. I hope <lb/> it was not due to this detour of his, but at any rate Douglas ought to <lb/> have got near his destination in it before it happened which is lucky.   25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 2 letters just came separately. Rather a disappointed bw at first, thinking the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> was the only one &amp; that a gay &amp; giddy little p r had neglected to reply <lb/> to his Comforts circular , but more than smoothed down when another came, show- <lb/> ing what the p r was up to. So glad you are pleased old thing &amp; as usual<seg type="del">l</seg> <lb/> we seem to have got the same idea about the same time. How did the p r <lb/> like writing the big cheque I wonder. I'm rather  well  pleased it should have been for a <lb/> Charity, for Ulster &amp; for the Division.    I don't much like the idea of your going to Ireland in the winter but <lb/> it may be your duty to do so. I expect you'll stop with Sir George if you go. <lb/> It's rather nice having a p r  peeping   behind the political scenes, but her excursions etc with <lb/>the Duchess seems quite natural to a b w.   You must find things a little difficult when people try to pump you about <lb/> the Div. You can always say that I think the GOC a strong man, &amp; you can <lb/> add if you like but I a little wish he were a more bigoted Ulsterman, &amp; Add a little <lb/> laugh but of course my husband has very  much  stronger views  still  <seg type="del">which</seg> than many others.   I wonder what Carson thinks of Redmond. I should think more of his <lb/> sincerity &amp; patriotism if he advertised it a little less, but I have no doubt it is <lb/> good business from a political point of view to divert attention from the utterances <lb/> of the Bp of Limerick &amp; some of his colleagues. What is <seg type="unclear">Devlin </seg> doing, remaining <lb/> mum? If so he will have Redmond out of the leadership later when he has <lb/> ceased to be useful with the gullible B.P.   Post ! ! ! 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>