<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3565">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David Sheehy to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, circa May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David Sheehy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from David Sheehy (1844–1932), Hanna&#39;s Father, to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), David writes in the aftermath of Hanna&#39;s husband Francis&#39; death. David then discusses his living situations, as he is currently living in Bath, writing that he wishes he were where Hanna is. He then shares his knowledge of the trial that will occur and sends his love.

David Sheehy was a parliamentarian and the father of Hanna Sheehy Skeffington. Though he supported Irish involvement in the first World War and did not approve of Hanna Sheehy Skeffington&#39;s feminist politics, he was a member of the IRB and interceded for the release of his son in law Francis Sheehy Skeffington after he was imprisoned for anti-war protests. He formally declared bankruptcy in 1915 and was forced to sell the family home, living briefly in Bath, England before moving in with his widowed daughter, Margaret Sheehy, in Dublin.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3565</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1174">David Sheehy</persName>
              <date>1916-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0522">Bath, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1932</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3565_img_2968_1"  type="Letter"  url="922ce4a640abbe61fd48475300945753.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3565_img_2968_1"/>
             <lb/>Bath. Wednesday.   Dearest Hanna,   We were very glad to get a letter from<lb/>you, melancholy as the reading o fit was to both<lb/>of us. I am retruning you the Press Cuttings, and I also<lb/>enclose you a letter wjich I got today from Germaine.<lb/>Mother is something imporved these days, and is<lb/>not as depressed as she has been. I don't yet know<lb/>when we can leave Bath — perhaps not for three<lb/>weeks yet:  <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> that she has commenced to mend<lb/>she may steadily improve, and the better she is<lb/>when going the better she will be able to bear the<lb/>hardship of the journey without being thrown<lb/>back. We are hoping that the necessary lodging<lb/>may be found for us somewhere in the same<lb/>neighbourhood as ye are. We have all the news<lb/>of how you all are, but we are longing to be<lb/>amongst you. I suppose ye are certain to get<lb/>an inquest. But that can only be a preliminary<lb/>to the trial of the murderer, which I hope will<lb/>be a public one. I got a long   a few days<lb/>ago from Dr Skeffington giving his record of the case,<lb/>but nothing that I did not know. I expect the subject<lb/>will be soon discussed in Parliament. I will go to London<lb/>on the occasion. I presume Dillon will be in London next<lb/>week, and he may then press the Prime Minister for the<lb/>trial of the murderer. With fondest love to you all<lb/>from Mother and your affectionate<lb/> Father    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>