<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0825">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 18 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender notes the terrible weather and expresses guilty relief that he is not in the trenches, as conditions there are &#39;really awful&#39;. He recounts a recent ride he undertook upon his horse, Fanny, and praises her fortitude in the weather, deeming her &#39;a true British lady&#39;. Spender mentions the writing of Christmas letters, the probable imminence of his holiday leave, and a batch of correspondence he has recently received relating to the Irish question. He refers to Lillian&#39;s house and servants, makes recommendations for the allocation of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund, and complains that Lillian&#39;s letters invariably arrive late.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/108</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/825</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0825_img_2376_1"  type="Letter"  url="f11f1f7721190333d2f722e8c921cb09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0825_img_2376_2"  type="Letter"  url="6c88c7239e6be45713c4950d4cf91e02.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0825_img_2376_1"/>
              D633/1/1/108    Dec,18   My pr.   Going to turn in in a few minutes but will begin a few lines <lb/>to you first. Very wet all day &amp; the trenches must, I know be <lb/>really awful so that we are lucky to have escaped them for so long <lb/>&amp; I hope the  worst  weather may be over before we take our over some- <lb/>day, tho' this sounds shirking.  Today I went on with my Village defence scheme, Fanny <lb/> taking me out. She really is a game old beast for she dislikes <lb/>the rain intensely but when we had gone 200 yards &amp; she had <lb/>shown  clearly  that she did not approve, she just scampered all the way <lb/>&amp; I have never to use a single whip or spur to her; it is <lb/>all will â a true British lady. â  I am afraid I shall shirk my usual Xmas letters except <lb/> just the family.  18.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> My birthday letters from all your family turned up today <lb/> &amp; were by no means the less welcome for being so early, tho' <lb/> Why did you say they must be posted on the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to reach <lb/>me in time, &amp; why in that case did you not write them <lb/> yourself?    I hear the General intends coming on the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> &amp; it is <lb/> barely possible that I may come over that night too !!! I feel <lb/> sure something will turn up and knock the whole leave on the <lb/>head. Meanwhile Richardson expects to get off on 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> &amp; will  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0825_img_2376_2"/>
              <lb/>look you up, so warn the family.  A huge mail today with letters from Sir George &amp; Craig <lb/>the latter reads rather like an old man's. The former says that HP has <lb/> got command of the Reserve Brigade. I wonder if Gen' Powell put in <lb/> for it; if so it is too bad. If not he has himself to blame for not <lb/> taking my advice. Sir G says I think the Gen' has a special <lb/> down on 3 of us himself Mc <seg type="unclear">Cammon</seg> &amp; me. I wonder?? If so it <lb/> really shows extraordinary penetration on their part, tho' I says it <lb/> but not for repetition.    I hope to write to the family for Xmas but meanwhile give <lb/> them my best thanks.   I am so sorry about the house. I'm afraid there is no chance of <lb/> its being reduced to meet your wishes. I don't know how you stand <lb/> in regard to dates nor when you expect Maggie &amp; Sarah to return to you.    Poor thin little FA as the WR calls you. I think I know <lb/> what <seg type="del">it</seg> FA  means, in fact I'm sure, but it ought to be Funny Apology <lb/> for an animal (FA) <hi rend="superscript">2</hi> in fact in algebra, but then WR may not agree.   Most certainly NO grants for Xmas dinners from your funds. It <lb/> is a most outrageous demand. Please let your committee understand that <lb/>there will be countless <hi rend="underline">real</hi> demands upon all their funds later, when <lb/>wounded &amp; others get back. I should be furious to think that our <lb/>gift was frivolled away on Xmas dinners for which the Canteen funds <lb/> can pay without difficulty. You can let the Committee know my <lb/>views with which I am aware the General fully agrees He is <lb/>is all for accumulating funds for future requirement.   Richardson &amp; I were out with him this morning. Off to a <lb/>lecture of Boylan Smiths. All <hi rend="underline">your</hi> letters arrive a day late. The <lb/> Family's letter posted the day after yours arrived to time. Can you explain <lb/> Perhaps you ought to put <seg type="unclear">on</seg> post earlier?  <seg type="closer"> Your <lb/> BW </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>