<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3084">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John N. Barran to Arethusa Leigh-White, 21 December 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John N. Barran</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>John Barran writes to Arethusa Leigh-White confirming he has spoken to Mr McCann in London, who has written to Mr Harris who is in command of the South-Western area. Barran states that the YMCA have faced the same difficulties in many places in Ireland. He further states that the YMCA is interdenominational. It appears that Mrs Leigh-White is looking to establish a soldiers and sailors club for wounded or invalided soldiers and sailors from the Bantry area. 

This is a letter from the extensive Bantry Estate Collection, held in the Boole Library of University College Cork. The collection, which covers a period of 300 years, contains the formal records regarding the legal, financial and general administration of this large house and estate in County Cork.  
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>UCC Library Special Collections and Archives</repository>
                  <collection>The Bantry Estate Collection, BL_EP_B_3157</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3084</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0068">John N. Barran</persName>
              <date>1915-12-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1695">Stafford Hotel, St James&#39;s Place</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arethusa Leigh-White</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3084_img_2488_1"  type="Letter"  url="8b121a8ea9e13c3fe59c37971b15d59b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3084_img_2488_2"  type="Letter"  url="809097377815e6676ce8b88bb319a615.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3084_img_2488_1"/>
            sense, &amp; of course, <lb/>you know, no one <lb/>will appreciate your <lb/>opinion more <lb/>than Edward himself.   Yours <sic>affectly</sic>   Arethusa Leigh - White   Stafford Hotel <lb/>St James Place   20.4.16   My Dear Ernest   I know that Edward <lb/>has spoken to you about the <lb/>trusteeship. You know how deeply <lb/>I should appreciate it if you <lb/>can see your way to accept <lb/>it. I quite understand you <lb/>hesitating, but it will be a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3084_img_2488_2"/>
            very great disappointment to me <lb/>if you cannot accept. I don't <lb/>know any one who would have <lb/>such confidence as yourself, nor <lb/>any one so quick to realise <lb/>the true Interest of Edward, myself <lb/>&amp; the children.   You know too, that you can <lb/>depend upon me to assist <lb/>you &amp; that you can always <lb/>rely upon my discretion &amp; common
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>