<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1764">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Mary Ellen O’Rahilly, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Mary Ellen (‘Nell’) O’Rahilly. The letter concerns the death of Mary O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s brother, Micheal. In this letter the author offers condolence for his death and mentions that a cross has been made in his honour. The letter also notes that it was sent by hand as the writer is unsure where the family is living. It continues on to discuss the burial of Micheal and the glory that he is due.

Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated. 

Nell was also involved in the Nationalist movement as a member of Cumann na mBan and was imprisoned after the Rising for her role.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/121/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1764</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Ellen O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1762">Northumberland Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1764_img_1220_1"  type="Letter"  url="b725e2680ea97d7a6ac29992821dbd67.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1764_img_1220_2"  type="Letter"  url="677fa6e0c73e3c0d1332e13c54f28945.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1764_img_1220_3"  type="Letter"  url="9c08bcd45af629a6b9386f217b027984.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1764_img_1220_4"  type="Letter"  url="b7423de6bde540baf81a183138928184.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1764_img_1220_1"/>
             9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916   My dearest Nell,   Need I tell you<lb/> how deeply I sympathize<lb/> with you in all your sorrow <lb/> and trouble - may our<lb/> dear Lord comfort and<lb/> console you as He alone <lb/> can. I have prayed<lb/> much for poor Michael,<lb/> every day since I heard <lb/> the sad news I made <lb/> the Way of the Cross for <lb/>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1764_img_1220_2"/>
            his soul R.I.P. and I got<lb/> a great many of the<lb/> children to do the same.<lb/> I feel very much<lb/> for his poor wife, Anna<lb/> and you - will you<lb/> please show this letter<lb/> to his wife and tell<lb/> her I do not forget her<lb/> in my poor prayers.<lb/> It is a great consolation<lb/> to know that Michael<lb/> was so good, everyone<lb/> speaks highly of him,<lb/>
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1764_img_1220_3"/>
            and I am glad he was <lb/> saved from a public trial<lb/> - he met death bravely<lb/> like a hero and we<lb/> have all reason to be<lb/> proud of him - but<lb/> you will all miss him<lb/> sadly for a long time,<lb/> however our Blessed<lb/> Lord knows best, may<lb/> His holy will be done.   I am sending this<lb/> letter by hand as I do<lb/> not know if you are<lb/>
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1764_img_1220_4"/>
            at present living in<lb/> Northumberland Road<lb/> or not - I should love<lb/> to get a line from you when<lb/> you have time, but I well<lb/> understand how you feel<lb/> just now - I suppose<lb/> poor M. will be brought<lb/> later on to Ballylongford<lb/> &amp; there he will D.V. get all <lb/> the honour &amp; glory which<lb/> is his due.   Again assuring you of <lb/> my deepest &amp; most heartfelt<lb/> sympathy and with much<lb/> love to the three of you   I remain<lb/> Your loving cousin  SM <seg type="unclear">Clery</seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>