<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1050">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Earl of Shaftesbury to Matthew Nathan, 15 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Anthony Ashley-Cooper</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Anthony Ashley Cooper (1869-1961), H.M. Lieutenant of Co. Antrim to Matthew Nathan, Under-secretary for Ireland, concerning the appointment of Deputy Lieutenants for County Antrim. He states that 27 D.L.s are allowed and there are currently 23. He also clarifies that the Major Roger Casement, D.L. for Co. Wicklow is not the same person as the Antrim nominee of the same name, but a distant cousin.Anthony Ashley Cooper, 9th Earl of Shaftsbury, served as Lord Lieutenant of Antrim from 1911 to 1916, Chancellor of Queen&#39;s University, and Lord Lieutenant of Dorset from 1916 to 1952. Cooper retired from the British Regular Army in 1899, but would continue to serve as captain, and later lieutenant colonel of the North of Ireland Imperial Yeomanry. During the Great War, Cooper held the temporary rank of brigadier-general, and was subsequently honoured with the rank in 1919.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP/1916/3692/15, NAI CSO RP/1916/3692/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1050</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1010">Anthony Ashley-Cooper</persName>
              <date>1916-02-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1949">Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1050_img_314_1"  type="Letter"  url="e1ab2432e3ef979795a503e9e6bcd373.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1050_img_314_1"/>
                The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle.   Dear Sir.   Please see  your  list of D.Ls for Co. Antrim <lb/>revised. <lb/>Number allowed 27 <lb/>Number existing 23. <lb/>Major Roger Casement D.L. for Co. Wicklow <lb/>mentioned in your letter is not my <lb/>Antrim nominee but a distant cousin. <lb/>Please expedite issue of commissions <lb/>suggested to His Excellency by me <lb/><hi rend="underline">31st December last</hi>. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  Shaftesbury <lb/>H.M.L. <lb/>Co. Antrim </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>