<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1709">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles P. O'Neill to Matthew Nathan, 30 Mar 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles P. O&#39;Neill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Charles P. O’Neill, a solicitor based in Dublin to the under-secretary for Ireland, Sir Mathew Nathan (1862–1939). Mathew Nathan had become under-secretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell (1850–1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned due to his misjudgement and failure to stop the Rising.  The letter is a request by Charles P. O’Neill to be considered for the vacant position of Chief Crown Solicitor, which had become available after the death of Malachy J. Kelly. In the letter he outlines his previous experience in various public positions and goes on to claim he has the support of the members of parliament for the city of Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>NAI/CSO/RP/1916/5729/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1709</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0246">Charles P. O&#39;Neill</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0489">Chambers, 36 Dawson Street, Dublin.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0890">Dublin Castle</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1709_img_1166_1"  type="Letter"  url="be1393bf79d4066fa15438b4037013dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1709_img_1166_2"  type="Letter"  url="4db89d62f0d33471684baa461b9146cb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1709_img_1166_1"/>
             Chambers, 36 Dawson Street, Dublin  30 March 1916   Sir   I beg to offer myself as a Candidate <lb/> for the position of Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland. I was <lb/> admitted a solicitor in the Easter Term 1892 - just 24 <lb/>years ago, and have continuously practised my <lb/>profession since that time.    I am and have for many years been <lb/> acting for several Public Bodies including <lb/>The Blackrock Urban Council Co Dublin <lb/> The Rathdown Rural Council Co Wicklow <lb/>The <seg type="unclear">grange</seg>Board , and also acted <lb/>as Law agent for the Kilmainham Urban <lb/> District Council before that District was taken <lb/> into the City.   I have had experience of every branch of a Solicitor's Practice, <lb/>from the Kelly Sessions to the House of Lord's <lb/> and have also had during the past 17 years a <lb/> considerable amount of business before the <lb/> Committees of both Houses of Parliament    I herewith enclose copy of letter from <lb/> my old friend Mr John Clancy K.C. MP for <lb/> North Dublin expressing his opinion as to my <lb/> professional standing.    I have the honour of having the support <lb/> of all the members of Parliament for the City and
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1709_img_1166_2"/>
            County of Dublin and also of Mr T P O' Connor MP. <lb/>&amp;Joseph Devlin MP and other members of <lb/> Parliament.  I propose to obtain and send <lb/> you letters from some of the judges of the <lb/> High Court and from leading members of the <lb/>Bar who know me.    I have been Chairman of the Pembroke <lb/>Urban District for the past five years and <lb/>am acting as Local Controller of Recruiting <lb/> in that District.    I am Sir <lb/>Your obedient servant   <hi rend="underline">Charles P O' Neill</hi>   The Right Honourable <lb/>Sir Matthew Nathan <lb/>Dublin Castle 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>