<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2233">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to 'Canon', 10 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to &#39;Canon&#39;. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
In the letter, Montgomery discusses the threat of Home Rule, stating that the six county scheme i.e. partition, should be accepted due to the situation what he was told by James Craig (1871-1940) and Edward Carson(1854-1935), Unionist leaders. Montgomery goes on to discuss how he feels it is a betrayal of the Protestants of Donegal, Monaghan and Cavan who signed the Solemn League and Covenant, however he feels they would be safer on the borders of a six county Ulster than an unstable nine county Ulster.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingbourne Papers, D/627/429/30</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2233</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Canon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2233_img_1678_1"  type="Letter"  url="678d51d1ebad9c332bc3c2ada19054ce.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2233_img_1678_1"/>
            Copy  11th June, 1916.   My dear Canon,   I send you back your Republican newspaper, as you may <lb/> wish to keep it among your curiosities or give it to someone else.   The present position about the exclusion of Ulster is <lb/> not pleasant; but in view of the state of things as revealed to <lb/> us privately by Sir Edward Carson and Colonel Craig, I believe <lb/> we ought if possible to profess our readiness to agree to the <lb/> six county scheme, and I believe that, though this would look <lb/> like a forsaking of our brother <sic>Govenanters</sic> in Monaghan, Cavan <lb/> and <sic>Donegall</sic> that they would really be safer on the borders of a <lb/> secure six county Ulster than inside the very insecure citadel <lb/> of a nine county Ulster: I say insecure because the Nationalists <lb/> would form too strong a body inside the nine counties, being <lb/> able as it is to return a majority of parliamentary representatives. <lb/> It appears to be a mad act of the Government at this moment to <lb/> propose to bring the Home Rule Act into operation for any part <lb/> of Ireland, and I hope that if we agree to acquiesce in the six <lb/> Counties scheme we shall make it very clear that we do not <lb/> approve, and take no responsibility for any such setting up <lb/> of Home Rule immediately after the Rebellion.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>