<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2264">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to William Coote, 9 Spetember 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924). Montgomery was a lawyer and politician. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter was addressed to William Coote (1853-1924). Coote was a politician and in 1916 he was representing South Tyrone in the Imperial Parliament as a Unionist and continued to do so until 1922.
This letter concerns the appointment of certain candidates to the officials position at the sanatorium and their religious affiliations.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/61</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2264</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-09-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Coote</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2264_img_1707_1"  type="Letter"  url="e6ccc18d8d2b927c2e21cce91a7c59ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2264_img_1707_1"/>
             Private  Copy   9th September 1916    Dear Mr.Coote,   Many thanks for letting me see enclosed, which is very<lb/>encouraging. I will let you know as soon as I hear anything<lb/><sic>form</sic> Sir Edward Carson; but it is possible he is away resting<lb/>after an arduous Session, and there may be some delay.     It is a great pity that your proposal was not carried at<lb/>the County Council when the Protestants had not a better candidate.<lb/>I really could not vote for Milligan against Stafford in view of<lb/>the words of my declaration, and of the manifest superiority of<lb/>Stafford's qualifications. I greatly regret that neither of the<lb/>head officials of the Sanatorium should be protestants; but my<lb/>conscience is fairly clear, as I proposed the best qualified of<lb/>the candidates for the Medical Officership who is a protestant,<lb/>and he was thrown out on the first vote.   Yours very truly,   P.S. Mrs. Montgomery would have been very glad to see you here<lb/>yesterday, but you were quite right to attend the meeting of the<lb/>Sanatorium Committee under the circumstances, and I hope things<lb/>went right there. You will be glad to hear that Mrs. Montgomery's<lb/>Sale was well attended and successful. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>