<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0894">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard Cruise to Arethusa Leigh-White, 14 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard Cruise</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Richard Cruise to Arethusa Leigh-White (1885-1959). The two page handwritten letter relates to police in Bantry and referring to incidents around the country. This is a letter from the extensive Bantry Estate Collection, held in UCC Library in University College Cork. The collection, which covers a period of 300 years, contains the formal records regarding the legal, financial and general administration of this large house and estate in County Cork.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>UCC Library Special Collections and Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Bantry Estate Collection BL_EP_B_2553, Bantry Estate Collection BL_EP_B_2553</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/894</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0028">Richard Cruise</persName>
              <date>1916-05-14T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0144">Bantry, Co. Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arethusa Leigh-White</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0894_img_2472_1"  type="Letter"  url="90ae4877f84bf12bac29bd29bfd8865c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0894_img_2472_2"  type="Letter"  url="0fa0524f9840af65740d114e1de6059d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0894_img_2472_1"/>
              From Richard Cruise <lb/>(head of RIC in Bantry)    Bantry    <hi rend="underline">14. V. 1916</hi>   Dear Mrs Leigh White,   I thought the letter I enclose from my <lb/>brother might interest you. He was a Gaelic <seg type="del">Lean</seg><lb/>League enthusiast &amp; I can recall his camping out on <lb/>one of the Arran Isles years ago with John M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Neill <lb/>so he is in a position to speak of that side of the <lb/>movement. On the whole I think his conclusions <lb/>are sound â but the worst of Ireland is that everyone <lb/>has a solution in his and then they send over <lb/>a chief Secretary who is so torn to pieces between 'em <lb/>all that he does nothing.  So you remember our effort to stop Peter O'Hourihane coming <lb/>on his rounds organising disaffection? they put <lb/>that file in a pi<seg type="del">n</seg>geon hole &amp; on some other matter <lb/>allowed me to understand that I was not to worry <lb/>them. It is really a scandal the way they tied <lb/>our hands .... a premium was put on smug <lb/>complacency in police work and any man <lb/>that tried to make them think was Sandbagged. <lb/>'We don't want police work' was the motto â well <lb/>they got what they wanted with a vengeance.   Just to think of it the Inspector General of the RIC in England <lb/>&amp; Dublin Castle held by 13 men they say when the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0894_img_2472_2"/>
              rebellion started!! and this 3 days after the <lb/>Casement incident &amp; the sinking of the German ship <lb/>If the Government are serious they must make radical <lb/>changes in both the D.M.P &amp; R.I.C Crime Special <lb/>Staffs.  We had a week or 10 days of tension in Bantry â the <lb/>little knot of O'Hourihanes friends were very anxious <lb/>to do something â probably shoot a policeman or two <lb/>â but it did not come off. The Canon came quite out <lb/>of his shell and in the end got the arms &amp; ammunition <lb/>from them. I made no arrests.  I do hope they will appoint a live man Chief Secretary <lb/>â it would be a stroke of genius to appoint William <lb/>Martin Murphy if he is young &amp; strong enough and <lb/>would take it.  We had great excitement in Bantry receiving the 107 from <lb/>the poor S/S Cymrie ... I missed you tremendously! <lb/>everyone was good enough however to be pleased about it <lb/>â Your husband was very civil to the American Consul <lb/>&amp; this report to the American Ambassador (he showed it to me) <lb/>did not omit an essential point. The Captain <lb/>specially thanked the B.V.A.S. &amp; this appeared in the papers.  I must apologize for this terribly long letter â You will think the <lb/>tribe of Cruise <hi rend="underline">Cruise</hi> have developed an itch for writing!  Eileen is very well &amp; joins with me in sending kind Regards <seg type="closer"> Yours very Sincerely  Chief </seg> P.S. I had an urgent letter from Mrs Aitchison to go out at once â her nurse would not leave &amp; <lb/>was imputent etc. etc. â I went &amp; the nurse left. She was lucky to escape with a <lb/>trifling cut on the hand &amp; some damage to her belongings. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> A. asked Eileen to send the children out <lb/>when she went to Cork &amp; we laughed all the way home! I am afraid she'll end in the Asylum <lb/>or in prison. Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Wilkinson is also worrying me about her servants....we RIC <lb/>are maids <lb/>of all work.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>