<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4696">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to Norman Moore, 3 May 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Norman Moore (1847-1922) had a strong connection with the Royal College of Physicians. From its inception in 1883, he belonged to the Committee of Management that first planned and directed the Conjoint Board examination, and from 1901 to 1922 he represented the College on the General Medical Council. He also became the president of the R.C.P. London.

From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-89</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4696</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1919-05-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Norman Moore</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4696_img_4033_1"  type="Letter"  url="fe8cd9c1972e52f249c6e7eb8b0182f1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4696_img_4033_1"/>
             3rd May 19.   Sir Norman Moore, Bart., M.D., <lb/>President R.C.P., <lb/>London.   Dear Sir Norman,   It gives me great pleasure to have the honour to <lb/>forward you a copy of the following resolution which was <lb/>carried by acclamation at a meeting of the President and <lb/>Fellows of this College held yesterday the 2nd Instant :- <lb/> Resolved: that the President and Fellows of the Royal <lb/>College of Physicians of Ireland hereby offer their heartiest <lb/>congratulations to Sir Norman Moore, Bart., President of the <lb/> Royal College of Physicians of London and Honorary Fellow <lb/> of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, on the well <lb/>deserved honour which has been conferred upon him by His <lb/>Majesty King George V.   I have the honour to remain, <lb/>Dear Sir Norman, <lb/>Yours faithfully, <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>