<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0735">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from McCotter to George Hackney, 30 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>McCotter</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Nellie McCotter to George Hackney (1889-1977). McCotter thanks George for his recent letter, and writes that they have been wondering how George was getting on ever since &#39;the great &amp;amp; glorious charge of the Ulster division&#39;. McCotter expresses regret that only the &#39;young and fresh are allowed the privilege of going in active service&#39;. McCotter writes that the display of the Ulster battalions has silenced the pacifists and the Nationalist newspapers. McCotter gives news of &#39;Arthur&#39;, mentions the effects of shell-shock on men sent home from the front, and hopes that George will soon have a chance to visit home. McCotter mentions receiving a letter from a &#39;boy I thought had been done for&#39; and pities the condition George and &#39;all you boys&#39; are living in, declaring that &#39;we don&#39;t half realize all you men are doing to keep us safe here in England.&#39; This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney, a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;. In 1916 he was injured and spent some time a Hospital in Calais, France, and in Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6-9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/735</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0613">McCotter</persName>
              <date>1916-08-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2062">73 Charlwood Street, London S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0391">19 Ward, 35 General Hospital, Calais, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_1"  type="Letter"  url="ba43d9bb6ab7338bc7d6fa2e79461b7c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_2"  type="Letter"  url="3bd3a0e8767344717208fc53feee8ee2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_3"  type="Letter"  url="f2d39addd3ecf761829c3dd5f2707686.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_4"  type="Letter"  url="5040ee2bd0bf956c5957345df4b721e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_5"  type="Letter"  url="6dd6b2ac6642f12b3a36c2f1f66c9b58.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_6"  type="Envelope"  url="d6907344fde4058a414cda4435f86dad.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0735_img_2245_7"  type="Envelope"  url="333539b43db826d34d7c340fee0b9443.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_1"/>
                73 Charlwood St.,  London, S.W.     30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Aug. 16   My dear George,   I was very pleased to <lb/> get your letter this morning (at <lb/> present I am at Hale Common, Farnham <lb/>nr. Aldershot, so your letter went from <lb/> Mortimer House, to Charlweood S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. &amp; on here. <lb/> I often wondered where you were,&amp; how <lb/>you were getting along since the great <lb/> &amp; glorious charge of the Ulster Division, <lb/>you bet your boots I felt as proud as <lb/> a peacock when I read all about it <lb/> later. I would have given anything <lb/> just to have been at hand to help <lb/> the boys who were bowled out, but <lb/>only the young &amp; fresh are allowed <lb/>the <sic>privelege</sic> of going on active service <lb/> wish I was 20 yrs younger I'd <lb/>be near the firing line. Our Div.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_2"/>
              got an awful slaughtering, but <lb/> not a man showed the white <lb/>feather, 'Carsons goose steppers' <lb/> made a name for themselves <lb/> which any reg<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> might be proud <lb/> of, a friend wrote me that the <lb/>Nationalist papers were all <lb/> dumb on the subject. The enclosed <lb/> cutting I cut out of the 'Post' &amp; <lb/> had sent in to Arthur on the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> not knowing then that he had <lb/> been put out of action on the way <lb/> up, bit of shrapnel through <lb/> left shoulder &amp; one of the R.A.M.C. <lb/>men turned him, the letter was <lb/> returned to me last week: so the <lb/> cutting may interest you or some <lb/> of the boys. Arthur was in a number <lb/> of Hospitals before going to a Convalescent <lb/> Camp at Eastbourne &amp; on the <lb/> 16th<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. he &amp; a number of the Ulster <cb/> boys crossed to Belfast on leave. <lb/> I saw Y.C.V. on the shoulder of one <lb/>of the boys, all seemed in good <lb/> form, I had a couple of hrs with <lb/> Arthur, he expected to be sent <lb/> back to the Ulster Div. base at <lb/>B. <seg type="unclear">Sinclair</seg> until further orders. <lb/> A big number suffer from shell <lb/> shock Lieut. A Wallace was sent <lb/> home, has go another mths leave <lb/> &amp; is at some ng. sea port. It <lb/><sic>wd</sic> do you good to get sent over <lb/> to Eng. or Ireland for a while <lb/> not much chance of a cure <lb/> within sound of the guns. You <lb/> seem to be luckier in the <lb/> weather than we are, it has <lb/> been very wet, awful thunder <lb/> showers; much colder. Sunday <lb/> it showered at intervals all day  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_3"/>
              Yest. it never ceased, today has <lb/> been fine since about 9 A.M. <lb/> but there is quite a cold feel <lb/>in the atmosphere. Your Auntie <lb/>sent me a card from Euston that <lb/> she was off to Ireland &amp; felt very <lb/> sad having no one to see her off, if <lb/>she had written to me in time I <lb/> could as I was on the idle list for <lb/> a short time after leaving <lb/>Mortimer House. Letters just in <lb/> from Steele, the boy I though had <lb/> been done for, I nursed him at Tring <lb/> 1914 &amp; have been writing &amp; sending an <lb/> odd paper since he went to the Front <lb/> last year, he has been attached <lb/> to another Batt. &amp; so did not get the <lb/> pcl. or papers, but said the boys <lb/> had maybe more need of them that <lb/> he had. I do hope to hear a <lb/>good account of your mother  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_4"/>
              from your Aunt, I expect she is longing <lb/> for a sight of you, and surely <lb/> they will send you home for a <lb/> wee rest soon. Have just heard <lb/>that Arthur is at Ballykinlar, <lb/> he will probably be sent out with <lb/> a draft soon. I pity all you boys <lb/>when I turn into my comfy bed every <lb/> night, we do not half realize all <lb/> our men are doing to keep us safe <lb/> here in Eng. The <sic>Rumanians</sic><lb/> joining the Allies has given the <lb/> enemy a bad turn &amp; it looks <lb/> jolly like as if <hi rend="underline">'Tins'</hi> will have <lb/> to follow suit, the Bulgarians &amp; <lb/> Turks must feel jolly sick now <lb/> that they ever trusted the gentle <lb/>Hun. &amp; Austria. Well we <lb/> have got the whip hand now <lb/> &amp;must keep it until Germany  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_5"/>
              is stripped bare, no peace until <lb/> they have paid for all their <lb/> deeds of destruction. Unfortunately <lb/> we cannot take a Hun life for every <lb/> foul murder done by them, but <lb/>they must be made to pay in some <lb/> way. I am scribbling this in my <lb/> pts. room. I feel very ashamed <lb/> when I look at your copperplate <lb/> writing from the trenches at 11 p.m. <lb/>With many good wishes &amp; most <lb/>sincerely hoping that you <lb/>will get home for a spell <seg type="closer"> Your very sincerely  Nellie McCotter </seg><seg type="postscript"> I have two nephews at the front somewhere <lb/> one is in the R.A.M.C. Dr. Norman Davidson <lb/>&amp; the other Chaplain R.C. <seg type="unclear">Mackleoun</seg><lb/> you may come across them <lb/> sometime. </seg> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_6"/>
              <hi rend="underline">RC</hi><lb/>10/9/16 <lb/><hi rend="underline">repd</hi><lb/>2/10/16  <seg type="del"><hi rend="underline">Hospital</hi></seg>  APO4  Lce-Corp G. Hackney, 14/148 15 <lb/><seg type="del">14</seg>14th (8) Batt. R.I. Rifles, Y.C.V. <lb/><seg type="del">B. <seg type="unclear">Reg</seg><lb/> <lb/>France</seg>   19 Ward  35 General  Hospital     
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0735_img_2245_7"/>
               Rear of envelope Two date stamps Army Post Office B 9 sp 16 B 10 sp 16  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>