<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2733">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Ford Hutchinson to Alec C Tate, 17 December, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Ford Hutchinson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Ford Hutchinson to his cousin Alec Tate, describing his life in Wellington,  New Zealand as a Church of Ireland minister. 

Alec C Tate served with British army in India before he married Millicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. 


</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Tate Papers, D2859/3A/4/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2733</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0170">William Ford Hutchinson</persName>
              <date>1916-12-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0101">Whitcombe public writing room, Wellington, New Zealand</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alec C Tate</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1657">Glenlua, Ballycastle, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2733_img_2153_1"  type="Letter"  url="d2a09ecc51449a48ac6d75169a229469.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2733_img_2153_2"  type="Letter"  url="1a4fd8594d400bc51d8ada9bbb108baf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2733_img_2153_3"  type="Letter"  url="f7089543018324e5049e30ca2bb6d9b3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2733_img_2153_1"/>
             WHITCOMBE'S PUBLIC WRITING ROOM<lb/>Wellington 191<lb/>2  in London.  My present job is a very light one.<lb/>We have taken rooms near the<lb/>station here, &amp; I go every Sunday<lb/>to <seg type="unclear"></seg>  &amp; <seg type="unclear"></seg>  , 20 miles out<lb/>by the 9.30 train, for morning &amp; evening<lb/>Service alternately in each place.<lb/>At the former place I am a guest<lb/>at a big farmers place,   nice<lb/>people called Wall, &amp; at the latter<lb/>stop with the Clerk of the Asylum.<lb/>His name is Holder, he is the<lb/>champion sweet pea grower    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2733_img_2153_2"/>
              WHITECOMBE'S PUBLIC WRITING ROOM<lb/>Wellington 191 <lb/>3  in N.Z. May is coming out some<lb/>Sunday to stay the might &amp; have<lb/>a look at his lovely garden.  This job will last till 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Feb when<lb/>the new Vicar is expected to arrive.  I quite enjoy going about from place<lb/>to place. My last place was<lb/>just across the harbour, a lovely<lb/>spot 45 minutes by steamer from<lb/>Wellington. We get to know a lot<lb/>of nice peoeple this way. We spent<lb/>the time between this job &amp; my<lb/>present one with the head of<lb/>  at Masterton, people  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2733_img_2153_3"/>
             WHITCOMBE'S PUBLIC WRITING ROOM<lb/>Wellington 191<lb/>4  called Sommerill, very nice indeed.<lb/>Mrs S &amp;her sister are Belfast people<lb/>and used to play a lot of bridge.  We are having fairly hot weather<lb/>now, the wind has at last<lb/>gone down.  May joins me in sending love<lb/>to you all &amp; best wishes for the<lb/>safety of your boys who are<lb/>doing their bit.  Your affect cousin<lb/>W. Ford Hutchinson 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>