<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0397">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Muriel MacDonagh to Kitty O'Doherty, 1 September 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Muriel MacDonagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Muriel MacDonagh to Katherine (Kitty) O&#39;Doherty thanking her for the money she had received from Jennie Wyse Power (1858-1941). O&#39;Doherty and Wyse Power were both active in the aid associations set up in the aftermath of the Rising to assist dependant&#39;s of those killed or injured during the Rising, as well as those who lost employment.Muriel Gifford (1884-1917) married Thomas MacDonagh in 1912 and they had one son. She tragically drowned on a family holiday in 1917. Thomas MacDonagh (1878-1916) was a poet and teacher. A leading member of the Dublin Brigade of the Irish Volunteers, he was one of the principle organisers of the Easter Rising and one of the seven signatories of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic. He was executed on 3 May 1916 in Kilmainham Gaol.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Thomas MacDonagh Family Papers, Collection List No 131, Ms. 24,376 /1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/397</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0031">Muriel MacDonagh</persName>
              <date>1916-09-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1283">34 Bloomfield Avenue, S.C.R., Dublin.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Katherine O&#39;Doherty</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0397_img_166_1"  type="Letter"  url="a84515b7c2338572d18e1a056686a78a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0397_img_166_1"/>
               2/80     I.IX.16    34 Bloomfield Av  S.C.R.   Dear Mrs O'Doherty,   I find that I have not<lb/> yet acknowledged receipt of<lb/> the cheque for £50 which<lb/> was handed to me by<lb/> Mrs Wyse Power on Wednesday<lb/> Please thank the Committee<lb/> on my behalf for it &amp; also<lb/> for the kind letter accompany-<lb/> ing it. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely<lb/>  <hi rend="underline">Muriel MacDonagh</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>