<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5369">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nora Ring to Susan Daly, 9 November 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nora Ring </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/23/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5369</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0549">Nora Ring </persName>
              <date>1923-11-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1213">The British Bank of South America, Bahea, Brazil </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None"> Susan Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1405">Knockane, Firies, Co Kerry, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_1"  type="Letter"  url="d5b0a6e3971084fa1526b2ff23194db9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_2"  type="Letter"  url="67215b29390cc1f2d953c9e47ef17433.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_3"  type="Letter"  url="401fa4b0d2965c49e658ab7807fff95f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_4"  type="Letter"  url="c598a9a3e443130272717b8b40e57ec3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_5"  type="Letter"  url="87c3e160713b1560ed4e72e30a04e625.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_6"  type="Letter"  url="8fdef9addbd56a61970d6a1381a1c312.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5369_img_4654_7"  type="Envelope"  url="3733ee4962b2a7556cb6a9c30798e4d3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_1"/>
             P41/23/13   The British Bank of South America<lb/>Caira —41<lb/>Bahia<lb/>Brazil    9th November 1923    My dear Susan   At last — I have found a few<lb/>moments in which to scribble you a note to<lb/>let you have my new address. All our<lb/>letters are addressed to the Bank as it is<lb/>the safest mode of delivery — I have been<lb/>7 weeks here and I have been kept busy<lb/>since I arrived, although I must say I have<lb/>done nothing really worth while — Labour is<lb/>so cheap here with all the niggers that none<lb/>of the white people work — I love the place<lb/>already — the bay is very pretty — such<lb/>a lovely blue sea all studded with<lb/>little islands. We live quite near a<lb/>beautiful sandy beach. Our house is<lb/>situated just as Jim’s house in Valencia<lb/>and we can bathe all the year round,<lb/>the sea is quite warm sometimes. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_2"/>
            <hi rend="”underline”">2</hi> Well Susan Jen will tell you all about our wedding &amp;<lb/>remind her to give you a photo although they are<lb/>awful <seg type="unclear">peaks</seg> . Such a glorious honey moon trip as I<lb/>have had — being with the few days we spent in the<lb/>peace and solitude of Glendalough! It was lovely<lb/>there — we had a full moon also — so it was a<lb/>real honey-<hi rend="”underline”">moon</hi>— we motored through the Vale of Avoca<lb/>I saw the Meeting of the Waters. I admired the scenery<lb/>but it cannot be compared with the majestic-rugged<lb/>beauty of the Kingdom. Even Paddy admitted that although<lb/>we were in the Wicklow of the Byrne Clan —   In London we couldn’t call our souls our own<lb/>between my being introduced to the Byrne family there<lb/>&amp; mailing my brother &amp; numerous relatives we were<lb/>tired of trotting about &amp; glad to get on the “Andes” at Southampton on  31st August  The is a lovely ship and the largest Royal Mail boat going from Europe to S. America. We had a lovely cabin on the   side &amp; in the dining salon we have a nice small table near the port—hole. We had a splendid land &amp; dancing   after dinner every evening. So we enjoyed ourselves to perfection. We called at Cherbourg — Conurra — Vigo — Lisbon —Maderia and Penamluco. Conurra &amp; Vigo we reached on 2nd September — arriving at Conurra at day break &amp; reaching Corunna Vigo at 5 o’clock the same evening. We went ashore at Lisbon &amp; motored all round the city. We had lunch in a quaint old café where Paddy got the nigger band to play Brazilian   for me. At Madeira we enjoyed ourselves thoroughly - I won’t attempt to describe Madeira —it is so beautiful — &amp; it is one of the few places whose picturesqueness has not been exaggerated — we went up to the hotel in the Summit in a funny old mountain railway. The native kids threw bouquets of flowers at us on our way up       
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_3"/>
            <hi rend="”underline”">3</hi> We came down in a toboggan drawn by two<lb/>natives — they simply went like the wind.  We saw some exquisite lace embroidery<lb/>there — I sent a card to Tomas from Madeira.<lb/>Hope he got it — I should like to write<lb/>him a long letter about — my voyage but<lb/>I hope he will be released before this letter<lb/>reaches you — so he can read it.  After we left Madeira we were on the<lb/>open sea for 7 days — we did not call<lb/>at any port and the only land we could<lb/>get a glimpse of was the Penal Settlement<lb/>of Fernando — Noninna —! how cheerful! -  I was ever so sorry when the trip came<lb/>to an end. I could live all my life in a<lb/>ship especially as neither of us was sea sick.<lb/>Some friends came on board at Penamluco<lb/>&amp; 24 hours later Nora Bean <seg type="unclear">na </seg> <seg type="unclear"> as</seg><lb/>landed in Bahia – all the natives were in the docks to greet us — &amp; they salaamed &amp; uttered what seemed to me   unintelligible sounds but which was in really bad Portuguese.   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_4"/>
            <hi rend="”underline”">4</hi> They shouted O’Mayor &amp; patted Paddy on<lb/>the back &amp; salaamed once more to the<lb/>Senhora do Mayor” — (wife). I was amused.<lb/>We motored to this house &amp; I was delighted<lb/>with it — &amp; I must say Bahia is far beyond<lb/>my expectations — it is decidedly pretty<lb/>&amp; I like the climate — the heat has not<lb/>been too oppressive — but still one cannot<lb/>wear even the flimsiest coat. It is lovely<lb/>to see the blue sky and the sunshine<lb/>always — people get up around 5-30am<lb/>(I am the exception to the rule naturally<lb/>but they go to bed early also — The British<lb/>&amp; American colonies are getting larger every<lb/>day and there are quite a number in<lb/>the French &amp; German colonies — T<lb/>he White ladies spend their time visiting<lb/>&amp; going to tea &amp; sights. I am the youngest lady married or single in the colony and I have great fun. Imagine me soberly sitting at a tea sight with a group of Stolid English matrons when my 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_5"/>
            <hi rend="”underline”">5</hi> Celtic blood wants me to get up &amp; shake every one of them<lb/>to wake them up. They are the usual type of<lb/>English women one meets abroad trying to do the<lb/>great thing”. As you may well imagine — neither my<lb/>age or my nationality make me have anything in<lb/>common with the people who are old at 25<lb/>They get very grooved when they remain out here a<lb/>long time. The men are also at these tea <seg type="unclear"></seg>  but<lb/>I amuse Paddy immensely every evening by telling him<lb/>all about them — He is always afraid they might   <lb/>have the misfortune to mention “Ireland” or “troubles” —<lb/>and that I shall be had up for “wilful wholesale<lb/>murder” of the ladies of the colony. I tell him they have<lb/>not intelligence enough to know where Ireland is<lb/>much less discuss the political question — I like<lb/>the Americans and the French ladies — the American Consul’s wife is a most intelligent woman. She has been all over the world — we are great friends as she has a claim on old Ireland also. We were at a lovely Ball at the French Club given in honour of the Officers of a French Battleship that called at the port — the decorations were lovely and we were all given moire silk  with the name of the ship in gilt letters — I danced all the time and enjoyed myself thoroughly — we are to have a dance at our own club on the 10th. The nigger servants are great. “The Black Watch” I call them. They go about so silently — the police &amp; soldiers here are a scream — Brazilians &amp; niggers all mixed up — They seem to have ammunition galore because they are always firing about at nothing. What a pity some of our friends could not lay their hands on it! How are all the boys — give my love to them all especially  . Do not forget to send me    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_6"/>
            <hi rend="”underline”">5</hi> Poor Charlie’s Mortuary Card. I often think<lb/>of him. (RIP) Have you got a school yet?<lb/>If you happen to see the Whelans<lb/>remember me to them.  I hope you will write me a long letter<lb/>&amp; tell me all about yourself &amp; our friends<lb/>Give me love to your Mother &amp; keep a big<lb/>share yourself.  It seems such a short time ago since<lb/>you were sitting near my bed —when you<lb/>came to say goodbye—! That was the day<lb/>Paddy returned from London —he is the<lb/>same old Paddy I knew in Valencia<lb/>and we are as happy can be. God<lb/>has been very good to me in giving me<lb/>such a husband. Jen called us “The<lb/>Babes in the Wood” &amp; the people hear say the same thing   with love &amp; good wishes from Nora  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5369_img_4654_7"/>
              Miss. Susan Daly<lb/>Knockane<lb/>Firies<lb/>Co. Kerry<lb/>Ireland  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>