<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1168">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 22 May 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Francis M. Shaw&#39;s talk with Father Hartigon and his zero masses for the May.Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/27, IJA/CHPI/54/27</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1168</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-05-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1168_img_3845_1"  type="Letter"  url="bd9a579fab0e1bcb1a2d8bfcdd06671c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1168_img_3845_1"/>
                32 B.G H. Amara    22 May 1918   Dear Father Provincial,   Just a hasty line <lb/>to report progress. I am well on <lb/>the convalescent road, though still <lb/>officially a lying case. I was able to <lb/>hear Mass at Kut on Pentecost Sunday, <lb/>in pyjamas &amp; dressing gown. I have had <lb/>a chat with an orderly here who knew <lb/><hi rend="underline">Fr</hi> Hartigan, &amp; had a tremendous admiration <lb/>for him, because of the way in which he <lb/>looked out for the men, and stayed with <lb/>them when he found them. This lad is not <lb/>a Catholic either. <hi rend="underline">Fr</hi> Hartigan's grave is <lb/>about a mile &amp; a half from here. I hope to <lb/>be able to give you some particulars in my next.  The address at top is only <lb/>temporary. I am on the way to Basra. <lb/>Would you please tell <hi rend="underline">Fr</hi> Farley that my <lb/>masses for May are <hi rend="underline">0.</hi> I am writing <lb/>a separate note to him. But accidents etc. <lb/>I get the notices alone. <hi rend="underline">Frs</hi><seg type="unclear">Gannon</seg> &amp; Hubert <lb/> today. R.I.P.  <seg type="closer"> F.M. Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>