<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1119">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, [1916]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from May Fay (1897-1976) to James Finn (1877-1922) regarding preparations for their upcoming wedding. In reply to a previous letter fro James May writes that she had not seen the correspondence between Sir General John Maxwell (1859-1929) and the Bishop of Limerick, Edward O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), but will try and get a copy.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. After his death she held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1119</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1589">Ballinea, Mullingar, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1119_img_350_1"  type="NULL"  url="ba94cfdc1e0656942376a3e47050ca85.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1119_img_350_2"  type="NULL"  url="aa6503efce7cfc4f5a6d4e3e7a01c4f0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1119_img_350_1"/>
              I had to get my paper <lb/>signed I was near drawing <lb/>back altogether sooner than <lb/>brave the Mullingar priest <lb/>so now you see what <lb/>I sacrificed for you. <lb/>I was ashamed of my life. <lb/>I am sure he  (the priest)  was pitying <lb/>the man  Beginning of the letter    Togherstown  Ballinea  Mullingar   My dearest James   I got your letter this morning I am sure you were <lb/>expecting a letter from me, but the post leaving 芒聙聹<hi rend="underline">advance</hi>' time <lb/>&amp; the men working by old time <seg type="del">makes</seg> leaves the post gone <lb/>before they even quit, as you will see I had the letter written on Monday <lb/>&amp; posted it in Mullingar yesterday. We had a nice day in <lb/>town芒聙聰 better than today anyway I had my dress fitted it looks <lb/>very well I think &amp; my hat also but I can tell you I was very sick <lb/>of the job of turning &amp; twisting &amp; standing all the time while being <lb/>fitted. We settled about a motor, <hi rend="underline">booked</hi> one for me &amp; one <lb/>for you he said any car he芒聙聶d send would be all <hi rend="underline">right</hi><lb/>he芒聙聶ll charge by the mile so he could not say what <lb/>either would come to. We could not let him know the hour <lb/>at the time but you can tell him Tuesday night when you <lb/>arrive in Mullingar I suppose <hi rend="underline">8.30 old time</hi> would be about <lb/>the hour, would that suit you let me know &amp; it will be alright <lb/>what time will we have to  leave  this at do you know? I think we <lb/>won芒聙聶t fast that morning I mean for Holy Communion the drive <lb/>would be very long for you we can go the Sunday before <lb/>instead like the woman going to Mass on Sat instead of Sunday  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1119_img_350_2"/>
              About the ring I asked you to send me the card <lb/>although a hole I would make myself in a card <lb/>would do full as well I suppose but about the ring <lb/>itself. I know I never could wear any but the two <lb/>rings on that one finger so whether it be large or <lb/>small I don芒聙聶t know which would be the best. I think I will <lb/>leave it to your taste I liked your taste in the watch &amp; <lb/>as well you have the advantage of having seen both the <lb/>ring &amp; the finger I dare say unless you have great eye <lb/>&amp; memory altogether you forget my ring finger is fat and short <lb/>I got my first present yesterday from Mrs Keilan <lb/><hi rend="underline">A Silver Tea pot</hi> I hope you will get something nice <lb/>for yourself.  We did not see the Cork Examiner and Jennie always sends <lb/>it to us when there is anything on it she must not have <lb/>got it but I will ask her. I heard that Bulfin was in <lb/>the G.P.O &amp; in uniform so he cannot get off so easy <lb/>I have no more news so good bye. I hope we won芒聙聶t have <lb/>weather like this for our wedding whatever about the honeymoon. <seg type="closer"> Best love from your own loving  May </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>