<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1156">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 25 June 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s new address and the people who he met there.Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/14, IJA/CHPI/54/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1156</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1917-06-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1459">Bombay, India</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1156_img_3833_1"  type="Letter"  url="f140a904205427d7a8b72b648f91d7ce.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1156_img_3833_1"/>
                25 June 1917   Dear Reverend F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Provincial, P. C.   If you write to me at 'Archbishops House, <lb/>Wodehouse R<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Bombay', I shall most probably get any letters <lb/>you send â i.e. if they reach India at all. Don't send any <lb/>valuables' I am in very good health. I enclose cheque for <lb/>50 pounds â not that I know exactly how much I have <lb/>to my credit but I think I have a good bit more than <lb/>that. Not being an expert business man I hardly ever know <lb/>how I stand; and being at least one month from <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Gregor's doesn't help matters. At present I can't say who <lb/>ids drawing my pay for me â or whether anyone is. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Gregor's said <lb/>they would continue to draw it until told otherwise. You'd never <lb/>guess whom I met here â F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> O' Mahony! He is <lb/>still on the 'Egypt'. He has been here some days and will <lb/>remain a bit yet. He will be on the same boat as myself. I <lb/>am in a perpetual state of melting although it is the <lb/>cool season. I hear it is about 120<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> up Basra way. It <lb/>is heaven to be in one <seg type="unclear">four</seg> houses again. I go up on my first <lb/>trip in a day or two. A great number of the crews of vessels <lb/>out this way are Catholics â <seg type="unclear">Goanese</seg> â and good ones. I have <lb/>also met F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><seg type="unclear">Guntensperger</seg> â you remember the St. Gall man.  F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lander is 5 hours away at Posna. I saw F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Garrold S.J. at <lb/>Durban. He is now in E. Africa. I hear a report that some of the <lb/>English mails have not reached Bombay of late. I am anxious <lb/>for any news of home. I learnt from F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> O' Mahony of the deaths of <lb/>F<seg type="foreign">r</seg> Tom Maher and B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1Mahon R. I.P I said their Masses. Hoping all <lb/>are well. <seg type="closer"> I remain <lb/>Your Reverences servant in Christ,  Francis M. Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>