<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4020">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Miss M. Cox, Secretary of the Irish Volunteer Prisoners Aid Society, 2 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Miss Cox detailing the provision of the requirements of the prisoners of Frongoch such as tobacco, clothing and fruit.  The author suggests that individual Committees take responsibility for specific supplies.  The letter details the cost of providing provisions to Wandsworth, Woking, Lewes, Stafford, Wakefield and Knutsford prisons.

The letter also refers to an enclosed copy of a letter sent to Mr. Henry Dixon at Frongoch.  

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS8434:16-12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4020</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-09-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">M Cox </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1713">252 Lower Broughton Road, Manchester, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4020_img_3404_1"  type="Letter"  url="00a27ee2545a0c91190d6ffced77d2b3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4020_img_3404_1"/>
              2nd sept 1916   <seg type="del">31. VIII. ’16</seg>   Miss. M. Cox,<lb/>(Hon. Secretary Irish Volunteer Prisoners Aid Society),<lb/>252, Lower Broughton Road, Manchester.    Dear Miss. Cox,   Further to previous correspondence for the in-<lb/>formation of your Committee I enclose copy of a letter<lb/>which we have just sent to Mr. Henry Dixon at Frongoch.<lb/>I think we are now on the road to being able to deal with<lb/>the requirements of the Camp in a systematic manner.<lb/>Our Committee is rather of the opinion that the best<lb/>way to attain this end is for each outside Committee<lb/>to make itself responsible for some one particular re-<lb/>quirement. You will see that the Cork Committee have<lb/>made themselves responsible for the tobacco supply. We<lb/>are willing, as you will see by the enclosed letter, to<lb/>make ourselves responsible for part, or if necessary for<lb/>the whole of the remainder. There are the questions of<lb/>clothing, periodicals and books, some few luxuries such<lb/>as fruit etc., about which we hope to hear more both<lb/>from Mr. Dixon and the Censor shortly, when I will<lb/>communicate with you again. In the meantime would<lb/>you please place the matter before your Committee and<lb/>let me know if they agree with our suggestions, or if<lb/>they would propose any modification.  In one of your letters you informed me of what your<lb/>Committee had sent to the Camp and I am afraid that in<lb/>replying the rush of the work at the time caused me to<lb/>overlook the courtesy of your reciprocating, for which<lb/>I hope you will excuse me. Up to the present we have<lb/>expended £ 146  on the prisoners, of this amount £ 53, <lb/>has gone to Frongoch (£40 in cash, the balance in supplies<lb/>the remainder having been expended on Wandsworth, Woking,<lb/>Lewes, Stafford &amp; Wakefield, and Knutsford.   Yours truly,  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>