<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5659">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Dublin to the Chief Crown Solicitor, Dublin Castle, 24 February 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A series of letters between the Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Dublin and the Chief Crown Solicitor, Dublin Castle concerning an injury sustained by Patrick Sheehan while he was working as a casual labourer employed by the Forage Department to handle hay, oats and straw. The series of letters concerns possible compensation as this was an injury sustained at work. 

This letter indicates that the government does not insure against injuries.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_3785_8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5659</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-02-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0388">Royal Hospital, Kilmainham, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5659_img_753_1"  type="Letter"  url="37a63ccfc847fef4ae466cd41db68834.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5659_img_753_1"/>
            <lb/>Ref. No.155/5746. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Subject. Injury to Patrick Sheehan.</hi>  A.A.O., Ireland, <lb/>Royal Hospital, <lb/>Dublin.   <hi rend="underline">Tel.No. 4809.</hi>  24th February, 1916.   The Chief Crown Solicitor, <lb/>Dublin.   Sir,   Herewith I enclose corres- <lb/>pondence concerning an accident to a work- <lb/>man ( named Patrick Sheehan) employed by <lb/> the District Purchasing Officer, Cork. He <lb/> dislocated his ankle whilst engaged in <lb/> carrying a bundle of empty sacks.   I understand that the Government <lb/> do not insure against accidents, and would <lb/> be obliged if you would kindly inform me what <lb/> the position is with regard to this man, who <lb/> considers that he is entitled to compensation.   Yours faithfully,   G M   Colonel, <lb/>Administrative Area Officer.  <lb/>M.R.  Administrative Area affair. <lb/>What was the time of this man's employment <lb/>if the contract was in waiting please amend it <lb/>M. Kelly <lb/>25.2.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>