<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0867">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Bernard Connolly to the Under Secretary of Ireland, 14 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Bernard Connolly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Drogheda town clerk, John Connolly (1878-1919) to the under secretary of Ireland regarding Article 31 of the Schedule to the Local Government (Application of Enactments) Order, 1898. Connolly inquiries whether it is possible to have the number of members on the council altered. At the time this letter was written Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was serving as the under secretary of Ireland. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as a replacement for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5618/12108/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/867</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0376">John Bernard Connolly</persName>
              <date>1916-07-14T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1287">Drogheda, Co. Louth, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0867_img_2429_1"  type="Letter"  url="46838de129a341ee4dc343b516bbfbbd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0867_img_2429_1"/>
                TOWN CLERK'S OFFICE, DROGHEDA.    The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle,  DUBLIN.    Sir    Referring to Article 31 of the Schedule to the Local <lb/>Government (Application of Enactments) Order, 1898, which <lb/> provides for the alteration of the Wards of a Borough. I <lb/>beg to enquire whether it is competent for the Council of a <lb/>Borough by petition to the Lord Lieutenant to seek to have <lb/>the number of members of the Council altered? Section 26 <lb/>of the Order referred to clearly vests in a County Council <lb/>such powers in relation to an Urban District, but it is not <lb/>so clear that the Lord Lieutenant has the same powers in <lb/>relation to a Borough. <seg type="closer">  I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant  J.B. Connolly </seg> Assistant Under Secretary  Submitted: I think <lb/>the Town Clerk may be informed <lb/> that his Council should be guided <lb/> in the matter to wh. he refers by <lb/>their legal advisors. The <sic>Solr</sic> General <lb/>should approve.  W.B.C <lb/>18/2/16  I agree with Mr <lb/>Henry's suggestion: it would be a <lb/>mistake for us to advise every local body that <lb/>asks for advice. JOC 19.9.16  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>