<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4558">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman, 12 November 1915.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Martin Mahoney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman. Mahoney, a parish priest in Minnesota, edited the Catholic weekly &#39;Manifestos&#39;. The letter refers to political and religious matters including references to Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Collection, Ms. 47,604/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4558</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0410">Fr. Martin Mahoney</persName>
              <date>1916-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1659">Mendota, Minnesota, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4558_img_39_1"  type="Letter"  url="53157820a62b5da431f0c122f3e03aee.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4558_img_39_1"/>
             J  Mendota Minn  12.11.15  Dear Mr S.   You've passed the Censor.<lb/>O.K! Madness surely tis: mostly from badness too, more of the<lb/>ugly ways of Cain. My, but what a conversion from '<hi rend="underline">laissez-faire'</hi>!<lb/>What a quite German rise to government in earnest in one year! Had<lb/>that come a few years ago we should be in the millennium mnow. And the<lb/>mission preachers might take a long holiday. And still an odd crank<lb/>of them might find right now a fine field. In Bess's days it looked in<lb/>Spain as if about all there was for God to be angry with &amp; punish was in England.<lb/>And so all the good people of Spain &amp; outside it were praying for the Armada.<lb/>And the Lord deigned to explain the upshot to some highly favored &amp; holy<lb/>one. England did not deserve being set <seg type="unclear">alight</seg>, &amp; Spain deserved being<lb/>punished…. And as does Ireland. And I'm grieved not to see some<lb/>one, several, saying so, &amp; convincing the people that they are called on<lb/>not only for <seg type="del">econom</seg> economic retrenchment but for humble self<lb/>afflicting penance, In which mood they'd look with high favor on every<lb/><sic>deamening</sic> of those pagan luxuries they <hi rend="underline">lately</hi> so stoutly fought for.<lb/>Maybe even if the priests have to go it is no worse than they &amp; their<lb/>people deserve for the universal neglect of the Love from Heaven given<lb/>some years by poor  . Maybe this last year will have given<lb/>them all a new idea of the efficacy there can be in <sic>thracts</sic>, posters, car<lb/>toons, in those bizarre, unlofty forms of literature which, the nation Eiré<lb/>have so changed the views &amp; ways of whole peoples &amp; continents.   Notice how the Poles, cousin of ours in <seg type="unclear">felinisity</seg> take to abstinence<lb/>&amp; fasting. Their action may well serve you <seg type="del">for</seg> to  start the idea in Eire.<lb/>There is now &amp; especially thereabouts so much sham &amp; lying &amp; <seg type="unclear">fourberie</seg><lb/>that all the Heavens Powers would be mightily struck by something so<lb/>novel &amp; different as humble self-reproach &amp; penitential fasting: try<lb/>it, do ye!  The ad. going <seg type="unclear">Mitchell</seg>books in 3 issues  each  of the IW, the St Paul Cath Bulletin<lb/>&amp;&amp; the Pillsbury Elsevier, brought me $1.90, .30<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>, .00<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>, so desperately are we<lb/>under some sort of Curse of Columbkille. What a lift to the Irish melody &amp; to <seg type="unclear">read</seg><lb/>those Miss Petersons' articles: <seg type="unclear">but</seg> — not a book that she has mentioned — &amp;  <lb/>recommended is, or ever has been <seg type="unclear">accredited</seg> in the Leader. Start on it an appeal<lb/>&amp; subscription but for a gratis supplement reproducing on a 4 or 8 page sheet the<lb/>best of <seg type="del">what</seg> the songs &amp; <seg type="unclear">airs</seg> she mentions, plus what she so unaccountably<lb/>omits, the Heather Glen.   Be not beat by evil, but beat evil by God!    M.M  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>