<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4374">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J. Beatty to Edward Carson, 16 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J. Beatty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from J. Beatty to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/19/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4374</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0277">J. Beatty</persName>
              <date>1916-10-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0535">19 Mary Street, Clonmel, Co. Tipperary, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4374_img_3729_1"  type="Letter"  url="50550caa83acd5667073a9afea3792e3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4374_img_3729_2"  type="Letter"  url="62c73320b9e51f2bc5ebda9de53fa1da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4374_img_3729_3"  type="Letter"  url="f98b2b955a4e8ccbef698ff54c99ab8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4374_img_3729_1"/>
             P.S. <lb/>My name <lb/>not to be <lb/>disclosed. <lb/><hi rend="underline">J. Beatty</hi>.   19 Mary Street <lb/>Clonmel <lb/>Ireland   <hi rend="underline">16:10:16</hi>  <lb/><hi rend="underline">To</hi> <lb/>The Rt. Hon. Sir E. Carson K.C.M.P.  Sir.   I beg to send you a few particulars <lb/>of events in Ireland which may <lb/>be of use to you in the debate on <lb/>Redmond's motion, which i notice is <lb/>to take place on Wednesday next. <lb/>Please do not disclose my name <lb/>as I could not live here if you did:-   On Sunday 24 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Septr. there was <lb/>a hurling and football tournament <lb/>in Limerick City. Excursion trains <lb/>had been arranged to bring <lb/>contingents
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4374_img_3729_2"/>
            from Dublin and other parts, but <lb/>these were all cancelled ont the 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> <lb/>Sept. Still large crowds came <lb/>from Limerick County Clare &amp; <lb/>Tipperary. When the tournament <lb/>concluded over a thousand young <lb/>men "fell in" to order in the football <lb/>field and marched through the <lb/>City (Limerick) in military order. <lb/>This large crown halted in front of <lb/>William St. Police Barracks and <lb/>cheered and shouted for Sinn <lb/>Feinn and the Dublin Rebels. <lb/>When they satisfied themselves <lb/>they marched away. The authorities <lb/>did not interfere; and I have <lb/>not heard that any one was <lb/>made amenable for this disloyal <lb/>and rebellious demonstration.   On the following Sunday (1:10:16) <lb/>the Counties of Limerick and <lb/>Tipperary played their finals <lb/>in Dungarvan. The excursions <lb/>to Dungarvan were not restricted. <lb/>There were ten thousand people <lb/>present according to the Clonmel <lb/>Nationalist &amp; Chronicle. Crowds <lb/>of these young men sang rebel <lb/>songs, and cheered for Sinn <lb/>Fein and the Dublin Rebels <lb/>in the public streets.   In the <seg type="del">house</seg> Public house of <lb/>a man named Coughlan <lb/>which was open during the <lb/>evening, seditious speeches <lb/>were delivered, and the <lb/>health of the Kaiser toasted <lb/>by a man standing on a <lb/>porter barrel and responded <lb/>to with the greatest enthusiasm
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4374_img_3729_3"/>
            by crowds inside and outside the house, <lb/>and nothing  has been  done since by the <lb/>authorities. This matter has <seg type="unclear">barely</seg> <lb/>been reported: the Inspector in <lb/>Waterford has a peculiar way of doing <lb/>things. He wants to please the <lb/>R.C. bishop &amp; clergy. I hear he <lb/>acted in the capacity of a steward <lb/>and not as a police officer at Mr. <lb/>Redmond's meeting. He stood on <lb/>the platform in Uniform and <lb/>surveyed those in the hall before <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Redmond appeared.   You may make any use you like <lb/>of this information which is true <lb/>but you will please keep my name <lb/>a secret. I could not live here if it <lb/>were known I wrote this. I am an <lb/>Ex. Sergt. of RIC &amp; now an Inspector <lb/>in the N.S.P.C.C. I hear and see a lot. <lb/>If this kind of matter is any use I <lb/>would gladly supply more.    I am Sir <lb/>Yours obediently   T. Beatty 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>