<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3737">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Isabella Tuckey to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 16 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Isabella Dorthea Tuckey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from schoolteacher Isabella Dorthea Tuckey to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding the health of Owen, Hanna&#39;s son, who has been absent from school on account of illness. The letter then moves on to discuss the position of an applicant, Miss Summers. Isabella explains that the selection process is decided by committees and that there are a large number of applicants, but that she hopes that the woman Hanna has written about is one of the four selected.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,604/13-28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3737</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1080">Isabella Dorthea Tuckey</persName>
              <date>1915-11-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0594">11 Frankfort Avenue, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3737_img_3125_1"  type="Letter"  url="1c6b0069a3537377add04c7e272620c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3737_img_3125_2"  type="Letter"  url="6d05c02fecd8685c6f8768072b690f8f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3737_img_3125_3"  type="Letter"  url="b05ef645922290c15c1d6e62987fc3b8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3737_img_3125_1"/>
             16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Nov. <lb/>1915   RATHGAR KINDERGARTEN. <lb/>&amp; <lb/>TRAINING COLLEGE. <lb/>11 FRANKFORT AVENUE.   Dear Mrs. Sheehy Sheffington   I am glad Owen is <lb/>better and that it is <lb/>nothing infectious. I <lb/>hope we shall soon <lb/>see him back at school.   About Miss Somers - I <lb/>should be glad to <lb/>support her, but the <lb/>thing is for the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3737_img_3125_2"/>
            most part in the <lb/>hands of a sub committee, <lb/>who are to select four <lb/>names to bring up <lb/>before the committee on <lb/>Monday, so the voting <lb/>will be restricted to <lb/>those four.   There are over a hundred <lb/>applicants, so the work <lb/>of the sub committee is <lb/>pretty heavy.   I hope Miss Somers may <lb/>be among the four
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3737_img_3125_3"/>
            selected.   Yours very sincerely    Isabella D. Tuckey 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>