<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2901">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir  Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 28 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. In July 1916, he was temporarily transferred to a Corps HQ on a separate section of the front. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

In this letter, Spender discusses his qualms about leaving his old Division and the welfare of his brother Rex. He gives an account of his current position, mentioning its distance from the fighting, the lack of opportunity to ride one&#39;s horse, and the early start of the working day. He commends Lillian for her postponement of her time off from working with the wounded, noting that July (because of the Battle of the Somme) has been a particularly bad month for casualties. Spender suggests that it will be a very long time before he himself can go on leave, as he is currently &#39;on trial&#39; in his new position. He discusses mutual acquaintances and financial matters. Finally, he declares that he is not a pessimist, but nevertheless believes that the war will continue for a very long time - and will not be won by military means alone.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/363</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2901</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2901_img_2310_1"  type="NULL"  url="6430d628d3239df771c0f5c2992195e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2901_img_2310_2"  type="NULL"  url="c9de9671cf1798ab063dfb9266d267e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2901_img_2310_3"  type="NULL"  url="1f4751272791e40f0b31f4b58a8ee658.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2901_img_2310_4"  type="NULL"  url="a186d9899be9eab63042c8445b81f3f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2901_img_2310_5"  type="NULL"  url="421b0877971e2df89a0520232dc75639.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2901_img_2310_6"  type="NULL"  url="aa5f39b862011ddec5931c324d79d6f8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2901_img_2310_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/363  28 July    My Pr   I wish I could get your letters of<lb/>Monday which ought to be turning up<lb/>now in order to know whether you ap-<lb/>prove or not. I still have qualms &amp;<lb/>a distinct feeling of <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>lack<lb/>of <sic>frankners</sic> to old Rex  I sent him on a good budget today<lb/>&amp; hope I shall hear how he is getting<lb/>on. I hope he appreciates your hampers,<lb/>which are I hope getting to him now. If<lb/>mater is at Crouboro still she might like<lb/>you to order from the stores unless 24 HPG<lb/>cook can send a cake but Jessie will<lb/>probably arrange this for her if she is<lb/>not away  There is a big battle going on but<lb/>where I am one is quite out of things till 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2901_img_2310_2"/>
             one motors up. To those who can return<lb/>to a bed &amp; a square meal well cooked<lb/>War is very different to what it is to<lb/>those that are in it all the time.  I meant to ride today but M Gill<lb/>&amp; Douglas had both disappeared. I must<lb/>have a system in future so that I can<lb/>get hold of my horses when I want to.<lb/>It is not very good for them <seg type="unclear">loafing</seg> here  The Corps Commander gets up at<lb/>6 <seg type="del">15</seg> regularly &amp; has breakfast at 6.30<lb/>being in the office well before 7. I don't<lb/>get up as early as he but manage to<lb/>get to the office at the same time.  Your first letter has come &amp; as usual<lb/>I find our feelings are <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> much  alike<lb/>almost exactly so, thanks be. I should<lb/>jolly well think your committees would 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2901_img_2310_3"/>
             2   D1633|1|1363   not let you go. I do hope you don't<lb/>regret your country villa now, but in<lb/>view of your work I really think it<lb/>wise. Of course when I gave you my<lb/>advice I knew what was likely to take<lb/>place &amp; how busy you would be in July.<lb/>Perhaps by the middle of August you<lb/>may be able to slack off work &amp; I<lb/>suppose Maggie &amp; Co will want a holiday<lb/>too. In that case cannot you get a<lb/>fortnight at the seaside — probably September<lb/>will be better or at Rex's taking one of<lb/>your family with you.<lb/>You must not want on my coming<lb/>home for a very long time now. In the<lb/>first place if I remain in the Corps I do<lb/>not see leave for a long time after it opens,<lb/>&amp; if as is more probable I go to another 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2901_img_2310_4"/>
             division on trial it would not do for<lb/>one to ask for leave for <seg type="del">another</seg> at least 2<lb/>months after arrival. You will understand.<lb/>I have got one of your Army letters, &amp; expect<lb/>the other today. There is a bit of delay<lb/>tho' we are only 6 miles E of their HQ.<lb/>The first of your 15 Corps letters has arrived.<lb/>Yes HQ 15 Corps is right address.<lb/>I hope you will like Mr. Heney as<lb/>all I hear of him is fine. I think he<lb/>must be the Brigadier — who came from<lb/>the Innis Fus— quoted in the papers as<lb/>being so brave &amp; setting such a magni-<lb/>ficent example to the men. I wish<lb/>his successor or rather the officer who<lb/>took TH's place was anything like him<lb/>That Bde &amp; Richardson are rather unhappy.<lb/>May you have a really delightful week and<lb/>Please give me Sir Ralph's address so that 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2901_img_2310_5"/>
              3 D/1633/1/1/364   I rather wonder whether G N will<lb/>absolutely ignore my name in his report or<lb/>whether he will give me a mere mention<lb/>I fancy the former in which case it is<lb/>just as well I have left or comments<lb/>might have been made not all of them<lb/>to my disadvantage though. I wrote<lb/>him a letter of farewell but could<lb/>not <seg type="unclear">want</seg> it very warmly &amp; did<lb/>not attempt to do so.  I don't think I agree about the<lb/>weekly parcel to Rex. At any rate at<lb/>first I should like to spoil him<lb/>&amp; he will write if he does not want<lb/>as much.  I did the OPR &amp; Income Tax<lb/>papers. Cox assesses us at £2500, but<lb/>this is an over estimate as it includes 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2901_img_2310_6"/>
             the average of past year's dividends &amp;<lb/>this years government pay.  Yes we <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> to the permanent rank<lb/>but there will be so much of that, that<lb/>it does not matter. It is quite easy to<lb/>say he was . . . .  No, leave is not open &amp; not likely<lb/>to be for some time.  This big envelope ought to last<lb/>you most of your train journey<lb/>&amp; save you a whole magazine  Rex may like books, &amp; a very<lb/>brief line from you saying you would like to<lb/>act as his agent  in anything which Jessie has not been appointed would I know cheer him as<lb/>much as anything could.  Do not let it be supposed that I am<lb/>pessimistic about things. I think we<lb/>can more than hold our own — a little<lb/>more, but cannot win a victory by military<lb/><seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> only.  Your <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> W Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>