<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0757">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Patrick Langford Beazley to his son, Piaras (1881-1965). Patrick writes to Piaras concerning the blackouts, describing various motor accidents with night time collisions. Patrick closes stating that &#39;nearly every young man here is now wearing khaki or an armlet.&#39; The day before, 2 March 1916, the Military Service Act came into force, introducing conscription across Britain.Patrick Langford Beazley was born near Killarney, Co. Kerry, son of a tenant who had been evicted from the Lansdowne estate. The Beazleys were an old family in Kerry, of English origin. Married with Nancy (Nanny) Hickey, he was the father of Piaras Béaslaí. He was the editor of the Catholic Times from 1884 until his death in the early 1920s. Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley) was an English born writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, journalist and a member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He wrote twenty plays between 1913 and 1939.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NLI MS 33,972 / 11, NLI MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/757</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0757_img_229_1"  type="Letter"  url="cf7ee16e9f2faf5ac18c9c45aea13bc4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0757_img_229_2"  type="Letter"  url="2c82bd7d551a730ae78a15988790cb52.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0757_img_229_1"/>
              mother says: send me the stockings    'Glengariff'  Rudgrave Square  Egremont  Cheshire    3rd March 1916   My dearest Pierce,   We were very glad to <lb/>get your letter of the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, <lb/>ult. especially as it was <lb/>a considerable time â two <lb/>or three weeks â since we <lb/>had heard from you.It was <lb/>pleasant to know you had <lb/>been very busy, because it <lb/>meant earning, though hard <lb/>work. I hope the opportun<lb rend="hyphen"/>ities have proved no less <lb/>favourable since. Langford <lb/>told us in his letter that  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0757_img_229_2"/>
              <lb/>you were well and looking well. <lb/>I hope you will take <lb/>good care of yourself in <lb/>the trying weather and let <lb/>us hear from you. Here <lb/>the weather could scarcely <lb/>be more trying. It varies <lb/>from day to day and several <lb/>times in the day sometimes. <lb/>Today it has been threatening <lb/>to snow, but has not ac<lb rend="hyphen"/>tually done so. The dark<lb rend="hyphen"/> ness at night, however, is <lb/>the greatest trial. It is <lb/>really terribly disconcerting. <lb/>There are numbers of cars <lb/>in which people have been <lb/>hurt through colliding <cb/><lb/>with lampposts and other <lb/>obstacles of the kind. Mrs. <lb/>Rose dashed into a tall <lb/>letterbox and smashed her <lb/>false teeth. An Irish girl <lb/>who is in service near <lb/><sic>hear</sic> walked up to a lamp <lb/>post and tried to go around <lb/>it, with the result that her <lb/>face was battered. Mother <lb/>and I are quite well, <lb/>thank God, but have no <lb/>news. Nearly every young <lb/>man here now is wear<lb rend="hyphen"/>ing Khaki or an armlet. <lb/>Evidently a great many men <lb/>are wanted <seg type="unclear">jobs</seg>.  With fondest love from <lb/>Mother and Myself. <seg type="closer"> Always affectionately,   Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>