<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6680">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David Wilson to WB Yeats, 11 April 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David Wilson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 8. Folder: Unidentified - Z (8.3)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6680</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0336">David Wilson</persName>
              <date>1917-04-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1286">66 Kenilworth Road, St. Leonards-on-Sea, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6680_img_None_1"  url="phpzMLz7B.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6680_img_0_1"/>
              66 Kenilworth Rd<lb/>St Leonards-on-Sea    11th April 1917    Dear Mr Yeats:   I think I told you in my last<lb/>that today was the one on which I should probably have trouble<lb/>with the military authorities when therefore the cards turned<lb/>up I was compelled to test only one pack in a very hurried<lb/>and unsatisfactory manner.  What I call the position<lb/>test gives the four of spades - the negative test gives<lb/>the King of Diamonds.  Presumably therefore this card is<lb/>the four of spades-  Owing to the letter being an invitation in which I<lb/>had to carry out this test I expect it is all wrong.  Please<lb/>write and tell me if this is so but do not say what the<lb/>card was.  In the meanwhile perforce I will have to delay<lb/>the test of the other pack, although if I am hindered<lb/>long the aura will have vanished.   Sincerely yours<lb/><hi rend="underline">David Wilson</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>