<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6289">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Caitlín Ní Aoda to Charlie Daly, 10 February 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Caitlín Ní Aoda</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Caitlin Ni Aoda, Feymore ,Cresslough, County Donegal to Charles Daly, Prisoner, Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Co. Donegal. She mentions that Christy [] has been captured by the National Army. 2 pages and 1 envelope.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/2/21/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6289</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1460">Caitlín Ní Aoda</persName>
              <date>1923-02-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0612">Feymore, Cresslough, Donegal, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Charlie Daly  </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1693">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Tirconail, Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6289_img_None_1"  url="6d7dde9bed8dcda348055533bbe0df25.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6289_img_None_2"  url="21b290c9fd77cd72f61c442d32f28c6d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6289_img_None_3"  url="1209236c08f08fd9ff2ca49cf1371aa2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6289_img_0_1"/>
             P41/2/21/24   Feymore<lb/>Creeslough    10-2-23    <seg type="foreign">A Cara</seg>   you will be wondering I suppose why<lb/>none of us wrote you this long time, but<lb/>we always put it off from one time to<lb/>another, thinking that perhaps you would<lb/>take courage yourself &amp; drop us a line<lb/>I suppose you all wondered when you saw<lb/>Christy land in with you. Isnt it too<lb/>after all of the care we were trying<lb/>to give him this last Five months. I am<lb/>sure Christy dont feel too good poor boy.<lb/>how could he. He will tell you all himself<lb/>as to how he was taken I mean. we cant get<lb/>used to him been gone atall, you cant imagine<lb/>how lonely we all Feel. And his brother was<lb/>captured on last sunday morning also down<lb/>at home. wasnt that very funny that the<lb/>two should be captured on the same day<lb/>poor Chriss I do hope that they will send him to<lb/>an Hosp - as he will never be able to stick<lb/>prison. We didnt get any word From him since he<lb/>went away. I was over at Ballyconnell on monday<lb/>but wouldnt be allowed in we are sending on<lb/>his clothes on monday. I had a letter From<lb/>Dan yesterday. he asked me did C. get the<lb/>letters that yourself &amp; him wrote. none came yet 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6289_img_0_2"/>
             How are all the boys getting along. tell them<lb/>we all send our Kind regards to them. I am<lb/>going to write to Frank &amp; Tim. Do you hear<lb/>from Ginger at all we got no word since he<lb/>went to Kildare. Well Daly there were<lb/>some terrible reports going around this part<lb/>about you boys - but I am sure they were<lb/>no worse than they might have been: you were<lb/>lucky birds alright. Dan say that you<lb/>have good times in there &amp; that you were<lb/>making rings. You will be able to give us<lb/>all a ring when peace comes. Dan says that<lb/>you all did away with your face protection<lb/>I am glad of that. We could not help laughing<lb/>that night Daly because the birds nest<lb/>as Rosina called them looked very much<lb/>out of place. All your friends at Feymore<lb/>are well Neil Mac Bride wishes to be<lb/>remembered to you all. I wish you would<lb/>see some of his songs now: I will Finish<lb/>up this time. hoping to hear from you<lb/>soon. Father Mother Mary &amp; all send<lb/>their Kindest regards to you all   <seg type="foreign">beannac leat do cara<lb/>Caitlin nic Aodha</seg>    We had a letter from Patk yesterday &amp; they<lb/>are all in good health. He wishes to be<lb/>remembered to you all. Kate 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6289_img_0_3"/>
              Mr Charles Daly<lb/>Prisoner<lb/>Drumboe Castle<lb/>Stranolar<lb/>Co Donegal  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>