<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3903">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 19 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-73</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3903</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1820">8th Royal Irish Fusiliers, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2113">Melrose, Dalkey, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3903_img_3280_1"  type="Letter"  url="eb5d4cc388ea5ae67664f17b2b4be092.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3903_img_3280_2"  type="Letter"  url="bbee13777ab3f4c92da0b94236630b09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3903_img_3280_3"  type="Letter"  url="f5cfeba3d5e99b9bdb45ef3ecb06d7a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3903_img_3280_4"  type="Letter"  url="274b8d1fddd23da0a899a12895a3e435.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3903_img_3280_5"  type="Letter"  url="c41e1844b175ad7fd6e94ecb9bbe1d8d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3903_img_3280_6"  type="Letter"  url="dcaf8c1fb653e2f9b722a8ab8a42cfa4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3903_img_3280_1"/>
             8th.R.Irish Fusiliers,<lb/>France   19/6/'16    My dear Father,   My postcard will have told you of my pleas<lb/>ant crossing both from Ireland and England,and of<lb/>my safe arrival here on Thursday evening.  On my way over Isuddenly remembered a promise I<lb/>had made to visit the Sisters at Newport,Mon. if at<lb/>all possible, and as Ihad a day to spare Ithought<lb/>I could not do better than drop down there. As<lb/>luck would have it my ticket ran from Dublin to<lb/>France<seg type="del">S</seg><seg type="del"></seg>, so I changed at Chester and went down<lb/>South by the G. Western R1. Ticket collectors<lb/>looked puzzled to find me so far off the track,<lb/>but I ended all argument by asking them to deny<lb/>the fact that I was making my way surely,if slowly<lb/>towards France. Had I examined my ticket sooner I  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3903_img_3280_2"/>
             might have gone round by the North of Scotland,<lb/>taken a dive for Cornwall and so worked on towards<lb/>the land of frogs and Frenchmen, I had a very<lb/>warm welcome from the good Sisters,but unfortunate<lb/>ly the Mother Provincial whom I wanted to see was<lb/>away on visitation,and the girl whom I had sent to<lb/>Newport as a novice was in another house some dis-<lb/>tance away, so I saw neither of them.  The following morning I went to London,slept<lb/>at Farm St.and crossed to Boulogne on Thursday,<lb/>reaching Bethune about eight the same evening. My<lb/>travelling companion was a corpulent Major who<lb/>spent most of the 6 1/2 hours' train journey getting<lb/>outside a formidable pile of provisions with  which  he had<lb/>provided himself,the whole being steadied by two<lb/>large baskets of strawberries. For a while I fear<lb/>ed he would bust,as the Yanks say,and then un-<lb/>charitably I hoped he would,as I had had to run<lb/>for my train and was starving in consequence,but<lb/>my friend did not offer me a bite.  <sic>Iput</sic> up in the hotel that night and next morning, 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3903_img_3280_3"/>
             Friday,made my way up to the trenches where the <lb/>Brigade had gone. I had hardly got there whed <seg type="unclear">when</seg> I <lb/>met with an adventure which at first I did not in <lb/>tend to mention fearing it might make you more un- <lb/>easy about me,but on reflection it seems right I <lb/>should not keep from you this last mark of the <lb/>good God's wonderful protection which has been so <lb/>manifest during the past four months.   I was standing in a trench quite a distance from <lb/>the firing line,at a spot almost as safe as Dalk- <lb/>ey itself,talking to <seg type="del">m</seg> some of my men when e <lb/>heard in the distance the scream of a shell. It <lb/>was evidently one of those random shots,which <lb/>Brother Fritz sends along from time to time, as <lb/>no one came after it. We very soon became pain- <lb/>fully aware that our visitor was heading for us <lb/>and that if he did not explode in front of our <lb/>trench his career would certainly come to an end <lb/>close behind us. I did not feel very uneasy for I <lb/>knew we were practically safe from flying frag- <lb/>ments which would pass over our heads,but none of <lb/>us had calculated that this gentleman had madeup 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3903_img_3280_4"/>
             his mind to drop into the trench itself, a couple<lb/>of paces from where I stood.  What really took place in the next couple of<lb/>seconds I cannot say; I was conscious of a terr-<lb/>ific explosion and the thud of falling stones<lb/>and debris. I thought the drums of my ears were<lb/>split by the crash and I believe I was knocked<lb/>down by the concussion but when i jumped to my<lb/>feet I found the two men who were standing at my<lb/>left hand, the side the shell fell, stretched dead,<lb/>though I think I had time to give them absolution<lb/>and the Last Sacraments. The poor fellow on my<lb/>right was lying badly wounded in the head; but<lb/>though a bit stunned and dazed by the suddenness<lb/>of the whole thing I was absolutely untouched<lb/>though covered with dirt and blood.  My escape was nothing short of a miracle, for<lb/>a moment before I was standing on the very spot<lb/>the shell fell and had just moved away a couple<lb/>of paces. I did not think it was possible to be<lb/>so near a high explosive and not be <seg type="del">g</seg>killed and 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3903_img_3280_5"/>
             (5)  <lb/>even now I cannot account for my marvellous es-<lb/>cape. In saying this I am not quite truthful, for<lb/>I have not a doubt where the saving protection<lb/>came from. I had made up my mind to consecrate<lb/>some small Hosts the following morning and put<lb/>them in my pyx<seg type="del">a</seg> as usual, but as I walked through<lb/>the little village on my to the trenches the<lb/>thought came to me that with so much danger about<lb/>it would be well to have our Blessed Lord's com-<lb/>pany and protection. <sic>Iwent</sic> into the church, opened<lb/>the tabernacle and with the Sacred Host resting<lb/>on my heart set out confidently to face whatever<lb/>lay before me, little did I think I was to be so<lb/>near death or how much depended on that simple<lb/>action. That is the explanation of the whole thing<lb/>I trusted Him and I believe He just allowed this<lb/>to happen on the very first day I got back to<lb/>make me trust Him all the more and have greater<lb/>confidence in his loving protection. 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3903_img_3280_6"/>
             (6)   Whether it was my trip in Lena's motor, Mai's vile <lb/>pills or the fearful guzzling of those memorable <lb/>days at home I never felt better or fitter in my <lb/>life. All the same I am hoping that my next trip <lb/>will be the last and will see the end of this <lb/>dreadful war, a thing which is not impossible.   Au revoir, my time is up. Love to all.   Willie. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>