<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4325">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of a letter to William St John Brodrick, 15 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to William St John Fremantle Brodrick, 1st Earl of Midleton, (1856-1942). St John Broderick was a British Conservative Party and Irish Unionist Alliance politician.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4325</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William St John Broderick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4325_img_3685_1"  type="Letter"  url="0e6135fdb7066ef34b263b351ae3aa14.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4325_img_3685_2"  type="Letter"  url="a8b44b820fafc9d3fb4cdbc3cc149eae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4325_img_3685_3"  type="Letter"  url="9b99575c982466b98ec0fb69f5d3f535.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4325_img_3685_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">PRIVATE></hi>   15th June 1916.   Dear Lord Midleton,   I am very glad to hear that there is a prospect of <lb/>vigorous opposition to the impudent efforts of our so—called <lb/>Coalition Government to <sic>instal</sic> a Sinn Fein administration in <lb/>Dublin as the aftermath of the landing of Casement and the <lb/>horrible outrages in the Irish capital in which many British <lb/>officers and men perished. No-one has dared to advance any <lb/>serious argument for the monstrous proposal, but for one <lb/>reason or another unintelligible to the onlooker, we are <lb/>exhorted to acquiesce in this cowardly capitulation. It is <lb/>surely one of the most pitiable events of our time, which is <lb/>saying a great deal, and all of a piece with the record of <lb/>the Coalition. After the many painful experiences we have <lb/>had in recent years Unionists have no right to be surprised <lb/>at any betrayal of principle by their leaders, or rather <lb/>misleaders. However it is not from the party point of view <lb/>that one regards this or anything else as such a crisis, but <lb/>from the national point of view. It is not a question con— <lb/>fined to the Irish factions, whether in the North, the South, the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4325_img_3685_2"/>
            <lb/>East or the West of the country. It vitally affects the <lb/>whole United Kingdom and the British Empire, to say nothing <lb/>of our Allies. If the War has taught us anything it is <lb/>surely obvious that we cannot afford to allow a hostile <lb/>Government to be established on our flank, either from the <lb/>military or the naval point of view, as with the probable <lb/>development of arrangements in the future, aviation and sub— <lb/>marines, etc., the position will become ten times more <lb/>dangerous than in the past. As you well know, the Sinn <lb/>Fein movement is very formidable and very widespread in <lb/>many parts of Ireland and we are, in the old familiar <lb/>phrase, asked to provide a revolution with its "armed <lb/>plant". Dillon's "indiscreet" and infamous speech in the <lb/>House of Commons gave us a glimpse of the spirit by which <lb/>the new Irish Government would be animated. It would be <lb/>superfluous to mention the inevitable effect on Egypt and <lb/>India of the premium which Asquith and Co. propose to <lb/>place on treason.   In the present state of Parliament with its pain— <lb/>ful lack of independence in both Houses, especially in
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4325_img_3685_3"/>
            the Commons, it may be difficult to arouse opposition, but <lb/>I would most strongly urge that every effort should be made <lb/>and that it should not be confined to Irishmen alone, <lb/>because Englishmen have an immense stake in this question.   It is too long to discuss in a letter but there is <lb/>one point which I would particularly urge, namely, that in <lb/>past years the House of Lords was the cock—shy of Demagogues <lb/>for its supposed subservience to the Unionist leaders, and <lb/>was wont to be described on Radical platforms as "a branch <lb/>of the Carlton Club". Now it has an opportunity of showing <lb/>its real independence by throwing out a measure as danger— <lb/>ous to Great Britain as the Declaration of London is now <lb/>seen to have been, and one which is recommended to the <lb/>House of Lords by the Unionist leaders or rather misleaders <lb/>no less than by the Radical confederates with whom they <lb/>are now hand in glove.   Yours sincerely,   Please forgive typewriting, which is due to writers' cramp. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>