<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0060">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Brother Vincent O'Kelly to the Chief Secretary, 3 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Brother Vincent O&#39;Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Brother Vincent O&#39;Kelly in Rochestown Monastery to the Chief Secretary&#39;s office, Dublin. O&#39;Kelly requests an official to come and see him, asking that they come in person rather than write as he would not receive the letter. The letter was directed towards the chief secretary&#39;s office. At this time the chief secretary was Augustine Birrell. Birrell (1850-1933) served as the chief secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish education system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares and, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred leading to his resignation on 1 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/6877/3/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/60</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0476">Brother Vincent O&#39;Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-04-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1047">Rochestown Monastery, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1578">Chief Secretary's Office, Dublin Castle, Dublin, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0060_img_1122_1"  type="Letter"  url="bde613fa9009e24e0dcd62cb7c81b09a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0060_img_1122_1"/>
                Rochestown Monastry  Co Cork    Apr. the 3 1916   Dear Sir   would you be <lb/> so kid as to send down<lb/> one of the officials as I<lb/> want to him urgently<lb/><sic>pleas</sic> do not write as<lb/> I would not get your letter <lb/> but come in person<lb/> <seg type="closer"> Yours truly <lb/> Brother Vincent O'Kelly </seg> Please refer to the local<lb/> police for discreet <lb/> attention  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>