<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0670">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary, describing the relatively comfortable billet he is in at the moment, the awful weather, and his recent sickness. Davidson describes various duties concerning working with and repairing machine guns. He writes he has not received any food or clothes lately and requests soda bread and leather gloves.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/670</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_1"  type="Letter"  url="4f779fca333a41a117a9df4cf579dda8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_2"  type="Letter"  url="65181fa1f23b94774f72abc0c2759ff5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_3"  type="Letter"  url="e08f1601d60e96ee4a89a3cd57ba2fbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_4"  type="Letter"  url="fae6a3dd775f02654833e8056803c507.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_5"  type="Letter"  url="f1a49391fcbe5517093557a4c71b3d44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_6"  type="Envelope"  url="57b6edf9dfc539d535db5d1e096fd287.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0670_img_2163_7"  type="Letter"  url="ba68aa75bd3068f0966c1717a3a732da.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_1"/>
                12/11/15   My Dearest Mother   - It's over a <lb/> week now since I wrote you <lb/> but having written to K &amp; Father in <lb/> the meantime there was really nothing <lb/> to tell you &amp; besides I have had <lb/> a very busy time of it recently. It was <lb/> good of you dear Mother to write me <lb/> so often &amp; I have now 4 letters of <lb/> yours before me to acknowledge dated <lb/> 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>, 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I was just <lb/> reading your last, telling me what <lb/> a bad time poor Kathleen was having <lb/> when the wire arrived with the good <lb/> news that Baby had arrived &amp; that <lb/> both were doing well. I can <lb/> imagine how delighted &amp; relieved <lb/> Douglas will be to receive the news. <lb/> I think K was hoping for a boy  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_2"/>
              <lb/>but still I don't suppose she will <lb/> be at all disappointed. Well <lb/> as regards our doings out here <lb/> the Brigade starts back to the <lb/> trenches on Monday but they are <lb/> only to be there for a short spell <lb/> (about 2 weeks) &amp; it has been decided <lb/> to leave all the Machine Gunners &amp; <lb/> Bombers here to continue their training <lb/><seg type="del">&amp;</seg> so I shall be remaining also to <lb/> superintend the M G instructions &amp; as <lb/> O C details. The weather is simply <lb/> awful at present - it has scarcely <lb/> stopped raining for past 3 days <lb/> so am lucky to be left here in <lb/> comfortable quarters when the move <lb/> is only for such a short time. <lb/> I have a machine gun range fixed  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_3"/>
              <lb/>up about 2 miles from here &amp; <lb/> all the guns in the Bde, assemble <lb/> there each day for shooting &amp; various <lb/> kinds of training. We take lunch <lb/> with us &amp; spend the whole day <lb/> there so I have quite a busy time <lb/> of it. The Batts. are billeted in <lb/> neighbouring villages but I expect <lb/> when the Bde. leaves for the trenches <lb/> the detachment left behind will <lb/> all be billeted in this village. <lb/> I ride every day to the range &amp; <lb/> frequently also to the various <lb/> villages where the Batts. are billeted. <lb/> but of course have nothing like <lb/> the amount of riding here that <lb/> I had when we were in the <lb/> trenches, &amp; I was going to various  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_4"/>
              <lb/>parts of the line each day. <lb/> I have been rather seedy for the last <lb/> 2 days - a bilious turn - &amp; have <lb/> been in bed since yest. afternoon, <lb/> however I am much better this <lb/> evening &amp; expect to be quite all <lb/> right again by tomorrow. There <lb/> is a very good little Dr. in the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Fus. <lb/> who are in this village &amp; he has been <lb/> looking after me. Have not seen <lb/> Gerard for some little time but he <lb/> was then in good form &amp; looking <lb/> well. His Batt. the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> is about 3 <lb/> miles away from here. We <lb/> heard yesterday that Charlie M. has been <lb/> granted another 3 months leave so <lb/> he must be a good deal worse <lb/>than he imagined. It is unfortunate  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_5"/>
              <lb/>for him &amp; also for the Batt. but he <lb/> will at least miss most of the <lb/> winter out here which is something to <lb/> be thankful for. Was glad to hear <lb/><seg type="unclear">Hammis</seg> was looking so well - I hope <lb/> he will soon recover the use of his <lb/> arm. You mentioned that you <lb/> had sent me a box of fruit but so <lb/> far no parcels of any kind have <lb/> reached me within the last 2 weeks. <lb/> I have also been expecting the parcel of <lb/> clothes I wrote for. Probably they will <lb/> come within the next day or so as also <lb/> cakes etc. By the way Mother dear <lb/> if you can send any butter, would <lb/> you include some soda bread, <lb/> Quite a number of the men have it <lb/> sent out to them &amp; it makes such <lb/> a pleasant change from the ration <lb/> bread we get. My gloves have <lb/> almost worn out &amp; I would  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_6"/>
              <lb/>like you to send me <lb/> 1 pr leather with gauntlets &amp; fur lined <lb/> 1 pr woollen <lb/> 1 ' ' mittens. <lb/> My size is 8=1/2 but the leather <lb/> gloves especially are better to be <lb/> on the large size as then ones hands <lb/> keep warmer. Hoping to have <lb/> further good news of K in your <lb/> next letter &amp; with love to all  <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  Jim </seg>  Have not yet received the tubes of <lb/> shaving soap &amp; toothpaste. Hope they <lb/> will come soon as my supply is <lb/> almost finished.  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0670_img_2163_7"/>
              <lb/> On Active Service <lb/><seg type="unclear">17 Nov</seg>  Mrs S.C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  Ireland  <lb/>JS Davidson <lb/>12 - 11- 15   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>