<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3310">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Clara Moser to Herbert Samuel, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Clara Moser</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-11716-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3310</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0391">Clara Moser</persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1624">29 South Anne Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1103">Herbert Samuel</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3310_img_2724_1"  type="Letter"  url="a4b7c6a9083ab0eecf73644d3fb7dd7f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3310_img_2724_1"/>
             DUBLIN WATCH COMMITTEE<lb/>29 South Anne Street<lb/>Dublin.  CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>11716 - - 8 JUL 1916<lb/>OFFICE   3rd June 1916.   To the Right Hon. Herbert L.Samuel  <lb/> Dear Sir,   Now that the question of rebuilding of the Sackville<lb/>Street area is under consideration the members of the Housing<lb/>Sub-Committee of the Dublin Watch Committee are anxious to<lb/>draw your attention to certain local conditions which are<lb/>liable to be overlooked.  We feel very strongly that any effort to rebuild the<lb/>demolished streets on a grand scale will be waste of time and<lb/>money so long as the slum problem is left untouched.  It is impossible to emphasise too strongly the corroding<lb/>influence of slums on the value of house property in Dublin.<lb/>It is usual to find the most filthy areas behind, and often<lb/>surrounded by, the best class of property. The result is<lb/>obvious. The value of the houses in the neighborhood drops<lb/>and often the residential houses themselves become tenements<lb/>while the stables at the back are used for human habitation.  According to the Report of the Royal Commission on Housing<lb/>Conditions in Dublin 1914 there were then 22,701 persons living<lb/>in houses unfit for human habitation and incapable of being made<lb/>so.  So long as these places are allowed to exist their proximity<lb/>will gradually undermine the value of the best streets, and they<lb/>will breed in the minds of the inhabitants that form of discontent<lb/>which ends in desperation and which must always be expected to<lb/>break out in ruinous violence until the evil which causes it has<lb/>been completely removed.   Yours faithfully, <lb/> Clara Moser. <lb/>Hon. Secretary Housing Sub-Committee<lb/>of Dublin Watch Committee 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>