<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4283">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 14 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/222</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4283</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-14</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4283_img_3647_1"  type="NULL"  url="dedf733bf5fe85e085bee84b9caf2bb3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4283_img_3647_2"  type="Letter"  url="76e8132cf78869b7df5f78ad24f05daf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4283_img_3647_3"  type="Letter"  url="9f56bddcd167415abf01063415d6dd67.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4283_img_3647_4"  type="Letter"  url="1e074cb3c3362f62a04dad663365adde.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4283_img_3647_5"  type="NULL"  url="77856dcee1c71456dd2720fa25809ebf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4283_img_3647_6"  type="NULL"  url="86d1af69939ad5435a9dd3f1ec3714e7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4283_img_3647_1"/>
             14 April 16   I hope the wire I sent yesterday may have <lb/> arrived in time to prevent my letters from being <lb/> too confident in raising false hopes. I don't <lb/> think any one but a pr knows how much <lb/> the b w feels the blow. The other members of <lb/> the Staff think I don't care, unless my rather crusty <lb/> temper betrays me. Yesterday at mess they were <lb/> talking about the vagaries of promotion etc, when <lb/> it seemed to strike them suddenly that mine was the <lb/> most astounding case. I smiled &amp; said I had done <lb/> things in the past with my eyes open &amp; was quite <lb/> prepared to suffer the consequences, &amp; all of them <lb/> thought here is a curious animal without ambition.    Place when he heard a little about my past <lb/> military career began to look most uncomfortable to <lb/> find himself senior to one who was holding 6 years
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4283_img_3647_2"/>
             ago a position which he would have given anything <lb/>for 2 years ago. I was at a big demonstration <lb/>at one of the schools yesterday &amp; saw General <lb/>after General who had been my contemporaries. <lb/>Some of them eyed me with a superior glance <lb/>of "you're done for", others spoke to me as an <lb/>equal, &amp; 2 of them came &amp; had a <seg type="unclear">long back</seg>, <lb/>one of them saying "for me to be a General &amp; <lb/>you a Captain "is the most topsy turvy world I <lb/>have ever seen." This was meant very kindly <lb/>&amp; I know quite honestly, &amp; what is more (in <lb/>writing to you only) it is the real facts of the case.   Sometimes I admit I am a little amazed <lb/>at the world eg when I <seg type="unclear">hear</seg> that <seg type="unclear">M Calmont</seg> <lb/>is looked upon as so good a CO that he is to be <lb/>given an early Brigadier ship.   Now old thing I don't want you to get the idea <lb/>that I am living in the land of grievances — I am not <lb/>&amp; I am quite prepared to make any personal sacrifice for <lb/>this country or for the Ulster cause, but it is as will <lb/>that you &amp; I should realise that our position after the <lb/>war will be one which it will be of no use trying <lb/>to explain to the outside world. To attempt to do so <lb/>even would be to strain the credulity of one's <lb/><seg type="del">best friend</seg> acquaintances &amp; even of one's friends &amp; <lb/>relations. It is only those in the know — Carson <lb/>Craig &amp; one's nearest relations who will understand <lb/>to a <hi rend="underline">partial</hi> extent —  Even <seg type="unclear">Mab</seg> &amp; Edward won't be more than puzzled  To others the situation will <lb/>be unbelievable, even one's  old  Military friends will find <lb/>it hard to follow, &amp; as I do not intend to go <lb/>through the remainder of life trying to explain <lb/>one will have to drop them. This will entail <lb/>either going into  comparative  seclusion, or taking up a life <lb/>which is entirely non-military. I am not trying <lb/>to raise up ghosts, but as you will admit no one will be
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4283_img_3647_3"/>
            <lb/>able to follow an attempt at a laboured explanation on <lb/>my part that I with 20 years regular service as a Captain <lb/>or possibly a Major?, whilst X with 2 years service is a <lb/>Major or Lt Colonel. With other rebels made Lt Cols <lb/>— like Crawford —  — or General like M'Cjalmont younger than myself  the matter is quite unintelligible.   Why I write in this strain is that I want you <lb/>to realise how much I value the thought of indepen — <lb/>dence in the future, &amp; consequently that our present <lb/>prosperity is not to be treated as a test of our <lb/>future standing when I lose £650 in army pay <lb/>&amp; rubber deflates to normal conditions. I don't <lb/>want you to screw &amp; skimp, nor to think you <lb/>cannot help relations or others, but I do wish you <lb/>to see clearly that this year is not a true test <lb/>of the future, &amp; that  in  anything you do this year you <lb/>will make this clear.   I was wondering if it might not be possible to <lb/>help Carson — We could probably spare £500 this year
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4283_img_3647_4"/>
            <lb/>later, but the difficulties would be great <lb/>even if one did it anonymously, tho' it would <lb/>feel like doing something for the Country. I think <lb/>it is advisable that they should both feel the pinch <lb/><seg type="del">f</seg>a bit as sacrifice of that kind will be good <lb/>for the man, &amp; she will delight in it.   I enclose a letter from Craig. Don't make <lb/><hi rend="underline">any</hi> comments on it outside. There is evidently <lb/>something up which we do not know of as <lb/>he is anything but a pessimist. Either the <lb/>Naval situation is not satisfactory or <seg type="del">we</seg>  they  <lb/>are getting a true account of Germany's <lb/>latent strength at last. He evidently has given
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4283_img_3647_5"/>
            <lb/>up all idea of turning out the Government but hopes <lb/> that a powerful opposition may give them stimulus.   The worst/of it is that the opposition will <lb/> consist largely of disgruntled people &amp; cranks some <lb/> of the most level heads still being led by BL <lb/> or hypnotized by Grey's apparent statemanship.    We are 3 days behindhand in papers. This &amp; the <lb/> recall from leave of all ranks may mean something <lb/> serious.   Hickman has put in for leave on very <lb/> Urgent private affairs &amp; is getting it (!). I <lb/> fancy he expects to be home for an exciting <lb/> time. It is wonderful how these Military <lb/> <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">Great</seg></seg> big wigs still play up to the political <lb/> side they affect to despise.    He and the GOC have had a good set to in <lb/>which the latter has come out top. I should not <lb/> be surprised if H fails to return, &amp; he may do <lb/> something on his own whilst at home.   I am glad to see that the Duchess &amp; Lady <lb/> C are both keeping up the CC work so well. I <lb/> honestly expected they would have got bored with it <lb/> before this. Later the latter may have to drop it. <lb/>I expect they are both stimulated by the p r's <lb/> example . She is doing good work.    I'm so  much pleased to hear about the eyes, <lb/> but do get the glasses at once or you shall get <lb/> a bad scolding. I don't like your heads. They <lb/> are too frequent. I am interested in your <lb/> experiment of a chummery. I don't know Mrs <lb/> H so will not attempt to prophesy. It will largely <lb/> depend on the firmness with which you maintain
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4283_img_3647_6"/>
            <lb/>your independence of each other from the start, &amp; how <lb/> outspoken you are with one another.   I was to have ridden with the General this <lb/> morning but he thought the ground too wet <lb/> so you have got the rather doubtful benefit <lb/> of this lengthy letter.   I don't think the p r will misunderstand <lb/> the b w's long tirade. It is not a plaint against <lb/> fate or Providence. It is merely an endeavour to get <lb/> the p r to see clearly what he foresees in the future, <lb/> which he knows that she will be willng to <lb/> share with him — grey tho' it may be — perhaps <lb/> with some pink tinges for the b w , but only <lb/> too imbued with faded brown for a p r.   Your b w    Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>