<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6664">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Fletcher-Vane to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 23 June 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, Francis Fletcher-Vane criticizes MP John E. Redmond for not really representing the will of the Irish people within the British House of Commons. He also asks Walsh to spread his nationalist views in the US, to make sure that the Irish Americans are on his side.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph C. Walsh Papers. Letter Earls - Foy</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6664</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0659">Francis Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1917-06-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0977">Rodes Hall, Crowborough, Sussex, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6664_img_None_1"  url="phpCNBIyz.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6664_img_None_2"  url="phpKFcn11.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6664_img_None_3"  url="phpo3Uduu.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6664_img_None_4"  url="phpEVZeXW.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6664_img_None_5"  url="phpDQUyrf.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6664_img_0_1"/>
              Rodes Hall<lb/>Crowborough, Sussex    23rd June, 1917    My dear ---   I can assure you that nothing would give me greater<lb/>pleasure than to go out to America and indeed I have done not a little<lb/>to try to get there. In the first place I was assured of a good command<lb/>and though I loathe war on principle, I am too much of an Irishman not<lb/>to like the excitement of fighting. My view is this that we have all of<lb/>us a very important duty to do all in our power to end the brutal stu-<lb/>pidity of war-but seeing that neither you nor I had anything to say in<lb/>making or prosecuting this war, the fact that we are in it carries no<lb/>responsibility-beyond that of seeing that no ignoble things are done<lb/>within our own sphere of action. The same feeling ruled me in Dublin<lb/>last year. I hated and despised the policy which I had to carry out-I<lb/>had to fight men who suffered from a grievance and who fought in a<lb/>chivalrous manner, that they were my countrymen and that their grievance<lb/>was also mine, made it harder-yet had I refused to take my place in the<lb/>fight much worse things might have happened, than any gain which my<lb/>exemption from the fight could have caused. For example a good many more<lb/>innocent men would have been killed in Portabello Barracks than were<lb/>killed  ........ until we .cut the painter-not of Empire, for I am a<lb/>British Commonwealthman-but of English influence in Ireland-we can have<lb/>no internal peace. We can, therefore, have no solid influence.  The lamentable fact is this-I say so as one who while<lb/>being more Irish than English-and yet more Universal than either(be-<lb/>cause I have travelled much) the bourgeoise atmosphere of England saps<lb/>the virile energy of the Irish-and was before the little Rebellion of<lb/>last year doing infinite harm. Pearce foresaw this. The Communal    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6664_img_0_2"/>
             -2-  spirit which is the basis of the Brehon Law, which is expressed in the<lb/>universal hospitality of the natural Irish,which is shown by the rapid<lb/>acceptance of the Cooperative movement,which is demonstrated by the<lb/>much easier disciplining of Irish Troops at the Front, was being slowly<lb/>destroyed by English Commercial ideals. The leaders of the so called Ir-<lb/>ish Party in Parliament were the first sufferers from this fell dis<lb/>ease.  The revolt against them which we call Sinn Fein,is noth-<lb/>ing more than the jibbing of a people who believe that they are being<lb/>led into servitude. And they are right. They were being led into a<lb/>servitude to ideals which are foreign to all their traditions. Their<lb/>Leasers had been captured by the promises held out of the advantages of<lb/>Constitutional agitation-plus £400 a year.  The little blaze of the Easter Rising knocked them all<lb/>silly. As I know, God help me, Redmond et hoc gereris, feared the Rebels<lb/>more thatn they feared the dominance of English ideals in Ireland.  When I came to Redmond on the 2nd May, 1916-before any<lb/>of the Rebel Leaders had been executed-and told him that innocent Irish<lb/>men like Skeffington, were being slaughtered by English officers, and said<lb/>to him that you have now the opportunity of using this knowledge as a<lb/>lever to prevent unnecessary executions of rebels-he was<hi rend="underline"> </hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">cold.</hi></hi> At any<lb/>rate  he  did nothing to prevent the most foolish policy-and brutal-namely<lb/>the slow executions,over two weeks,of the Leaders in the Revolt-<lb/>among whom were included 2 Assistant Scout Masters of Irish Boy Scouts,<lb/>aged 22 and 23 ( Colbert and Hewson ). The Irish Leaders in Parliament<lb/>were dumb in this crisis-thinking no doubt how the revolt might affect<lb/>their influence. So between the 3rd.May and the 12th. Pearce, McDonnagh,<lb/>Plunkett,Connolly and the rest-were done to death. Some of the choic-<lb/>est spirits in Ireland. And though perhaps the execution of some few<lb/>of them was necessary-there is no possibility of doubt that the shoot-<lb/>ing of 16 for a revolt of a few thousdands, was entirely unnecessary, was 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6664_img_0_3"/>
             -3-  <hi rend="underline">impolitic,</hi> and might have been prevented.  Had the Irish Leaders in Parliament, on that day when I<lb/>reported to them the murders of Skeffington etcet. , risen to the occas-<lb/>ion-moved the adjournment of the House and played havoc with the whole<lb/>dirty place, they would have prevented the killing of at least a half<lb/>of the rebels.  William O'Brien <seg type="del">i</seg>s<seg type="del"> </seg> was  the one man among them (and he was ill)<lb/>who seemed to realise the opportunity.  Let me put the mattter clearly before you..  On the 2nd. May-I having reported the murders of three<lb/>innocent men (by an officer who, though under my command, I had been pre-<lb/>vented by the Irish Headquarters from placing under arrest for his accts<lb/>and who a week afterwards was still allowed to be in command of troops)<lb/>to the War Office, <seg type="del">I </seg>proceeded to the House of Commons, and there in the<lb/>presence of Mr. John Burns told the story to the Irish Leader, Mr. John<lb/>Redmond. The day before in Dublin I had heard that the Military Auth-<lb/>orities were going to shoot every man they could. I, therefore, said to<lb/>Mr. John Redmond that I placed in his hands facts of murder by a Brit-<lb/>ish officer, and that I hoped that he would use these as a lever with<lb/>the Govenment, to prevent an exuberance in executions of rebels. Nat-<lb/>urally, Redmond had all the cards in his hand-my bona fides was undoubt-<lb/>ed for I had just reported the same thing to the Secretary for War.  Yet nothing was done, by the united effort of the Irish<lb/>Party, until the 16 were executed.  I am a man accustomed in War, to act quickly-and to me<lb/>the greatest crime is that of delay. The Leader of the Irish Party<lb/>delayed until he saw which way the cat jumped-or was likely to jump-<lb/>and I have no use for such leaders. Moreover, his delay ruined his<lb/>party because for right or wrong, an Irishman who rebels, we, who know<lb/>Irish History, cannot honestly condem as such. And even if condem-<lb/>ing we might attempt to prevent the folly of violent retaliation.  The fact remains that what we call Sinn Fein is the       
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6664_img_0_4"/>
             -4-  repudiation of the policy of mild compromise which has failed owing to<lb/>its own intrinsic weakness. 16 men were shot in cold blood for a lit-<lb/>tle rebellion-and the National Leaders did not try to prevent un-<lb/>necessary shootings. So they have lost power!!  Now Sinn Fein, if properly led-as the soul of Ireland is<lb/>behind it-should settle for all time the Irish question. But I am not<lb/>sure.  But of this I am sure it can-if it will-ally itself with<lb/>the spirit of the European peoples. This War was at first a very noble<lb/>Crusade-for freedom of a small Nationality, for the Defence of France<lb/>unjustly attacked. For this all Irishmen and the majority of Englishmen<lb/>who joined in 1914 came out for to fight.  They did not come out to fight for trade,or conquest,or<lb/>Imperialism. Yet since the War commenced the Authorities have changed<lb/>the objective. Now it is for trade routes to the East,for German Col-<lb/>onies captured,for Alsace and Lorraine,for Constantinople,for Trieste-<lb/>and other things which not only have nothing to do with the original<lb/>sacrifice but are in some respects directly opposed to the interests<lb/>of those who first volunteered. Extension of trade for example is dir-<lb/>ectly opposed to the interests of the Workers until their share of<lb/>the profits of trade which they make by their industry is adjusted.<lb/>Any expansion of Commerce by any country is only a means by which the<lb/>Capitalist hopes to postpone the day of reckoning-the balancing of the<lb/>account,between Men and Labour.  Therefore,you will see that the volunteers of 1914-1915,<lb/>the vast majority of whom are Socialists, or Trade Unionists, are going<lb/>now to put their end in to prevent Capitalist Imperialism  The lines indicated by the Russian Republic-and in a<lb/>less distinct form by President Wilson,are those which the Labour Party<lb/>in England are demanding.  As these are so closely in touch with the soul of Ire- 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_6664_img_0_5"/>
             -5-  land-there should be no difficulty. The Irish Americans must be with<lb/>us.  This war,therefore,must be the last War-of this I am<lb/>sure every man <seg type="del">engaged</seg> in the ranks of the many Armies engaged is quite<lb/>clear-but it also must not end in a Peace which is dictated by the in-<lb/>terests of an interested Class. Peace when it comes must be a People's<lb/>Peace,not that thing, a ephemeral thing, a Capitalist one.  I do not know how these opinions agree with yours. If<lb/>they do, let them be known as far as you can in America. What I have<lb/>said in this letter as to the futility of the Irish Parliamentarians is<lb/>my honest view looking at the matter,while deeply interested,from the<lb/>outside. There is no strong man among them-and if there is he is still<lb/>kept in bonds by the Machine.  So if I may be allowed to suggest-take the wider Ir-<lb/>ish line, Sinn Fein,often extreme in expositon-is now the only Irish<lb/>policy. It is narrow often,but behind it all is the Soul of Ireland,<lb/>which fights and struggles <seg type="del">the </seg> against injustice and wrong, just as<lb/>much when the wrong is done to another as to itself. This is chivilry.   Francis Fletcher-Vane<lb/>of Hutton  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>