<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1169">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 25 June 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Father Fanted who visited Francis M. Shaw&#39;s town and the high temperatures which kept churches closed. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/28, IJA/CHPI/54/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1169</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-06-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1169_img_3846_1"  type="Letter"  url="2d06c6dcf46b30931a068017a80407be.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1169_img_3846_1"/>
                Basra    25 June 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   I am attached temporarily to No.1. <lb/>British Base Depot, here, the ordinary chaplain having <lb/>gone to hospital. Continue to send letters to Bombay. I had <lb/>a letter from your Reverence lately, dated I think 7 April, in <lb/>which you referred to the safety your priests in the great <lb/>push. I hope F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>MacSheahan has since given signs of <lb/>life. I wrote to F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Fitzgibbon to congratulate him on the <lb/>V.C. F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><seg type="unclear">Ganold</seg>S.J. passed through Basra about three <lb/>weeks ago. He is now somewhere up the line with a Cavalry <lb/>brigade. Hot weather has begun. At our Church in the <lb/>town the thermometer has been up to 111<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>in the shade and is <lb/>always over 108<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> during the day. In less sheltered camps it <lb/>has been as high as 122<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> in the shade. One great blessing <lb/>is the comparative coolness of the nights. At present there is a <lb/>strong wind blowing out clouds &amp; clouds of dust. All the <lb/>roofs of houses, and all military huts are simply dry mud, so <lb/>when a wind blows it is like burning <seg type="unclear">purge</seg> on the hill <lb/>at home. And of course the desert is simply dry mud too.  I have been able to say 19 Masses for F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley in <lb/>June; I shall send him a separate note, but it would <lb/>be better to tell him in case of accident. Last night <lb/>Reuters contained the result of East Cavan. There <lb/>must be great rejoising. <seg type="closer"> I commend myself to all your prayers,  Francis M Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>