<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2997">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter  from Patrick J. Little, 15 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick J. Little, Editor</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick J. Little, editor of the New Ireland newspaper, to an unknown recipient. Enclosed in the letter are three versions of a portion of a document from Dublin Castle telling of plans to arrest members of the Irish Volunteers and other related organisations. Little appeals to the recipient of the letter to use his influence to discourage such action in order to avoid bloodshed.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>P104/1342/001</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2997</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0321">Patrick J. Little, Editor</persName>
              <date>1916-04-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0824">New Ireland Office, 13 Fleet Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2997_img_240_1"  type="Letter"  url="8a33e968c0da7baabb65e63fc08d1566.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2997_img_240_2"  type="Letter"  url="90883983f700aac67afa33ca7a1581be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2997_img_240_3"  type="Letter"  url="a2881b6ad148f1a03191aea1b98b933f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2997_img_240_4"  type="Letter"  url="d2b818c9e17886b52ae150ca8ebe836a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2997_img_240_1"/>
             NEW IRELAND Office,<lb/>13 Fleet Street,<lb/>Dublin  . April 15th. 1916.    Sir,   The gravity of the present situation in Ireland<lb/>compels me to invite your serious attention to the<lb/>enclosed. It is a copy of portion of a document recent-<lb/>ly addressed to and on the files in Dublin Castle.  In view of the deliberate intention here revealed<lb/>on the part of the Government to cause bloodshed in<lb/>Ireland by an attack on the Irish Volunteers. — a body<lb/>formed openly in pre—war times — in a manner certain<lb/>to provoke armed resistance. I appeal to you to use<lb/>your influence public and private, in whatever manner<lb/>you may consider would best benefit this country.   Yours truly,    Patrick J. Little  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2997_img_240_2"/>
             The cipher from which this document is copied<lb/>does not indicate punctuation or capitals.  'the following precautionary measures have been<lb/>sanctioned by the irish office on the recommendation of<lb/>the general officer commanding the forces in ireland all<lb/>preparations will be made to put these measures in force<lb/>immediately on receipt. of an order issued from the chief<lb/>secretarys office dublin castle &amp; signed by the under<lb/>secretary &amp; the general officer commanding the forces<lb/>in ireland first the following persons to be placed under<lb/>arrest all members of the sinn fein national council the<lb/>central executive irish sinn fein volunteers general<lb/>council irish sinn fein volunteers county board irish sinn<lb/>fein volunteers executive committee national volunteers<lb/>coisde gnota committee gaelic league see list a three &amp;<lb/>four &amp; supplementary list a two.......<lb/>....... dublin metropolitan police and royal irish<lb/>constabulary forces in dublin city will be confined to<lb/>barracks under direction of competent military author<lb/>—ity an order will be issued to inhabitants of city to rem<lb/>—ain in their houses until such time as competent milit—<lb/>ary authority may otherwise direct or permit pickets<lb/>chosen from units of territorial force will be placed at<lb/>all points marked on maps three and four accompany<lb/>—ing mounted patrols will continuously visit all points<lb/>&amp; report every hour the following premises will be oc<lb/>—cupied by adequate forces and all necessary measures<lb/>used without need of reference to headquarters first<lb/>premises known as liberty hall beresford place number<lb/>six harcourt street sinn fein building number two daw<lb/>son street headquarters volunteers number twelve<lb/>dolier street nationality office number twenty five rutl—<lb/>&amp; square gaelic league office number forty one rutland<lb/>square foresters hall sinn fein volunteer premises in city<lb/>all national volunteer premises in city trade council prem<lb/>—ises capel street surrey house leinster road rathmines<lb/>the following premises will be isolated &amp; all commun—<lb/>ication to or from prevented premises known as arch—<lb/>bishops house drumcondra mansion house dawson street<lb/>number forty herbert park larkfield kimmage road wood—<lb/>townpark ballyboden saint endas college hermitage rath -<lb/>farnham &amp; in addition premises in list five d see maps<lb/>three &amp; four  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2997_img_240_3"/>
             Secret Orders issued to Military Officers.  The cipher from which this document is copied does not indicate<lb/>punctuation or capitals.  The following precautionary measures have been sanctioned<lb/>by the Irish Office on the recommendation of the General Officer<lb/>Commanding the Forces in Ireland. All preparations will be made<lb/>to put these measures in force immediately on receipt of an Order<lb/>issued from the Chief Secretary's Office, Dublin Castle, &amp; signed by<lb/>the Under Secretary &amp; the General Officer Commanding the Forces<lb/>in Ireland. First, the following persons to be placed under arrest:—<lb/>All members of the Sinn Fein National Council, the Central Executive<lb/>Irish Sinn Fein Volunteers, General Council Irish Sinn Fein<lb/>Volunteers, County Board Irish Sinn Fein Volunteers, Executive<lb/>Committee National Volunteers, Coisde Gnota Committee Gaelic<lb/>League. See list A 3 and 4 and supplementary list A2. . . .<lb/>Dublin Metropolitan Police &amp; Royal Irish Constabulary Forces<lb/>in Dublin City will be confined to barracks under the direction of<lb/>the Competent Military Authority. An order will be issued to<lb/>inhabitants of city to remain in their houses until such time as the<lb/>Competent Military Authority may otherwise direct or permit<lb/>Pickets chosen from units of Territorial Forces will be placed at all<lb/>points marked on Maps 3 and 4. Accompanying mounted patrols<lb/>will continuously visit all points &amp; report every hour. The<lb/>following premises will be occupied by adequate forces, &amp; all<lb/>necessary measures used without need of reference to Headquarters.<lb/>First, premises known as Liberty Hall, Beresford Placee ; No. 6<lb/>Harcourt Street, Sinn Fein building; No 2 Dawson Street; Head—<lb/>quarters Volunteers; No. 12 D'Olier Street, Nationality office;<lb/>No. 25 Rutland Square, Gaelic League Office; No. 41 Rutland<lb/>Square, Foresters' Hall; Sinn Fein Volunteer premises in<lb/>city; all National Volunteer premises in the city; Trades<lb/>Council presmies, Capel Street; Surrey House, Leinster Road,<lb/>Rathmines. THE FOLLOWING PREMISES WILL BE ISOLATED,<lb/>&amp; ALL COMMUNICATION TO OR FROM PREVENTED:—<lb/>PREMISES KNOWN AS ARCHBISHOP'S HOUSE, DRUM—<lb/>CONDRA; MANSION HOUSE, DAWSON STREET; NO. 40<lb/>Herbert Pasrk; Larkfield, Kimmage Road; Woodtown Park, Ballyboden;<lb/>Saint Endas College, Hermitage, Rathfarnham; and in addition<lb/>premises in list 5 D, see Maps 3 and 4. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2997_img_240_4"/>
             <hi rend="underline">The following Official Document which has reached us, in<lb/>cipher, needs no comment. the precautions taken in '99 were<lb/><hi rend="underline">simplicity itself compared to them.</hi></hi>  The following precautionary measures have been sanctioned<lb/>by the Irish Office on the recommendation of the General Officer<lb/>commanding the forces in Ireland. All preparations will be made<lb/>to put these measures in force immediately on receipt of an order<lb/>issued from the Chief Secretary's Office, Dublin Castle, and<lb/>signed by the Under—Secretary and the General Officer commanding<lb/>the forces in Ireland. First the following persons to be placed<lb/>under arrest — all members of the Sinn Fein National Council.<lb/>the Central Executive Irish Sinn Fein Volunteers ; General Council<lb/>Irish Sinn Fein Volunteers; County Boards Irish Sinn Fein Volunteers;<lb/>Executive Committee National Volunteers; Coisde Gnotha Committee<lb/>Gaelic League - see list A three and 4, and Supplementary List A Two.  Dublin Metropolitan Police and Royal Irish Constabulary<lb/>forces in Dublin City will be confined to Barracks under direction<lb/>of competent military authority, &amp; order will be issued to<lb/>inhabitant's of city to remain in their houses until such time as<lb/>competent military authority may otherwise direct or permit.<lb/>Pickets chosen from units of territorial force will be placed at<lb/>all points marked on maps three and four accompanying. Mounted<lb/>patrols will continuously visit all points &amp; report every hour.<lb/>the following premises will be occupied be adequate forces &amp; all<lb/>necessary measures used without need of reference to headquarters.<lb/>First premises known as Liberty Hall, Beresford Place; Number six<lb/>Harcourt Street — Sinn Fein Building — Number two Dawson Street -<lb/>Headquarters Volunteers — Number twelve d'Olier Street — Nationality<lb/>Office - Number twenty-five Rutland Square — Gaelic League Office<lb/>— Number forty-one Rutland Square — Foresters' Hall — Sinn Fein<lb/>Volunteer premises in city; all National Volunteer premises in<lb/>city; Trade Councl premises Capel Street; Surrey House Leinster<lb/>Road, Rathmines. The following premises will be isolated &amp; all<lb/>communications to or from prevented — premises known as Archbishop's<lb/>House, Drumcondra; Mansion House, Dawson Street; Number forty<lb/>Herbert Park; Larkfield, Kimmage Road; Woodtown Park, Ballyboden;<lb/>St. Enda's College, Hermitage, Rathfarnham, and in addition<lb/>premises in list five D — see maps three and four. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>