<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0089">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate English to her son, Patrick, 23 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate English</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Kate English (b. 1855) to her son, Patrick (1894-1970). Kate writes of receiving his letter and how happy she was to get it. She mentions that Patrick&#39;s cousin, Mickie, is serving at the front and was surprised when he heard of the trouble. She writes him to let the officer in charge of him that he has six cousins who are fighting in France, and lists them.This letter is part of a correspondence shared between Kate and Patrick during his imprisonment in Stafford and later Frongoch.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/89</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0077">Kate English</persName>
              <date>1916-05-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0478">Dunsink Cottage, Castleknock, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0112">Frongoch Prison, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0089_img_1163_1"  type="Letter"  url="170aa57ae4ee471b559c19b1fc251535.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0089_img_1163_2"  type="Letter"  url="f701e2cc305f78cb1fe784bfe58de74d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0089_img_1163_3"  type="Letter"  url="0dc6e9caf436a40d7be5e7238ec16e01.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0089_img_1163_1"/>
                Dunsink Cottages  Castleknock    23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> May 1916   My Dear Patrick   I received your<lb/> letter on Monday 22 May I<lb/> was delighted when I got it<lb/> as I was anxious to hear <seg type="unclear">from</seg><lb/>  for 3<lb/> letters and I got no reply<lb/> perhaps you did not receive<lb/> them. I am sending you a<lb/> parcel it contains a cake<lb/> shirt socks tie brush  7  books<lb/> collar and <seg type="del">and tie</seg> towel &amp; soap<lb/> Beads if you are allowed<lb/> to get tea or sugar or  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0089_img_1163_2"/>
              anything you want let me<lb/> know or will you be let<lb/> take money. let me know<lb/> in your next letter  I am keeping strong myself<lb/> I hope you are the same<lb/><sic>dont</sic> be fretting as you<lb/> will be a man yet. you<lb/> are but a child. Keep up<lb/> your poor heart as we<lb/> are all praying for you.<lb/> We had a letter from Mickie<lb/> at the front he has got<lb/> promotion. he was surprised<lb/> when he heard of the<lb/> trouble.  Tell the officers in charge<lb/><cb/> of you that you have 6<lb/> first cousins fighting in<lb/> France. Michael English Christy Fenlon Annie's Husband<lb/><sic>thats</sic> Joe O'Mahony Brigid Reillys<lb/> Husband. Sergeant Kelly and<lb/> the 2 Reillys of the high<lb/> Road. Lord Wimborne is<lb/> leaving Ireland and Nellie<lb/> &amp; Frank expects to be going <lb/> away with them. Jamesy<lb/> David Katie Nellie and<lb/> all the rest of us join<lb/> sending you our best love<lb/> hoping to hear from you<lb/> soon again. my eyes will <lb/> be strained watching an<lb/> answer to know if you<lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0089_img_1163_3"/>
              got the parcel all right<lb/> <seg type="closer"> Good—Bye. My Dear<lb/> Son Patrick and God<lb/> Bless you. Good—Bye x x x x x x<lb/> x x x x x x<lb/> I remain<lb/> Your Ever Loving  Widow  Mother<lb/>  M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> K. English </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>