<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1358">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Muldoon to Mabel FitzGerald, 26 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Muldoon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from politician and lawyer John Muldoon MP (1865-1938) to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). Mabel was particularly active in attempting to secure the release of her husband, who had not taken an active part in the actual fighting and Muldoon offers his support. He writes that the prisoners should all be released withing six months (a general amnesty did not take place until 1917) and the sentences were unjust as, in cases like FitzGerald&#39;s, the prisoners had been given no opportunity to defend themselves and call witnesses.Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Desmond FitzGerald Papers, P80/1586/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1358</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0968">John Muldoon</persName>
              <date>1916-05-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1983">Dunedin, Orwell Park, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1358_img_709_1"  type="Letter"  url="ddfd2c9082c87bf6ac6a893278e32c84.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1358_img_709_2"  type="Letter"  url="ac5de59ace38db4d68611226bd317278.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1358_img_709_3"  type="Letter"  url="313a74d3cc1167d2248616e723407e1e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1358_img_709_1"/>
                Dunedin, Orwell Park   Dublin   26-5-16  <hi rend="underline">Private</hi> Dear Mrs Fitzgerald   - I am in <lb/> receipt this morning of your <lb/> letter upon the case of your <lb/> husband, &amp; I assure you <lb/> I would be willing to do <lb/> anything in my power to <lb/> help you. This whole business <lb/> has broken my heart, but <lb/> there are others who have <lb/> suffered more, a great deal <lb/> more, than I have.  I feel confident in <lb/> telling you that if things <lb/> go well &amp; if the country <lb/> recovers itself soon, these <lb/> sentences may not, will  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1358_img_709_2"/>
              <lb/>not last six months. The <lb/> prisoners will all be restored <lb/> to their homes, &amp; released.<lb/> I am also satisfied that <lb/> under any circumstances <lb/> these sentences, such as <lb/> that inflicted upon your <lb/> husband, could not be <lb/> justified - could not be <lb/> defended . He was tried <lb/> before a court-martial where <lb/> he had no proper means of <lb/> making a defence or <lb/> calling witnesses or proving <lb/> his innocence &amp; I am <lb/>sure that sentence can <lb/> never stand when <lb/> people are restored to  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1358_img_709_3"/>
              <lb/>reason, &amp; the passions of the <lb/> moment have passed away.  I wish you could send me <lb/> the speech which your <lb/> husband made in Bray, <lb/> after which he was sent <lb/> to Mountjoy.  Be assured of my <lb/> sympathy. &amp; believe me <seg type="closer"> Your obedient servant  John Muldoon </seg>  P.S. Capt Donelan M.P. to <lb/> whom I fancy you have already<lb/> written authorises me to say <lb/> that he will co-operate in <lb/> every effort on behalf of <lb/> your husband   JM   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>