<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2728">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Tate to his mother, Millicent Tate (née Farren), 1 June, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Tate</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Tate to his mother in which Take is concerned with the health of his family at home. He describes life in Pakistan: the arrival of a military colleague, a forthcoming trip, and the completion of a new bomb. 

Alec C Tate served with British army in India before he married Millicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. James spent the majority of the war in India during which time the Indian Expeditionary Force was dispatched to Mesopotamia. This letter is part of a collection that he wrote to his parents detailing his movements and his day to day experience.


</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Tate Papers, D2859/2/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2728</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0347">James Tate</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0744">The Club, Rawal Pindi, Pakistan</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Millicent Tate</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1676">Slieve na Failthe, Whiteabbey, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2728_img_2149_1"  type="Letter"  url="b3a711c22625d6e3cefb243cd72beb4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2728_img_2149_2"  type="Letter"  url="1032807eeedcd79f99caf7c2d4f1d859.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2728_img_2149_3"  type="Letter"  url="bd5f6c2143f73ef587457149635f96f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2728_img_2149_4"  type="Letter"  url="dac6f37d8d834178eef90b31fb00a198.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2728_img_2149_5"  type="Envelope"  url="3b86a56f728ed339b0769ec4f3f4263b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2728_img_2149_6"  type="Envelope"  url="a56b6a3801287935f9344adee0045b22.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2728_img_2149_1"/>
             The Club RawalPindi   Thursday 1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> June 16   My dear Mother   Thank you very much for your letter <lb/>which I got last mail. I am <lb/>very sorry to hear about Baby <lb/>and I hope she is getting on <lb/>well. I got a letter from uncle <lb/>Bav this week &amp; he says <seg type="del">you</seg>  the kids  <lb/>have all got whooping cough
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2728_img_2149_2"/>
            <sic>wether</sic> this includes Phillis or not <lb/>I don't know. Anyway you must <lb/>have your hands full. Billy <lb/>arrived here on Tuesday from <lb/>Peshawar. He was on his way <lb/>to Murree to see the dentist <lb/>went off on Wednesday afternoon <lb/>&amp; I expect him back any time <lb/>this evening. He seems to be
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2728_img_2149_3"/>
            in great form. And is still recruiting. <lb/>I am going up to Gharial on Saturday <lb/>for a fortnight. I have heard no <lb/>more about my going on active <lb/>service but may do any day <lb/>now. I have not been able to <lb/>get a syce yet but have <lb/>got a bearer <sic>allright.</sic>   P.M.<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> do not like going to the
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2728_img_2149_4"/>
            Persian Gulf at all.   Bits of the new pumping engine <lb/>have arrived but not enough <lb/>to make any show. The new <lb/>bomb is nearly finished. Prince <lb/>has sent two <sic>dummys</sic> up to <lb/>the division. He wanted to show it <lb/>to Billy but he retired behind <lb/>a pillar &amp; said he would rather <lb/>not as I had helped to make <lb/>it. I hope all the invalides are getting <lb/>on well. With love to all from your <lb/>loving son   Jimmy 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2728_img_2149_5"/>
             Mrs. A. C. Tate <lb/>Slieve-na-Failthé <lb/>Whiteabbey <lb/>Co Antrim <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2728_img_2149_6"/>
             RAWAL PINDI CLUB. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>