<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1019">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Postcard from Eileen Corrigan to her mother, Mrs Corrigan, 24 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eileen Corrigan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This postcard was written by Eileen Corrigan (d. 1993) to her mother. Eileen had arrived in Dublin on 24 April 1916, the first day of the Easter Rising, from Belfast to sit her exams in the Trinity College and wrote this note to her mother in order to let her know that communication for Dublin had stopped but that she had arrived safely. Eileen Corrigan was one of just four female students who sat their exams as the Easter Rising progressed outside Trinity&#39;s walls. They were rewarded with lunch in Provost Mahafy&#39;s house hosted by his wife, Frances Letitia.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, TCD MS 3987a/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1019</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0901">Eileen Corrigan</persName>
              <date>1916-04-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs Corrigan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1949">Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1019_img_289_1"  type="Letter"  url="2121798b8c459d5f925b3e614d40b131.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1019_img_289_2"  type="Letter"  url="32dcb72f6622936257d029657b5ca0c9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1019_img_289_1"/>
                  Rathmines    Dublin   Y.W.C.A.    24th April  1916     Just a line to let you know <lb/> I arrived safely, in case the <lb/> papers should make you <lb/> anxious. All communication <lb/> is stopped from Dublin <lb/> but a lady promised to <lb/> post this tomorrow from <lb/>the North. Everything will <lb/> probably be all right <lb/> tomorrow, as the military <lb/> are coming from Curragh. <seg type="closer"> With love  Frog. </seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1019_img_289_2"/>
                 Mrs Corrigan  The Manse,  Green Road,  <hi rend="underline">Knock</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Belfast</hi>     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>