<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0390">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Henry A Robinson to Robert Chalmers, 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry A. Robinson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Henry A Robinson (1857-1927) to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). The letter concerns Sir Thomas J. Stafford (1857-1935), 1st baronet, doctor and medical commissioner of the Local Government Board of Ireland, who has been unable to work due to ill health. Stafford has missed considerable periods of work (twelve months in the last four years). Robinson writes to inquire about what pay, if any, Stafford should receive due to his being absence because of a recent operation. Sir Henry Augustus Robinson was an Irish public servant. He was primarily responsible for the drafting and implementation of the local government act of 1898, and shortly before the bill became law was appointed vice-president of the Local Government Board.Robert Chalmers was the under-secretary for Ireland. Chalmers became under-secretary for a brief period following the resignation of Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) following the 1916 Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5613/9101/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/390</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1440">Henry A. Robinson</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1501">Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0390_img_1653_1"  type="Letter"  url="5ce20399dd4856e08553efe1692692a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0390_img_1653_2"  type="Letter"  url="ef2a2ba26d1714c9e7e5f531a79a8a71.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0390_img_1653_1"/>
                Local Government Board, Dublin.    29th May, 1916   No. 60/M/1916. Office.  Sir,   I desire to bring under the notice of Their <lb/>Excellencies the Lords Justices and The Lords <lb/>Commissioners of His Majesty's Treasury the case <lb/>of Sir Thomas J. Stafford, Bart., C.B. , etc., Medical <lb/>Commissioner of the Local Government Board for <lb/>Ireland, who is at the present time absent from duty <lb/>on sick leave.  During the past four years St Thomas Stafford, <lb/>owing to the state of his health, has been compelled <lb/>to be absent from duty for considerable periods, and <lb/>from 1st July, 1912 to the 31st December, 1912 he <lb/>was so absent on full pay. From the 1st January, 1913 <lb/>to the 31st January, 1913 he was placed on half pay, <lb/>and resumed duty on the 1st February, 1913. Later in <lb/>that year, as his health was unsatisfactory, Sir Thomas <lb/>Stafford was again unable to perform his duties, and <lb/>he was on leave of absence on <hi rend="underline">half</hi> pay from the 1st <lb/>September, 1913 to the 31st January, 1914, when he again <lb/>returned to the Office.  Sir Thomas Stafford had to undergo an operation <lb/>for appendicitis on the 5th April, ultimo, and, although <lb/>now convalescent, is not yet able to resume duty. As <lb/>his sick leave amounts in the aggregate to twelve months <lb/>during the past four years it is necessary, under <lb/> Article  The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle.  Under Secretary <lb/>May a copy of this <lb/>letter be sent to the <lb/>Treasury for directions? <lb/>J.L. <lb/>29.V.16.  Yes, giving date <lb/>of his birth, <lb/>RC 30/5/16  Copied Rd. 31/5  Date of birth- <lb/>3rd May,1857.  Done &amp; Copied <lb/>MP. <lb/>31/5  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0390_img_1653_2"/>
              Article 19 (4) of the Order in Council of 10th January, <lb/>1910, to report the matter to Their Lordships to decide <lb/>what payment ( if any) in respect of salary shall be made <lb/>to him during the present period of sick leave.  Sir Thomas Stafford entered the service as a Medical <lb/>Inspector of the Board on the 3rd February, 1890 and has <lb/>therefore completed twentysix years service, and is entitled <lb/>under the Treasury Warrant to seven added years. His <lb/>pensionable service is therefore thirty three years, and, <lb/>as he did not adopt the provisions of the Superannuation <lb/>Act, 1909, in the event of retirement, his full pension <lb/>would amount to 33/60ths of £1,200, his present salary as <lb/>Medical Commissioner, of which he has been in receipt <lb/> since the 5 May, 1902.  I suggest for Their Lordships' consideration that <lb/>half pay, (£600 a year), might be allowed to the Medical <lb/>Commissioner as from the 5th April until he is able to <lb/>return to duty, which he hopes to do in a few weeks. In <lb/>the meantime his duties are discharged during his absence <lb/>by one of the Medical Inspectors.  I desire to add that the Office of Medical Commissioner <lb/> is a statutory one and, in the event of Sir Thomas Stafford's <lb/>retiring from the service, a successor would have to be <lb/>appointed by the Crown. <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  HA <hi rend="underline">Robinson</hi> <lb/>Vice President.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>