<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0857">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 21 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender thanks Lillian for gifts she has recently sent him, but protests that he does not need &#39;luxuries&#39; as a sign of her affection. He briefly mentions the internal politics of the staff of his office, expresses regret that he is due to dine with the 7th Division, fourteen miles away, and wishes for news of his brother Rex. He gives many details of the &#39;fearful complications that have risen in regard to leave&#39;, and discusses his and Lillian&#39;s own plans for his time off.Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/115</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/857</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0857_img_2417_1"  type="Letter"  url="d8b083fa1ebb8cafed036f3eb4b41e5f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0857_img_2417_2"  type="Letter"  url="c1ef7fadc5ea45a467f3b5a215669807.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0857_img_2417_1"/>
                21 Dec 15   My Pr   As usual no Sunday letter from you but luckily one from Mater <lb/>which <hi rend="underline">of course</hi> makes a good substitute! Your fruit has come, whilst I <lb/>tender thanks to the pr, I ought also to scold her, as these <hi rend="underline">luxuries</hi>are not <lb/>required by a bw in present conditions, &amp; he has no need of these signs of <lb/>a pr's affection. If circumstances change I won't hesitate to let you know.   Really the Genl has the most unfortunate way of putting things. <lb/> He said to Russell last night 'If by any chance you are going to the <lb/>office after dinner you might....' As Russell never by any chance <lb/>misses going there for  2 to  3 hours this was not the way to put it. R is <lb/>too much inclined to take up a defensive half apologetic attitude with <lb/>him &amp; it does not do.   Tonight I am to dine with the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div 14 miles away. I <lb/>wish I could have got out of it, especially as it is very wet.   I wish I could hear more about Rex's movement's. Except <lb/>for strange references in Mater's letter I know nothing.   Fearful complications have arisen in regard to leave! <lb/>If one goes to Ireland one gets an extra day. Singleton who<lb/> wants to go with me intends to go to Ireland in order to do this, <lb/> &amp; he wants me to do the same ! If I don't I shall presumably<lb/> have to find my way back by a long Rl journey instead of by<lb/> motor. I hardly think it good enough to go to Ireland merely<lb/> to get the extra day even with one's ticket paid for  <hi rend="underline">unless I go to see Rex!</hi>  The arrangements  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0857_img_2417_2"/>
              are as follows.  Arrive Victoria 7.30 <hi rend="superscript">pm</hi> 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi><lb/> Leave ' 8 AM 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>if I go to Ireland <lb/> 8 AM 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>if I don't go to Ireland. <lb/>You can decide this for me!  I will <hi rend="underline">not</hi> take the extra day unless I go to Ireland, but <lb/> am quite prepared to go there by morning train &amp; return by <lb/>next night train, if thought worth while, especially as it costs  neither me nor <lb/>the Govt nothing. You must however let me know by the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.  As regards our own plans I will fit in with anything <lb/>you like - London the whole time, I of Wight (? <seg type="unclear">Freshwater</seg> ) <lb/>or some South Coast town -  ? Chisilbeach  - Ireland -  Devonshire  but you must square the <lb/> family. Poor overworked Pr, but it is no use my trying <lb/>to make plans here. Some of the plans you can leave <lb/>till I come back  if you wish as long as you settle the main question<lb/>about Ireland.  I will try to write a family letter on the <lb/>subject of my experiences at the front.  <seg type="closer"> Your b w  Wilfred B Spender   21 Dec 15  </seg><seg type="postscript"> Mrs N has wired something about a 'ball' this may change all the <lb/>leave proposals totally, making me a week or more later ! </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>