<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2680">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. M. Carroll to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 1 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. M. Carroll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by M. M. Carroll to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 until his death.

In this letter Carroll congratulates O’Dwyer on his correspondence with General Maxwell (1859 – 1929). This includes the most renowned of the letters written to Maxwell on 17 May 1916 in which O’Dwyer  described the General as a &#39;military dictator&#39; and denounced the execution of the Easter Rising&#39;s leaders ‘in cold blood’. The Bishop also criticised the deportation of thousands of suspects without trial and declared Maxwell&#39;s regime ‘one of the worst and blackest chapters in the history of the misgovernment of this country’.

Carroll states that she is proud to know that there is someone to stand by them at such a terrible time and expresses sympathy for the poor fellows that died heroes.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/M/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2680</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0471">M. M. Carroll</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2680_img_2102_1"  type="Letter"  url="6dec0681f137757baaf92c7fea31bee2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2680_img_2102_2"  type="Letter"  url="608d3f118fcc27ca4c102a75d4e91043.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2680_img_2102_3"  type="Letter"  url="da2899aed60ba3c6949a193c2d4cb974.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2680_img_2102_1"/>
             E. COCQUEREL &amp; SONS, LTD.<lb/>LONDON &amp; PARIS,<lb/>2, MARY ST., DUBLIN,<lb/>20 GRESHAM ST., BELFAST.<lb/>Head Offices {128-130, Commercial St.,<lb/>LONDON, E.   June 1 1916,   To the most Rev E T O'Dwyer<lb/>Bishop of Limerick   Rev Dear Father   Will you allow<lb/>me to congratulate you<lb/>on your lovely letter<lb/>in this weeks Irish Times<lb/>as a Catholic Business<lb/>Girl &amp; many more of<lb/>my Girls friends are<lb/>proud to know<lb/>that we have some<lb/>one to stand by us<lb/>at such a terrible 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2680_img_2102_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">2</hi> time, in sympathy<lb/>with the poor fellows<lb/>that died Heroes.<lb/>we don't forget<lb/>your letter that<lb/>that appeared Re the<lb/>Irish emigrants.  May God spare you<lb/>&amp; God love<lb/>Ireland.<lb/>&amp; hope You will excuse<lb/>me for intruding &amp;<lb/>taking the liberty of<lb/>writing you. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2680_img_2102_3"/>
             I am Rev Dear Father<lb/>Yours Respectfully<lb/>M M Carroll<lb/><sic>Managress</sic> of the above<lb/>establishment  <lb/>To the Most Rev Dr O'Dwyer<lb/>Bishop of Limerick 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>