<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1034">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Labour Party of Bruff, Co. Limerick to British PM H.H. Asquith, February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Labour Party of Bruff</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Labour Party of Bruff, Co. Limerick to British Prime Minister Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928). The letter requests that the British government amend the Labourers Ireland Act, ensuring that each Irish labourer that volunteered in the British army would get a cottage and 10 acres of land; a fair award for &#39;those heroes who are fighting to protect the integrity of the British Empire from Common foe.&#39;The Labourers (Ireland) Act of 1911 secured funding for the erection of 5000 cottages around Ireland. Herbert Henry Asquith was Liberal Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1908 to 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO/RP/1916/3610/3, NAI_CSO/RP/1916/3610/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1034</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0589">Labour Party of Bruff</persName>
              <date>1916-02-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0899">Bruff, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">H.H. Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1034_img_303_1"  type="Letter"  url="a2a088486d40c11e485255d6a1f3cf7b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1034_img_303_1"/>
                20.2.1916    Labour Assembly Room Bruff    To the RT. Hon. H.H. Asquith, K.C.M.P.   My Lord   At a meeting of the Labour Party <lb/>of Bruff, Co.Limerick, the following <lb/>resolution was unanimously adopted on <lb/>the proposal of Mr.John F.Osborne, Pres. <lb/>and member of the I.L.L.A. of all <lb/>Ireland :— 'That we call on the Prime <lb/>Minister of England, most respectfully, <lb/>to amend the Labourers Ireland Act, <lb/>through the channels of legislation, to <lb/>give each labourer who volunteered <lb/>under Lord Kitchener's appeal to the <lb/>young men of Ireland, a cottage and <lb/>ten acres of land — those heroes who <lb/>are fighting to protect the integrity of <lb/>the British Empire from Common foe.   office <lb/>1919 P.S. 31/1 <lb/>Mr Brennan <lb/>Have you file 1919? <lb/>IOML <lb/>28/2   Mr Connolly <lb/>1919 was <lb/>dealt with <lb/>by the US <lb/>&amp; was never <lb/>put away in <lb/>the Registry  <lb/>29.2.16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>