<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0684">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Clara Mary Davidson, 21 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson (1877-1916) to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.James Davidson writes of news from home, &#39;Kathleen&#39;s baby&#39; and his father&#39;s promise to send pistols. He has had a very busy time with administrative duties since the Brigade left for the trenches. James writes of the constant movement of his Brigade and refers to them being put into a different Corps. He is of the opinion that &#39;they are doing their best to destroy the individuality of the Division&#39;. He is grateful for warm clothes as it was near freezing, and writes about other parcels received from home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/684</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-21</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_1"  type="Letter"  url="f420b93a5a441cc0635c520cee61742b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_2"  type="Letter"  url="3cb19ed6bc3973be72f575d6b6b5b9b6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_3"  type="Letter"  url="59ab4c67846aacbe0cbebc2ef71d43e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_4"  type="Letter"  url="756870adbca1854543c2a4e9f662462e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_5"  type="Letter"  url="e583edfa4ee6b1691ae75c282aeb876c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_6"  type="Letter"  url="90db20bbb4c7e54b43e1bc11d466c394.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0684_img_2176_7"  type="Envelope"  url="8e92748255abc02d70b6191f6aad4780.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_1"/>
                21/11/15   My Dearest Mother   Since I wrote you <lb/> on Tues. last I have had your welcome <lb/> letters of 10<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> 12<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> &amp; 15<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>. I was so <lb/> pleased to hear all the news about <lb/> Kathleen's dear little Baby &amp; it is <lb/> splendid that both are doing so <lb/> well. I have also had 2 letters <lb/> from Father dated 10<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> &amp; 13<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> &amp; would <lb/> you please give him my best thanks <lb/> for them for I might not have time to <lb/> write again for several days &amp; it is <lb/> now getting late. I was so interested <lb/> in all the particulars he gave me <lb/> about the pistol &amp; forward to <lb/> the first few arriving out here.  I was speaking the other day about <lb/> the pistol to the Brigadier &amp; as he <lb/> said 'that is just the thing we  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_2"/>
              require — something which will fill the <lb/> gaps between Hand Grenades &amp; <lb/> Artillery' It certainly looks as if <lb/>the Pistol would do so. I have <lb/> been having a very busy time of it <lb/> since the Brigade left for the trenches, <lb/> as there is a lot of office work to do <lb/> looking after all these Details &amp; then <lb/> in addition there is the supervision <lb/> of the Machine Gun training. Today <lb/> (Sunday) the men had a day off, <lb/> but I spent practically the whole <lb/> time in the office making up all <lb/>kinds of returns &amp; answering letters <lb/>&amp;c. It seems almost certain <lb/> now that we shall be moving from <lb/> here this week to some new <lb/>centre where the Brigade will join <lb/> us on leaving the trenches, as we <lb/> are apparently to be put into a <lb/> different Corps. It looks as  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_3"/>
              if they could not make up their minds <lb/> what to do with the Ulster Division the <lb/> way they push us about. They are <lb/> certainly doing their best to destroy the <lb/> individuality of the Divisions as one <lb/> Brigade has already been cut off &amp; <lb/> another one put in its place. Then <lb/> one of the Batts of this Brigade has been <lb/> taken away to another one &amp; we have <lb/> got a Batt of Lancs Fus. instead. <lb/> It is rather bad policy I should think <lb/> but we have all long ago ceased to <lb/> be surprised at anything that happens <lb/>in the Division. I only hope at <lb/> present that any move on our part <lb/> will be delayed till after the Brigade <lb/> returns, for if we have to go before <lb/> then, I shall have an awful time <lb/> with all these Details in connection <lb/> with billeting &amp; getting the huge amount <lb/> of stores left behind transported.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_4"/>
              The day after I last wrote we had more <lb/> snow which was followed by rain, then <lb/> frost &amp; today it was just a little above <lb/> freezing point &amp; bitterly cold. Fortunately <lb/> the parcel with warm underclothes <lb/> came on Sat. &amp; I now feel a great <lb/> deal more comfortable.The summer <lb/> things I was wearing felt very light <lb/> but I partly made up for this by <lb/> wearing 2 waistcoats. And now <lb/> dear Mother I must thank you for <lb/> all the good things you sent me. <lb/> They all arrived by the same post <lb/> as the parcel of clothes &amp; nearly <lb/> filled a mail bag by themselves. <lb/> There were 2 from Foster green with <lb/> cakes &amp; sweets, 1 with butter which <lb/> arrived in splendid condition, <lb/> 1 shaving cream &amp; 1 toothpaste. <lb/> They came at a most opportune <lb/> time for on that evening we,  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_5"/>
              (that is the 3 Brigade officers remaining, <lb/> myself, the Signal &amp; Grenade officers) <lb/> gave a little dinner party to the <lb/>8 other officers in charge of the Details <lb/>&amp; the sweets, cakes &amp; fruit were <lb/>greatly appreciated. Next time <lb/> however Mother dear please don't <lb/> send so much in the sweet &amp; cake <lb/> line, I think there must have been <lb/> about 8 large boxes of sweets &amp; I <lb/> have had to give away a good <lb/> many as I could not possibly carry <lb/> them when we move, as we are about <lb/>to, this week. Hoffman for some <lb/> reason again sent a pot of shaving <lb/> cream instead of a tube. If he <lb/> had no tubes a stick of soap would <lb/> have been better as I have no room <lb/> in my pack for any bulky articles. <lb/> I shall want a small supply of <lb/> medicines before long to fill up my  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_6"/>
              little case but it will be time <lb/>enough when I write again &amp; <lb/>I will then send a list of what <lb/>I require. I shall be very <lb/>glad to receive the warm gloves <lb/>for the cold these days on the range <lb/>is awfully penetrating. The <lb/>poor chaps in the trenches must <lb/>have been having a very hard <lb/>time of it. I only hope that in <lb/>addition they have not had many <lb/>casualties. It is just midnight <lb/>so must come to a close. With <lb/>fondest love to all &amp; hoping to <lb/>have further good reports soon <lb/>of K &amp; baby <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  Jim </seg> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0684_img_2176_7"/>
              On active service <lb/>Recd 25<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>Nov 1915   Mrs S. C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  Ireland   21/11/15 <lb/>J Davidson  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>