<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4169">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/55</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4169</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4169_img_3541_1"  type="Letter"  url="40653013e8fbc2c827aa2791db97b65b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4169_img_3541_2"  type="Letter"  url="67bcbdf67e2cc68d151dc69cb1609b5b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4169_img_3541_1"/>
             12. Nov.   My p r   I hope this may reach you before you leave Banbury but if <lb/>not I expect then will be a letter awaiting you at 24 &amp; you won't miss much.   The p r is such an affectionate hitch creature that the b w came trembl— <lb/>ing off his stilts &amp; I am not sure if he did not succeed in barking <lb/>his hands in doing so. He quite expected the p r to get up on stilts too, <lb/>when put c/o Miss Deane, &amp; thought it would be rather fun to see her <lb/>then, instead of that she comes alongside frisking looking very small, &amp; <lb/>coaxes him down.   Your letter to the professor is A1, but for these days methinks <lb/>it is a hitch too humble, tho much to the point &amp; businesslike. The <lb/>b w would many years ago perhaps have written like that, but now he <lb/>would certainly have stated "was to have been appointed chief assistant <lb/>to...., when waylaid by a wild animal, &amp; carried off into the <lb/>wild of Ulster.    I look forward to the answer &amp; wonder how you can manage <lb/>it, &amp; where you will live. St   is not an ideal centre to <lb/>get away from, &amp; I can see a very scared little p r running up the steps <lb/>from Kings +, &amp; a very tired p r going down them.    There is not much news. The 107 Bd appears to have got <lb/>rather a bad name for <sic>slackners</sic> in the trenches, not fear but lack <lb/>of care in rebuilding &amp; a general tendency to <seg type="unclear">idleness</seg>. Consequently the other <lb/>have to go back for another fortnight's instruction. I hope to arrange <lb/>to go up for another 2 or 3 days but shall not much bother about <lb/>the night work this time.   No Allenby has not succeeded Conchman (!) but as you will see in
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4169_img_3541_2"/>
            the paper has followed <seg type="unclear">Munro</seg>.  (who has gone to Servia) as Commander of an army. Conchman's success <lb/>is Withycombe, which sounds Cornish. There will be further <lb/>changes in the 107 Bch &amp; I am afraid not without reason, but as <lb/>the new CO. will probably be boys with 5 years service, it isn't <lb/>much use as a reek. Connyn is AAQMG now.    For some minutes yesterday I was cogitating applying for a battalion <lb/>but Russell tells me that no psc office required on the staff would be <lb/>allowed to go to Reg' duty, &amp; as a report has gone in that R &amp; I are <lb/>satisfactory I cannot go now even if I want to apparently! Really <lb/>tis a strange world &amp; I do look forward to the time when one can <lb/>regain one's liberty once more.    The watch so far has behaved perfectly. I was a little <lb/>sniffy at first as the price seemed to cheap for a good antich, but <lb/>I am beginning to think the pr may have been rather clever — <lb/>not quite the first time either! — It is perfect at night in showing up <lb/>very well.   Glad your cold is gone. I think I have another as <lb/>the result of my yesterday's boast.   Would you have behind that Singhton is almost if not <lb/>quite a professional on the piano, &amp; a la Corny Grain. I have not <lb/>heard him  but other say so . His boy of 10 can play <hi rend="underline">anything</hi> at sight.   I shall be much surprised if K does not take command <lb/>in the East.   Goodbye to a very dear pr from her b w    Wilfrid B. Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>