<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4383">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Clerk of the Crown and Peace, County Dublin, to Robert Chalmers, 21 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Clerk of the Crown and Peace, County Dublin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by the Clerk of Crown and Peace, County Dublin to the Under-Secretary, Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938).  In this letter, the County Clerk writes to Chalmers to confirm the appointment of the Justices of Peace on the Joint Visiting Committee for Mountjoy Prison.

Sir Robert Chalmers was appointed Under-Secretary of Ireland in 1916, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the Easter Rising. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers 1916, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10531</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4383</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0154">Clerk of the Crown and Peace, County Dublin</persName>
              <date>1916-06-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0860">Green Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4383_img_3737_1"  type="Letter"  url="999369c7b4dbea40e717037993a228f3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4383_img_3737_1"/>
             <lb/>Ref. No. 8983-15  21st June 1916.   Sir,   In to you Circular letter of the 24th. May last,<lb/>I beg to say that the Grand Jury, at the last County Commission<lb/>Court, appointed on the Joint Visiting Committee for Mountjoy<lb/>Prison, the Justice of the Peace whose names are set out on the<lb/>enclosed form.  I am, Sir,<lb/>Your obedient servant  <seg type="unclear">Illegible signature</seg><lb/>Clerk of the Crown and Peace.  Thomas L. Plunkett D.L<lb/>Portmarnock House, Baldoyle<lb/>Thomas Clarke<lb/>28 Belgrave Sq. Monkstown<lb/>William Bobbett<lb/>Hansfield House, Clonsilla<lb/>Charles Stonwell, 22 Clyde Road, Dublin   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>