<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4704">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Phelps to the Secretary of John Hopkin's Press, 19 January 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Gunther Justin Phelps</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Robert Gunther Justin Phelps (b. 1876) served as librarian to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland from 1897.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-207</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4704</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0781">Robert Gunther Justin Phelps</persName>
              <date>1917-01-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0844">Baltimore, Maryland, United States of America</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4704_img_4041_1"  type="Letter"  url="6d49f34a7d9f6c84f2120289bf4a39d6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4704_img_4041_1"/>
             19th JANUARY 17.   The Secretary, <lb/>Johns Hopkins Press, <lb/>Baltimore, Md.   Dear Sir,   In your letter of the 9th Dec., ult., I regret to find my <lb/>request for a copy of the October 1914 No., of the American <lb/>Journal of Insanity mentioned as a complaint indeed it <lb/>was no such thing. From the Editor of the Dublin Journal of <lb/>Med. Science this Library <sic>receivesa</sic> copy of the Journal and <lb/>the volumes are bound for reference. This being the only <lb/>Medical Library in Ireland where a file of the Journal can <lb/>be got for reference I hope that the Editor will grant a copy <lb/>of the issue so as to keep the file complete   Trusting that you will understand that I was making no <lb/>complaint in this matter and will receive ny <seg type="del">p</seg> apologies <lb/>for any annoyance caused,   I remain, Dea Sir, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Librarian.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>