<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5386">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from K. Casey to Willie Daly, October 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author> K. Casey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/7/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5386</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0171"> K. Casey</persName>
              <date>1923-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0531">Roxboro, Co Limerick, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Willie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1460">Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5386_img_4671_1"  type="Letter"  url="0212c1401f2c07224774c8758371f8c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5386_img_4671_2"  type="Letter"  url="a4920957bef4bfd72059550272fc9824.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5386_img_4671_3"  type="Letter"  url="7f8ed4cc43c4c38b8359be7a0601554b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5386_img_4671_4"  type="Letter"  url="d088760c30822cb171be4b9002fdf39f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5386_img_4671_1"/>
             I got<lb/>the address<lb/>when I had<lb/>this letter written  P41/1/15   Roxboro <lb/> Oct 24th    My Dear Willie,   It is about<lb/>time that I should think<lb/>of you in fact I am a long<lb/>time thinking of writing to you<lb/>I am sure you felt bad about<lb/>poor Charlie he is in heaven<lb/>I hope I am sure that it is all the<lb/>good people that is done to<lb/>death our Lord had to suffer<lb/>for our sins &amp; he forgave his<lb/>enemies I did not see your mother<lb/>or father since the election I am<lb/>sure you felt delighted to have 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5386_img_4671_2"/>
             cousin John get elected<lb/>our <seg type="unclear">pricts</seg>  pulled well for<lb/>him all the same he did<lb/>not get too many votes in<lb/>this parish do you hear<lb/>often from Tom &amp; is he getting<lb/>on good. I am sure he is not<lb/>in one camp with you. It was<lb/>a very bad summer.<seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg>   <lb/>is asking for the turf every<lb/>sunday I suppose he is getting<lb/>very cold. You heard <seg type="unclear"> questionable reading </seg> <lb/>got married to May at<lb/><seg type="unclear">Patrick O'Sullivans</seg>. Dan<lb/>took a trip away since<lb/>you left he is much improved     
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5386_img_4671_3"/>
             I hope you will be coming<lb/>home when this letter will<lb/>reach you as a many are<lb/>leaving out &amp; some are<lb/>arresting as well Cronin<lb/>at <seg type="unclear">Brachil   </seg>was taken last<lb/>sunday. Nealy   Curtin was<lb/>left home I am sending<lb/>you some cigarettes I hope<lb/>you will get  them  alright I had<lb/>not your address so I put<lb/>on Peter Costeloes name<lb/>Hoping you are good.<lb/> From K. Casey <lb/>   Roxboro   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5386_img_4671_4"/>
             I am sending you your double<lb/>packages of fags I hope<lb/>the government will soon<lb/>leave ye out as your   is<lb/>preaching to girls get<lb/>married at 14 years &amp;<lb/>boys at 17 so he ought<lb/>speak for our prisoners<lb/>to release them &amp; marry<lb/>them he would make<lb/>a little penny as the<lb/>times is very bad with<lb/>him no pigs or cattle<lb/>buying only for a little<lb/>butter.<lb/> Goodbye from Conn <lb/> K. Casey   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>