<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1091">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Sir Arthur Stanley from Dr Steevens' Hospital Board, 31 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Sir Arthur Stanley expressing the support of Doctor Steeven&#39;s Hosptial for the proposed college of nursing. However, the letter also states that approval of the scheme cannot be granted by the hospital until the details of the scheme have been properly considered. Enclosed with the letter is a list of general principles the hospital considers essential to the success of any such college. Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>TPCK-2-6-1-2, TPCK-2-6-1-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1091</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-01-31</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0219">Sir Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1091_img_3242_1"  type="Letter"  url="bf37e795f0810bac0ed28c37e132df1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1091_img_3242_2"  type="Letter"  url="824e7ec174405d48d73465d2d54c1ad1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1091_img_3242_3"  type="Letter"  url="b39bf04b2c6f711bc16625f12a670e0f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1091_img_3242_4"  type="Letter"  url="d3023fb5f6049a6b6b299a785dbd9be3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1091_img_3242_1"/>
               Dear Sir.   Your letter of December 30, 1915 <hi rend="underline">re</hi>the foundation of a College of Nursing, together with a report on the matter prepared by Dr Kirkpatrick, were considered by the Board of this Hospital at the meeting on February 22, 1916.   I am directed to inform you that the Board of Doctor Steevens' Hospital are anxious to consider favourably any scheme for the better organisation and training of nurses. While, however, it appears probable that the proposed College may effect this desired end my Board is unable to express any approval of it until opportunity has been given of considering the scheme in more detail than is at present possible.  I am desired further to submit for your consideration the following general principles which my Board considers are essential to the success of any such College as is proposed.  Should the scheme be developed further my Board will be glad to give it a very careful consideration. <seg type="closer"> Yours etc   To The Hon. Arthur Stanley, M.P., M.V.O.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1091_img_3242_2"/>
              Principles suggested by the Board of Doctor Steevens' Hospital <lb/>as essential in the foundation of the proposed College of <lb/>Nursing.   1. The Executive Board for the management of the College <lb/>should be largely in the hands of elected representatives of <lb/>the trained nurses themselves, and should also be respresentat — <lb/>ive of the various parts of the United Kingdom.   2. The relations that are to exist between this <lb/>Executive Board of Management and the General Council of the <lb/>College must be carefully defined so as to protect as far as <lb/>possible the various interest concerned.   3. The certificates of the college should be given only to <lb/>those nurses who have undergone a satisfactory course of <lb/>Hospital training, and passed the requisite examinations of <lb/>the College.   4. The minimum period of the curriculum, and also the size <lb/> of the Hospital where the training of the nurses is to be <lb/> carried out should be satisfactory.   5. Local centres for the training and the examination of <lb/>the Irish, Scotch, and Provincial nurses must be established <lb/>by the college. The teachers in such local centers should be <lb/>appointed by the Executive Board of the College.   6. The Board of Examiners that is to conduct the final <lb/>examinations of the College must be so constituted as not to <lb/>give undue preference to any centre for teaching and <lb/>examination.   7. All training schools recognized by the College must <lb/>rigidly satisfy the minimum requirements of the College, or <lb/>be struck off the list of recognised schools. Frequent and <lb/>efficient inspection of the schools will be necessary to <lb/>attain this object. Every facility should be extended to those <lb/>schools that do satisfy the requirements of the College, and  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1091_img_3242_3"/>
              that desire to be recognized by the College.   8. It should be an object of the College to protect the <lb/>regularly trained nurse in every possible way from the unfair <lb/>competition of those who have not submitted themselves to <lb/>such training.   9. Provision should be made for recognition by the <lb/>College of those nurses in practice at the time of the <lb/>foundation of the College.   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1091_img_3242_4"/>
              Letter from Steevens <lb/>to Mr Stanley <lb/>with suggestions re College.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>