<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0473">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peggie O'Sullivan, Birmingham, to James Ryan, 1 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peggie O&#39;Sullivan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Peggie O&#39;Sullivan to James Ryan (1891-1970). O&#39;Sullivan writes from Birmingham shortly after Ryan had been moved from Stafford to Frongach. She offers to send a parcel and asks what Ryan would like to receive. She also enquires about conditions in Frongach and suggests sewing sand bags as a &#39;splendid organisation&#39; and a &#39;great nerve sorter&#39;.James Ryan studied medicine at University College Dublin. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch, and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, Collection P88</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/473</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0027">Peggie O&#39;Sullivan</persName>
              <date>1916-07-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1191">99 Ashted Row, Birmingham, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0851">Frongach Detention Camp, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0473_img_182_1"  type="Letter"  url="b158ff8e0ab8952fc6117e2d518278ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0473_img_182_2"  type="Letter"  url="45c9e97c33e9846d5019a3eaaca532f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0473_img_182_3"  type="Letter"  url="de37d00da4339422132e8d07def875a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0473_img_182_1"/>
                99 Ashted Row  Birmingham    July 1 1916.   <seg type="foreign">A chara</seg>   First of all. I hope you got the roses safely<lb/> &amp; that they were not too faded. I hope the extreme<lb/> language in the note did not shock you. I really <lb/>think you were let off lightly because yours<lb/> was the first I tied up. As we went on<lb/> we wrote worse &amp; worse things. Ask some of<lb/> the boys to show them to you if they have not <lb/>already done so.  This will be very tame as I've<lb/> only just got up. On Saturday morning we<lb/> stay in bed till 12 o'clock or so, have breakfast<lb/> in bed about 10 &amp; our correspondence. So you <lb/>will see that I am not fully awake yet.<lb/> I had a card from Mortimer this morning.<lb/> I hope to have the pleasure of printing some<lb/> of these snaps soon. As soon as you can, <lb/>write &amp; let me know, if there is anything<lb/><sic>atall</sic> you want. Which do you prefer <lb/>cigarettes or a pipe &amp; tobacco. We shall  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0473_img_182_2"/>
              send a parcel from the 6 of us soon &amp; I <lb/>would like to know what you really need &amp; <lb/> what you wish for. Do be sensible &amp; let <lb/> us know, <seg type="del">wh</seg> because it is a work of <seg type="unclear">grad</seg><lb/> on our part, &amp; we feel out of the running if we <lb/> cannot help you. Send a list, never mind <lb/> if it is long; all the better, &amp; put down <lb/> everything.  I was hoping that the weather <lb/> would be fine &amp; warm for you in Bala but <lb/> if we are having a specimen of it to day. <lb/> Its awful, cold, windy &amp; pouring rain. <lb/> We heard that you all looked grand going <lb/> to the station, fitted out with <hi rend="underline">tailor-fitted</hi><lb/>overcoats &amp; hand sewn boots. Two of the <lb/> girls went on Thursday. We were fearfully <lb/>disappointed. I would love to be there to give <lb/> a cheer &amp; join the singing. Did you have a <lb/> march at the other end. I hope you had a <lb/> nice <hi rend="underline">tea</hi> waiting for you at the final. Are <lb/> there many soldiers on guard &amp; how do <lb/> you get your meals? Have you any work <lb/> to do? Sewing up sand bags is a splendid <lb/> occupation &amp; is a great nerve <sic>sorther</sic><lb/> especially if the needle goes in your finger  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0473_img_182_3"/>
              half an inch.  I hope you don't think I am forward <lb/> in writing to you. But, I imagine that a letter <lb/> would cheer you up when an exile or rather <lb/> an untried prisoner. All the others send their <lb/> best love &amp; hope to see you in 4 weeks time.<lb/> We are sorry that you have left Stafford in a way. <lb/>We quite miss our weekly visits to the gaol. <lb/> I never thought I would ever be a visitor to <lb/> such a place. But it quite lost its horror for <lb/> me to hear the musical ring of the voice &amp; <lb/> the laughter that can't be squashed.  Hoping to hear soon. Don't forget <lb/> to mention what you would like  <seg type="closer"> Love &amp; best wishes from   Peggie O'Sullivan </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>