<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3399">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M C Seton to Robert Chalmers, 5 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M C Seton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from M C Seton to Robert Chalmers asking for information concerning &#39;ex-military criminal lunatic James Coghlan&#39;.
Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-11536</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3399</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0066">M C Seton</persName>
              <date>1916-07-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2088">India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3399_img_2810_1"  type="Letter"  url="cc85cfd7d71a222b44307456c3deb6df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3399_img_2810_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="54d7ed7fa6f15f49787dc12cf54f2ff6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3399_img_2810_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="fa67600745b1e7b6f9a6085131718b20.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3399_img_2810_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="b685a206af50cc0a4eb382b97250cbd5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3399_img_2810_1"/>
             INDIA OFFICE, <lb/>WHITEHALL, <lb/>LONDON, S.W.    5 July 1916.   Sir,   With reference to Sir Edward O'Farrell's letter No. <lb/>20278 dated the 13th December last regarding the discharge <lb/>from the Dundrum Criminal Lunatic Asylum of the ex-military <lb/>criminal lunatic James Coghlan, I am directed by the <lb/>Secretary of State for India in Council to forward for <lb/>the information of their Excellencies the Lords Justices <lb/>copy of a despatch from the Government of India in which <lb/>they ask to be informed, with reference to the provisions <lb/>of sub-section 1 of section 10 of the Colonial Prisoners <lb/>Removal Act 1884, of the powers possessed by the authorities <lb/>in the United Kingdom with regard to the discharge of <lb/>European criminals removed from India and of the circumstances <lb/>in which these powers can be exercised.    Mr.Secretary Chamberlain would be glad to receive in <lb/>due course the observations of the Lords Justices on these <lb/>points.   A similar enquiry is being addressed to the Home Office <lb/> and the Scottish Office with regard to the cases of European <lb/>criminals removed to England and Wales and to Scotland, <lb/>respectively.   I have the honour to be, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   M.C. Seton   The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3399_img_2810_2"/>
            No. 8 OF 1916. <lb/>GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. <lb/>HOME DEPARTMENT. <lb/><hi rend="underline">MEDICAL.</hi> <lb/>Jails.  To <lb/>THE RIGHT HONOURABLE AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, <lb/>His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. <lb/>Simla,   the 25th May, 1916.   SIR,   We have the honour to invite a reference to your despatch no. 20 (Public), <lb/>dated the 4th February, 1916, forwarding certain papers regarding the discharge <lb/>from the Dundrum Lunatic Asylum of the criminal lunatic James Coghlan, <lb/>and in connection therewith to bring the following points to your notice.   2. James Coghlan was convicted of murder and sentenced to death by the <lb/>Punjab Chief Court in 1910. The sentence was commuted by order of the local <lb/>Government to one of penal servitude for life on the ground that the prisoner <lb/>had become insane, and had he remained in a lunatic asylum in India, he <lb/>would on becoming sane have been remanded to jail to serve the re- <lb/>mainder of his sentence. It is obviously undesirable that European criminals <lb/>sent home from India under the provisions of the Colonial Prisoners Removal <lb/>Act, 1884, should meet with appreciably more lenient treatment than they <lb/>would have received in India in common with other European and Indian <lb/>prisoners, and if, as appears to be the case, the authorities in the United <lb/>Kingdom have power to order the premature discharge of certain classes of <lb/>such prisoners without our knowledge or consent, we apprehend that it may be <lb/>necessary for us to exercise considerable caution in availing ourselves of our <lb/>powers under the Act. We would ask therefore, that we may be informed, <lb/>with reference to the provisions of sub-section 1 of section 10 of the Act, of the <lb/>powers possessed by the authorities in the United Kingdom in this respect and
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3399_img_2810_3"/>
            <lb/>of the circumstances in which these powers can be exercised. On receipt of <lb/>this information we will consider our position in the matter further.   We have the honour to be, <lb/>SIR, <lb/>Your most obedient, humble Servants,   CHELMSFORD. <lb/>BEAUCHAMP DUFF. <lb/>R. H. CRADDOCK. <lb/>W. S. MEYER. <lb/>C. H. A. HILL. <lb/>C. SANKARAN NAIR. <lb/>G. R. LOWNDES. <lb/>G. S. BARNES. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3399_img_2810_4"/>
            No. <lb/>GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. <lb/>HOME DEPARTMENT. <lb/><hi rend="underline">MEDICAL.</hi> <lb/>Jails. <lb/>No. 8, DATED SIMLA, THE 26TH MAY, 1916. <lb/>(Copy.)  LETTER TO HIS MAJESTY'S SECRETARY OF STATE <lb/>FOR INDIA   SUBJECT: <lb/>Discharge from the Dundrum Lunatic Asylum <lb/>of the criminal lunatic James Coghlan. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>