<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1104">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Rosamond Jacob, 10 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Rosamond Jacob regarding a number of topics from literature to suffrage. After thanking Jacob for her gift to his son Owen, Skeffington enquiries if there would be an opportunity for him to speak in Waterford on his impression of America. He mentions two stipulations for this service: he may say whatever he likes and he may receive donations for the Irish Citizen. Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916), journalist, was a prominent feminist, activist and co-founder of the Irish Women&#39;s Franchise league in 1908. In 1912, he and his wife, Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), founded the suffragist newspaper The Irish Citizen. A staunch pacifist and nationalist, Sheehy Skeffington opposed Irish involvement in the Great War. During the Easter Rising, he attempted to organise a civilian defence force to prevent looting and saved the life of a British officer under fire. Arrested on the evening of Tuesday 25 April 1916, Sheehy Skeffington and two other civilians were shot by firing squad on the morning of Wednesday 26 April.Rosamond Jacob (1888-1960) was a suffragist, republican, and writer. Jacob regarded the First World War as an imperial war, and she demonstrated against the recruitment campaigns. Though she joined Cumann na mBan she disparaged its quiescence towards Redmond, and was critical that the home rule bill contained no provisions for female suffrage.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47;, Ms 33,612/18-33</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1104</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-01-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Rosamond Jacob</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1104_img_3318_1"  type="Letter"  url="4b5e407dbd21e49cfec0058f5fcb1619.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1104_img_3318_1"/>
                11, Grosvenor Place,  Rathmines, Dublin.    10-I.-16.   Dear Miss Jacob,   Yes, my idea of Lancelot is taken from Malory. I discovered <lb/>Malory when I was very young,- about nine, I think, but certainly <lb/>before I was eleven, - and feasted on it for years. I shall have to <lb/>record it in my autobiography as one of the 'Books That Have Influ- <lb/>enced Life' in a high degree. Tennyson I read much later.  Owen Lancelot sends you an expression of thanks, - rather curt, <lb/>but all his corresponence is that. He is making good use of the <lb/>paints, which happily <sic>synchronised</sic> with the arrival of a new painting <lb/>book from America, - which<seg type="del">k</seg>, with my other things, was held up at <lb/>Liverpool for examination!  I am anxious to speak on my 'Impressions of America' in some <lb/>places outside of Dublin, with the double object of doing some pro- <lb/>paganda work and raising a little money for the IRISH CITIZEN, which, <lb/>as you will have seen, is sadly in need of fund. Would there be <lb/>any chance of my getting an opportunity to speak in Waterford? I <lb/>don't care under what auspices, provided (1) i am free to say what I <lb/>like, and (2) I get expenses and a donation from the proceeds for the <lb/>IRISH CITIZEN. I should be much obliges if you would consult with <lb/>any people in Waterford likely to be interested, and let me know <lb/>what are the prospects. <seg type="closer"> With all good wishes,  <hi rend="underline">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>