<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0248">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Blake &amp; Kenny to Sir Matthew Nathan, 29 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Blake &amp;amp; Kenny Solicitors</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Blake and Kenny Solicitors Est. 1892 on behalf of Michael Connolly (b.1885) to Sir Matthew Nathan. In the letter Blake &amp;amp; Kenny state that they are forwarding a petition on Michael&#39;s behalf in the hope that he will be able to carry on his business. The enclosed petition states that Michael is sole executor of his father, Edward Connolly&#39;s (c.1836-1915), will and that his brother, Stephen (b.1887) has lodged a caveat against proving Edward&#39;s will.Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7594/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/248</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1483">Blake &amp;amp; Kenny Solicitors</persName>
              <date>1916-04-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0324">St. Francis Street, Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0248_img_1428_1"  type="Letter"  url="28cd83c5e531a66bcd9d29b57fef2784.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0248_img_1428_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="6a373e4ba56e21007e9b925e5b607329.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0248_img_1428_1"/>
               I.Ack will have attention (to <sic>Solrs</sic>) <lb/> II. Inspector General ,R&amp;C, For report     Blake &amp; Kenny Solicitors  St Francis Street, Galway    26th April 1916   Re: W. Conolly, Roundstone, Co Galway  Dear Sir,   We send you herewith <lb/> petition on behalf of above <lb/> licensed trader in Roundstone <lb/> praying that His Excellency <lb/> will permit him to carry <lb/> on his licensed business.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  The Under Secretary <lb/> Dublin Castle </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0248_img_1428_2"/>
               TO HIS EXCELLENCY <lb/> THE LORD <hi rend="underline">LIEUTENANT OF IRELAND</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">PETITION of - <lb/> MICHAEL CONNOLLY </hi>  of Roundstone in the County of Galwlay, Shopkeeper, <lb/> Sheweth That :-   The late Edward Connolly was possessed of a <lb/> house in Roundstone attached to which was a License - <lb/> He died on the 10th day of December 1915 having made a Will of which I am sole Executor -   My Brother has lodged a Caveat against proving <lb/> this Willl and although License has been assigned to me <lb/> at Petty Sessions that Assignment only held good until <lb/> the C <hi rend="underline">l</hi>iden Sessions held on the 14th of this month - <lb/><sic>Mt</sic> Brother who is disputing this Will seeks to <lb/> establish a Will of an earlier date but I also am entitled <lb/> to the licensed premises under the earlier Will - The <lb/> Recorder had no power to grant a Transfer of the License <lb/> at Quarter Sessions without Probate of the Will of deceas- <lb/> ed.   The Suit in which I am Plaintiff to prove the <lb/> Will of my late Father Edward Connolly is entered for <lb/> hearing before a Special Jury of the City of Dublin on <lb/> the 17th May next and I pray that I may be <hi rend="underline">allowed </hi> to carry on the Business of licensed Publican until the <lb/> next Quarter Sessions in June -  <seg type="closer">  Dated 28 <hi rend="superscript">th </hi>April 1916    Michael Connolly </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>