<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0707">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Terrence Duffin to Edward Duffin, 3 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terence Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Terence Duffin to his brother Edward. Terence writes describing the wet and muddy conditions in the trenches. He writes of the General who inspires him with confidence and mentions Captain Day who is the new Brigade Major. Although he qualifies for leave in January but is not sure he will get it.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109-A, Duffin Papers D2109-A</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/707</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0305">Terence Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1387">Headquarters, 107 Bde, B.E.F.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0707_img_None_1"  url="53e61d9327ebbecd31d6373acbf89405.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0707_img_None_2"  url="8a9729d85adfa6483fbfd2ed5f7acc90.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0707_img_None_3"  url="d23a04eff449b8848d45142e74af12e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0707_img_None_4"  url="2b6f2ad03773fef256edf827b3fa116a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0707_img_0_1"/>
                <hi rend="superscript">3/12/15</hi>    Hd. Qrs  107 Bde  B.E.F.   My dear <hi rend="underline">Edmund</hi>   We have just finished with <lb/> the cold spell, and the snow which <lb/> was quite heavy has disappeared, <lb/> also the frost ГўВЂВ” it has now been <lb/> raining steadily for two days &amp; <lb/> the result is better <seg type="unclear">I'm afraid</seg> than <lb/> described as far as the trenches are <lb/> concerned &amp; you are either up over <lb/> your thighs in water or up to your <lb/> knees in thick mud ГўВЂВ” fearfully <lb/> hard to walk through even, let alone <lb/> live in ГўВЂВ” I often wonder how the <lb/> men can stand it ГўВЂВ” However the <lb/>'Bosch' must be as badly if not <lb/> worse off in their part of the line, which <lb/> is all we have to comfort ourselves <lb/> with! Even   though out here  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0707_img_0_2"/>
              <seg type="unclear">ophone</seg> sent out &amp; now can have <lb/> music in the evenings!   Our General is very cheery <lb/> and a splendid man all round <lb/> who inspires you with absolute <lb/> confidence ГўВЂВ” You know that he <lb/> has little to learn as a Brigadier <lb/> ГўВЂВ” he has been <sic>extraordinary</sic> lucky <lb/> to have come right through the war <lb/> without a scratch especially as <lb/> he has been through almost every <lb/> fight of importance you could <lb/> mention.  Capt. Day our new Brigade Major <lb/> is a good fellow too ГўВЂВ” an Irishman <lb/> from Clones, who was prev- <lb/>iously the General's adjutant &amp; <lb/> has been with him from the <lb/> start ГўВЂВ” With two such experienced <lb/> men we should be all right!  I hear of big changes in <lb/> ГўВЂВ” the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Batt. The Colonel has <lb/> gone home ГўВЂВ” Gordon is now in  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0707_img_0_3"/>
              <lb/>command and the Adjutant <lb/> has reverted to Qr Master.  You never know whether <lb/> your next step will be up or <lb/> down! Possibly my next step <lb/> will be down ГўВЂВ” I wonder I have <lb/> held my present job even as long <lb/> as I have!  The General goes on leave next <lb/> week and Day shortly after <lb/> him ГўВЂВ” I qualify about Jan <lb/> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> but it does not follow that <lb/> I get it.  I had rather a sad <lb/> letter from poor old Gen. Coachman <lb/> yesterday. He is at home with <lb/> nothing to do and apparently <lb/> feels it deeply ГўВЂВ” It was rather <lb/> unkind letting him keep command <lb/> even out here and then ordering <lb/> him back.  I have had no letters  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0707_img_0_4"/>
              <lb/>for some days but we have <lb/> been told that mails both ways <lb/> will be uncertain till after Xmas.  I got my winter flannels <lb/> safely and was glad to have them.  I could do with a decent <lb/> pipe as I broke one and the other <lb/> is somewhat far through ГўВЂВ” You <lb/> might post me out one.  Glad to hear Olive will be <lb/> home for Xmas ГўВЂВ” I had a line <lb/> from her and also from Emma. <seg type="closer"> Best love to all Ever your loving  <hi rend="underline">Terry</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>