<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0859">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender expresses dread at the possibility that the 16th (Irish) Division may soon be joining his own 36th (Ulster Division). He asks Lillian to let Sir Edward Carson (1854-1935) know that while the officers of the 36th Division and those of various Irish brigades have &#39;got on excellently&#39;, the same is not true of the ordinary soldiers, and according to the men there would have been &#39;real trouble, if they had not been separating so soon&#39;. Spender then argues that many people, including Ulstermen, do not reckon full with the &#39;Ulster temperament&#39;. Spender then detours at length along the path of Christmas-related sentiment. He then gives the news that a colleague, Captain W. Lindsall, has gotten engaged, and asks Lillian to send the couple a present worth roughly three pounds In a postscript, Spender mentions that the General is fully aware that he was up with the 107th Brigade, but &#39;has not said a word on the subject&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/117</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/859</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0859_img_2419_1"  type="Letter"  url="303e4df0f5761d72f44b7c10f36ddb9f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0859_img_2419_2"  type="Letter"  url="db0e1e6ef8f735b9eabe20b9265668a3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0859_img_2419_3"  type="Letter"  url="303e4df0f5761d72f44b7c10f36ddb9f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0859_img_2419_1"/>
                22 Dec 15   My Pr   You really seem to be getting quite excited over things,<lb/> but you mustn't count too much on things.   Richardson will I hope travel on with this letter so<lb/> he may turn up any day. Mayne has left.   Again I hear that the 16 Div is coming here after all<lb/> or bits of it. I do hope it's not true.  You may not have got my family letter with news of<lb/> my visit to the 107 Bge, but you can let Sir EC know<lb/> that whereas <seg type="del">the</seg> our officers have got on excellently with the Dublin<lb/> &amp; other Irish Regt, the men have not done so equally, &amp; in<lb/> fact Douglas who of course was able to get much more into<lb/> touch with the men told us that there would have been <lb/> real trouble, if they had not been separating so soon. People<lb/> who do not know the Ulster temperament - including many<lb/> Ulstermen â do not realize how they play with smouldering<lb/> flames when they say that things are all right.  Is this my Xmas letter? I think so &amp; my little<lb/> Pr will find a corner very warm for her when she<lb/> takes the wings of thought to it, &amp; tho' I should say it was anything  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0859_img_2419_2"/>
              <lb/>but a comfortable corner  I have no doubt she can fit herself<lb/> in it as snugly as she has done this past 2 <hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi> years &amp; more so.   I shall remember <seg type="del">yo</seg> her perhaps just a little more than usual,<lb/> tho' that won't be easy because.....(naturally because I have so many<lb/> other things to think about ?).    If no little parcel is on her table to display to the others<lb/> as she likes to do so much, she can smile quietly to herself knowing<lb/> that she is getting a really big present this time as soon as the<lb/> bw can come home &amp; settle it. Funny little animal I believe<lb/> she would almost <seg type="del">as</seg> sooner have a parcel with pink string than<lb/> the  5 bits of red paper called Govt bonds which I hope to be able to <lb/> put into her paws &amp; which will I hope bring in at least 20<lb/> little golden circles to her afterwards.  I had a very pleasant but quiet little dinner with the <lb/> 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div last night &amp; found that <seg type="unclear">Lindsell</seg> was being married<lb/> on the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Jany to a Miss Hollam? Daughter of Admiral Hollam<lb/> - any relation? - Any how could you send a wedding<lb/> present to Capt. W Lindsell <hi rend="superscript">RA</hi> Langley House Chichester, choosing<lb/> something about 3.00. I have served with him such a <lb/> lot that I must remember him &amp; if possible I will send <lb/> a letter later. You can select the <seg type="unclear">idea</seg> from one of our<lb/> presents as to what is likely to be useful. Must stop with my<lb/> very best Xmas wishes  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0859_img_2419_3"/>
              to the family<lb/> whose letters I hope<lb/> to be reading on Saturday, &amp; my best <lb/> of best love to that curious little animal<lb/> who has occupied so<lb/> much if not the whole<lb/> of her BW. <seg type="closer">  WB Spender </seg><seg type="postscript"> PS The Gen knows I was<lb/> up with the 107 Bde but <lb/> has not said one word on<lb/> the subject </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>