<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2525">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John P. Boland to Inspector General R.I.C., 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Pius Boland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by John Pius Boland (1870 – 1958). Boland was an Irish nationalist politician and lawyer. Like the other members of the Irish Party, Boland was taken completely by surprise by the Easter Rising in 1916 but continued to hope that an agreement could be forged by the various political groupings in Ireland. 

The letter was sent to the inspector general of the Royal Irish constabulary (RIC). Up until July of 1916 this position had been occupied by Sir Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain (1856 – 1944). Chamberlain held the position from 1900 until his resignation in July 1916, making him the second longest serving inspector general in the force&#39;s history. He was succeeded by Sir John Aloysius Byrne (1874 -1942). Byrne was a soldier and administrator. In Dublin, during and after the 1916 rising, he held the rank of brigadier-general in the Irish command while acting as deputy adjutant-general.

The letter was written by Boland as a query to the authority behind the policy of prohibiting the selling of certain postcards depicting the Rising in a local Kenmare shop.  Enclosed with the letter is a report from the district inspector’s office stating that a prosecution would not be judicious as Kenmare has been very quiet during and since the Rising. The note also states that Norah Casey was anti-British before the Rising and therefore can now be looked at as a Sinn Féin sympathiser. There is also another enclosure of a statement describing the event and the republican photographs which Casey was advertising in her shop and an amendment allowing for the ordinary display of portraits unaccompanied by Sinn Féin badges or cards or documents containing &#39;last words&#39; of rebel leaders.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13271-2 </collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2525</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0029">John Pius Boland</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0077">House of Commons, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Inspector General R.I.C.</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1958</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2525_img_1957_1"  type="Letter"  url="46aab88132309e50193f86d7cde266c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2525_img_1957_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="cc0eb4bc7c4a6aef9adec4559283b4d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2525_img_1957_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="e1ccfc5a8124221145a4634640b38966.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2525_img_1957_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="e70d8a8c92cc515158fefa03869eeece.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2525_img_1957_1"/>
             July 11. 1916.   Dear Sir   I have been informed by a Kenmare<lb/>shop keeper that the local police have warned<lb/>her against selling certain postcards picturing<lb/>the late rising.  I should be glad to learn if this action<lb/>is the result of directions from headquarters or<lb/>is purely directed locally.  I may add that I have not seen the postcards,<lb/>and that I express no opinions in consequence<lb/>as to the wisdom or otherwise of the<lb/>police action.   <sic>Yrs</sic> truly <lb/> John P. Boland  <lb/>The Inspector Gen.<lb/>R.I.C.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2525_img_1957_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Display of Rebel Photographs<lb/>in Kenmare</hi>  COUNTY OF Kerry<lb/><lb/>DISTRICT INSPECTORS OFFICE<lb/><hi rend="underline">Kenmare  4.7.1916 </hi>   I beg to submit copy of State-<lb/>ment sent to Garrison Com-<lb/>mander Queenstown. In sub-<lb/>mitting it I said -<lb/>I think a prosecution would<lb/>not be judicious. The town<lb/>of Kenmare has been very<lb/>quiet during &amp; since the<lb/>rebellion, &amp; I attribute the<lb/>putting up the photographs<lb/>again to the advice probably<lb/>of some Sinn Feiner who would<lb/>like to gain some notoriety<lb/>for Kenmare. <seg type="unclear">Norah Casey</seg><lb/>has been anti-Btitish before<lb/>the rebellion &amp; may now be<lb/>looked on as a Sinn Fein<lb/>Sympathiser   <!-- illegible signature -->  <hi rend="underline">The Inspector General</hi> <lb/><lb/> C.I.<lb/>Report result<lb/><lb/>W A O'Connell<lb/><seg type="unclear">DIT</seg><lb/> 5/7/16  <lb/><lb/> I Office acknowledge<lb/>receipt &amp; say that<lb/>inquiries are being made<lb/><lb/>II C.I.<lb/>Were these ordinary<lb/>photographs of the rebels<lb/>By what special orders<lb/>did the Sergeant take action<lb/>W A O'Connell<lb/><seg type="unclear">DIT</seg><lb/> 12.7.16  <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Done</hi><lb/> 13/7    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2525_img_1957_3"/>
             County Inspector's Office,<lb/>Tralee.  7th day of July 1916 <lb/>Transmitted.  ID.I. for<lb/>C.I. on Insp 2/11<lb/><lb/>F A. Britten<lb/>D.I. Kenmare  8.7.16   I beg to state the C.M.A has<lb/>informed me that no police<lb/>action is to be taken.   <!-- illegible signature --> <hi rend="underline">The County Inspector</hi><lb/> County Inspector's Office,<lb/>Tralee.  <lb/> 10th day of July 1916 <lb/>Submitted.<lb/><seg type="unclear">Hugh ONeill</seg><lb/>C.I.<lb/>I.G.<lb/> County Inspector's Office,<lb/>Tralee.   14th day of July 1916 <lb/>Transmitted.<lb/>F A Britten<lb/>D.I. Kenmare  I.D.I. for<lb/>C.I. on duty   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2525_img_1957_4"/>
             Sinn Fein Photographs displayed in Shop Window.<lb/><lb/> Kenmare  4:7:16.   I beg to report that on Saturday 1st that I saw<lb/>a number of Photos of Sinn Fein leaders displayed in the shop<lb/>window of Miss Norah Casey of Henry St. Kenmare. I entered the<lb/>shop and told Miss Casey that there was a military order prohibiting<lb/>the displaying of those Photographs in shop windows and I<lb/>warned her to remove those she had displayed. She replied<lb/>if it is an order I suppose I must obey it, but how am I<lb/>to sell the Photos if people don't know I have them? I<lb/>said that whatever about the selling, she could not have<lb/>them displayed in the window and that to avoid trouble<lb/>she had better remove them. She then removed the<lb/>Photos displayed.  When on patrol last night I again saw the following<lb/>Photos displayed in her shop window viz :- Finian Lynch, B.A.;<lb/>Sean MacDiarmada; Michael O'Halloran; E, Daly;<lb/>Cornelius Colbert; J.J.Walsh T.C. Cork; Countess Markievicz;<lb/>Sheehy Skeffington &amp; P.H. Pearse. Each Photo was headed<lb/>Irish Rebellion May 1916 and underneath gave the name<lb/>of the Photo displayed.  On passing Miss Casey's shop this morning I saw<lb/>some of the Photos still displayed in the window.   R. Harvey Sgt 56188<lb/>Dist Inspr.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>