<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2852">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 11 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

In this letter, Spender describes a recent German incursion into his trench, gives details of his feud with an officer, &#39;P&#39;, whom he sees as incompetent, and regrets the departure of a respected colleague. He also suggests the imminent eruption of &#39;chaos in Ireland&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/310</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2852</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-06-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2852_img_2265_1"  type="NULL"  url="e345f2f4d7ed8ba210e70546e3c218f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2852_img_2265_2"  type="NULL"  url="41e47c515c325c0db1c5d0296eab2fd8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2852_img_2265_3"  type="NULL"  url="620f13fccca84ca0e7cde64ac6b4a4c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2852_img_2265_4"  type="NULL"  url="b43e4b23899f6bfad4c51755ef07eb97.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2852_img_2265_1"/>
              D1633/1/1/310    June 11     My pr   Still very much in the dumps in spite of <seg type="unclear"></seg> <lb/>ageing letters. We had a heavy attack last night &amp;<lb/>I’m sorry to say for the first time the Hun got<lb/>into our trench for a minute tho’ way too soon turned<lb/>out.   I believe our men behaved very gallantly but<lb/>some men are missing who were out on patrol.<lb/>It makes me furious by saying they were  probably  captured<lb/>in our lines &amp; assume that our men are lying.  I told him he did not understand the Ulstermen<lb/>&amp; he thinks   a partition, but it makes me<lb/>hopeless. He always assumes the worst &amp; thank god <lb/> <seg type="unclear">usually</seg> finds out he is wrong, &amp; thinks it is an<lb/>exception.      I told him we could not afford to prevaricate<lb/>in our reports as the men would soon find it out &amp; 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2852_img_2265_2"/>
             never forgive us. He is incredulous tho’ I have<lb/>proven to him that they are not the ordinary type<lb/>with who he has been “associated” who are glib<lb/> <seg type="unclear">hais</seg>. I showed him the men reading thin bibles<lb/>which rather surprised him, but he cannot see the<lb/>power of information. The pity of it. The English<lb/>are   unfit to govern Ulster.    I hear the Lord Mayor gave great offence by<lb/>his speech at this meeting. I’m afraid the Knighthood<lb/>has spoilt a good man. No chance of the  <lb/>bribed in this way.   I hope the fine weather has just come in<lb/>time to let you have a very restful week end<lb/>but wish the   feeding.   R misses Gen. H, but the promotion<lb/>of Col. Henry is the great loss. His strong    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2852_img_2265_3"/>
             religious views &amp; his strength of character<lb/>was just what the Ulstermen want.  We do seem unlucky. No one  outside  knows<lb/>how heroic our men really are, &amp; no one is<lb/>able to give them the appreciation they deserve.  P calls me an idealist. If it means<lb/>believing you are going to get the best out<lb/>of men &amp; getting it, I am.  I was up till nearly 2AM this<lb/>morning so am not much inclined to write.  Hope for a longer letter tomorrow.<lb/>So glad you will have   &amp; Ed<lb/>&amp; can explain things to them. I have given<lb/>up hoping to do it on paper.    The MP still hold out glimmers of hope,    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2852_img_2265_4"/>
             &amp; I think there will be chaos in Ireland<lb/>later, so perhaps the b w   &amp; p r   may<lb/>again become amphibious &amp; fish in<lb/>troubled waters, tho’ not for their own benefit.    They are curious animals &amp; a very<lb/>funny match, but apparently get on<lb/>all right.   Your b w<lb/>Wilfrid B Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>