<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0678">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his mother, Sara Montgomery, 13 October, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A Long letter from William Montgomery to his mother describing his five days as temporary battalion commander in the trenches. He wonders what the old field officers would think of such rank madness. He describes his army servant and the general attitude to servant&#39;s to the officers they serve. He writes that the truly appalling battalion commanding business does not worry him as much as settling a fire loss claim with R N Kennedy. He would not like to be a soldier in peace time and thinks he wouldn&#39;t have much bother getting in again if there was another war in this generation. &#39;This one ought to satisfy this generation though.&#39;The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/678</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-10-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sara Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2095">Monacherra, Malone Park,Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_1"  type="Letter"  url="1cc2e279094f84e770fa639983bda65f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_2"  type="Letter"  url="fa8926f1d9eb188b66f77fb7c99e5401.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_3"  type="Letter"  url="30e2029d48cee5d63e1166a02cf0b351.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_4"  type="Letter"  url="774e3ff971a0ad9a4927b13670708789.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_5"  type="Letter"  url="4e29a04f9daa8f9eca018bb5dd0ce384.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_6"  type="Letter"  url="665d91c653ffb82864893d4b41ab463a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_7"  type="Letter"  url="1999df1d06215971e7bc4dd276778fd3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_8"  type="Letter"  url="4ce125130ad4ee135941801dd6523be0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_9"  type="Letter"  url="e1f5e6fb82fbda3785d538f100457a38.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_10"  type="Letter"  url="c4d253270803b6815886da18f962dfdc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_11"  type="Letter"  url="a659e208b5c9b558882be645f47ad331.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_12"  type="Letter"  url="8446f95f3c497c72eae7a21a058349f4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_13"  type="Letter"  url="4c8097ad356b6eb5d23368ad07815902.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_14"  type="Letter"  url="9d44e08164971e2a88113b2a52e0ed17.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_15"  type="Letter"  url="5b0d1be6c405f45e6b928a387ca3bdff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_16"  type="Letter"  url="a66bda8e93abe7ca466262174bb44b1c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_17"  type="Letter"  url="40fe3fa3dfd3097d99b255b0ff8bad3c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_18"  type="Letter"  url="2d90e83a95d575ee449c5defe3e05730.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0678_img_2170_19"  type="Letter"  url="e46bae5aa0bf16981e0cccd8b1d273dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_1"/>
                In the Field    13.10.16   My Dear Mother   Very many <lb/>thanks for yours of 30th <seg type="unclear">ult</seg><lb/> written from Portrush, <lb/>also for your parcels of <lb/>Home baked bread, You <lb/>should just see how it <lb/>disappears. Awful it is.  I am writing you this <lb/>on this Sunday notepaper <lb/>because I think perhaps <lb/>you will like to receive <lb/>a letter from a real <lb/>live Battalion Commander <lb/>who at the same time  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_2"/>
              <lb/>happens to be a quite <lb/>near relation of your <lb/>own. It is very <lb/>temporary of course being <lb/>only for 5 days in all, <lb/>but they are 5 days in <lb/>the trenches &amp; it hasn't <lb/>happened accidentally, as <lb/>the real C.O.. knew of it <lb/>when he went on leave <lb/>himself &amp; discussed it <lb/>with the Higher Powers <lb/>that be &amp; they didn't object.  It is an extraordinary <lb/>condition of affairs though <lb/> when one thinks of it.  Just imagine the <lb/>thoughts &amp; expressions <lb/>of one of the real old  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_3"/>
              <lb/>Regular Field officers if they come to <lb/> hear of such rank madness. Why! <lb/>they wouldn't even trust me to command <lb/>one of their Companies on a Barrack <lb/>Square under close supervision, much <lb/>less fight a Battalion in the line. And <lb/>yet a lot of imitation soldiers like me <lb/>are doing a heap more responsible <lb/>work than I am &amp; a lot of Pukka Regulars <lb/>are either at home or taking orders from <lb/>them. I have been much grieved to  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_4"/>
              <lb/>hear of Matts condition. <lb/>If he is still alive, please <lb/>tell him I think of him <lb/>here often, If he is to go <lb/>we shall all miss him <lb/>badly in the office. Still <lb/>you know he dies quite <lb/>comfortable with his <lb/> boots off &amp; plenty of <lb/>warning. Our <lb/> fellows don't do that here. One <lb/>is very apt to get callous <lb/>I fear. I passed a <lb/>couple of men this morning <lb/>pushing a truck. As I <lb/>approached, of course, the <lb/>truck stopped &amp; the men <lb/>came to attention and <lb/>saluted. (All very proper &amp; <lb/>as it should be)  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_5"/>
              <lb/>I, giving my usual well <lb/>known imitation of dignity, <lb/> ( Maynard Sinclair can <lb/> describe it, but perhaps <lb/>not to you ) returned the <lb/>salute &amp; passed on. I did <lb/>not know or hadn't noticed <lb/>what was on the truck <lb/>until an officer who had <lb/>been walking with me <lb/>re-joined me &amp; said - ' They <lb/>were men of - I said <lb/>who were? And he replied - <lb/>Those on the truck. It <lb/> appears there were 4 of <lb/>them. At least the person  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_6"/>
              <lb/>buried four this afternoon.  I suppose it really is <lb/>a dreadful state to get <lb/>into, but honestly I almost <lb/>touched that truck in <lb/>passing and never noticed <lb/>its load.   I have just passed my <lb/>Battalion orders for issue. <lb/>Very nice it looks too, neatly <lb/>typed at the top of a sheet <lb/>of foolscap. <lb/>Battalion Orders <lb/>by <lb/>CAPT. W.A. MONTGOMERY. D.S.O. <lb/>Comdg. 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Batt. Royal Irish Rifles   Funnily enough, the men <lb/>love these decoration &amp; are <lb/>most careful that everyone  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_7"/>
              <lb/>knows their officers possess them, They get <lb/>most annoyed if they see a personal letter <lb/>coming to me for instance if it is improperly <lb/>addressed ! My present servant was in a <lb/>fearful state a few days ago, I understand, <lb/>because a box I had made for me did not <lb/>have the letters after my name, He told <lb/>the men who brought it that it was no <lb/>Bl-dy use to <hi rend="underline">him</hi>like that that - to take it <lb/>back &amp; <hi rend="underline">finish</hi> it. Men are children, only <lb/>more so. He has bought some white <lb/>paint, I hear , with a view to some decorating  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_8"/>
              <lb/>on that base on his own <lb/>account. He will do it too. <lb/>Although I have expressly <lb/>forbidden him to<seg type="del">o</seg>. He <lb/>simply cant bear the sight <lb/>of it as it is. and it is <lb/> most extraordinary how <lb/>a good servant regards one's <lb/>odds &amp; ends of things. They <lb/>really regard them as their <lb/>own personal property. My <lb/>feelings in the matter are <lb/>quite secondary. Any good <lb/>servant is or ought to be <lb/>most frightfully hurt if <lb/>his officer dares to know <lb/>where to find any of his <lb/>own things. He looks upon <lb/>it as a personal insult <lb/>of the blackest shade - <lb/>far worse than if one  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_9"/>
              <lb/>cast hateful aspersions <lb/>on his immediate <lb/>ancestry. this redheaded <lb/>Judas I have now for <lb/>instance, has put on the <lb/> most frightful side since <lb/><hi rend="underline">we</hi> came to Batt. H.Q.  I didn't see him myself <lb/> but when I arrived at <lb/>my own Coy. H.Q. this <lb/>morning, they told me that <lb/>my servant (Russell) had <lb/>been looking for me, dressed <lb/>up as an H.Q. orderly, if <lb/>you please. I hadn't told <lb/>him to come there at  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_10"/>
              <lb/>all, much less turn <lb/>himself into an orderly. <lb/>But there you have it. <lb/>He deliberately went <lb/>to the front line from <lb/>his quite safe &amp; quiet <lb/>place , simply to <hi rend="underline">talk</hi><lb/>down to his own pals. <lb/>He took damned good <lb/>care I didn't see  him though.  In some respects, mother <lb/>mine, we are worse than <lb/>women. Seniority in <lb/>a company mess of servants <lb/> is much more strictly <lb/>observed than even by the <lb/>officers. The Coy. Comdr's servant <lb/>for instance is a <hi rend="underline">very</hi> important <lb/>person indeed. He doesn't <lb/>even need to go on working  
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_11"/>
              <lb/>parties. And woe betide the silly <lb/>young Coy. Sergt. Major who tries to <lb/>cross him in any way. He usually <lb/>finds himself in hot water very soon. <lb/>The servant quite casually lets him <lb/>down or give him away in some way <lb/>or other. Taking them all in all though <lb/>they are more fun that yours &amp; of <lb/>course at least 90% would always die <lb/>for their officers. And some of the things <lb/>they do. Ye Gods! The awful things they  
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_12"/>
              <lb/>do with food, clothes &amp; <lb/><seg type="unclear">fruit</seg><hi rend="underline">all for the best.</hi> I <lb/>would die of boredom if <lb/>they didn't keep on doing <lb/>them too. This one I have <lb/>now, for instance, is almost <lb/>too good a thief. He uses <lb/>no discrimination at all. <lb/>It is a disease with him.  He has also a mistaken <lb/> idea that he is a bomb &amp; <lb/> explosives expert. I was <lb/> awakened this morning <lb/>by a hammering noise, <lb/> and there he was with a <lb/> knife, Soldiers one busily <lb/> engaged in hammering &amp; <lb/><sic>prizing</sic> off the end of a <lb/>German Hand grenade in <lb/>order to get at the explosive <lb/>(T.N.T) When he got it out  
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_13"/>
              <lb/>He started digging at it <lb/>with a large spike thing <lb/>he had &amp; then he capsized <lb/>it out on a piece of a board <lb/>on which he had laid his <lb/> lighted cigarette butt. ( We <lb/>both smoke the same cigarettes <lb/>by the way) He moved the <lb/>lighted cigarette a little to <lb/>one side &amp; said quite <lb/>calmly - Its very like brown <lb/>sugar , Sir , soft &amp; wet. As I <lb/> had more than a shrewd <lb/>suspicion that he was <lb/>doing all this either to get <lb/>me up quickly or to try out  
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_14"/>
              <lb/>my nerve or both, &amp; as <lb/> I happen to know almost <lb/>as much as he <hi rend="underline">thinks</hi> he <lb/>does about this particular <lb/>explosive I went one up <lb/>on him by telling him to <lb/>thrown his blasted brown <lb/>sugar on the fire &amp; get <lb/> me some hot shaving water.  This was something he <lb/>didn't know about &amp; it <lb/>shook him up a bit, but he <lb/>quickly discovered that <lb/>if he did what he was told <lb/>&amp; there was anything wrong <lb/> about it I would go west <lb/>too, so he just did it. If <lb/>you happen to meet any <lb/>person looking for a  
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_15"/>
              <lb/>brand new definition of faith, you may <lb/> tell him of this one. It is quite literally <lb/>true that he didn't know the stuff <lb/>makes a grand firelighter &amp; he <hi rend="underline">does</hi> know <lb/> what it makes if it is suitably detonated, <lb/>&amp; because I told him to do it, he did it. <lb/>In any case I think even if it had been <lb/>detonated &amp; he knew it &amp; I knew it &amp; told <lb/>him to put it in the fire, rather than be <lb/>caught trying it on me he would still <lb/>do it. <hi rend="underline">You</hi> will understand this. So do  
            <pb n="16" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_16"/>
              <lb/> I &amp; that is just why this <lb/>artist is my servant now.   Well it is quite time I <lb/> closed now. I am not very <lb/> busy, but I am sleepy &amp; <lb/>in this life one is unwise to <lb/>miss sleep when the mood &amp; <lb/> the opportunity synchronize. <lb/>( Quite neat that, isn't it?) I am <lb/>getting quite literary. I think <lb/>I will write a book or <lb/>something someday. Does <lb/>one write the book first &amp; choose <lb/>the title after or does one start <lb/>with a title &amp; write about it?   You will gather that the <lb/>truly appalling responsibility <lb/>of this Battalion Commanding <lb/>business doesn't worry me much, <lb/>no not as much as trying to <lb/>settle one little fire loss with <lb/>R.N.Kennedy used to do. This is  
            <pb n="17" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_17"/>
              <lb/>perfectly true. It is also <lb/>very interesting &amp; becomes <lb/>more so the longer it is <lb/>considered. It is in me <lb/>somewhere., I fear. But <lb/>where it came from I don't <lb/>know. I wouldn't be a <lb/> soldier in peace however <lb/>for a considerable consideration <lb/> - no not even if I could afford <lb/>it. I don't think there ever <lb/>will be much trouble <lb/>getting in if ever there is <lb/>another war in this generation.   This one ought to satisfy <lb/>this generation though.  
            <pb n="18" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_18"/>
              <lb/> 
            <pb n="19" facs="L1916_0678_img_2170_19"/>
              <lb/>news. I am really stopping now <lb/>Goodnight ( This word can be rather <lb/>more than a mere form here.)  <seg type="closer"> Your quite irresponsible but <lb/>loving Son <lb/> WM </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>