<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5551">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 19 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
He&#39;s looking forward to his next visit to Togherstown (Lockardstown). He&#39;s working in his office on a Saturday afternoon. He&#39;s been trying to help his cousin Johnnie find a job</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5551</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-02-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0802">National Health Insurance Commission (Ireland), Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0273">Togherstown, Co Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5551_img_647_1"  type="Letter"  url="0508dcfd490dc3de1adb68274263d819.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5551_img_647_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0415ebf19baa29d0cd7180e1fea5f3b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5551_img_647_3"  type="Letter"  url="96509d5d0374115570e4890421a06769.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5551_img_647_1"/>
            <!-- End of the letter written sideways on the left hand side. --> I know you wouldn’t come<lb/>between a hungry man<lb/>and his food. So goodbye<lb/>my dearest love for the<lb/>present. Hope to have a<lb/>letter from my darling girl<lb/>tomorrow. With fondest love<lb/>and kisses  From your loving   James    National Health Insurance Commission (Ireland),<lb/>Pembroke house<lb/>Upper Mount Street,<lb/>Dublin.    19th Feby, 1916.    My dearest girl,   I must keep my promise that<lb/>you should have a letter tomorrow but<lb/>I am pretty afraid I shall not be<lb/>able to make it very interesting as I have<lb/>absolutely no news at all to relate. Luckily<lb/>I won’t be in the same difficulty next<lb/>week as I presume you will not insist<lb/>on my sending you a letter from Lockardstown<lb/>to Togherstown on Sunday next.I am<lb/>looking forward very keenly to my visit<lb/>as I’m dying to see you. How is the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5551_img_647_2"/>
             ankle getting on since you went home.<lb/>I suppose all right now that you have such<lb/>a lazy time as you say you have.<lb/>We are expecting Moll home tomorrow for<lb/>a few hours. It’s grand for her to<lb/>be so near now, she can come home any<lb/>time she pleases. My mother had a<lb/>note from her during the week. She finds both<lb/>the town and the staff in the office<lb/>very pleasant so we are all hoping she<lb/>will get on well.     On re-reading your letter (I always<lb/>read them about 20 times) I was sorry<lb/>to see that your mother and yourself<lb/>were so worried about Tim. Of course it’s   hard lines that he should have to go<lb/>so far away at his age but all the<lb/>same he’s amongst his own to a certain<lb/>extent and Jennie &amp; himself will be<lb/>great company to each other. Besides there<lb/>are plenty at home in any case to keep<lb/>your mother company and it’s a good<lb/>job for any young chap to stir out early<lb/>if he has to earn his own living. I see too<lb/>many cases here in town of fellows living on<lb/>their parents up to 20 and 25 years of<lb/>age and then trying for rotten clerks jobs<lb/>in Government Departments at 25/- or 30/-<lb/>a week. That reminds me that I have<lb/>been enquiring about Johnnie in a few places  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5551_img_647_3"/>
             places but up to the present without success.<lb/>It’s the <hi rend="underline">devil entirely</hi> to get jobs for men<lb/>clerks at present; the women are taking the<lb/>bread out of all our mouths but I’m still<lb/>hoping that I may succeed. Pity he’s not<lb/>hearing anything from Cork. I thought that was<lb/>pretty well a dead cert. Tell Mrs Seery that<lb/>I am making further efforts and I will write<lb/>to her in any case next week.  Today is a great improvement on<lb/>yesterday. It’s very bright and pleasant but<lb/>very cold. I’m writing this in the office and the<lb/>fire is gone out as well as all the staff (Saturday<lb/>afternoon) so I’m afraid you won’t be able to read<lb/>it my hands are so cold. I must close now. One<lb/>of the beautiful charwomen put her head in just now<lb/>so I must go. She is evidently wondering what the<lb/>hell is keeping me in and she wanting to clean up the<lb/>room. In any case I want my dinner and I 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>