<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3088">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 15th May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Peter Mooney was born on 5th February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne. Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie (b. 1884) were brought up by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18th October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St.Omer and Passchendael, in Belgium.

Peter was an avid correspondent with his sister Kate and this letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters. This letter was written to Dunbyone county Meath to Peter Mooneys sister Katie Mooney. Peter asks a lot about the farm and how everything is getting on at home. He is very eager to find out what has been going on at home and what he is missing out on. He talks about the farm a lot and is asking who has been taking over his jobs on the farm.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3088</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-05-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0428">Dunboyne, Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1970</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3088_img_2493_1"  type="Letter"  url="89d6dd353697b56bb2ff1abd6c72dfd9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3088_img_2493_2"  type="Letter"  url="3c5bb400314e2364ca0bc34904f83722.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3088_img_2493_3"  type="Envelope"  url="2c77d3e7e34bfd64689a9e672044f7bf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3088_img_2493_1"/>
             May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   Dear Kate   Many thanks for your very <lb/>nice letter of the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. which I received <lb/>in due course. I am very pleased to <lb/>hear that your are all enjoying good <lb/>health. You seem to have got on very <lb/>nicely with the tillage. John Ward <lb/>has certainly treated us very well. <lb/>I hope the Department will leave us <lb/>in peace as under the circumstances <lb/>I think we have done very well. <lb/>I was very pleased to hear that <lb/>Bryan Mc Cabe is getting o well on <lb/>the road of recovery. I hope you <lb/>will enjoy your visit to John &amp; Mrs <lb/>Yourell's new home. I will have a <lb/>great time with him when I get <lb/>my leave. Mrs Pat Ward seem to be <lb/>doing things on a very grand scale. <lb/>It must be a very nice place now. <lb/>Matt Geraghty cannot be complimented <lb/>on his conduct he seems to have made
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3088_img_2493_2"/>
            a very bad example of himself.   I would feel very pleased if you could <lb/>manage to send me a small size Primus <lb/>stove it is very handy for boiling <lb/>water. I am sure the <seg type="unclear">general</seg> Army &amp; Navy <lb/>Stores could supply you with what I <lb/>need. Mr Moore seems to have gone <lb/>to the bad once more he is well paid. <lb/>I expect I will call him a traitor. <lb/>The Sinn Feiners must be getting a <lb/>strong hand mind you they will <lb/>want a lot of watching just now. <lb/>The Labour Union must be causing <lb/>some trouble too. I expect to see Mr <lb/>Whitworth leaving Heberstown <lb/>owing to the way they are carrying <lb/>on. The weather is simply beautiful <lb/>just now many a night I sleep out <lb/>I the open it is so very healthy you- <lb/>know. I will now say goodbye <lb/>&amp; wish you all the very best of Good <lb/>luck.   Good- Bye.   P.Mooney   I will write soon again. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3088_img_2493_3"/>
             Mrs K Mooney <lb/>Caulstown <lb/>Dunboyne <lb/>Co Meath <lb/>Ireland 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>