<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4332">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Crozier to Edward Carson, 26 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Baptist Crozier</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>John Baptist Crozier (1853–1920) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Crozier was a Church of Ireland clergyman who served as Archbishop of Armagh and Primate of All Ireland from 1911–1920. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4332</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1356">John Baptist Crozier</persName>
              <date>1916-06-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0401">The Palace Armagh, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1920</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4332_img_3691_1"  type="Letter"  url="24ac3b611ea443cf9c672f3e2ca47751.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4332_img_3691_2"  type="Letter"  url="9c8abd62e9d1bc7308257cab8a845c89.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4332_img_3691_3"  type="Letter"  url="9346b3110524d89e2ca790e06770015d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4332_img_3691_4"  type="Letter"  url="ebc52dd0f93ec1cc225b9503a40b58a4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4332_img_3691_5"  type="Letter"  url="f95373be6ee96745fe356be77dc92b58.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4332_img_3691_1"/>
             D1507/A/17/26  PAGE 1 OF 2  100   The Palace,<lb/>Armagh.   <!-- address is in invisable notepaper heading stamp --> June <hi rend="underline">26.1916</hi>    My Dear Ned   Many thanks for<lb/>yours. The Bishops of course<lb/>at their meeting looked at<lb/>the question simply from the<lb/>standpoint of it's effect on the<lb/>Church all over Ireland  As regards the Covenant<lb/>I think it has been faithfully<lb/>kept when the 3 exempted<lb/>Counties asquiesced and<lb/>released their comrades.<lb/>I myself was a Co Cavan<lb/>Covenanter where I signed<lb/>it in company with my 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4332_img_3691_2"/>
             own Tenants &amp; others.<lb/>And I feel sure that if<lb/>I had been present at<lb/>your meeting I could not<lb/>have opposed <hi rend="underline">as a<lb/>Covenanter</hi> the decision<lb/>come to, in fact I always<lb/>felt that Lord Farnham,<lb/>Saunderson, <seg type="unclear">Burrowes,</seg><lb/>&amp; Johnston had a right<lb/>to speak for the County<lb/>&amp; they refused to take<lb/>the responsibility of<lb/>objecting.  But as Bishops of the Church<lb/>we protest against the<lb/>flagrant breach of faith and<lb/>honour on the part of the<lb/>Government. We protest,<lb/>as representing the best part<lb/>of the population all over<lb/>Ireland, against the Church<lb/>of Ireland not having been<lb/>consulted by the Government<lb/>in such a grave matter<lb/>&amp; above all we protest that,<lb/>as far as we are concerned,<lb/>We are utterly in the dark 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4332_img_3691_3"/>
             as to any Imperial Necessity<lb/>for such an appalling<lb/>change of Government of<lb/>Ireland as is contemplated.  I cannot but think<lb/>that the Unionist Members<lb/>of the Cabinet have been<lb/>utterly tricked and should<lb/>have taken their stand on the<lb/>impossibility of considering<lb/>any such measure<lb/>during the war crisis.  This is all that the<lb/>Bishop's Resolution means<lb/>&amp; is in no sense a criticism<lb/>on, or a condemnation of,<lb/>the action of the Ulster<lb/>Covenanters.   As ever <sic>affecy</sic>   John B: Armagh 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4332_img_3691_4"/>
             D1507/A/17/26  PAGE 2 OF 2  103   Private   <lb/>I may add very<lb/>definately after a<lb/>conversation <hi rend="underline">now</hi><lb/>with the Bishop of<lb/>Down that we<lb/>Northern Bishops do<lb/>feel that if Home 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4332_img_3691_5"/>
             Rule were bound<lb/>to come here now,<lb/>that perplexing<lb/>trend the very<lb/>private mention<lb/>so far as Ulster<lb/>is concerned.<lb/>But we all feel  <lb/>( i.e. Southern &amp;<lb/>Northern Bishops<lb/>alike) that the<lb/>whole thing is a<lb/>breach of faith on the<lb/>Governments part<lb/>&amp; that we at any<lb/>rate know of <hi rend="underline">No<lb/>Imperial Necessity</hi><lb/>J.B.a <!-- In pencil --> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>