<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5826">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter (transcript) from Lord Cavan to John Redmond, 8 February 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frederick Rudolph Lambart</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Frederick Rudolf Lambart  (1865-1946), 10th Earl of Cavan, was head of the XIV Corps of the British army which he commanded at the Western Front during the Great War, or World War I.
John Redmond MP (1856-1918), was an Irish nationalist politician and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party between 1900 and 1918.
The writer is happy to announce that the Guards Division is now part of his command. He has read about a recent meeting in Galway and he is very hopeful. He feels the demand for reinforcements is growing and says it would be a good step forward if they could reinforce while Germany cannot do so.
Redmond was a key figure in the recruitment of Irish nationalists to the British army during the war.
This is a typed version of Lord Cavan&#39;s handwritten, which also survives. In addition, there is a note dated 25 January 1916. Lord Cavan thanks Redmond for his kind words. The 36th (Ulster) Division, recruited largely from Ulster Unionists, has joined him and the men are &#39;full of zeal&#39;. He regrets the exclusion of the south and south west from &#39;its share in the common burden&#39; and says the men would enjoy the fighting if they tried it.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Erskine Childers Papers, Collection List No 161; Ms. 15,175</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5826</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0744">Frederick Rudolph Lambart</persName>
              <date>1916-02-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2032">Headquarters, XIV Corps</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1946</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5826_img_927_1"  type="Letter"  url="9149e537e6d5acad91477eae6a653915.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5826_img_927_2"  type="Letter"  url="a9020c26fe3f4f1c1800c3931e16e10d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5826_img_927_1"/>
            Lord CAVAN to R   Feb 8 '16   HQ 14th Corps BEF   The Guards will be a part of my Corps directly I need not say <lb/> how delighted I am ..... I am sure the demand for reinforcements <lb/> is bound to be very great by the autumn and if we CAN reinforce <lb/> when Germany CAN'T we shall have made a big step forward <lb/>v truly yrs Cavan   Jan 25 '16   Dear Mr Redmond Thank you for your little book and the <lb/> kind things said about the Guards and myself I now command the <lb/> 14th Corps and this includes the Ulster divn. <sic>Tey</sic> have not been <lb/> tried yet in action but they are full zeal and energy and <sic>thei</sic> <lb/>discipline seems good It is unutterably sad to me that it <sic>shd</sic> <lb/>have <sic>bn</sic> necessary to exclude Ireland from its share of our common <lb/> burden and I feel sure that although we probably differ very <lb/> considerably as to methods by which we <sic>wd</sic> bring about Unity we <lb/> cannot be wrong to aim at it Nobody really <sic>wd</sic> ENJOY this <lb/> fighting more than the men of the South and South-West if they <sic>wd</sic> <lb/> but try it Yrs v truly Cavan 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5826_img_927_2"/>
             47, HALSEY STREET <lb/>CADOGAN GARDENS S. W. 3 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>