<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1247">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 23 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) following their recent engagement. James attempts to cheer May up after he recent illness and writes about the hesitations he had in asking for her hand. James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1247</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-01-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0557">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1247_img_436_1"  type="Letter"  url="c62e97e9ed9b7181f09f72d6a5c02610.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1247_img_436_2"  type="Letter"  url="ae49e1cfbf38885dc23107f5582b2065.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1247_img_436_3"  type="Letter"  url="706a0da6c07ec30517935befb06d8103.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1247_img_436_1"/>
                39, Belgrave Square,  Rathmines,  Dublin.    23 January, 1916   My dearest May,   I came down to breakfast this <lb/>morning with a wild hope that I might <lb/>have a note from you but without without any <lb/>real expectation of it because I knew <lb/>Saturday would be a busy day with you <lb/>in addition to your being the sole housekeeper <lb/>at present. Needless to say therefore how <lb/>overjoyed I was to get your dear note. Even <lb/>although it was a short one, I'd rather have <lb/>it than the finest literature in the English  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1247_img_436_2"/>
              language. I was very sorry indeed to see that <lb/>you are not yet quite well and I sincerely <lb/>trust — selfishness as usual — that it <lb/>won't interfere with my seeing you this <lb/>week. It is sweet of you to say that you <lb/>are looking forward to your visit to <lb/>Dublin. You can imagine how I look <lb/>forward to it and to seeing my dear <lb/>girl in a few days more. Please don't get <lb/>into the dumps again. If you do, I'll be <lb/>inclined to think you're getting sorry for <lb/>your bargain. Just to cheer you up I'll <lb/>tell you a joke. I was coming home one <lb/>day about a week ago and as usual <lb/>I was thinking about you — I may confess this <lb/>is a habit of about three years standing— I looked up suddenly and there was <hi rend="underline">Venus</hi><lb/>shining down on me benevolently from the <lb/>evening sky. This is gospel truth — and <lb/>ever since I have her company on my <lb/>way home in the evening. If you like to <lb/>see for yourself , you'll see her any evening <lb/>about half an hour after sunset in the <lb/>Western sky. You can't mistake her as <lb/>you can't see any other star so early after <lb/>sunset. So now you know.  I wrote to Mrs Seery on Friday as <lb/>well as yourself so I hope that will service <lb/>her jealousy and keep her in good humour <lb/>till I see you both. I was way laid on <lb/>O'Connell Bridge yesterday by Josephine , Mrs <lb/>George and Kathleen and had to stand the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1247_img_436_3"/>
              usual chaff from them all. Mrs G said <lb/>I was a sly boy. Now I wonder am I. <lb/>I thought that every one could see as <lb/>plain as possible that I was after you for <lb/>a very long time past. To tell truth <lb/>the only thing I ever found wrong with <lb/>you was your age. I was always ashamed <lb/>to speak and so I put it off although I <lb/>have the idea at the back of my head <lb/>for the last three or four years.  Well, my dearest dear, it's twelve <lb/>midnight now so I must close up. I couldn't <lb/>manage to write in time for first and know <lb/>I shouldn't have time tomorrow but you'll <lb/>have this on Tuesday. Let me know early what <lb/>day you're coming. I shall close now with <lb/>warmest love and kisses to my dearest girl. <seg type="closer"> Goodbye, dear. <lb/>Your loving  <hi rend="underline">James</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>