<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1100">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 23 [January] 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother, Mary. Marie writes of accepting 4 badly wounded soldiers who were &#39;operated on&#39; prior to their invalidation back to England; that they are short of orderlies and staff, and that they are opening more tents. She feels doing the right thing by working as a VAD. Marie Helena Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary,&#39; was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF132-1916, BF132-1916</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1100</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1540">Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0303">Monkstown</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1100_img_329_1"  type="NULL"  url="da3043a688379785e08635ac862f4e93.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1100_img_329_2"  type="NULL"  url="efce3140a941ada817c8690177265dbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1100_img_329_3"  type="NULL"  url="09245e8bb63b277e05e787ad7838a508.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1100_img_329_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">Sunday 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1916</hi>   My very fondest Mother   Ever so many thanks <lb/>for your letter. I am <lb/>delighted to think you are <lb/>away having a change &amp; <lb/>sincerely hope it will do <lb/>you a great deal of good <lb/>as I think you need one <lb/>very badly. I am afraid <lb/>I have left a few days <lb/>without writing but we <lb/>have had a terrible <lb/>rush again &amp; have not <lb/>been off for the last <lb/>few days, I am just <lb/>off for an hour or so <lb/>now so I am just writing <lb/>to let you know I am <lb/>very well. The convoy <lb/>that came into my <lb/>tent were fairly  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1100_img_329_2"/>
              bad &amp; had to have <lb/>four operated on before <lb/>they were able to go <lb/>to England — but am <lb/>glad to say 5 went <lb/>today — but one of them <lb/>was very bad &amp; I'm <lb/>afraid will suffer a <lb/>great deal on the journey <lb/>however he will make <lb/>up for it when he gets <lb/>to England to care &amp; <lb/>looking after. We have <lb/>had a terrible rush &amp; <lb/>are very short of orderlys <lb/>&amp; staff as we are opening <lb/>so many more tents. <lb/>However we are only doing <lb/>what everyone else is <lb/>doing &amp;we are very <lb/>lucky to get off at all <lb/>these times. I see they <lb/>were advertising in  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1100_img_329_3"/>
              every paper for V.A.D.s <lb/>they cannot get enough <lb/>I am so glad I came &amp; <lb/>feel I have done the <lb/>right thing. I wasn't <lb/>able to go to Mass today <lb/>but I am getting up <lb/>I hope for 6.30 tomorrow <lb/>morning.  Hoping this will find <lb/>you &amp; all A.1. <seg type="closer"> Best of Love <lb/>In haste  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>  I shall answer letter <lb/> in a day or two. <lb/><hi rend="underline">M.</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>