<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0058">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B. Maguire to Lady Clonbrock, 15 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>B. Maguire</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from a prisoner of war, B. Maguire, South Lancashire Regiment, to Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Maguire was then a prisoner of war in a camp in Limburg, Germany. He writes that he had received a postcard stating that bread had been sent to him but he had yet to receive it. He also notes that he has received one of the two parcels of cigarettes that Lady Clonbrock had sent. Maguire enquires about his wife at home, the health of Lady Clonbrock and her family and mentions that he is in good health but the weather is cold in the camp.Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No 54, Collection List No 54, Ms. 35796 (14)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/58</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1539">B. Maguire</persName>
              <date>1916-10-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1237">Ahascragh, County Galway</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0058_img_112_1"  type="Letter"  url="317606859fbb7514c7d8156b5f77dac0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0058_img_112_2"  type="Letter"  url="2921cdf17f485f82f4fc0cfa48c6073f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0058_img_112_3"  type="Envelope"  url="9506c897994092d9fa2597e0133e8129.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0058_img_112_1"/>
              <seg type="foreign">Kriegsgefangenenlager</seg> Limburg (Lahn),   15/10/1916  <lb/>This is my address :   Prisoner of War  Name : B Maguire South Lancs Regt  Regt. No.7587 Comp. 6 Batl. 2 No. 274  Camp of Prisoners of War  Limburg (Lahn) Germany.  <lb/>The indications mentioned must be reproduced in the address.  Dear Lady Clonbrock   I now <lb/>take the pleasure in sending <lb/>you this letter hoping to find <lb/>you and all at home in good <lb/>health as this leaves me <lb/>in the best at present. I <lb/>have received a P.C. from <lb/><sic>Beirne</sic> saying that the were  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0058_img_112_2"/>
              <lb/>sending me on Two Breads <lb/>weekly but I have not received any yet <sic>there</sic>P.C. <lb/>was dated 2/10/16. As soon <lb/>as I receive any of the Breads <lb/>I will let you know I have <lb/>not yet received the first or <lb/>second lot of Cigarettes that <lb/>you ordered to be sent to <lb/>me your last lot was the 16/9/16 <lb/>it has not yet reached me <lb/>but as soon as it does I will <lb/>let you know I hope my <lb/>wife is in good health <lb/>and also your own People <lb/>I hope you are getting good <lb/>weather at Home it is cold <lb/>here <sic>know</sic>more at present <lb/>hoping to hear from you <lb/>soon again I remain  <seg type="closer"> Yours  B Maguire </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0058_img_112_3"/>
              <seg type="foreign">Kriegsgefangenenlager</seg><lb/>Limburg (Lahn). <lb/>This is my address :   Prisoner of War  Name : B Maguire South Lancs Regt  6 Batl.Camp 2 Batl. No. 274  Camp of Prisoners of War  Limburg (Lahn) Germany.  <lb/>The indications mentioned must be reproduced in the address.   Right side  <seg type="foreign">Kriegsgefangenensendung. <lb/>Adresse : </seg>  M. Lady Clonbrock  Clonbrock  Ahascragh  Co Galway  Ireland.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>