<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2253">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Charles Hubert Montgomery, 30 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to his son Charles Hubert Montgomery (1876-1942). Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Hugh Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland. Charles Hubert Montgomery was a civil servant and diplomat and master of the ceremonies, an important diplomatic position, in 1916.
In the letter Montgomery discuses the tactics of David Lloyd George MP (1863-1945) and Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), prime minister, in promising John Redmond (1856-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, Home Rule for his loyalty in the war to show the United Kingdom as united during the war. Montgomery then argues that full power should be returned to John Maxwell (1959-1929), commander-in-chief of Ireland, and that there should be control over the police and army until the new Irish government is agreed upon. The position of Edward Carson (1954-1935), Unionist leader, and Unionist groups is discussed, stating that they will only accept negotiations on the base of a six county exclusion from Home Rule.  Montgomery then explains that the Ulster Unionist Council agreed that Carson should engage in negotiations on the basis of the six county plan. This decision by the Ulster Unionist Council became controversial and opposed by many southern Unionists.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/49</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2253</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Heaton Hubert</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2253_img_1697_1"  type="Letter"  url="4021c03b4e75dfe3757729b619b6677d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2253_img_1697_2"  type="Letter"  url="6596ccf0571b8d13a6929636090cbf3f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2253_img_1697_3"  type="Letter"  url="f4f58ce5c95d036f30e594ea0bf1c0bf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2253_img_1697_1"/>
             Strictly private &amp; confidential  <lb/> 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June, 1916. <lb/> My dear Rubert,   In answer to your note of yesterday;  <seg type="del">Apparently</seg> the object of Asquith's &amp; LLoyd George's,<lb/>apparently foolish, &amp; certainly dangerous, contrivance was<lb/>the production of eye-wash to enable Redmond to keep a sufficient<lb/>following together in Ireland &amp; in America in support of his<lb/>professed policy of loyalty to the Empire during the war, so as to<lb/>persuade our Allies &amp; neutral nations that we were a United<lb/>Kingdom for the purposes of the war — more eye-wash — This<lb/>being so, the best thing to do now, I suppose, is to conduct<lb/>the negotiations so as to produce the maximum of eye-wash with<lb/>the minimum of mischief &amp; danger. There must be some reason<lb/>for supposing that tolerably thin eye-wash will serve the purpose;<lb/>otherwise even Asquith &amp; LLoyd George would hardly have conceived<lb/>the project. Let enough be done to enable it to be said that<lb/>Redmond received an offer to bring the Home Rule Act into<lb/>immediate operation. This in itself is clearly mischievous,<lb/>but that particular mischief has already been done and cannot<lb/>be made much worse by going a step further. The negotiations<lb/>are obviously capable of being almost endlessly protracted:<lb/>meanwhile full powers should be restored to Sir John Maxwell —<lb/>I say restored, because it is clear that his action has latterly<lb/>been hampered, and it should be made quite clear that he is to<lb/>remain Military Governor of Ireland with full power over the<lb/>Army and the Police till the new form of Government is fully    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2253_img_1697_2"/>
             -2-  <lb/>fledged. Devlin &amp; Co. have induced their followers to accept the<lb/>LLoyd George basis of negotiation by holding out to them that to do<lb/>so would bring with it an immediate <sic>avolition</sic> of Military Rule, &amp;<lb/>also an amnesty for the imprisoned rebels. If he is allowed<lb/>to go on making play with these forms of eye-wash there must be<lb/>an absolute determination not to allow any such concession to take<lb/>actual shape till the distant day when the Home Rule Government is<lb/>in a position to rule, as neither the Ulster Unionist Council,<lb/>nor Carson, nor the Nationalist Convention have accepted any complete<lb/><sic>porposal</sic>; but only authorised the continuation of negotiation on<lb/>the general basis of the exclusion of six Ulster counties, &amp; the<lb/>bringing of the Home Rule Act into operation during the war. There<lb/>is no reason why the negotiations should not be protracted till<lb/>after the presidential election, or the conclusion of peace: or<lb/>if such very protracted negotiations would make the eye-wash too<lb/>thin the negotiations might be brought to an apparent conclusion,<lb/>and Redmond allowed to begin making preparations for getting his<lb/>new machine ready for work. This might take him almost any length<lb/>of time, and I do not suppose that he himself would be in any<lb/>desperate hurry actually to assume the Government of Ireland, as<lb/>with such assumption his real difficulties would be only beginning.<lb/>This scheme is an odious one in any shape; but you asked me what I<lb/>think would be the least disastrous mode of issue, and this is the<lb/>best that occurs to me at present. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2253_img_1697_3"/>
             -3-  Note that all the Ulster Unionist Council at Carson's<lb/>suggestion resolved was, to authorise Sir Edward Carson to<lb/>continue the negotiations on the basis of the suggestion explained<lb/>to this meeting, and to complete them if the details are arranged<lb/>to his satisfaction. I take it that part of the Asquith Lloyd<lb/>George scheme was to put Carson &amp; the Ulster Unionists into a<lb/>difficulty, and to crown their efforts to say that the true authors<lb/>of the Rebellion were Carson &amp; the Ulster Volunteers by holding<lb/>them up to odium as preventing a possible friendly settlement<lb/>of the Government of this country. Carson having induced his<lb/>followers here to make the right tactical move in the game<lb/>from this point of view may, I think, be trusted so to conduct<lb/>the negotiations as to gain further points in the manoeuvring<lb/>for position, and to put our opponents in the wrong if the<lb/>negotiations breakdown. Probably the most satisfactory way out<lb/>of the <seg type="foreign">imbroglie</seg> would be for the negotiations to breakdown in<lb/>such a manner as would enable us to persuade the British Elector<lb/>that the breakdown was due to the unreasonable nature of the<lb/>Nationalist demands. The forces now arrayed against Redmond<lb/>in this country may very likely oblige him to make unreasonable<lb/>demands. With regard to these details which under the Ulster<lb/>resolution must be arranged to Sir Edward Carson's satisfaction.<lb/><lb/> Yours affectionately,        
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>