<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4300">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from W.T. Bailey to Edward Carson, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.T. Bailey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from W.T. Bailey to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4300</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0307">W.T. Bailey</persName>
              <date>1915-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0700">3 Earlesfort Terrace, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4300_img_3662_1"  type="Letter"  url="32afe036a9a73f1111e53aa0c6bedb70.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4300_img_3662_2"  type="Letter"  url="848ce447c7167ffe6a54589e19cc918f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4300_img_3662_3"  type="Letter"  url="e5ae5e79d06b7cb58e96d4a5995a1117.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4300_img_3662_4"  type="Letter"  url="bdd6c34169cc7c46f52e17e9da27d66d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4300_img_3662_1"/>
             Bailey. Irish Recruiting <lb/><hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   3 Earlsfort Terrace <lb/>Dublin.   22 Dec. 15   My dear Carson.   I read your speech <lb/>last night with much <lb/>interest.   It seems to me that <lb/>recruiting has been <lb/>killed in Ireland by <lb/>the policy adopted by <lb/>the government. It is <lb/>the fashion to say that <lb/>Ireland has done "splendidly"
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4300_img_3662_2"/>
            <lb/>when the truth is that in all <lb/>but the Unionist districts of Ulster <lb/>it has done very badly.   Irish soldiers have fought <lb/>magnificently but there are <lb/>very few of them &amp; as compared <lb/>with the rest of the British <lb/>Isles Ireland is very <lb/>backward indeed in recruiting.   Birmingham on the last <lb/>Saturday of Lord Derby's <lb/>campaign enlisted more <lb/>men than all Ireland <lb/>did in the six months of <lb/>Lord Wimborne's campaign.   Now practically no <lb/>recruits are coming <lb/>forward in Ireland. There <lb/>have been about 10,000 <lb/>got in 6 or 7 weeks since <lb/>Lord Wimborne commenced <lb/>operations but 50,000 <lb/>were asked for - and <lb/>50,000 was immensely <lb/>under the proper propertion <lb/>as measured by England <lb/>&amp; Scotland.   It would be <lb/>interesting to find out <lb/>on what principle or <lb/>basis the demand was
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4300_img_3662_3"/>
            <lb/>limited to 50,000 for Ireland. <lb/>On the British analogy it <lb/>should have been 200,000, <lb/>at least. In the South &amp; <lb/>Midlands of Ireland it is <lb/>now becoming the practice for<lb/> <lb/>young men of military age <lb/>to form hands sworn not to <lb/>Enlist and the <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> (<hi rend="underline">Sinn</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Fein)</hi> Volunteers are gaining <lb/>large numbers of recruits owing <lb/>to the belief that the government <lb/>will not dare to apply <lb/>compulsion to them.   It would be well to <lb/>get out the figures of recruiting <lb/>in Ireland according to Counties <lb/>&amp; Provinces. Ulster has done <lb/>very much better than South &amp; West.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4300_img_3662_4"/>
             Every anti recruiting <lb/>influence has been <lb/>given free play in <lb/>Ireland &amp; <seg type="del">a</seg>host of <lb/>papers bitterly hostile <lb/>to England are allowed <lb/>to circulate unrestricted <lb/>all over the country.   Ever sincerely yours   W.T. Bailey 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>