<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1538">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff to Lady Clonbrock, 25 February, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs. Arthur Goff</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff, honorary secretary of the Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation, to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Mrs. Goff had a similar role to Lady Clonbrock in the Irish Women&#39;s Association, formed in London in the Spring of 1915 for the purpose of providing food and comforts for prisoners of war belonging to Irish Regiments. 
Mrs. Goff is writing about looking after men prisoners who, strictly, belong to other organisations. She had sent a list of the men to the I.W.A., asking if she could retain two of the men, one in particular to whom she had sent parcels on a weekly basis since 1914.
Mrs. Goff also sends a list (not available) of all Connaught Rangers prisoners to whom she has been sending parcels from time to time. 
She says that she has many prisoners from the Dublin Fusiliers and the English Regiments but the Irish Women&#39;s Association is the only organisation &#39;which does not seem to want their funds lightened by having men taken off their hands&#39;.
There is a further note on the back of this page telling Lady Clonbrock that all of the men on her list are paid for by adopters, and she believes that this is in accord with Government policy.
An information sheet setting out the modus operandi of the Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation is enclosed.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1538</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1236">Mrs. Arthur Goff</persName>
              <date>1916-02-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0673">Belfort House, Dundrum, Co. Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1538_img_1006_1"  type="Letter"  url="38f8142d535f0eadfc17892806f429b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1538_img_1006_2"  type="Letter"  url="2b08a7ba2f989ffa3f27c016e48b903c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1538_img_1006_3"  type="Letter"  url="da70454aa1f64cc752f4171e9b865490.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1538_img_1006_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="4dc1caa8e10a7743719cef91bae9b9e0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1538_img_1006_1"/>
             Hon. Sec., <lb/>Mrs Arthur Goff, <lb/>Belfort House, Dundrum, <lb/>Co Dublin   Dundrum,  Feb 25th 1916  <lb/>Co Dublin   Dear Madam ,  In September last I wrote to the commanding <lb/> officer of the Connaught Rangers, sending him a list <lb/> of Prisoners of War I had been looking after since the <lb/> beginning of the year. In fact I had had acknowledgement <lb/>from C Hanly before Christmas 1914   Colonel Clancy's reply I enclose. As I was then a <lb/> very small organisation I feared to take the responsibility <lb/> of men who had others to look after them &amp; as the <lb/> Irish Womens Association were getting the Departmental fund <lb/> for looking after the men I felt it would not be <lb/> right to keep them. So I wrote to the Irish Womens Assoc <lb/> to that effect requesting to be allowed to keep on <lb/> Wallpole. &amp; especally Mahon. who was a local man <lb/> &amp; to   I had sent a wealthy parcel since Xmas <lb/> 1914. Their reply I also enclose. It seemed to me unreasonable <lb/> especally as all his people live near me &amp; his wife <lb/> wished me to look after him   she subscribed 2/- per <lb/> week towards his parcels. When I got Sergent Alfred <lb/> Cowell's letter I wrote again to the I W A because <lb/> they had agreed to my  him amongst others <lb/>. My letter I enclose also their answers.   I am sorry to give you all this trouble &amp; to
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1538_img_1006_2"/>
            send you so much correspondence but I fear it is <lb/> the only way to explain these things   If not asking too much I would like all enclosures <lb/> returned.   I now send you a list of the Connaughts to <lb/> whom I have been sending parcels from time <lb/> to time. If <hi rend="underline">you tell</hi> me it is no longer necessary <lb/> to do so I will stop. The names with an X against <lb/> them we have <seg type="del">send</seg>been sending a weekly parcel. to <lb/>   from Berne, tobacco &amp; cigarettes from London   I supply them with all underclothes including <lb/> boots. The weekly parcels they have been getting since <lb/> the beginning of the year. The bread soon after <lb/> that organisation was started.   I have many of the .  &amp; many more <lb/> from English.  &amp; the Irish Womens Assoc <lb/> is the only organisation which does not seem <lb/> to want their funds lightened by having   <lb/> taken off their hands.   I hope that you will continue to allow us to adopt <lb/> the men with the X against their names.   Hoping you will forgive my troubling you at such <lb/> lengths.   yrs truly   E  Goff  P.T.O.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1538_img_1006_3"/>
             All the men I have on my list are being payed <lb/> for by different adopters, It being I understand <lb/> the Government &amp; the Directors Generals wish <lb/> to encourage such private individuals &amp; <lb/>share influential friends 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1538_img_1006_4"/>
             The Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation <lb/>APPROVED BY THE WAR OFFICE <lb/>and <lb/>Under the auspices of the Central Advisory Committee, RDF   The funds of the above organisation entirely keep the men. It undertakes to look after <lb/> each prisoner by a weekly parcel of foodstuffs, a supply of bread weekly from Berne, tobacco <lb/> and cigatettes out of bond from the British and American Co., London, besides underclothing <lb/>, boots, etc.   Every man costs under 5s. per week, which includes everything except clothes.   A parcel is also despatched at once to every new appeal, of which there are many. No <lb/> matter what regiment the man may belong to the parcel is sent and continued until such time <lb/> as the man is taken on by his own Regiment or Depot.   Any man already on the list can be adopted for 2s. 6d. per week, all goods being sent in <lb/> the adopter's name; or 5s. per week for a new man or one of the adopter's own choosing.   All contributions of money, clothes (old or new), boots, etc., will be gratefully received.   Office hours at No. 1 Sydenham Road. — 11 a.m. until 1 p.pm every day except Wednesdays <lb/> and Saturdays; Tuesday afternoons from 2-30 until 6-30 p.m. for labelling and packing, when <lb/> all visitors are welcome.  <lb/>TEA-------4-30 p.m.  A Committee Meeting will be held every Friday morning at 12 noon, this being formed <lb/> of any subscribers who may wish to attend.  <lb/>All work absolutely voluntary.  Communications and contributions to be addresses to the Hon. Secretary —   MRS ARTHUR GOFF, <lb/>Belfort House, Dundrum, <lb/>Co Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>