<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5075">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell, 5 December 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

Summary of the present letter:

Letter from Willie to his mother.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5075</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-12-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5075_img_None_1"  url="5b2baaead555229b389e9ac5add004c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5075_img_None_2"  url="f53c7ce0fda66eec24e0b4eb437ead43.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5075_img_0_1"/>
              5/12/17    My dear Mamy   No news. I was delighted<lb/>to get your splendid parcel this<lb/>morning containing such a<lb/>beautiful pheasant. It came in<lb/>perfect condition and we eat it for<lb/>lunch and i intend to finish it<lb/>off tonight. Also the fruit<lb/>chocolate &amp; in fact everything in the<lb/>parcel was most acceptable.  The weather is very cold but<lb/>fine and I have lots of warm<lb/>clothes. If you have another<lb/>couple of pairs of socks, I could<lb/>do with them now as the great<lb/>difficulty here is washing, in fact<lb/>if I remain in these parts I will try<lb/>sending small parcles of washing<lb/>home. The difficulty is to get things<lb/>dried. I can get them washed in<lb/>any shell hole but I can never 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5075_img_0_2"/>
             get them really dry.  I am at present 40 feet below<lb/>ground level in a boche dug-out.<lb/>It is much better than being in<lb/>a cold trench.  I was delighted to get Daddys<lb/>long letter yesterday too.  We<lb/>have been on the move all the time<lb/>lately.  That parcel could not possibly have<lb/>come at a better time - &amp; again<lb/>thanks vey much indeed for it.<lb/>I have not run out of writing paper<lb/>but accidentally left it packed up<lb/>in my kit so have only my<lb/>note book to write in till I get<lb/>back to my kit.  Best love to all<lb/> Your most affect Son<lb/>Willie   P.S. Bobby seems to be getting on<lb/>A.1. now. His writing is<lb/>wonderfully improved.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>