<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1486">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs. E.N. Gilbert to Nancy O'Rahilly, 30 August 1916. </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs. E. N. Gilbert</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). The writer, Mrs. E.N. Gilbert, refers to the birth of Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s son. She writes that it is &#39;glorious to be the mother of a man&#39; - even though, it seems, the writer&#39;s preference would have been a daughter. She urges Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly to tell her boys all about their heroic father, Michael (1875-1916), and this will help bring them to a heroic manhood worthy of his memory and fame.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly. The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/092/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1486</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0511">Mrs. E. N. Gilbert</persName>
              <date>1916-08-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0956">825 North 20th Street, Philadelphia, U.S.A.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1486_img_939_1"  type="Letter"  url="e121b0d7235aa973d1842188541a3e15.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1486_img_939_2"  type="Letter"  url="d287cdac97fd6d136d2e9d2a1c2a1321.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1486_img_939_1"/>
                August 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    825 N.20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> St.  Phila   Dear, dear Nannie   Had it been the <lb/> will of our dear Lord, I surely <lb/>would have rejoiced in your having <lb/> a daughter, but it is glorious to <lb/> be the mother of a <hi rend="underline">man</hi> and <lb/> you must grow every day <lb/> more and more proud of your  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1486_img_939_2"/>
              <lb/>five splendid sons. I cannot express <lb/> the love and sorrow for you that <lb/> are filling my heart, yet I <hi rend="underline">know</hi><lb/>that you will be sustained and <lb/>comforted and the words that <lb/> you can say to your boys of their <lb/> heroic father will be all sufficient <lb/> aid to you in leading them up <lb/> to a manhood worthy of his <lb/> memory and fame. Dr. and Mr. Gilbert <lb/> want to be remembered and I'll pray <lb/> that some time even in this life we may <lb/> see you. <seg type="closer"> Mrs. E. N. Gilbert </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>