<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3265">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from G. W. Scroope to William Dawson, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>G. W. Scroope</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5616-3607-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3265</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0053">G. W. Scroope</persName>
              <date>1916-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0936">The Central Criminal Lunatic Asylum, Dundrum, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1322">William Dawson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0936">The Central Criminal Lunatic Asylum, Dundrum, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3265_img_2682_1"  type="Letter"  url="a5b685a33b72a729a004de15e812aa44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3265_img_2682_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5dd9f706b828999abf3e167c7c1ce75.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3265_img_2682_1"/>
             1809  In any further correspondence on<lb/>this subject, the following number<lb/>must be quoted<lb/>5445/15.<lb/>Subject :-  All communications<lb/>to be addressed to—<lb/>The Governor,<lb/> The Central Asylum,<lb/>Dundrum,<lb/>Co.Dublin <lb/><lb/> The Central Criminal Lunatic Asylum,<lb/>Dundrum, Co. Dublin <lb/><lb/> 22nd December 1915 <lb/><lb/> Gentlemen   I reply to your inquiry per telephone to—day<lb/>regarding the financial estimate for the year 1916—17, I beg<lb/>to state that it would not be adviasable to make any reduction<lb/>in the provision under Sub—heads E. and F.  Owing to the fact that in the year 1904—5, it was<lb/>found necessary to obtain a Supplementary Estimate of £60, these<lb/>two sub—heads were raised in accordance with the instructions<lb/>contained in your letter No 70, dated  9th March 1905 , as follows;-  I am also to state that the estimate for 1905—6 cannot<lb/>now be increased, and that the total sum provided must there—<lb/>fore be made to meet all charges, but for future years you should<lb/>leave a margin on the vote to provide for such contingencies as<lb/>have arisen this year. The Treasury suggest that this might be<lb/>done either by reducing the deduction from the Victualling <lb/>Sub-head   To The Inspectors<lb/>of Lunatics <lb/> DUBBLIN CASTLE.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3265_img_2682_2"/>
             (2)  Sub—head (say from the £200 to £100), or by adding substantial<lb/>sum to some item of the vote as a precautionary measure.  The latter practice has since been adopted, as the same<lb/>contingencies might occur again in any year, and in fact a<lb/>supplementary vote has on more than one occasion been avoided<lb/>by the application of the savings on some sub—heads towards<lb/>the excesses on other subheads  With regard to the reciepts or credit sub—head, I<lb/>beg to quote the follownig balances on the Farm and Garden at<lb/>the close of  the  finiancial year stated:-<lb/><lb/>1904-5 £201<lb/>1905-6 £200<lb/>1909-10 £202<lb/>1910-11 £204<lb/>1911-12 £206<lb/>1913-14 £207  Any other receipts mentioned <seg type="del">other</seg> under this heading are<lb/>surrendered to the Exchequer as Exchequer Extra Receipts.  As it has been proved n former years that the<lb/>balance on the Farm aand Garden does not generally exceed the<lb/>sum of £200 to any appreciable extent, it would not be advis-<lb/>able to raise thee appropriation in ad of the Victualling Sub-<lb/>head beyond this sum.   I am, Gentlemen,<lb/>Yourr obedent Servant<lb/>G. W. Scroope [Questonable reading.]<lb/>Resident Physician Governon.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>