<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5280">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Victoria Mary Tyrrell 1, April, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell writes to wish his sister a happy birthday. He is in a different country than he was before. The streets are paved with big stones. His journey took 54 hours and was mainly by train. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5280</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-04-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5280_img_None_1"  url="96e918742d9f3a05a154d51c0e80e329.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5280_img_None_2"  url="bcdb2110beeaa805e67c7087b591db58.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5280_img_None_3"  url="695b7a0eaf6868544defaf742cc6e9af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5280_img_None_4"  url="2e10e63ad97f487d828b33daa8545485.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5280_img_0_1"/>
              1 April 1917    My dear Minnie,   Just a birthday letter and I hope it will arrive<lb/>in time. Many happy returns of the day. Here I am<lb/>now with the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd </hi>Batt so address my letters<lb/>accordingly. This is a totally different kind of<lb/>place to any I have seen out here before. Of<lb/>course it would be as we are in a different<lb/>country. We are out in huts several miles<lb/>behind the lines and you would not know<lb/>that there was a war on at all unless you were<lb/>told. I do not know how long we will be<lb/>here <seg type="del">as</seg> but when we do leave it is to go<lb/>further back from the line so I do not expect<lb/>to be in the trenches for some time.<hi rend="underline"> </hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">There is</hi></hi></hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"></hi><lb/><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">no necessity </hi> <hi rend="underline"> for me </hi> </hi></hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"> </hi></hi></hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">to write every day</hi></hi> </hi>and<lb/>there will be nothing to write about. It was<lb/>a long journey up from the base and for<lb/>some unknown reason they brought us<lb/>round in a semicircle. The journey occupied<lb/>altogether about 54 hours. I arrived with the<lb/>battalion at 4 am this morning <seg type="del">le </seg>Luckily<lb/>I met some other officers who were coming  <seg type="unclear"></seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5280_img_0_2"/>
             here too and they knew the way. There was a<lb/>cart for our kit at the station. We had about<lb/>5 miles to walk so when we got in it didnot<lb/>take me long to get to sleep. It was lucky<lb/>that I had lots of grub for the train. One<lb/>fellow had a tommy cooker (which I forgot<lb/>to get) and I had lots of Bovril so we<lb/>made it but we had no water that we<lb/>could be sure of so we made it with Vichy<lb/>water. It is some thing like soda water<lb/>but went very well. This place is very<lb/>clean and dry. The roads are all paved with<lb/>big paving stones. The lane into the camp<lb/>is the only bad bit we met at all.  There are very few here whom I know<lb/>except some who got their commisions<lb/>lately from the ranks. The C.O and <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>seem very nice as indeed does every one.  We are near some good towns so I<lb/>do not think I need any parcels at present<lb/>as we can get most things. I will write<lb/>and let you know if there is anything<lb/>I want but of course I have not got<lb/>settled down properly yet as I have only<lb/>been here a few hours. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5280_img_0_3"/>
             The train we came in had only two speeds<lb/>slow and stop! and it usually went at<lb/>the latter speed. but it was quite interesting<lb/>in the day time. It stopped for hours in<lb/>some places but one never knew when it would<lb/>go on again so could not get out though<lb/>I would very much like to have seen<lb/>some of the places we passed thro'.<lb/>I would have nearly had time to go &amp;<lb/>see Charlie Davison but had no idea<lb/>how long the train would wait.  Certainly this is a very quiet place. Far<lb/>different to where I was before. Jack Day<lb/>must be somewhere about here I think.<lb/>Also Dick White.<lb/>We have a nice sitting room here with lots<lb/>of papers etc to read and nice tables to<lb/>write at. I am writing this in it. You see<lb/>how far back we are when we can do<lb/>that. I do not know when the letters come<lb/>in or go out or anything here but they do not<lb/> got ti  go till evening sometime so this will<lb/>go today. Be sure and tell me how long<lb/>it takes my letters to reach you  I am beginning to forget the numbers 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5280_img_0_4"/>
             of my letters already so dont be surprised<lb/>if they go wrong. However I will try to keep a<lb/>note of them as it is a very good check.  I may be near where Garrett is too but<lb/>if so he is not near where you thought  he was. I met <seg type="unclear">Major</seg> Hume Kelly down at<lb/>the base the other day. You remember he<lb/>was adjutant of the camp I was at before  There is nothing more to say that I<lb/>can think of at present so with very best<lb/>wishes and with best love to all  Your most affec brother  <hi rend="underline">Willee.</hi>  P.S  I did <seg type="unclear">now</seg> find the little girl at Havre<lb/>as she had gone to Rouen and I had<lb/>no time there. Wasnt that bad luck. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>