<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5117">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 19, July, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell is working on roads and has experienced heavy rain. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5117</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-07-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5117_img_None_1"  url="9f46bc7266cbb619668c1b2cfc25e787.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5117_img_None_2"  url="7212022c3138213abdebc377b8be6e1d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5117_img_0_1"/>
              19 July 1917    My dearest Daddy   No real news of any kind. Everything<lb/>is just as usual. I am no longer quarter<lb/>master as Foster has returned from leave.  I am now back and in A company this time<lb/>Col. Goodman has got the D.S.O for the<lb/>last show Everyone is greatly pleased.  We are at present working on roads.<lb/>We have had some very heavy rain<lb/>the last two days. I hope your hay is<lb/>not getting it too. It would be a great<lb/>matter if you could get it up and done<lb/>with.  I hear rumours that we are going back<lb/>again shortly to where we just left.  I do not know whether there is any<lb/>foundation for them or not.  It will be great when you get Minnie<lb/>and Bobby home next week.  I am sure <lb/>you were very lonely without them.  <lb/>I see that the Nationalists say there is<lb/>no use to think trying to <seg type="unclear">coalist</seg> wh    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5117_img_0_2"/>
             the cluster in Kilkenny.  I wonder what will be the upshot<lb/>of the Convention. Probably a fice<lb/>fight.  I also note that they have to<lb/>bring Carson into the War Council<lb/>again.   No news so with best love from<lb/>Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>