<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1165">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 11 March 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the Catalogue of the Province recently received by Shaw.Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/23, IJA/CHPI/54/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1165</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1165_img_3841_1"  type="Letter"  url="0268c3ef275058cbb734bfb54fefff88.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1165_img_3841_1"/>
                11 March 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   I received by yesterday's mail, a letter from you, <lb/>the catalogue of the Province, two post cards with notice of death of <lb/>Father <seg type="unclear">Vendon</seg> and Father <seg type="unclear">Rothwell</seg>. R.I.P.; and a note from Fr Stanley. Thanks <lb/>very much for the catalogue. I feel more a member of the Province since <lb/>it came, and am very glad to know of the whereabouts of everybody. I <lb/>hope father McCann will come along. Ft Walton I have not met yet. My <lb/>parish is about half an hour smart walk from end to end, and is <lb/>made up of about twenty different units. My census so far has given me <lb/>106 Catholics, and is not yet completed. There is a Benedictine, father <lb/>Campbell, in a Hospital Unit here, who comes from Erdington, and knows <lb/>your brother Dom Patrick Nolan D.S.D. Ft Frank Browne's eldest brother is a <lb/>Doctor in the same hospital. Frank himself wrote to me by last mail. <lb/>His brother seemed to think he was in Italy, but his letter, dated 7 January, <lb/>came from France. He is a marvel.  I find my tent, which I share with C. of E. chaplain, is larger than I <lb/>expected. I put up a screen across my table, and have mass over before <lb/>he gets his nose out of the sleeping bag. However I told him not to let <lb/>me interfere with him in any way. I have proved in my own experience <lb/>during the war that God looks after people who are not much good at <lb/>looking after themselves.When I came to the tent there was not a stick <lb/>in it except the supporting bamboo poles. Before the week <lb/>was out a Catholic soldier on a railway-job had provided me with a <lb/>lovely reading table, which makes a splendid altar, and some large <lb/>pieces of rush-matting for my mud-floor; while an Indian sub-assistant <lb/>surgeon turned up soon after with some wooden cases for book <lb/>shelves - and all this on their own.  My present address, as I think I told your Reverence, is <lb/>no.16. Casualty clearing station. Mesopotamian Expeditionary Froce. All our <lb/>letters go home through Bombay, but some of yours out come direct. Anything <lb/>addresssed to Archbishop's House,Woodenhouse Rd. Fort. Bombay, will of course <lb/>still reach me; but 16 C.C.S. may be a week or two quicker.  Lastly, my younger sister wrote to me last October for some money, the letter only <lb/>reaching me today. I should feel very grateful if your Reverence could send her <lb/>on a little to Miss K. Shaw, o/e Mrs. Chandler, 66 Leith Mansions, <lb/>Elgin Avenue, Maiden Vale, London, W., <seg type="closer"> Your Reverence's sincerely in Christ  Francis M. Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>