<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0496">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Henderson Todd to J. M.Campbell, 28 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Henderson Todd</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Robert Henderson Todd (b. 1851), crown solicitor for the county and city of Londonderry, to James Henry Musen Campbell. In this letter Todd requests leave for a holiday in Buxton. He states that there is no pending criminal business for the County or City of Londonderry and that his leave would not be in conflict with the interests of his duty. He writes that his partner would be present during his leave and would inform him of any criminal activity during his leave.In April 1916, James Henry Musen Campbell (1851 - 1931) was appointed attorney general for Ireland. His formal re-election as MP, which was then necessary on assuming office, took place on Easter Monday 1916 as the Easter rising broke out.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13162</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/496</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1078">Robert Henderson Todd</persName>
              <date>1916-07-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1535">6 Shipquay Street, Londonderry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">J. M. Campbell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0496_img_1861_1"  type="Letter"  url="abaa8774971a4bb2817c74c6be99ff46.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0496_img_1861_1"/>
              Todd &amp;&amp; Mark<lb/> Solicitors<lb/> Robert Henderson Todd M A L L D<lb/> Crown Solicitor for County<lb/> and City of Londonderry<lb/> John Martin Mark<lb/><hi rend="underline">Telephone N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 149</hi><lb/>   6 Shipquay Street  Londonderry    28th July 1916   Dear Sir,   If you will be good enough to permit me, I propose <lb/> going to Buxton on Monday for the month of August.   There is no criminal business for the County or City <lb/> of Londonderry pending at present requiring my presence, and I do <lb/> not anticipate that my personal attendance will be requisite during <lb/> the month of August.   My Partner will be here during the month, and I have <lb/> arranged that any criminal business coming in will be promptly <lb/> attended to and that I shall be at once informed of any case arising <lb/> during the month.   If necessary, I shall, on receipt of a wire, be here <lb/> next day.   I trust you will be good enough to permit me to take <lb/> this holiday, which I very much require.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  R H Todd   The Rt. Hon. J. M. Campbell K. C., M.P  Attorney General for Ireland,  The Castle,  Dublin.   </seg> Request approved <lb/> Initialled 29-7-16 <lb/> Noted W P H 1/8 <lb/> Noted initialled 1/8 <lb/> Registered 31-7-16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>