<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3300">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Carroll to Henry Edward Duke, 1 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Carroll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10495-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3300</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1185">Joseph Carroll</persName>
              <date>1916-08-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0195">43 Merrion Square, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Henry Edward Duke</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_1"  type="Letter"  url="420bb204b27addf736d5b89195a596d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_2"  type="Letter"  url="93aee0a1d683dd7d13bd96d33b65abd0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="eaf3ccde67ba9cf477260bd3b77ebb62.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="e044b968568dd29fcb63451225aa0e4b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="a026ae08f00d083f9138e3fc7052a7cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="0655ce5b6f34111f179e9a567802c4c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="e84ebc6975d1eff393070965f148d5d6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="8541341c51ac4d75d4176008f017ac7a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="ce825158aa0d9ece568cfdb3cc064e1c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3300_img_2715_10"  type="Enclosure"  url="de9d7b6497428c8ee2fc1a841f845300.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">IRELAND.</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">REPORT.</hi>   43, Merrion Square, Dublin, ,<lb/> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> August, 1916. <lb/><lb/> Sir,   I have the Honour herewith to submit a report of the work<lb/>done in Ireland during the year 1915, under the Act 39 &amp; 40 Vict. c.77,<lb/>together with the following tabular statements:-<lb/>Table I. List of places registered under the Act for the<lb/>performance of experiments (18).<lb/>Table II. List of licensees who performed no experiments (16).<lb/>Table III. Number and nature of experiments performed by<lb/>each licensee.  An outhouse and laboratory at the Military Barracks, Tipperary<lb/>has been added to the list of registered places.  The number of persons holding licences at the end of 1915 was 27.<lb/>There were four new licences issued, 3 lapsed, 1 licensee died and<lb/>one licence was revoked at the request of the licensee. The<lb/>renewal of two licences was deferred.  The following certificates lapsed during the year:-<lb/>Five of A, one of B, two of C, one of EE, and one of F.<lb/>And new Certificates were granted as follows:-<lb/>Six of A, <sic>oneof</sic> B, and one of C.<lb/>Table III. shows that <seg type="del">590</seg> 590 experiments were performed by 17<lb/>licensees, 66 being under licence alone and 524 under certificate.  <lb/>488   To the Right Honourable<lb/>the Chief Secretary to the<lb/>Lord Lieutenant of Ireland  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_2"/>
             488 were simple inoculations under Certificate A. In 91 cases <lb/>the object of the research was physi o logical; in 442 the object <lb/>was pathological, and 57 <seg type="del">with</seg> had a therapeutic aim.   Three communications to learned <sic>socities</sic> are recorded as based <lb/>upon the experiments of 1915; two of them on  physiological  problems <seg type="del">of physiology</seg> <lb/>and one pathological.   I have every reason to believe that the holders of licences <lb/>have obeyed the spirit as well as the letter of the Act, and that <lb/>experiments have not been unnecessarily multiplied,   I am,&amp;c.,   Joseph O'Carroll 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_3"/>
             <lb/><hi rend="superscript">RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS. 25</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">IRELAND—continued.</hi><lb/>TABLE 1.<lb/>List of existing Places Registered for the performance of Experiments<lb/>under the Act 39 &amp; 40 Vict. cap. 77, in 191<seg type="del">4</seg>5<lb/>Place. Name of Registered Building<lb/>Dublin - - Albert Agricultural College (formerly Albert Model Farm), Glasnevin, — The Bacterio-<lb/>logical Laboratory. (<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>)<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Mater Misericordiae Hospital.— The Bacteriological Laboratory.<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - National Calf Vaccine Institute, Sandymount Road.<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Royal College of Science.— The Laboratory of Advanced Bacteriology.<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Royal College of <sic>Surgeous'</sic> School.—The Pathological and Physiological Laboratories. (<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>)<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Royal Veterinary College of Ireland.—The Pathological and Bacteriological Laboratories.<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Steevens' Hospital.—The Pathological Laboratory.<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Trinity College.—The Pathological and Physiological Laboratories.(<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>)<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - University College.—The Bacteriological Laboratory, Medical School, Cecilia Street.<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - -   <!-- University College --> The Physiological Department (Earlsfort Terrace).<lb/><!-- Dublin --> - - Veterinary Branch of the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for<lb/>Ireland.— The Diagnosis Laboratory.<lb/>Belfast - - Queen's University.—The Pathological and Physiological Laboratories.<lb/>Cork - - University College.—The Pathological and Physiological Laboratories. (<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>)<lb/>Galway --   <!-- University College --> The Physiological Laboratory.<lb/>Tipperary Military Barracks. An out-house and Laboratory.<lb/>(<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>) No person was licensed to perform experiments in this registered place during 191<seg type="del">4</seg>5<lb/>(<hi rend="superscript">b</hi>) The Laboratories in these places are registered separately.<lb/>O 326 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_4"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">26 RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS.</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">IRELAND—continued.</hi> <lb/>TABLE II. <lb/>List of Licensees who returned No Experiments under their Licences and <lb/>Certificates in 191<seg type="del">4</seg>5 <!-- table not transcribed --> Summary of Table II. Number of Licensees who returned no experiments - <seg type="del">10</seg> " Certificates A - - - - - <seg type="del">5</seg> " " B - - - - - <seg type="del">2</seg> " " EE - - - - - <seg type="del">1</seg> " " C - - - - - <seg type="del">1</seg>  Crofton W.M. <lb/>M.D. <lb/>Certificate A.   The Pathological Laboratory <lb/>Dr Steven's Hospital <lb/>Dublin   Denham J. <seg type="unclear">Kura</seg> <lb/>F.R.C.S.I. <lb/>Certificate A   The National Calf <lb/>Vaccine Institute, <lb/>Dublin.   Mason F.C. <lb/>M.R.C.V.S. <lb/>Certificat A   <seg type="unclear">Miller</seg> B.H. <lb/>M.R.C.V.S. <lb/>Certificate 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_5"/>
             <lb/><hi rend="underline">RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS. 27</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">IRELAND—continued.</hi><lb/>TABLE III.<lb/>Showing the Number and the Nature of Experiments returned by each<lb/>LICENSEE during the Year 191<seg type="del">4</seg>5 <!-- table not transcribed -->  [Table not transcribed. See table/image.] 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_6"/>
            <lb/>Table II (continued) <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Allister J.J. <lb/>Pye J.P. <lb/>Stokes   <lb/>Thompson W.H. <lb/>M.D. ScD.
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_7"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS.</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">IRELAND.</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">REPORT.</hi>  43, Merrion Square, Dublin,   <seg type="del">31st</seg> August <seg type="del">1915</seg>. 1916   Sir,   I have the honour herewith to submit a report of the work done in Ireland during <lb/>the year 191<seg type="del">4</seg>5 under the Act 39 &amp; 40 Vict. c. 77, together with the following tabular <lb/>statements :— <lb/>Table I. - List of places registered under the Act for the performance of <lb/>experiments <seg type="del">(17)</seg>. (18) <lb/>Table II. - List of licensees who performed no experiments <seg type="del">(19)</seg>. (16) <lb/>Table III. - Number and nature of experiments performed by each licensee.   <seg type="del">The Physiological Laboratory of University College, Galway,</seg>  An outhouse and laboratory at the Military Barracks Tipperary  has been added to the <lb/>list of registered places.   The number of persons holding licences at the end of 191<seg type="del">4</seg>5 was <seg type="del">39;</seg> 27 <seg type="del">an increase</seg> There were 4 <seg type="del">of 5</seg> new licenses.  issued, 3 lapsed, 1 licensee died and 1 licence was <seg type="unclear">revoked</seg> at the request of the licensee. The renewal of two licenses was deferred.   The following certificates lapsed during the year:— <lb/>Five <seg type="del">Six</seg> of A, <seg type="del">one</seg>  one of B, two  of C, and <seg type="del">one</seg> one of EE,  one of F .   And new Certificates were granted as follows :— <lb/><seg type="del">Eight</seg> Six of A, <seg type="del">three</seg> one of B, <seg type="del">two</seg> one of C, <seg type="del">one of EE, and one of F.</seg>   Table III. shows that <seg type="del">340</seg> 590 experiments were preformed by <seg type="del">20</seg> 17 licensees, <seg type="del">92</seg> 66 being <lb/>under licence alone and <seg type="del">248</seg> 524 under certificate. <seg type="del">210</seg> 488 were simple inoculations under <lb/>Certificate A, <seg type="del">of which 86 were made for the investigation of diseases of the lower <lb/>animals</seg>. In <seg type="del">132</seg> 91 cases the object of the research was physiological ; in <seg type="del">198</seg> 442 the <lb/>object was pathological,  and 59  with <seg type="del">either a diagnostic of</seg> a therapeutic aim ; <seg type="del">and in eight <lb/>cases the aim was medico legal.</seg>   <seg type="del">Three</seg> Three communications to learned societies are recorded as based upon the <lb/>experiments of <seg type="del">1914</seg> 1915 ; <seg type="del">all</seg> two of them on problems of physiology,  and one pathological.    <seg type="del">It occurs to me that where so many problems especially pertaining to the public <lb/>health are being examined by earnest and well-qualified persons they might be <lb/>invited to record in their annual reports a brief note of any results definitely <lb/>acquired by them. The fact that tubercle bacilli have been found in this or that <lb/>proportion of samples of milk submitted to examination ought to have publicity in <lb/>the interest of public health ; as things are at present, modesty or want of leisure may <lb/>delay or prevent the publication of results which may be of great importance. If <lb/>such results were recorded in licensees' returns this annual report would acquire a <lb/>scientific value ; while subsequent fuller publication of methods and results would <lb/>rather be promoted than prejudiced.</seg>   I have every reason to believe that the holders of licences have obeyed the <lb/>spirit as well as the letter of the Act, and that experiments have not been <lb/>unnecessarily multiplied.   I am, &amp;c.,   <seg type="del">Joseph O'Carroll.</seg>   To the Right Honourable <lb/>the Chief Secretary of the <lb/>Lord Lieutenant of Ireland. 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_8"/>
             <!-- Same page as image 10, but crossed over> <hi rend=\'underline\"><seg type="del">RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS. 23</hi> <lb/>Weizsacker, V. Wilson, S.A. Kinnier. Wright, Sir A.E. <lb/>White, C.P. Winfield, G. Yanagawa, H. <lb/>Willan, R.J. Woodman, E. M. Yates, A.G. <lb/>Williams, Major C. L. Woodward, H.M.M. Young, Miss M. C.W. <lb/>Wilson, J.T. Woolff, A.E.M. <lb/><hi rend=\'underline\"></hi> <lb/>TABLE IV. <lb/>LIST OF LICENSEES who have been unable, owing to absence on War Duty, <lb/>to furnish the RETURNS required. <lb/>Armstrong, R.R Lukis, T.S. Page, C.M. <lb/>Greenfield, J.G. Morley, J. Sewell, W.T. <lb/>Leishman, Sir W.B. Oliver, G.Y.</seg>-->[Table not transcribed. See table/image.] 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_9"/>
             RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS  <hi rend="underline">IRELAND.</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">REPORT.</hi>   43, Merrion Square, Dublin,    31st August 1915.    Sir,   I have the honour herewith to submit a report of the work done in Ireland during<lb/>the year 1914 under the Act 39 &amp; 40 Vict. c. 77, together with the following tabular<lb/>statements :—<lb/>Table I. - List of places registered under the Act for the performance of<lb/>experiments (17).<lb/>Table II. - List of licensees who performed no experiments (10).<lb/>Table III. - Number and nature of experiments performed by each licensee.  The Physiological Laboratory of University College, Galway, has been added to the<lb/>list of registered places.  The number of persons holding licences at the end of 1914 was 30; an increase<lb/>of 5 new licences.  The following certificates lapsed during the year:—<lb/>Six of A, one of C, and one of E.  And new Certificates were granted as follows :—<lb/>Eight of A, three of B, two of C, one of EE, and one of F.  Table III. shows that 340 experiments were preformed by 20 licensees, 92 being<lb/>under licence alone and 248 under certificate. 210 were simple inoculations under<lb/>Certificate A, of which 86 were made for the investigation of diseases of the lower<lb/>animals. In 132 cases the object of the research was physiological ; in 198 the<lb/>object was pathological, with either a diagnostic or a therapeutic aim ; and in eight<lb/>cases the aim was medico legal.  Three communications to learned societies are recorded as based upon the<lb/>experiments of 1914 ; all of them on problems of physiology.  It occurs to me that where so many problems especially pertaining to the public<lb/>health are being examined by earnest and well-qualified persons they might be<lb/>invited to record in their annual reports a brief note of any results definitely<lb/>acquired by them. The fact that tubercle bacilli have been found in this or that<lb/>proportion of samples of milk submitted to examination ought to have publicity in<lb/>the interest of public health ; as things are at present, modesty or want of leisure may<lb/>delay or prevent the publication of results which may be of great importance. If<lb/>such results were recorded in licensees' returns this annual report would acquire a<lb/>scientific value ; while subsequent fuller publication of methods and results would<lb/>rather be promoted than prejudiced.  I have every reason to believe that the holders of licences have obeyed the<lb/>spirit as well as the letter of the Act, and that experiments have not been<lb/>unnecessarily multiplied.  I am, &amp;c.,   Joseph O'Carroll.    To the Right Honourable<lb/>the Chief Secretary of the<lb/>Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_3300_img_2715_10"/>
            <hi rend="underline">RETURN RELATING TO EXPERIMENTS ON LIVING ANIMALS. 23</hi> <lb/>Weizsacker, V. Wilson, S.A. Kinnier. Wright, Sir A.E. <lb/>White, C.P. Winfield, G. Yanagawa, H. <lb/>Willan, R.J. Woodman, E. M. Yates, A.G. <lb/>Williams, Major C. L. Woodward, H.M.M. Young, Miss M. C.W. <lb/>Wilson, J.T. Woolff, A.E.M. <lb/><hi rend="underline"></hi> <lb/>TABLE IV. <lb/>LIST OF LICENSEES who have been unable, owing to absence on War Duty, <lb/>to furnish the RETURNS required. <lb/>Armstrong, R.R Lukis, T.S. Page, C.M. <lb/>Greenfield, J.G. Morley, J. Sewell, W.T. <lb/>Leishman, Sir W.B. Oliver, G.Y.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>