<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0849">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Postcard to Lily O'Brennan, 5 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Postcard addressed to the home of Éamonn Ceannt (1881-1916), at 2 Dolphin&#39;s Terrace, Dolphin&#39;s Barn, Dublin. The letter is unsigned. It is addressed to a Miss O&#39;Brennan, likely to be Miss Lily O&#39;Brennan (1878-1948), Ceannt&#39;s sister in law. This postcard discusses the distribution of a certificate related to Cumann na mBan business.Eamonn Ceannt was one of the leaders of the Easter Rising and a signatory of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic. During the Rising he commanded the garrison in the South Dublin Union. Following the surrender he was tried by court-martial and sentenced to death. He was executed on 8 May 1916. Aine Ceannt (1880-1954), a leading member of Cumann na mBan since 1914, fully supported her husband&#39;s separatist activities. She would later become active in the running of the Volunteer Dependants&#39; Fund, the Dáil courts, Sinn Féin, the Irish White Cross, and the Children&#39;s Relief Association. Áine&#39;s sister, Miss Lily O&#39;Brennan, lived with the Ceannts in Dolphin&#39;s Barn, throughout their married life. She was also a founding member of Cumann na mBan.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br. Allen Collection, Ceannt Collection, IE/AL/CC/1/31</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/849</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-04-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lily O&#39;Brennan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1650">2 Dolphin's Terrace, Dolphin's Barn, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0849_img_2409_1"  type="Letter"  url="1095db964365c5ece961b2a29bc065d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0849_img_2409_2"  type="Letter"  url="2f389568362a0ba528422d9f48d9337a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0849_img_2409_1"/>
                 Miss C Brennan  2 Dolphin Ter.  Dolphins Barn  Dublin     
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0849_img_2409_2"/>
                 <hi rend="underline">5/4/16</hi>   <hi rend="underline">Cnamb</hi>   The certificate will be distributed <lb/> at 25. on Friday next. I trust <lb/> you will find it convenient to attend.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>