<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4171">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lilian Spender. Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/56</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4171</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4171_img_3543_1"  type="Letter"  url="36402faff42f1e1946a7fb12b69c55c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4171_img_3543_2"  type="Letter"  url="aa693d0fec20dca52198e2c22c42e252.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4171_img_3543_3"  type="Letter"  url="f9cfbec3cfb0ebab7100ba2bd1caa869.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4171_img_3543_4"  type="Letter"  url="ee5ed262145333828eac94aa3adcf7a3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4171_img_3543_1"/>
             Nov. 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   Business.   My   Whilst I think of it. If you should <lb/>find yourself in the vicinity of the light blue <lb/>Rubber handbook &amp; can get it <hi rend="underline">without trouble</hi> I <lb/>wish you would take out all the loose bits of <lb/>paper in it &amp; send them to me. They are <lb/>scattered all over the book from Bukit Rajah <lb/>Castlefield  Hayton Hongkong  Kipityallu Kidingh N Hummock Selanger <lb/>United Shelfor <seg type="unclear">Ginoa Hunter Sewing</seg> &amp; possibly elsewhere.   I should like to glance at them in order <lb/>to estimate their prospect for the next few months <lb/>in order to see how much we can put in to <lb/>the War loans when they come out. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4171_img_3543_2"/>
             One ought to do as much as one can, &amp; tho' <lb/>we shall not know our personal outgoings till you <lb/>get settled down to your new life whatever it is, but <lb/>it will be something to have an estimate of incommings <lb/>however rough &amp; unreliable it may prove. You might, <lb/>whenever you get the passbook copy out the month's <lb/>extracts - no, there is no reason to bother<seg type="del">y</seg> you with <lb/>this as you can send me the passbook, but if you <lb/>happen to remember what Cox's charged against me <lb/>for my <seg type="del">£</seg> F<hi rend="superscript">co</hi> 100 I should rather like to know, as <lb/>it ought not to be more than £3.14-6 I think, &amp; <lb/>if they do I shall feel inclined to have notes sent <lb/>out   If you pay any calls for me would you let <lb/>me know, &amp; you will remember in estimating our <lb/>balance <seg type="del">a)</seg> that it includes <lb/>a) Carson money for office <lb/>b) Spender IV divisible at end of quarter
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4171_img_3543_3"/>
            &amp; that the calls of various kinds have to be paid <lb/>including £20 a <hi rend="underline">quarter</hi> to Carnsmoney <lb/>£35 each <hi rend="underline">half year</hi> life insurance <lb/>etc   These points of course necessitate rather a large <lb/>floating balance unless <seg type="del">you</seg> one calculates rather exactly <lb/>the dates of amounts due in &amp; out, which is not <lb/>always possible.    <hi rend="underline">If</hi> rubber keeps up above 2/6 our total combined <lb/>income including pay should be very nearly £2000 &amp; if <lb/>that proves to be the case we ought to put £1200 into the <lb/>War loan I think as my expenses in spite of occasional <lb/><seg type="unclear">fresh</seg> coats of fur &amp; other people's wine bills should not <lb/>be high  £12 a month?  The worst of it is an cannot look afraid, as <lb/>rubber might quite easily drop to 1/3 in which can <lb/>our income would be £1100 less, or this war might end <lb/>&amp; we want to buy a house! but all the same I want
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4171_img_3543_4"/>
             to stretch as far as I dare with a pr's permission for <lb/>the War loans - then will probably be many which <lb/>helps matter -. I wish I could feel hat it would be <lb/>expended all on rightful purposes, but I'm afraid 1/3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> is <lb/>badly &amp; extravagantly used. As long as nothing goes to <lb/><seg type="unclear">Squijfy's</seg> salary! Let me have your views <lb/>on this long epistle.   W. BS. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>