<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5154">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 16, June, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell expresses gratitude for a parcel containing cake and lemonade. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5154</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-06-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5154_img_None_1"  url="bde715842bd33de05f1c2eacecce4cb2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5154_img_None_2"  url="cdbdaf8deac77e21997345165ab9efcb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5154_img_0_1"/>
              16 June 1917.    My dearest Mamy   A thousand thanks for the lovely parcel<lb/>which came yesterday. Really you are more<lb/>than good. You have no idea how I love<lb/>them and everything is so delicious. That<lb/>cake is lovely and comes, in, I think better<lb/>condition that the fruit cake. The last two<lb/>parcels were particularly acceptable as up here<lb/>it is not easy to get extra stuff.  Those sweets two are lovely and the<lb/>lemonade A1 in this hot weather. It is<lb/>impossible to find a cool place anywhere.  You speak of cold in your letters.<lb/>I wish we had some of it.  In that Irish Life you sent I see an<lb/>account of the death of Col. T. V. P. Mc Common<lb/>and they have put in a photo of W.G.C.<lb/>McCammond of the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd </hi>and called it<lb/>T.V P Mc Cammon. I wonder what does<lb/>he think of it.  I am very glad to see that Bobby<hi rend="superscript"></hi> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5154_img_0_2"/>
             is sticking up for his own as<lb/>described in his P S to his letter He<lb/>is developing the offensive spirit.  There is not much news as you<lb/>can imagine. We are in camp well<lb/>behind and I expect will be going<lb/>right back.  Will write soon again but not<lb/>tomorrow as there is nothing to<lb/>write about.  With very best love from<lb/> Your most affec Son<lb/><hi rend="underline">Willie</hi>     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>