<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1242">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 16 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) expressing joy at her her letter confirming her affection for him and their engagement. James also advises May to warn her brother about news he has heard in relation to the beef market and regrets that she will not be able to visit him in Dublin as soon as he hoped.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1242</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-01-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0787">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1242_img_431_1"  type="Letter"  url="8ea1194a076e4fec2eb7ecd7af4238d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1242_img_431_2"  type="Letter"  url="342a9619bd4de3bad0084cbe076eb354.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1242_img_431_3"  type="Letter"  url="32c91112ca202f23a1b064c2eb30cdb2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1242_img_431_1"/>
                39, Belgrave Square,  Rathmines,  Dublin.    16th Jan, 1916.   My dear, dear girl,   This will have to be a <lb/>short letter if I am to catch the <lb/>post so I hope you will forgive me. <lb/>I need hardly tell you how delighted <lb/>I was to have your dear letter <lb/>and to see by it that you have a <lb/>real affection for me. I know that <lb/>I don't deserve it and I keep <lb/>wondering all the time what I have  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1242_img_431_2"/>
              ever done to deserve such a blessing. <lb/>I suppose good intentions sometimes <lb/>earn a reward such as your love <lb/>is and I know anyway that my <lb/>present intentions are sincere and <lb/>good. I hope, however badly the <lb/>execution may turn out, with <lb/>you to help me perhaps it may not <lb/>be so bad as I sometimes fear.  Well, my dearest, I was sorry <lb/>to see you won’t be able to <lb/>come up as soon as I had hoped <lb/> but I must only have patience till I <lb/>see you. I’m sorry to hear that <cb/> Jennie is knocked up but of course it <lb/>is nothing serious. It’s a good thing your <lb/>mother has decided to go down and <lb/>see her for I’m sure she wouldn’t <lb/>be contented till she saw her <lb/>mother. They will have a lot to say <lb/> to each other so perhaps she may not <lb/>come back as soon as I hope. However <lb/> there’s no use in my being selfish anyhow; <lb/>I ought to be more than thankful with <lb/>things as they are and I am too.  Tell Christy and Tommy Seery that <lb/>a friend of mine heard English cattle <lb/>buyers talking at Dublin market on <lb/>Thursday and saying that beef will be  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1242_img_431_3"/>
              1/6 a lb on the beast’s back before a month. <lb/>So they had better stiffen their prices for <lb/>any stall feds they have remaining. <lb/>From all I hear everything points to very <lb/>high prices for cattle in the near future. <lb/>So they’d better avail of the tip.  My mother was delighted to have <lb/>such a very nice letter from Mrs Fay <lb/>this morning. She let me see it and I <lb/>must say I was honestly amused with <lb/>her good opinion of this miserable sinner. <lb/>I can hardly help laughing every time I hear <lb/>people gassing about my goodness  Hope this catches the post so must <lb/>shut up with my heart’s warmest love to the <lb/>best little girl in the world. Please don’t laugh. It’s <lb/>true. <seg type="closer"> Yours ever fondly,  <hi rend="underline">James</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>