<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4315">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David Lloyd George to Edward Carson, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David Lloyd George</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from David Lloyd George (1863-1945) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. David Lloyd George served as Minister of Munitions during the Shell Crisis of 1915. His role as Minister won him wide-spread support across Britain. He took over the role of Secretary of State for War on 6 June 1916, after the death of Horatio Herbert Kitchener, (1850–1916) who died on board the cruiser HMS Hampshire when it was sunk by a German mine on 5 June 1916, while on course to Russia. Following the collapse of Asquith&#39;s government, Lloyd George became Prime Minister of the coalition government in December 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4315</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0876">David Lloyd George</persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1159">Ministry of Munitions, Armament Buildings, Whitehall, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1945</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4315_img_3676_1"  type="Letter"  url="441cacd4ce633e0d37c143b55567d0e5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4315_img_3676_2"  type="Letter"  url="8daf97f68ebb9af465fb30828332a6f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4315_img_3676_3"  type="Letter"  url="9265c869806f858b695f1d951b69d4cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4315_img_3676_4"  type="Letter"  url="12e9db4073b855ef82e63f411c741264.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4315_img_3676_1"/>
             1/2 Bay 44   PAGE 1 Of 4   MINISTRY OF MUNITIONS, <lb/>ARMAMENT BUILDINGS <lb/>WHITEHALL. <lb/>S.W.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">SECRET.</hi>  June 3rd., 1916.   My dear Carson,   Midleton seems to be working hard to prevent a <lb/>settlement. He is working up his friends to bring all <lb/>the pressure in his power to bear upon the Unionist <lb/>members of the Cabinet. Every prominent Unionist in the <lb/>South of Ireland is urged to write letters to Long and <lb/>Bonar Law and Lansdowne, and I have no doubt Chamberlain. <lb/>Long sends these letters on to me, and in the innocence <lb/>of his heart he thinks it is all a spontaneous outburst <lb/>of indignation. They all come practically from the old <lb/>landlord class. So far there has been no exhibition of <lb/>anxiety on the part of the big business men in the <lb/>South. Stewart is the exception, but I understand that he <lb/>is a considerable land agent. My information shows that <lb/>the business community is in a quiscent, if not in an <lb/>assentient mood. Stewart's deputation  for Monday  is a carefully <lb/>picked
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4315_img_3676_2"/>
            picked one. I have ascertained that some of the leading <lb/>Protestant Unionists of Dublin have been deliberately <lb/>left out. I have therefore asked Taylor, who is my <lb/>informant, to get Sir William Goulding, Mr, Dockrell, <lb/>Mr. Jacob, and other big business men from Dublin and <lb/>Cork - all Unionists - to come over to see me.   Since I saw you another suggestion has occurred <lb/>to me. I think it is most important that the Unionist <lb/>minority should be adequately represented in the <lb/>Provisional <seg type="del">Govern</seg>  Parlia ment at Dublin as well as in the <lb/>Executive. I therefore suggest that instead of having a <lb/>seperate House during the Provisional period the <lb/>Government nominees should sit in the first Chamber. We <lb/>might thus arrange that in the Lower Chamber there <lb/>should be 20 or 30, or even more, leading representatives <lb/>of the minority, and that in the Executive or Cabinet <lb/>there should be at least two Protestant Unionists. This <lb/>would be much more valuable than to pack these men into <lb/>a separate chamber. When the time comes to consider the <lb/>permanent settlement all this can be re-adjusted; but I <lb/>feel
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4315_img_3676_3"/>
            feel that the presence of a powerful minority in the Lower <lb/>Chamber would give the Protestant Unionists the greater <lb/>confidence at this time.   This terrible disaster in the North Sea makes it <lb/>more necessary than ever that we should get Ireland out of the <lb/>way in order to press on with the war. We cannot allow things <lb/>to remain as they are. We are losing on all fronts, and now, <lb/>alas, comes this omen from the sea, where we all thought <lb/>we were reasonably secure. The management of the war on the <lb/>part of the Allies is fortuitous and flabby, and unless <lb/>something is done immediately the British Empire and civilis- <lb/>-ation will sustain the greater disaster since thedays of <lb/>Attila. I must therefore have a talk with you with a view to <lb/>taking immediate action to force a decisive change in the <lb/>control of the war. An appreciation of the situation by the <lb/>General Staff has just come to my hands. It has filled me <lb/>with gloomy forebodings. There is no time to lose. I must <lb/>have a talk with you on Monday, not only about Ireland but <lb/>about the whole position, before you leave for Belfast. Let <lb/>us
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4315_img_3676_4"/>
            us settle Ireland promptly. It will give us both strength <lb/>and foothold to insist upon essential changes in other <lb/>spheres.   Yours sincerely,   <hi rend="underline">D Lloyd George</hi>   I should like to see you <hi rend="underline">before</hi> <lb/>you introduce the <sic>diputation</sic>. <lb/>Have you any news from Belfast?   The Rt. Hon. Edward Carson, K,C., M.P. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>