<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1330">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 21 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from May Fay (1897-1976) to James Finn (1877-1922) informing him of local news. Throughout the letter May has hidden five kisses for James to find.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. Following her husband&#39;s death May held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1330</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-02-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1330_img_649_1"  type="Letter"  url="dbf43fc171ae790b797ad34620b23249.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1330_img_649_2"  type="Letter"  url="f7b61ee02469c31a9d4d01540c07a305.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1330_img_649_3"  type="Letter"  url="15a414556bc98cdb3796b7e444a99cba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1330_img_649_4"  type="Letter"  url="51839705ae2a0afc29ad7873bb7c40a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1330_img_649_5"  type="Letter"  url="71f2bd21e155bd3b2acd66fe305f9a4a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1330_img_649_6"  type="Letter"  url="819b159ea11579b0109ae5719c29fd1e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1330_img_649_1"/>
              Puzzle: find the kisses <hi rend="underline">five</hi>    Togherstown  Ballinea    <hi rend="underline">Sunday</hi>   My dearest James,   <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>You are indeed <lb/>a very very good boy to think <lb/>of me for Sunday I was very <lb/>glad to get letter but I will have <lb/>better next Sunday Please God. <lb/>We met Mrs Kiernan at mass <lb/>she was going that eve to call  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1330_img_649_2"/>
              on the bride for <hi rend="underline">curiosity</hi> will <lb/>there be many calling on us <lb/>for curiosity I wonder. But <lb/>the best news of the day ГўВҖВ” <lb/>Johnnie had a letter from <lb/>a fellow in Pims saying the <lb/>clerkГўВҖВҷs job was certain when <lb/>the directors meet on the <lb/>29 Feb. It will be grand <lb/>if he gets it M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> S &amp; himself <lb/>are gone to Ballymore today <lb/>&amp; mother &amp; Christy to Mearscourt <lb/>(WynneГўВҖВҷs)  I am after being on one of the <lb/>corporal works of charity, down <lb/>seeing Essy &amp; Paddy Nolan. <lb/>They are suffering from colds &amp; <lb/>mumps and so I have special sympathy <lb/>for them. Mrs Nolan came too. <lb/>She read with me so I brought <lb/>her in and showed her my ring <lb/>fancy that to be the second <lb/>time for her to be in the house <lb/>She did not <seg type="unclear">adopt</seg> any of <lb/>JackГўВҖВҷs curiosity she was here <lb/>before when Jennie was getting <lb/>married, of course there was no <lb/>luck she did not wish me.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1330_img_649_3"/>
              About the ploughing match ГўВҖВ” <lb/>Joe only took third prize 10/ГўВҖВ” It <lb/>was better than nothing but he <lb/>was very indignant when <lb/>the decisions were given he <lb/>declared he could plough with <lb/>any of them when he came home <lb/>he told my mother he took <lb/>first &amp; <hi rend="underline">they wouldnГўВҖВҷt</hi> give <lb/><hi rend="underline">it to him.</hi> Favour in Hell he says, <lb/>none of this would be heard only <lb/>he got a few bottles of stout <lb/>to make him brave he is in a <lb/><sic>grate</sic> state about pigs he has to sell  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1330_img_649_4"/>
              afraid anyone else would get <lb/>a better  price  than him for comrade <lb/>pigs I am sure you are taking <lb/>a great interest in these things <lb/>you will be sorry to hear Mrs <lb/><seg type="unclear">Sinog</seg>Thomsom of NugentГўВҖВҷs cross <lb/>roads gave a wedding party <lb/>for her daughter, <hi rend="superscript">all</hi> the invited <lb/>guests did not turn up so <lb/>she is giving another <hi rend="underline">spree</hi><lb/>next Sat to give them all <lb/>a chance, very kind of herГўВҖВ” <lb/>Christy sold his cattle yesterday  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1330_img_649_5"/>
              ГӮВЈ21ГўВҖВ”10 he got, he was pleased I <lb/>think. T Seery got ГӮВЈ21 and he <lb/>was saying before his cattle <lb/>were better than ours so I donГўВҖВҷt <lb/>know which were the best ours <lb/>were seen at an advantage <lb/>in the <seg type="unclear">summer</seg> their <hi rend="underline">father</hi><lb/>that might have something to do <lb/>with it but sure the <hi rend="underline">poor widow</hi><lb/>wanted the 10/ГўВҖВ” worse than M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. S. <lb/>that was the whole of it I suppose. <lb/>Did you know Larry Cunningham one of his sisters, an old girl <lb/>of Ned Seery s is going to be x <lb/>married to a fellow the name <lb/>of Duncan there are a lot <lb/>of marriages spoken of; Jocie <lb/>Dardis she was  at  the nursing for <lb/>a while is to be married to a <lb/>Tom Manley I donГўВҖВҷt think  do  you <lb/>know either party, your mother <lb/>might.  How did you think of asking <lb/>for my ankle you will only <lb/>make me pettish like the children  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1330_img_649_6"/>
              if you take notice of me like that <lb/>I seldom feel it now. It must have <lb/>only been at started a bit.  Ned Seery is going very fast <lb/>after Lizzie Fox, they are telling <lb/>me but IГўВҖВҷd get it hard to believe <lb/>it. They say she meets him etc. <lb/>Mike Killian went so far as to say <lb/>she is getting fond of him (Ned S). <lb/>Tommy is still constant &amp; true. Johnnie <lb/>does not seem to have seen anything <lb/>to suit in the country.  I wonГўВҖВҷt say any more now afraid it <lb/>would be <hi rend="underline">taxed</hi> so I will wind up with <lb/>the usual amount of love <seg type="closer"> from your x loving  May Fay </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>