<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0095">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Gerrard to Augustine Birrell, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas M. Gerrard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas M. Gerrard, a Dublin-based solicitor and solicitor for the Royal College of Surgeons, to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), chief secretary of Ireland, for the position of chief Crown solicitor for Ireland, following the death of Sir Malachy Kelly.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5858/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/95</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0829">Thomas M. Gerrard</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1112">25 Westmoreland Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0095_img_1177_1"  type="Letter"  url="bfbfc91a29572e7f98e610b1c996faef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0095_img_1177_2"  type="Letter"  url="584353d454cbf748d1ceaee2a5d4922e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0095_img_1177_1"/>
              Letter to Rt Hon Augustine Birrell P.C.,M.P. page 1    25 Westmoreland Street,  Dublin    29th March 1916   Sir,   I have the honour to request that I may be appointed to the position <lb/>of Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland rendered vacant by the death of Sir <lb/>Malachy J Kelly. I was admitted a Solicitor on the 14th December 1895 <lb/>and since that date have practised in partnership with Mr Charles Daly <lb/>under the name of Thomas Gerrard &amp; Co in Dublin and at Drogheda County Louth   My firm is well known in Dublin and throughout Ireland and has conducted <lb/>many important cases.   I am also Solicitor for the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland. I <lb/>am the second son of the late Thomas Gerrard Crown Solicitor for Queens <lb/>County &amp; Carlow. I am of course over military age. All the remaining <lb/>members of my family have served or are serving with the Navy or Army. My <lb/>eldest brother Dr P N Gerrard, Captain Malay States Rifles Commandant of <lb/>the German prisoners camp at Signapore Straits Settlement was killed while <lb/>notifying the Town of Signapore of the mutiny of the Indian troops during <lb/>the war. My next brother J.D. Gerrard, who is a Resident Magistrate, is at <lb/>present serving with the Army Services Corp. My next brother Capt. H V <lb/>Gerrard, Second Border Regiment was killed with the Seventh Division at <lb/>the first battle of Ypres and my remaining brother Lieut. Col. &amp; L Gerrard  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0095_img_1177_2"/>
              is a wing Commander in the Royal Naval Air Service; my only nephew is <lb/>a Flight Lieutenant in the Royal Navel Air service.   I was born on the 14th December 1872. <seg type="closer"> I am Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant   Thomas Gerrard <lb/>The Right Hon. Augustine Birrell P.C. M.P.   Chief Secretary of Ireland  Dublin Castle  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>