<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4296">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter Wilfrid Spender to Edward Carson, 3 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Wilfrid Spender (1876-1960) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4296</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4296_img_3659_1"  type="Letter"  url="b7db3a0a80cc0c1ad30ced668a7b2a3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4296_img_3659_2"  type="Letter"  url="5d4c1477196aeb91398deb319b39236d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4296_img_3659_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Spender</hi> <lb/>Ulster Division   1915 <lb/>3 Dec   Dear Sir Edward   I have heard from my wife today <lb/>that she has mentioned to Lady Carson about the <lb/>appointment of three R.C. Staff Officers.   In case this may give a wrong impression I <lb/>am writing to say that one has left owing to ill- <lb/>health (Ryan). Both the other 2 Comyn &amp; Mayne <lb/>are good chaps &amp; Unionists, &amp; tho' it is not a tactful <lb/>thing to have done  on the part of the authorities,  I feel sure they are not themselves <lb/>intriguers.    The men seem to have quieted down since Redmond's <lb/>speech, &amp; I hope Xmas will go by without any unfor- <lb/>tunate incident unless he again attempts any "rousings".   You will be glad to hear that there is a general <lb/>wish in the Division for the return of the 107th Bdi <lb/>&amp; I hope they may be allowed to rejoin at the end of <lb/>the month. Unfortunately some of them are not very <lb/>anxious to come back as they   they were given
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4296_img_3659_2"/>
            <lb/>a bad name. If this may have been the case, I under- <lb/>stand they have done  very  <hi rend="underline">well</hi> &amp; lived it down. Certainly <lb/>the Regular battalions now with us in their place have <lb/>not proved superior to our own Ulstermen- <seg type="foreign">au contraire!</seg>.    Gen' Hacket Pain will return to England next <lb/>week &amp; could not doubt give you any information you <lb/>require.   We expect  the Division  to be transformed to another Corps very shortly, &amp; <lb/>I personally shall be glad as <seg type="del">some</seg> two of the Corps staff were <lb/>formerly very anti Ulster. Gen' Greenly, who is an old staff <lb/>college <seg type="del">frn</seg>friend of mine, took a very strong hire against us <lb/>then, &amp; tho' he is I think too good a fellow to harbour <lb/>any feelings now, it is better for many reasons that we <lb/>should be moved.   I feel that much that I write is more or less <lb/>gossip. Please treat it as such. One would not think of <lb/>such things if one had not learnt by <seg type="del">some what <seg type="unclear">bitter</seg></seg> <lb/>experience to suspect <seg type="del">it</seg> everywhere , &amp; one is probably quite <lb/>wrong in doing so.   Yours sincerely   Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>