<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1044">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frances Reddy to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, 5 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frances Reddy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Miss Frances Reddy, Carlow, to Lord Wimbourne, Lord Lieutenant General and General Governor of Ireland, containing her application for the grand of administration and license of the public house owned by her late sister Margaret Reddy to be transferred from Margaret to herself. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP/1916/3661/5, NAI CSO RP/1916/3661/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1044</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1490">Frances Reddy</persName>
              <date>1916-02-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0460">Carlow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Wimbourne, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1044_img_313_1"  type="Letter"  url="1d2f5aecfe39e470818503c03d40436f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1044_img_313_2"  type="Letter"  url="d6bc6a88a72adbb521232b1940665f5d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1044_img_313_1"/>
              To   HIS EXCELLENCY, the Lord Lieutenant General  and the Governor of Ireland.    The Humble Petition of FRANCES  REDDY of No. 67 Tullow Street, Carlow,  in the County of Carlow, spinster,   SHEWETH:   Your Petitioner extracted a Grant of Administration <lb/>on the 18th January 1916 to her sister Margaret Reddy, <lb/>late of No. 67 Tullow Street aforesaid, Spinster, who died <lb/>on the 8th day of November last and said Grant is herewith <lb/>sent.   The said Margaret Reddy was the proprietor of the <lb/>house know as No. 67 Tullow Street, Carlow, in respect <lb/>of which she was duly licensed for the sale of spirits, <lb/>tobacco, etc. in respect of said premises, and said licence <lb/>is also herewith sent.   Your petitioner resided with her said sister, and <lb/>still resides at No. 67 Tullow Street, Carlow, aforesaid, <lb/>and the usual temporary transfer at Petty Sessions was <lb/>granted to her on the 20th December 1916.   Your Petitioner made application at the Hilary <lb/>Quarter Sessions at Carlow on the 2nd day of February <lb/>1916, for a transfer of the said licence to her, and served <lb/>the usual Notices on the two nearest magistrates and pub- <lb/>lished the necessary notice in the local Newspaper, but <lb/>on the hearing of the application it was ascertained that <lb/>by an error on the part of her solicitor, the Notice of <lb/>Application had not been lodged with the Clerk of the <lb/>Crown and Peace as required by Section 2 of the 3rd and <lb/>4th Wm. IV. Chap. 68.   THERE  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1044_img_313_2"/>
              There was no objection to the granting of said <lb/>licence on the part of the police, or by any one at <lb/>said Quarter Sessions, but the judge held that the <lb/>application was not before him until same was lodged <lb/>with the Clerk of the Crown and Peace in the regular <lb/>way, and that he, therefore, could not grant the <lb/>application.   Your Petitioner, therefore, prays that she may be <lb/>allowed to keep open her business premises for the sale <lb/>of spirits etc. until the next Quarter Sessions for the <lb/>Division of Carlow which will be held on the 12th day <lb/>of April next, and at which she intends to apply for a <lb/>transfer to her of the said licence.  <seg type="closer"> And your Petitioner will ever pray <lb/>Signed    Frances Reddy   67 Tullow Street  CARLOW.    5th February 1916  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>