<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0786">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 7 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender mentions a report that he had to stay up late to write. He gives details of his daily ride upon his horse, Fanny. He mentions the illness of a mutual friend, and discusses the upcoming visit of the King. He also mentions that he has become popular among those officers who have realised that he was the author of the dispatches sent to the Cabinet.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/379</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/786</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-07</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0786_img_2323_1"  type="NULL"  url="054501602dbbf833e2734aee7f815157.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0786_img_2323_2"  type="NULL"  url="fbc023fcaa28ea559f5b48978921a4d6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0786_img_2323_1"/>
                7 Aug   My p r    If I had not not promised z 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><sic>instalment</sic> I <lb/>doubt if you would get even a scrap. Must sim- <lb/>ply <seg type="unclear">scramble</seg>, as I was kept by <seg type="unclear">Jim Kiggell</seg> CGS <lb/>for some time talking over one  long <seg type="unclear">report</seg>, which he <lb/>had already altered once and so I hoped hatched, but <lb/>which still needed revision. Had a nice ride on <lb/>Fanny in spite of the horse flies. By the way <lb/>Fanny also is kind enough to attract <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the <lb/>flies to herself, which the pr insists on giving <lb/>the b w the larger share â another advantage <lb/>in Fanny â a new one every day nearby ! ! !   She was much put out when I lost my <lb/>way in the village and eventually I let her <lb/>find our way home and seeing <seg type="unclear">Mr Gill</seg> in <lb/>the distance I got off &amp;let her walk <lb/>back alone which to the delight of the French <lb/>school children. It is such a pity. I know <lb/>I could do far better work with a pr on my <lb/>lap in present conditions of work &amp; I daren't <lb/>even suggest it when the King comes tho' <lb/>it is obviously in the interests of the service. <lb/>Perhaps however it wouldn't do as other  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0786_img_2323_2"/>
              people's work might suffer even tho' mine <lb/>improved. I had no idea Jack <seg type="unclear">Service</seg> was ill <lb/>do give news &amp; send our very sincere inquiries. <lb/>He would now be most useful in the Div &amp; <lb/>would probably even command of a Battalion <lb/>â the pity of it â.  I am glad that Ivy realises the importance of <lb/>the <seg type="unclear">support</seg> work but hope a holiday may be <lb/>possible for you later â not too much later â <lb/> &amp; only wish there was any prospect of <lb/>my being able to join you but that is also <lb/>lately out of the question. I have ordered <lb/>new breeches &amp; a new cap â good b w â <lb/> hope it arrives before HM, who may pay me <lb/>a visit.  I am quite popular with some <lb/>people who have heard I am writing dispatches  Goodbye pr. I could put up with <lb/>the Australian heat very well just now! <seg type="closer"> Your  b w<lb/> WB Spender  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>