<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1126">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of last letter and statement by Thomas MacDonagh, 2 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas MacDonagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is the last letter and will of Thomas MacDonagh. MacDonagh wrote the letter after hearing his sentence of death by firing squad. The letter outlines the details of his surrender, his thoughts on the failure of the Rising and his death sentence. MacDonagh reiterated his motive for his part in the 1916 Rising was “the love of my country, [and] the desire to make her a sovereign independent state.” It also details his wishes regarding his estate, and the letter concludes on a personal note words to his family.Thomas MacDonagh was one of the signatories of the 1916 Proclamation and a leader of the Easter Rising. He was convicted and sentenced to death by firing squad in Kilmainham gaol on 3 May 1916, with Padraig Pearse and Thomas Clarke, the first three of the Rising’s leaders to face execution. This is one of several copies of Thomas MacDonagh&#39;s last letter and will. This copy was written out by Muriel MacDonagh (MacDonagh&#39;s wife) and finished, by one of Plunkett&#39;s sisters (probably Fiona). It was based on the letter given to Mary MacDonagh, Sister Francesca, another of MacDonagh&#39;s sisters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, NLI44319-6-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1126</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1464">Thomas MacDonagh</persName>
              <date>1916-05-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0607">Kilmainham gaol</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Last letters before death</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1126_img_36_1"  type="Letter"  url="5051b70dcbde34e8138d7e145a129823.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1126_img_36_2"  type="Letter"  url="c1a2da2d8856ce2092541155924fc276.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1126_img_36_3"  type="Letter"  url="936f06503812180fe42834203f6f271a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1126_img_36_4"  type="Letter"  url="13b47b77c287cae731f099a1dfee8c47.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1126_img_36_5"  type="Letter"  url="275e7b00c91b9df0621e543d76887943.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1126_img_36_6"  type="Letter"  url="6407a1df5ccc6c1a24b94bc20b803cdf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1126_img_36_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">1</hi>    Kilmainham Gaol   <time>Midnight</time> Tuesday 2nd May    1916    I, Thomas MacDonagh, having now heard the sentence of the <lb/> Court Martial held on me today, declare that in all my acts â <lb/> all the acts for which I have been arraigned â I have been actuated <lb/> by one motive only, the love of my country, the desire to make her <lb/> a sovereign independent state. I still hope and pray that my acts <lb/> may have for consummation her lasting freedom &amp; happiness.   I am to die at dawn, 3.30a.m., 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> May. I am ready to die, and I <lb/> thank God that I die in so holy a cause. My Country will reward my <lb/> dust richly.   On April 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I was astonished to receive by a message from P. H. Pearse <lb/> Commandant General of the Army of the Irish Republic an order to <lb/> surrender unconditionally to the British General. I did not obey the <lb/> order as it came from a prisoner. I, as then in supreme command <lb/> of the Irish Army, consulted with my second in command and <lb/> decided to confirm the order. I knew that it would involve my death and <lb/> the deaths of other leaders. I hoped that it would save many true men <lb/> among our followers, good lives for Ireland. God grant it has done <lb/> so and God approve the deed âfor myself I have no regret.   The one bitterness that death has for me is the separation it brings <lb/> from my beloved wife Muriel, and my beloved children Donagh and Barbara. <lb/> My country will take them as wards, I hope. I have devoted <lb/> myself too much to national work and too little to the making <lb/> of money to leave them a competence.   God help &amp; support them, and give them a happy and prosperous <lb/> life.   Never was there a better, truer, purer woman than my wife Muriel, <lb/> or more adorable children than Don and Barbara.   It breaks my heart to think that I shall never see my children <lb/> again, but I have not wept or mourned.   I counted the cost of this and am ready to pay it  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1126_img_36_2"/>
              Muriel has been sent for here I do not know if she can come. <lb/> She may have no one to take the children while she is coming <lb/> if she does â   My money affairs are in a bad way, I am insured for Â£200 <lb/> in the New York life Co but have borrowed Â£101.   I think I am insured for Â£100 in the Alliance Co but have <lb/> a bank debt for Â£80. That leaves less than Â£120 from those <lb/> sources if they produce anything.   In addition I have insured my two children for Â£100 each <lb/> in the Mutual Co of Australasia. Payments of premium <lb/> to cease at my death, the money to be paid to the children <lb/> at the age of twenty one.   I ask my brother Joseph MacDonagh and my good and constant <lb/> friend David Houston to help my poor wife in these <lb/> matters.   My brother John who came with me and stood by me all <lb/> last week has been sent away from here, I do not know <lb/> where to.   He, if he can will help my family too. God bless him and <lb/> my other sisters and brothers.   Assistance has been guaranteed from funds in the hands <lb/> of Cumann na m'Ban and other funds to be collected <lb/> in America by our fellow countrymen there in provision <lb/> for the dependants of those  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1126_img_36_3"/>
              who fall in this fight. I appeal without shame to the <lb/> persons who control these funds to assist my family. <lb/> My wife and I have given all for Ireland.   I ask my friend David Houston to see Mr W.G. Lyon, <lb/> publisher of my latest book, <hi rend="underline">Literature in Ireland</hi>, <lb/> and see that its publication may be useful to my wife <lb/> and family. If Joseph Plunkett survives me and is  a  free <lb/> man I make him with my wife, my literary executor. <lb/> Otherwise my wife and David Houston will take <lb/> charge of my writings. For the first time I pray that <lb/> they may bring in some profit at last. My wife will <lb/> want money from every source.   Yesterday at my court-martial in rebuffing some <lb/> trifling evidence, I made a statement as to my negotiation <lb/> for surrender with General Lowe. On hearing it read after <lb/> it struck me that it might sound like an appeal. <lb/> It was not such. I made no appeal, no recantation, <lb/> no apology for my acts. In what I said I merely <lb/> claimed that I acted honourably and thoroughly in all <lb/> that I set myself to do. My enemies have, in return, <lb/> treated me in an unworthy manner. But let <lb/> that pass. It is a great and glorious thing to die <lb/> for Ireland and I can well forget all petty annoyances  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1126_img_36_4"/>
              in the splendour of this. When my son, Don, was <lb/> born I thought that <seg type="del">for</seg> to him and <seg type="del">an</seg> not to me <lb/> would this be given. God has been kinder to me <lb/> than I hoped. My darling little boy, remember me <lb/> kindly. Take my hope and purpose with my deed <lb/> for your sake and for the sake of your beloved <lb/> mother and sister. I would wish to live long, <lb/> but you will recognise the <seg type="del">this</seg> thing I have <lb/> done and see this as a consequence. I still  think  I <lb/> have done a great thing for Ireland,  and  with the <lb/> defeat of <seg type="del">the</seg> her enemy, won the first step of <lb/> her freedom. God bless you, my son.   My darling daughter, Barbara, God bless you. I <lb/> loved you more than ever a child has been loved. <lb/> My dearest love, Muriel, thank you a million <lb/> times for all that you have been to me. I have <lb/> only one trouble in leaving life â leaving you <lb/> so. Be brave darling. God will assist and bless <lb/> you. Good bye. Kiss my darlings for me. I send you <lb/> the few things I have saved out of this <lb/> war. Good bye my love, till we meet <lb/> again in Heaven. I have a sure faith of <lb/> our union there. I kiss this paper that goes  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1126_img_36_5"/>
              to you. <seg type="del">I ha</seg>  I have just heard that they have not been able to <lb/> reach you. Perhaps it is better so. Yet Father <lb/> Aloysius is going to make another effort to <lb/> do something. God help and sustain you, <lb/> my love. But for your suffering, this <lb/> would be all joy and glory. Good bye.  <seg type="closer"> Your loving husband  Thomas MacDonagh. </seg><lb/> I return the darlings' photographs. <lb/> Good bye, my love   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1126_img_36_6"/>
               This  is a  copy of the last <lb/> letter of <lb/><hi rend="underline">Thomas MacDonagh</hi>. <lb/> It was copied by his <lb/> wife Muriel, &amp; <lb/> finished by <lb/> Fiona Plunkett <lb/>from original letter <lb/>&amp; given to his sister <lb/>Mary. <hi rend="underline">Sr Francesca</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>