<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1425">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Louis C.P. Smith to Sir Malachy Kelly, 15 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Louis C.P. Smith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the Crown Solicitor in Cavan, Louis C.P. Smith (1867-1923) to the Chief Crown Solicitor of Ireland Sir Malachy Kelly (1851-1916). In the correspondence the two are discussing a case that involved the forgery of a Birth Certificate.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3908</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1425</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0183">Louis C.P. Smith</persName>
              <date>1915-12-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1533">Crown Solicitor&#39;s Office, County Cavan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0509">Malachy Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1425_img_837_1"  type="Letter"  url="c74236fa2365acac56e3f8792b8c1f49.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1425_img_837_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Copy.</hi><lb/>  CROWN SOLICITOR'S OFFICE,  CAVAN,    13th day of December 1915  <lb/>Ulster Winter Assizes, 1915. <lb/><hi rend="underline">County of Cavan.</hi><lb/>The <hi rend="underline">King v John Graham</hi>. Forgery of Certificate <lb/><hi rend="underline">of Birth</hi> Dear Sir,   I herewith enclose you by Return <lb/>for the Ulster Winter Assizes for the County <lb/>of Cavan, which I hope you will find in order.   This is the second time which the <lb/>Prisoner has been tried and on both occasions <lb/>the Jury disagreed. At the trial at the Cavan <lb/>Assizes Mr. Justice Gibson took a very serious <lb/>view of the case. Judge Kenny on the other <lb/>hand although he considered it a serious <lb/>matter, seemed more or less disposed to be <lb/>satisfied if the Jury brought in a Verdict of <lb/>Not Guilty, but said they would have great <lb/>difficulty in doing so. The Prisoner stands out <lb/>on the same Bail to the next Assizes for this <lb/>County. Having regard to his position it is <lb/>very hard to get a conviction here, although <lb/>the case is perfectly clear.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  Louis C P Smith <lb/>Sir M Kelly   Chief Crown Solr.  The Castle  Dublin  </seg> Seen. Submit papers before <lb/>next Assizes <lb/>J. G. <lb/>14' 12' 15.   Mr. Smith C S <lb/>Please see Attorney <lb/>General's Directions <lb/>M. Kelly <lb/> 15-12-15   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>