<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0903">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 3 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Peter Mooney (b.1886) to his sister, Katie (b.1884). Peter thanks Katie for the pouch of tobacco that was sent his way. He reports that the war seems to be getting no better, possibly referring to the British failure to break the German lines at Loos. Peter requests a nail scissors and the addresses of family and friends at home to write to. He closes with reference to the increasing number of recruits arriving to the front, wondering where they must be coming from. The recruits likely came from the British New Army regiments (so called Kitchener&#39;s Army), civilian volunteers who made up the depleted ranks of the British forces in 1915.Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This letter part of a collection of over ninety surviving letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/903</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1915-11-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1826">Ballincollig, Co.Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1232">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co.Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0903_img_2509_1"  type="Letter"  url="4a4cdc35ac247e5d7cd98b6e33396ece.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0903_img_2509_2"  type="Letter"  url="c3ac336a172ffced20bf5105cf2777d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0903_img_2509_3"  type="Letter"  url="bf9a0b861a96ed95399f46866d163aed.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0903_img_2509_1"/>
                Nov 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>1915   Dear Kate,   I received your letter<lb/> this morning alright. I was<lb/> glad to receive the papers<lb/> The war seems to be getting<lb/> no better. I forgot to tell<lb/> you that I got the tobacco<lb/> alright I will write when<lb/> I want more. When you<lb/> are writing again try &amp; enclose <lb/><seg type="unclear">Christy Mulans</seg> address as<lb/> I would like to write to him  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0903_img_2509_2"/>
              Tell Pat that I was asking<lb/> for him. You might send me<lb/> on a very small <sic>sciziors</sic> for<lb/> cutting my nails. Recruits<lb/> are coming in here every day<lb/> the wonder is where they are<lb/> coming from. You will have<lb/> to forgive me for writing such<lb/> a short letter. I will write<lb/> on Sunday again. I will now<lb/> say Good—Bye to all for<lb/> the present. <seg type="closer"> Your fond Brother  Peter Mooney </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0903_img_2509_3"/>
                Miss. K. Mooney  Caulstown  Dunboyne  Co. Meath    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>