<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2700">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy Duffin to her mother, Maria Duffin, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

Dorothy writes about the hot weather and about a train journey to Eastbourne on which &#39;the whole of London&#39; appeared to be travelling.

She write about a party she attended there and a conversation she had with the Colonel who was telling tall stories. She is sorry for Celia who apparently has been transferred to Stockport. She gives news of other people and she hopes her mother can make the trip to England.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/32</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2700</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1222">3 Chester Terrace, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2700_img_2120_1"  type="Letter"  url="04fd5b4ab559bd74a1474e41bc11d9e1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2700_img_2120_2"  type="Letter"  url="d9fa99461d48136b03440e2d5eae6bdd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2700_img_2120_3"  type="Letter"  url="c7735a808d00820cda0369180ef7b93f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2700_img_2120_4"  type="Letter"  url="db0a0ad3e65913abd2702c08beb7b2bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2700_img_2120_5"  type="Letter"  url="2eb379b28ad0be48693fb11a39a75723.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2700_img_2120_1"/>
             31.7.16   <hi rend="underline">3 Chester Terrace</hi>   Dearest Mamma   It is so hot <lb/> it is rather an effort <lb/>to write at all.   I'm sorry to be address- <lb/>ing this to Dunowen <lb/> again and that your <lb/> holiday is over. Tell <lb/> Helen I was glad of <lb/> her letter. Is Miss <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Stack</seg> in London?   I got off to Eastbourne <lb/> by an afternoon train
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2700_img_2120_2"/>
            on Saturday. Half London <lb/> seemed to be in it <lb/> &amp; we were packed like <lb/> herrings so it was blessed <lb/> to arrive. I went <lb/> to Devonshire <seg type="del">Hevn</seg> Park  with <lb/> Olive for tea &amp; there met <lb/> A.J. whose hands are <lb/> still being dressed. <lb/> He goes to Strangford <lb/> soon. On Sunday <lb/> we went to the <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Donnets <seg type="del">=</seg></seg> who were <lb/> having a tennis party.    Mildred Taylor is again <lb/> established there. I <lb/> saw no change in the <lb/>Colonel. He was telling <lb/> tall stories just the <lb/> same. There were some <lb/> rather unpleasant women <lb/> &amp; two or three pleasant <lb/> men. One kind one <lb/> gave us a lift home <lb/> in his car. Miss <lb/> Roberts was most kind <lb/> &amp; Olive was very well <lb/> &amp; cheerful. It was nice <lb/> to get a breath of sea <lb/> air. I came back <lb/> this morning by a 7.30 <lb/> train &amp; lunched with <lb/> Mrs Tomlinson (Miss <lb/> Darbyshire) and her
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2700_img_2120_3"/>
            cousin Mrs Cuthbert Johnson <lb/> whom I met before at <lb/> the <seg type="unclear">Beales</seg>.   I'm so sorry about <lb/> Celia as I cannot think <lb/> Stockport would be <lb/> nice. Miss Roberts <lb/> is writing to some <lb/> Hollins people near there <lb/> to look her up &amp; I <lb/> have written to Sheila <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Bligant</seg> as I believe they <lb/> know Manchester people <lb/> &amp; I believe Molly Carson <lb/> does also, but none <lb/> of you have sent
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2700_img_2120_4"/>
            her address. Olive was <lb/> asking for it also.   I had hoped to hear <lb/> from Papa that he <lb/> was coming over as <lb/> he mentioned this week <lb/> as likely.   I saw poor Mrs <seg type="unclear">Heymond</seg> <lb/> in Eastbourne &amp; Mrs <lb/>Eastwood was arriving on <lb/> Monday but Dickie <lb/> was suffering from whoop <lb/>ing cough.   The two youngest
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2700_img_2120_5"/>
            Hollins children were <lb/> with Miss Roberts &amp; <lb/> were very sweet. It <lb/> was nice to see <lb/> children again.   <hi rend="underline">Wednesday Evening</hi>    I kept this to hear <lb/> from you &amp; am hoping <lb/> very much you will <lb/> both make the effort <lb/> to come over. It will <lb/> be delightful to see <lb/> you. I believe Annie <lb/> has left Epsom. If <lb/>you go perhaps Aunt F <lb/> would put me up for <lb/> a night also. I hope <lb/> you won't feel the <lb/> heat too much - it <lb/> pretty bad here.   With love &amp; hoping <lb/> to see you soon.   <hi rend="underline">Dorothy</hi>   I return Terry's letter. <lb/> I'm glad you like the cushion - it was <lb/> Olive who shared in <lb/> the bag not me.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>