<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4584">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to Sir William Henry Thompson, 2 February 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

William Henry Thompson (1860-1918) acted as a scientific adviser to the Ministry of food in London. He advised the Food Controller in the drafting of schemes for the rationing of food. In 1914 he resigned from his position as Examiner in Physiology at the Royal College of Surgeons. In January 1918, he was decorated a Knight Commander of the Civil Division of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4584</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1918-02-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir William Henry Thompson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4584_img_3927_1"  type="Letter"  url="8c35c23fce5812b2284c211e5a73ef2a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4584_img_3927_1"/>
             2nd February   18.  Professor Sir W.H.Thompson, M.D., <lb/> Food Control Office, <lb/>London.   Dear Sir,   I am requested by the President and Fellows of the <lb/>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to forward you a copy <lb/>of the following resolution which was passed at a meeting of <lb/>the College held yesterday the 1st instant: <lb/>Resolved: "that the President and Fellows desire to express <lb/>to their Colleague Professor Sir William Henry Thompson <lb/> their congratulations on the honour of Knight Commander of <lb/>the British Empire recently conferred on him by His Majesty <lb/>the King."   I remain, <lb/>Yours faithfully,   Fellow &amp; Registrar. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>