<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0733">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John S. Campbell to George Hackney, 20 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John S. Campbell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John S. Campbell to George Hackney (1889-1977). Campbell thanks George for sending him information about his son Jack in a previous letter. He has written thrice to Jack asking about the nature of his injury but received no reply, and thus assumes &#39;it is in the privates&#39;. John asks if soldiers have any opportunity to spend money while in hospital, and if there is any point in sending Jack some. He writes several questions about how Jack is getting on and implores George to &#39;tell me all&#39;. He invites George to visit if ever he returns to Belfast.This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney, a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;. In 1916 he was injured and spent some time in Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6-7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/733</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0923">John S. Campbell</persName>
              <date>1916-09-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1580">Avondale Villas, Cyprus Avenue, Bloomfield, Belfast</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1546">31 Ward, 'D' Block, Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0733_img_2243_1"  type="Letter"  url="833425932741d88e461591c0c4b3f3c0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0733_img_2243_2"  type="Letter"  url="42b461ce48e7e54bda0e4dfa30e562b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0733_img_2243_3"  type="Letter"  url="530bab01c741c5b0d6438537fdd9ee0a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0733_img_2243_4"  type="Envelope"  url="f526fb47e3139c2b72f7f75616ec3b65.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0733_img_2243_5"  type="Envelope"  url="9b33ffdb85189accd58039884212a0da.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0733_img_2243_1"/>
                Avondale Villas,  Cyprus Avenue  ,Bloomfield,  Belfast.     Sept 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916  <lb/><name><sic>Corpal.</sic> George Hackney</name> Dear Sir   Your very welcome letter to hand <lb/> for which I am indeed exceedingly <lb/> obliged. I am indeed anxious <lb/> about my Son Jack. I wrote him asking him to let me <lb/> know the nature of the kick. <lb/>I am only guessing it is in <lb/> the privates &amp; I would like <lb/> to know, I also want to know <lb/>if money would be of any use <lb/> to him. I can't get any information <lb/> from him as you say his letters <lb/> are all censored. I understand <lb/> that when you Soldiers go into Hospital <lb/>your money stops. Now would you  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0733_img_2243_2"/>
              tell me if I could send him <lb/>say a few shillings for his <lb/>pocket. Could or would it be <lb/>any use to him. Can he get <lb/> out to spend it or buy anything <lb/>he wants. Of course we send him cigarettes &amp; parcel every <lb/>week to hospital. I am glad <lb/>he came through the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of July <lb/>free from wounds. How did <lb/>he stand the war. Is he <lb/>very nervous. You say he is <lb/>looking in the pink at present. <lb/>Is there any chance of him <lb/>getting home to Belfast as <lb/>he was not home since he left <lb/>for France. I would like to <lb/>see him &amp; so would his <lb/>mother. How was he getting <lb/>along in the Army. I know <lb/> you will tell me all   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0733_img_2243_3"/>
              If ever you are in Belfast <lb/>you might call at the <lb/>enclosed address.  Thanking you very much <lb/>for your kind letter <lb/>&amp; waiting your reply. <seg type="closer"> I am Yours Sincerely  John S Campbell </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0733_img_2243_4"/>
               Blank back of envelope   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0733_img_2243_5"/>
               Blank back of envelope   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>