<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0138">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lieutenant Colonel R. L. Owens to Anna O'Rahilly, 28 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>R.L. Owens</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Lieutenant Colonel R. L. Owens to Anna O&#39;Rahilly (d.1958). In this letter Owens states that he will call for a report from the man who was in command of his company on Moore Street during the 1916 Rising and that in the meantime he will make inquiries about Michael on Miss O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s behalf.This letter is part of a series of correspondence in which Miss O&#39;Rahilly is attempting to locate a watch belonging to Michael O&#39;Rahilly which was not returned to the family after his death. Owens was a Lieutenant Colonel at Richmond Barracks and served over the 3rd Battalion of the Royal Irish Regiment. This was one of the regiments involved in suppressing the Rising in 1916. Anna O&#39;Rahilly was the sister of Michael O&#39;Rahilly. Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/124/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/138</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1290">R.L. Owens</persName>
              <date>1916-05-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0863">Richmond Barracks, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0138_img_1258_1"  type="Letter"  url="2cf358d1d869ca6c8e7e15e386d0d707.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0138_img_1258_2"  type="Letter"  url="de8381e3056c17b59021162fcf7adf42.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0138_img_1258_1"/>
                Richmond Barracks,  Dublin    28<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> May 1916   Dear Madam,   I am in receipt<lb/> of your letter of the<lb/> 27<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> instant. I have<lb/> called for a report<lb/> from the officer  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0138_img_1258_2"/>
              who was in com<lb/> -mand of the Company <lb/> at Moore St<lb/> and on receipt <lb/> of the same a<lb/> further reply<lb/> will be sent for.<cb/> Meantime full<lb/> enquiries will be<lb/> made. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly <lb/> R.L. Owens <lb/> Lt Col<lb/> M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> A. ORahilly</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>