<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4272">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 7 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/209</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4272</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-07</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4272_img_3637_1"  type="Letter"  url="ad983e74caaafb141a120e79fbadf046.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4272_img_3637_2"  type="Letter"  url="a0550e9a5907b3e1ae883e114dfec8da.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4272_img_3637_1"/>
             7 April   My p r    Things become very easy for a b w with a little p r <lb/> to help him. I am more than reconciled now for I think Place <lb/> is good, &amp; with a good GSO1, &amp; a "very fair GSO2" the Division <lb/> will I hope not be let down by the staff !    It has again distinguished itself. There was another <lb/> scoup attack last night, and again our men played up &amp; the <lb/> enemy failed to get in tho' it was our weakest unit,— you <lb/> can guess which I mean — I believe they did well. For the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/> (? 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>) time the huns have failed with us but succeeded in the <lb/> next Division. I am afraid our men will not be altogether <lb/> sorry as the next Division treated us with "marked discourtesy>". <lb/> They are known as the "incomparables". The GOC when they came <lb/> offered to send up some of our experienced officers to teach them <lb/> the line they were taking over &amp; which we had held. <lb/> Their GOC gladly accepted so our officers went up. They <lb/> arrived at the front lines about M Night &amp; were sent straight <lb/> back with the retort "I don't think we have anything <lb/> to learn from a 6 month's division".   GOC is very seedy. He really ought to go home. <lb/> Perhaps Farnham will be able to explain things to him, <lb/> &amp; get him to do so, if he returns but I fear that may <lb/> not be for some time yet.   Major Long is here now from the base. He had a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4272_img_3637_2"/>
            <lb/>most awful journey living on chocolate for 48 hours. So <lb/> good for him to learn the discomforts of our men !    He too is anxious about future drafts for the Division    I have to go for evening runs as naturally Place has <lb/> to go out to learn the front but if I can sit by an open <lb/> window all day I do not mind so much.    I think Rex's would really be best for us if I get <lb/> home before May when Mater will be there, but this is <lb/> doubtful. Whether to go there in May I leave to you but <lb/> should be quite content. I do not think either very <lb/> likely but you might make all arrangements in case.   I enclose Blaker's letter which please file. It <lb/> is a strange request perhaps but I like its frankness &amp; <lb/> these are strange times. He has behaved nobly for he <lb/> was ever warning us of the war to come, &amp; when it did <lb/> come the land of his adoption treated him disgracefully. <lb/> This I hope is in the past, &amp; may there be a good future <lb/> before him, on which neither you nor I will look <lb/> with jealous eyes.   The b w would like a prance with a p r it may <lb/> come some day.   Your b w    Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>