<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0128">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert V. Laurenson to Mr Campbell, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert V. Laurenson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Robert V. Laurenson (b.1889), a staff clerk at the Royal Irish Constabulary, to Mr Campbell detailing Laurenson&#39;s whereabouts between 22 April and 1 May in accordance with a government order. In the letter Laurenson reports that he made several unsuccessful attempts to access the Royal Irish Constabulary office during this time period and that at one point he was unable to leave Sandymount as the military had closed all roads.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/23041916/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/128</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0892">Robert V. Laurenson</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr Campbell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0128_img_1213_1"  type="Letter"  url="afd51a6103de2cb81711bc4ba7a3e4d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0128_img_1213_2"  type="Letter"  url="39a14e4fe674a457f8ebfc64c3cca139.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0128_img_1213_3"  type="Letter"  url="f1a7948e1fe8017d9469f809eb5710ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0128_img_1213_1"/>
                Royal Irish Constabulary Office    4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916   Mr Campbell   I beg to report in compliance <lb/>with Government order <lb/>my movements between noon on 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/> inst and noon on 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> inst as <lb/>follows:-  April 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. In office till 1pm, then <lb/> home to 91 Tritonville Road, <lb/>Sandymount. In the afternoon <lb/>I went to Strand Road <lb/>and back home where I slept <lb/>that night.  23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>. Went with my wife to <lb/>Phoenix Park in the afternoon. <lb/>Slept at home.  24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Went with a colleague <lb/>a walk through Rathfarnham, <lb/>Glendhu and home <lb/> via Dundrum. In the evening <lb/>accompanied him to Nelson's <lb/>Pillar. Slept at home that <lb/>night.  25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Went into Dame Street <lb/>to get into the Office. <lb/>Being unable to do so <lb/> after waiting a considerable <lb/>time, I went to Phoenix <lb/>Park with a colleague <lb/>and home through the <lb/> City. In the afternoon I <lb/>went to Grosvenor Square <lb/>to enquire for a friend-  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0128_img_1213_2"/>
              April 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>(<hi rend="underline">Contd</hi>) one of the G.R. Volunteers from <lb/> Lansdowne Road Rugby Football <lb/>Corps - who had to get <lb/>shelter in Beggar's Bush barracks <lb/>after the rebels attack on <lb/> that Corps. Slept at home <lb/>that night.  ' 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Endeavoured to reach this <lb/> Office in the forenoon. In the <lb/>afternoon I went with my <lb/>wife to 81 Grosvenor Square <lb/>as we were unable to <lb/> return to Sandymount we <lb/>slept there that night.<lb/>  ' 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Went to town to see if I <lb/> could get into the Office. <lb/>I then went from Grosvenor <lb/>Square to Island Bridge with a <lb/>lady friend, who wished to <lb/> bring food to a relative we <lb/>believed to be ill. This <lb/>relative was employed in <lb/>Phoenix Park but we were <lb/> unable to get past Island <lb/>Bridge. I came home that <lb/>night with my wife and <lb/>Mrs Atkinson- wife of <lb/> volunteer referred to under <lb/>date 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>— and her young <lb/>son. Slept at home that <lb/> night.  ' 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Went into town to see <lb/>if Office could be reached. <lb/> Returned home via Ranelagh <lb/>where  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0128_img_1213_3"/>
              April 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>(<hi rend="underline">Contd</hi>) where I had to get <lb/>provisions. In the <lb/>afternoon went to <lb/> Grosvenor Square for any <lb/>news of friend in <lb/>Beggars Bush Barracks. <lb/>Slept at home that <lb/>night.  ' 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Went to town to try <lb/>and reach the Office. In <lb/>the afternoon I went to <lb/> Grosvenor Square. Slept <lb/>at home that night.  ' 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. In house all day <lb/>but for a walk down <lb/> Strand Road. Slept at <lb/>home.  May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Unable to leave <lb/>Sandymount as the <lb/> Military had closed all <lb/>roads. <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">R.V. Laurenson</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>