<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3869">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 17 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane (1861-1934) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) detailing his recent activities. Aside from visiting H.G. Wells, Vane discusses his recent dealings with British politicians regarding an inquiry into the death of Francis Sheehy Skeffington during Easter Week.

Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane was a British officer in command of Portobello Barracks. When he learned about the activities of Captain J.C.Bowen-Colthurst during Easter Week he reported the matter to his superiors but, sensing a cover-up, he went to London and reported it directly to Lord Kitchener and Maurice Bonham Carter, Private Secretary to the Prime Minister. Although Bowen-Colthurst was court-martialled and found guilty, Vane was &#39;retired&#39; from the military for his actions. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,608/1-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3869</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0659">Francis Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1916-07-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1846">National Liberal Club, Whitehall Place, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3869_img_3249_1"  type="Letter"  url="985bc5b0e29d981826a428834ffdfa77.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3869_img_3249_2"  type="Letter"  url="d41e81350dacfb4fa0fae1e453fb41d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3869_img_3249_3"  type="Letter"  url="08be72547674a62a8f93ae539b907c6e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3869_img_3249_1"/>
              National Liberal Club <lb/>Whitehall Place, S.W.     17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916.     My Dear Mrs Skeffington,    In have but now only returned from <lb/>Essex, were I was with, (all yesterday), <lb/>Mr H.G.Wells — with whom among <lb/>other things I discussed the Irish question, <lb/>and made him understand it. Though <lb/>so brilliant a man, I do not really <lb/>believe that he has quite grasped the <lb/>recent developments of it, but now I feel <lb/>sure he does.   Being away, therefore, I could not arrange <lb/>for the meeting between you and Mr Bonham <lb/>Carter, and I am not sure that even if it <lb/>had been here, that it would have been <lb/>wise. You see the Prime Minister has <lb/>all the papers, is dealing with these papers, <lb/>is forced to attend to my claims through
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3869_img_3249_2"/>
            <lb/>your lamentable affair, and has promised <lb/>1 To institute the Inquiry 2 To see according <lb/>to his public statement as to my action, <lb/>justice done.   The admission which he has made of the <lb/>justice of my case is a <seg type="unclear">portion</seg>, the admission <lb/>of <seg type="unclear">yours</seg>, therefore I do not think that <lb/>we need trouble about the matter so far.   I put the Government under an obligation to <lb/>me - the obligation involved a great injustice <lb/>to you. If the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, so must be the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>.   I leave here my declaration only signed <lb/>by me and witnessed by a Magistrate. <lb/>I do not think that they can send me <lb/>away out of recall as a witness, and <lb/>if they do, they must use this affidavit <lb/>as evidence.   I will let you know anything which happens, <lb/>and you will do the same.   My love and good comradeship to my <lb/>young friend Owen.    Yours very sincerely <lb/> Francis Vane of Hutton . <lb/>Major.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3869_img_3249_3"/>
             Have I to pay up at once? <lb/>Dr Js account <lb/>  <lb/>How soon moving? Part <lb/>the property? <lb/>Vane <lb/><seg type="unclear">Asquith</seg> <lb/>Healy 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>