<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1610">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Harry Boland to his mother, Kate, 19 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Harry Boland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Harry Boland to his mother Catherine &#39;Kate&#39; Boland (née Woods, c. 1861-1932). Boland was a keen member of the GAA, the Irish Republican Brotherhood and the Dublin Brigade of the Irish Volunteers. During the Easter Rising he was a member of the rebel garrison in the GPO and, despite having no officer rank, was sentenced to ten years&#39; penal servitude. He was imprisoned in Dartmoor, Lewes and Maidstone.
This letter was written while Boland was a prisoner in Dartmoor. He describes the journey to Dartmoor, his high spirits, refers to friends and family and also mentions that he has read about a settlement of the &#39;Irish Question&#39; between John Redmond, leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party, and Edward Carson, the Ulster Unionist leader. Boland&#39;s brothers, Gerald and Edmund, were also involved in the Rising and Gerald, referred to in the letters, was also imprisoned in England.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Mrs Sean O&#39;Donovan Collection; BMH CD/196/2/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1610</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1056">Harry Boland</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1395">Dartmoor, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Catherine Boland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1610_img_1074_1"  type="Letter"  url="f1e406b802f2fa17ab0c6695304a066c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1610_img_1074_2"  type="Letter"  url="8e512e3f7cd4fe5639bc14e9ad6ce33b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1610_img_1074_3"  type="Letter"  url="f906fde998ae5264fd7ad062cc29f4a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1610_img_1074_4"  type="Letter"  url="719aabdd44582d258424e21b47aff092.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1610_img_1074_1"/>
             In replying to this letter, please write on the envelope: <lb/>Number 1 Name H. J. Boland <lb/> Dartmoor Prison    The following regulations as to communications, by Visit or Letter, between prisoners <lb/>and their friends are notified for information of their correspondents    The permission to write and receive letters, is given to prisoners for <lb/>the purpose of enabling them to keep up a connection with their respectable friends <lb/>and not that they may be kept informed of public events.   All letters are read by the Prison Authorities. They must be legibly <lb/>written and not crossed. Any which are of an objectionable tendency, either to or <lb/>from prisoners, or containing slang, or improper expressions, will be suppressed.   Prisoners are permitted to receive and to write a letter at intervals, <lb/>which depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry and good conduct; <lb/>but matters of special importance to a prisoner my be communicated at any time by <lb/>Letter (prepaid) to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof if expedient.    In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving and writing a letter <lb/>may be forfeited for a time.    Money, Books, Postage Stamps, Food Tobacco Clothes, &amp;c., should <lb/>not be sent to Prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received <lb/>at the prison for that purpose.   Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce <lb/>any article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine and imprisonment, and any prisoner <lb/>concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.   Prisoners' friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorised persons to <lb/>send money, &amp;c., to them privately, under pretence that they can apply it for the <lb/>benefit of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such persons endeavour <lb/>to obtain money for themselves. Any letter containing such application, received by <lb/>the friends of a prisoner should be, at once, forwarded by them to the Governor.   Prisoners are allowed to receive Visits from their friends, according <lb/>to rules, at intervals which depend on their stage.   When Visits are due to prisoners notification will be sent to the friends <lb/>whom they desire to visit them.   No. 243 <lb/> (8254-20-4-00) 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1610_img_1074_2"/>
              May 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916     My Dear Mother , I arrived here on yesterday after travelling <lb/>24 hours. We left Mountjoy on Wed at 6.0 from North Wall we came <lb/> in a Troopship to Holyhead, we travelled across England &amp; were 15 hours <lb/>in the train. we came thro' Nth Wales to Chester thence to Crewe on <lb/> thro' Staffordshire to Birmingham, where we delayed some time, we were <lb/> much looked at  at  all the stations, we had an escort of Soldiers who I must <lb/>say were fine fellows giving us every civility! We came along thro Warwickshire <lb/>Somerset &amp; Devonshire to Plymouth &amp; the Glories of the South West of <lb/>England were enjoyed by us. We had much speculation as to our <lb/>destination Some of us said Portland whilst others said Dartmoor <lb/>Shouldice &amp; Donovan had many <sic>arguements</sic>over their Geography <lb/>as we passed thro certain towns Jack would say thats in Warwick <lb/>Conn would say "twas in Staffs &amp; so on we were all wondering where <lb/>we were bound for. when we arrived at Plymouth we were told <lb/>Dartmoor was to be our destination then we had much speculation <lb/>as to how many Irish were here before us but we were the first <lb/>contingent &amp; I had the honour of being the first Irish man to cross <lb/> the threshold. there was 12 of us in the Party &amp; we sang our <lb/>songs grave &amp; gay as we travelled along. to west of England. <lb/> I am afraid I wont have many visitors here as it is so far <lb/> away from home. however some old friend may be holiday <lb/>making along this way &amp; may call in to see me. At any rate I <lb/>can keep in touch with home as we all intend to earn every <lb/> privili<seg type="del">d</seg>ge we can while we are here. I was reading on my journey <lb/>that there is to be a settlement of the Irish Question by Carson <lb/>&amp; Redmond consenting to agree it would be a great thing to <lb/> us who are suffering for our country to know that we had <lb/>settled the Question. I am very happy &amp; quite resigned to my <lb/>fate &amp; I feel sure that we shall be together soon when <lb/>we can resume our old happy life I pray God to keep <lb/>ye all safe &amp; sound "till I come back I know it <lb/>will be a hard struggle for you to manage with out <lb/>me but God is good &amp; you are such a great heart 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1610_img_1074_3"/>
            <lb/>that you will find a way to carry on tell Ned that I got his <lb/>message from F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacMahon I was glad to hear that Ned <lb/>was working away as I thought the town would be Idle for some <lb/>time. I was very sorry to hear I hope it is not true that <lb/>Ena lost her position over the trouble. God knows She lost enough <lb/>without this. This Dartmoor is beautifully situated I remember <lb/> reading with delight a book named Lorna Doone it dealt <lb/>with the place I little dreamt that the time would come when <lb/> I should be brought a prisoner thro the very country I so <lb/>much admired when I read of its beauty by Kingsley. So Dear <lb/>Mother if you read Lorna Doone you will have an idea <lb/>of where I am. I have had a visit from the Chaplain I think He <lb/> is an Irishman We also will be allowed reading 2 Books per <lb/>week &amp; I have just had a very good dinner so you see Mother I <lb/>am in for a good holiday &amp; as I have <sic>no thing</sic> to be ashamed <lb/>of I will be at rest spiritually &amp; materially. Let me know <lb/> how things are with you at home. I hope Kathleen is keeping <lb/>well &amp; is she at business also my Dear Aunt give her a <lb/>special word from me &amp; tell her not to spoil the dog with <lb/> kindness. Tell Mr &amp; Mrs Treacy I send them all my love.   When you go into my old Firm Todd Burns &amp; Co go round <lb/>to the Millinery &amp; tell Mary OKeefe that I wish to be remembered <lb/>to her &amp; all the girls in the house &amp; tell Duggan to convey <lb/> the same to the men whom I worked with so long. Harty or <lb/>OToole might come over on a holiday to see me or Davy or <lb/>Tom Burke. if I gain the privilege of 2 letters per month <lb/> I will send one to OMahony &amp; Davy &amp; some of my friends. <lb/>I was told that 2 girls called to see me while I was in <lb/>mountjoy but were refused <sic>admissionn</sic> from the <sic>descriptin</sic> it <lb/>must have been Celia &amp; Anna tell them the first opportunity I <lb/> have I will return the visit, I have no care on me now if <lb/>I am assured that you are able to manage I have no doubt <lb/>of your courage &amp; I am sure you are better off now than you 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1610_img_1074_4"/>
            <lb/>when Father Died when you were left with 5 of us babies <lb/>to rear &amp; you reared us all &amp; gave us everything that was <lb/>necessary to us &amp; as Fathers friends stood to you then you will <lb/>find others now. Poor Gerald was deported I believe but <lb/>I am sure when things settle down in Ireland all <lb/>these men will be allowed home &amp; maybe some of us. <lb/>We are all to say <seg type="del">a</seg> prayer that the we will all <lb/>leave here together &amp; we have a grand holiday laid out <lb/>on our release. We are the most optimistic party that <lb/>ever entered this establishment we are convinced that when <lb/> all these wars are over then men will on reflection see that <lb/>we fought an old fight &amp; they may, especially if the Irish <lb/>Question is settled give a General Amnesty as they did in South <lb/> Africa. At the same time we are prepared to go our full time. <lb/> I want you to tell all my friends that I am quite happy cheerful <lb/> &amp; content I can not write to them all. If you would rather <lb/> keep my Croke Cup Medal &amp; give Mrs OToole my Dublin Championship <lb/>medal you may do so as she was very nice  to  me &amp; I promised <lb/>her that day on the field before the match that I would give <lb/>her the medal if we won you can keep the rest of them &amp; give <lb/> her the other. I wonder will I be too slow to play when I come <lb/>out, the regular life here will have me in great form. We <lb/> arrived here at 7.0 &amp; were a source of wonder to the <lb/> parish as I am sure it is an unusual sight to see 12 <lb/>men some in uniform &amp; some not marching under guard of <lb/>fixed Bayonets to prison but we marched with heads <lb/> up &amp; firm foot as Irishmen the people were quite <lb/>respectful to us, I will now close this note hoping I have <lb/>convinced you that I am quite happy &amp; settled &amp; will face <lb/>this business in the proper spirit so now may God Bless you <lb/>give you comfort &amp; keep ye all until happier days when we <lb/>shall all be united in home. You may be quite sure that <lb/>we will be well treated. Your loving son <lb/> Harry . 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>