<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0307">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maurice Moore to Alice Stopford Green, 27 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maurice Moore</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Maurice Moore (1854-1939), soldier and politician, to Alice Stopford Green (1847-1929), wife of historian John Richard Green (1837-1883). he letter relates to progress around a petition to save Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). Moore says he &#39;feels really reassured because everything that can be done has been done.&#39; Roger Casement had been arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Alice Stopford Green was an Irish historian and nationalist. While not a supporter of armed rebellion, her house provided a space for leading nationalists to meet. Stopford Green had collaborated with Roger Casement on Congo Reform and, after the Easter Rising in 1916, she tried to save him from execution. Colonel Maurice George Moore, author, soldier and politician, was the younger brother of the writer George Moore. A member of the provisional committee of the Irish Volunteers in 1913, he was made the organisation&#39;s Inspector General, spending much of 1914 organising the troops in Ireland. In 1916 he collected a petition with Agnes O&#39;Farrelly asking for a reprieve of the death sentence against Roger Casement.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, Ms. 13,088/9/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/307</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0505">Maurice Moore</persName>
              <date>1916-07-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0307_img_1529_1"  type="Letter"  url="21220a1b91140706d3e89af2ae342101.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0307_img_1529_2"  type="Letter"  url="8e6e60d7a9ec7c02678ac9d1c21905f9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0307_img_1529_3"  type="Letter"  url="6188a9dfe6545934f473c100143ca49f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0307_img_1529_4"  type="Letter"  url="271dee01290b51180daf438e44af2e26.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0307_img_1529_1"/>
              lists by book post    Buswells Hotel    July 27th   My dear Mrs Green   I enclose a list of our <lb/>signatures to date for your information. <lb/>Will you please pass on (if of no <lb/>use to you) to Miss O'Farrelly <lb/> Irish School  Gortahork Co Donegal so that <lb/>she may know. She is working <lb/>that part of the country &amp; Miss Young <lb/>Clare. The Dublin Corporation passed <lb/>a resolution &amp; sent it to me - this was <lb/>arranged by Mr Sherlock &amp; well <lb/>managed. We did not want an <lb/>angry wrangle.   I see the M.Ps went to Asquith  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0307_img_1529_2"/>
              <lb/>&amp; presented petitions. I got Yeats letter <lb/>in Freeman &amp;&amp; handed a copy to <lb/>an American Correspondent who cabled <lb/>(or tried to) to America. Also my letter <lb/>to Freeman he cabled. He said America <lb/>was most excited &amp; shouting for news.   I feel greatly re-assured today. <lb/>I think everything that can be done has <lb/>been done; at least as much as is <lb/>required if Gov. wish to let him off; if <lb/>they are determined the other way ten <lb/>times more would do no good. The <lb/>Unionists seem very bitter - bitter in <lb/>exact proportion as they themselves have <lb/>been involved (except Carson). The Cabinet <lb/>has disgraced itself thoroughly; Redmond <lb/>managed the showing up skilfully at all <lb/>events; he is good at that. I don't know  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0307_img_1529_3"/>
              <lb/>what the end will be. As far as I can <lb/>guess it was a deliberate attempt to <lb/>wreck the parliamentary party &amp; rid <lb/>itself for a number of years of the <lb/>incubus of an Irish party dictating <lb/>terms. Both parties seem equally involved. <lb/>Asquith &amp; c tried to do again what <lb/>Gladstone did to Parnell. He saw <lb/>an opportunity of smashing the party. <lb/>English politicians hated United <lb/>Irish party.   After I published the Cardinal's <lb/>letter the Archbishop of Dublin sent <lb/>in his adhesion. I am sending <lb/>you today's Freeman with my letter. <lb/>I thought it better to remark on the <lb/>libels; they are being spread far &amp; wide. <lb/>This is a good moment for it as  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0307_img_1529_4"/>
              <lb/>sympathy has risen high &amp; people <lb/>will be glad to be re-assured. After <lb/>a reprieve would be too late.   I have been writing an article on <lb/>his behaviour &amp; its objects. Miss <lb/>Bannister has been telling everyone <lb/>over here what you told me, as <lb/>it is not a secret. Unless there <lb/>is a distinct objection I think it <lb/>ought to be published.   The Independent put in our notices <lb/>but in a very condensed form. <lb/>Derry Journal puts them in full <lb/>&amp; had a leading article.  <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely  Maurice Moore </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>