<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1525">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs E.N. Gilbert to Madeleine, c. June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>E.N. Gilbert</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>An acquaintance of the writer&#39;s brother, anonymous and unknown to Madeleine, upon hearing of the death of &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly, sends a cheque, asking that a draft for the same amount be sent to Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly - the donor only wanting to be identified as &#39;a sympathiser&#39;.Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly, (1875-1916) was involved in the procurement of arms in the lead-up to the Rising and was involved in the Howth gun-running incident. He fought in the G.P.O. During the Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961), his wife, was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/34</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1525</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0530">E.N. Gilbert</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0226">823 N. 20th Street, Philadelphia, United States of America.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Madeleine</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1525_img_986_1"  type="Letter"  url="2a59a9d43840bf0ceecf8ac6f78148eb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1525_img_986_2"  type="Letter"  url="b01dfe5f07414465f03c479212da7da3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1525_img_986_1"/>
                525-N.20th St  Phila,   Dear Madeleine,   An acquaintance of <lb/> my brother's, hearing of poor O' Rahilly's <lb/> death, has written expressing his <lb/> regrets. He had heard of O' R. in convntion <seg type="del">ect</seg><lb/> with Lady Aberdeen and was much <lb/> interested in him. He encloses a cheque for <lb/> 26 <hi rend="superscript">-</hi> asking Dr to get a draft for that amount, <lb/> and send it to Mrs. O'R from 'A <lb/> Sympathizer', no name to be mentioned. <lb/> Dr wrote at once saying that he knew <lb/> nothing of Mrs. O'R's affairs and did we <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1525_img_986_2"/>
              know whether the cheque would be <lb/> acceptable or accepted, and suggested <lb/> keeping the <seg type="del">t</seg> cheque until he could consult <lb/> with you what you thought best to <lb/> do. Will you advice with <seg type="del">your</seg> family <lb/> and tell what you'd like done. I assure <lb/> you that it is from a <hi rend="underline">person you do</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">not know</hi>, probably never saw, and <lb/> of course was sent absolutely from the <lb/> man's own initiative. Love to the <lb/> dear little boys, and love and never <lb/> ceasing prayers for all my dear ones there  <seg type="closer"> E.N.G </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>