<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2627">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Duffin to Celia Duffin, 15 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Emma Duffin (1883 - 1979) to Celia Duffin (1888-1979). The letter concerns Emma&#39;s hospital experiences, including some minor illnesses she suffered. It seems she and Miss Watson were photographed. She mentions Sam, Charlie, Aunt Margaret, Terry, some of her patients and the local populace.

Celia Duffin, born in 1888, was one of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She attended the Cheltenham Ladies College. She served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#34;&#34;Escape Poem&#34; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell &amp; Co. Ltd in 1929.Emma served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. She served initially in Egypt and was transferred to northern France just before the Battle of Somme, where she remained to the Armistice in 1918. On her return to Belfast, Emma worked as an illustrator of cards and books, including children’s stories written by her sister Ruth.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/10/1/A/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2627</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1134">Emma Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1739">15th Gen Hospital Alex.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2627_img_2052_1"  type="Letter"  url="24d62a718a1b9af26fb9eb60dfabea8e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2627_img_2052_2"  type="Letter"  url="e99e5ab25c1a8599339f26abd451e3b9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2627_img_2052_3"  type="Letter"  url="47163c017864cdc61023567a615e6c74.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2627_img_2052_1"/>
             15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Gen. Hosp. Alexandria   Jan. 15/16.    My dear old Celia   It is rather an age since I wrote to you I'm afraid<lb/>I pity you on night duty. I'm afraid I'm due to go on again<lb/>soon &amp; I do so hate it. In the meantime I am still in my<lb/>tent and they are opening up more tents again<seg type="unclear">has them sent</seg><lb/>a sister she seems a dull but decent old girl, &amp; funnily enough<lb/>had a V.C.D. in Manchester called Duffin who came from Dublin.<lb/>I am off in the morning today which is rather unusual for<lb/>me rather nice for a change but I should not like it often.<lb/>I have been out taking photographs I hope they'll be a<lb/>success. I took an awfully fond lot as the <seg type="unclear">duchy</seg> when<lb/>I was seeing Celine Russell off but unfortunately the<lb/>roll stuck in my camera &amp; the light got in when I was trying<lb/>to get them out. I was in the sick room for five<lb/>days with a Gyppy Tummy not very bad &amp; I rather enjoyed<lb/>snuggling down in bed when the others were going on duty since<lb/>that I had an awful swelled face which made me feel<lb/>much <seg type="unclear">in there</seg> really, though I was on duty, but now I am<lb/>quite all right again. We had a week of awful weather,<lb/>storms &amp; tropical rain which flooded everything, came into<lb/>the corner of my room &amp; ran down the wall. I like<lb/>the letter which you sent me very much, didn't you get starved. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2627_img_2052_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline">2</hi>  The club was swarming with officers and there was a band<lb/>playing, quite a gay scene! The other day I had my 3 hours<lb/>off in the morning &amp; I and another V.A.D, Miss Watson went down<lb/>to the docks to take photographs, it is a fascinating part, and<lb/>we went all through the corn markets <seg type="unclear">buy</seg> through part of the<lb/>native quarters. I hope the photos will turn out well for they<lb/>should be rather good. I am pleased that Sam has<lb/>got a post at home, &amp; that Charlie is mentioned in dispatches.<lb/>Marjorie has only written to me twice &amp; Aunt Margaret never, not<lb/>even for Xmas. They are funny people! I suppose<lb/>Terry will have been home on leave by the time you get this.<lb/>How you will enjoy having him! Can't Celia get some<lb/>leave before signing on again, I think she should!<lb/>Tell Molly I may get her some stones, but the people are such<lb/>cheats here I must wait till I get hold of some one who knows<lb/>some thing about them. I had such a nice<lb/>patient last week, quite a gentleman in the <seg type="unclear"></seg>   .<lb/>Company, I used to think he must hate eating off enamel<lb/>plates &amp; drinking out of bowls etc. with the others but he had<lb/>not a bit of swank about him. He has some  <lb/>&amp; I had a letter from him yesterday. They nearly all write<lb/>&amp; often come back to see me if they are in camps here, it is<lb/>a miracle to me how grateful they are for every little thing<lb/>you do for them. I had an embarrassing Australian<lb/>who has now gone I am rather glad to say, he used to call me    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2627_img_2052_3"/>
             sometimes for the want of a little leisure and a nice book. <lb/>Some one sent out a dear little collection of poetry, all old <lb/> favourites with some books for the Tommies &amp; I have kept it <lb/>as they would never read them, and it was a perfect joy <lb/>to see some of them again. I wish you would get abroad <lb/>somewhere, it would be so much more interesting but if you <lb/>came out here you would be here for all the hot weather. <lb/>Have you signed in for another six months. My time <lb/>will not be up till April. Poor Dessie's affair <lb/>sounds to me rather a fiasco. It is a pity! I don't like the <lb/>sound of him at all. I have nothing to tell you for I <lb/>have been having a very quiet life lately. If I could only <lb/>show you the people, it is a perpetual ammusement to watch <lb/>them. You see a woman swinging along with an enormous bundle <lb/>on her head and a child perched on her shoulder, sitting up as straight <lb/>as a reed though it only looks about a year old, or a man in <lb/>a lovely blue robe riding on a white donkey with big milk cans in <lb/>panniers at each side, or a very old man bent double with a <lb/>big water skin on his back, there is a picture at every corner, <lb/>but descriptions are dull I think, &amp; nothing in the way of photographs <lb/>is much good for you live the colour.   Best love my dear   Write again when you can   Ever yours   <hi rend="underline">Emma.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>