<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4945">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charlie Daly to Ellen Daly, 31 October 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charlie Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Cormac (Charlie Daly) to Mrs Daly, 31 October 1921. He is sorry to hear about the fire at Firies and the subsequent death of Mossie Casey. He thinks the war will resume shortly.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/2/1/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4945</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date>1921-10-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1168">Ellen Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1923</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4945_img_None_1"  url="91c3918636562e32fd4fe761d4820e56.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4945_img_None_2"  url="be4bfe9b9b7349083830bcd691443988.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4945_img_0_1"/>
              Oct 31st    <seg type="foreign"></seg>   I got your letter of the 27th<lb/>yesterday. That acccident at Firies was<lb/>a sad one indeed. Tis too bad about poor<lb/>Mossie Casey but tis fortunate that more lives<lb/>were not lost.  By the look of things I think we are not<lb/>far from war again. Well we can face<lb/>it with more confidence this time &amp; with better<lb/>prospects of success. I am sorry in a way<lb/>that I was not able to give another<seg type="unclear"> visit</seg><lb/>home but if I did it would mean<lb/>so much time lost from my work here.<lb/>I might perhaps be able <seg type="unclear"></seg> for <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>time. Anyway I am satisfied with having<lb/>seen ye at all &amp; with Gods help it<lb/>wont be long until I get an opportunity<lb/>again. When I go home next I hope that<lb/>I wont have cause to be ashamed of<lb/>this part of the country. To tell you the<lb/>truth I was so much ashamed of it when<lb/>I was down that I did not care going<lb/>home again until I had something to say<lb/>for myself. Of course twas not my<lb/>fault that twas so but I felt it all the same.  I had a letter from Katty A yesterday<lb/>Michael is to arrive in Dublin today I<lb/>hope he will be sent on to me. You know<lb/>Free wants to get hold of him too. We<lb/>had an argument about him when<lb/>we met in Dublin. I have first<lb/>claim though.  Tis too bad that Fr. Murphy is<lb/>taking such a view of things but he'll<lb/>change when he cools down. Even<lb/>tho he doesn't <seg type="unclear">what need will he<lb/>care when hes in a </seg>    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4945_img_0_2"/>
             I have no time <seg type="unclear"></seg> more<lb/>I hope everybody &amp; everything at<lb/>home is going on well. I had a<lb/>letter from Kathleen Shanahan yesterday she<lb/>told me that Harry &amp; <seg type="unclear">Jerome Riordan</seg><lb/>arrived at Whelans after I left.<lb/>I am very sorry that I did not<lb/>meet them especially Henry<lb/>I suppose Tomas has not been home<lb/>since. By the way did he send my<lb/>father that razor yet?<lb/>Never mind about that <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>I am only sorry that I am not able<lb/>to send more but this <seg type="unclear">truce</seg> &amp;<lb/>trotting up to Dublin has been a<lb/>bit expensive. I may be able to<lb/>do better when the war is over. The<lb/>difficulty then will be in getting it<lb/>through.<lb/>I will write you soon<lb/>again<lb/> Slain Leat<lb/>Cormac   <lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>