<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0362">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to the Commandant, Prisoners of War, Frongoch, 25 October, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This copy of a letter was addressed to the commandant of the Irish prisoners in Frongach Internment Camp in Wales.The writer advises the commandant that Mrs Gavan Duffy, wife of George Gavan Duffy, has requested, on her husband&#39;s behalf, a copy of an official document relating to discipline among prisoners of war as Gavan Duffy is representing prisoner P. Daly at his forthcoming trial. The writer states that they will enclose a copy of the relevant Royal Warrant and that Mrs Gavan Duffy was advised that her husband should now apply to the camp commandant for a copy.George Gavan Duffy, (1882-1951), was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising. His legal practice represented many of those detained in the aftermath of the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD45/46/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/362</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-25</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Commandant, Prisoners of War, Frongoch</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0137">Frongoch Internment Camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0362_img_1600_1"  type="Letter"  url="743ca45fa20a4ff881ea5728f076b15b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0362_img_1600_1"/>
                <seg type="del">14</seg>15th October, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed to inform you that Mrs Gavan Duffy<lb/> has to-day called at the War office with reference to the<lb/> trial of a prisoner, P. Dal<seg type="del">z</seg>y, interned under your command,<lb/> which is understood to be fixed for Tuesday next.<lb/> Mrs Duffy has applied on behalf of her husband, Mr. Gavan<lb/> Duffy, for a copy of the Royal Warrant for the Maintenance<lb/> of Discipline among prisoners of war.  A copy is enclosed herewith and Mrs Duffy has<lb/> been informed that if Mr. Duffy applies to you, a copy will<lb/> be furnished to him. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Sir,<lb/> Your obedient Servant,  The Commandant, <lb/> Prisoners of War,<lb/> Frongoch.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>