<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1245">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 22 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A short card from May Fay (1897-1976) to her fiance James (1877-1922) stating that she&#39;s looking forward to a visit.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>Private, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1245</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-01-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2121">Togherstown, Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1427">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1245_img_434_1"  type="Letter"  url="318535bd40ee3dcb7e9bba9722096bf9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1245_img_434_2"  type="Letter"  url="74548a8ac175126f6e212b6cccef65e5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1245_img_434_1"/>
              M.Gar   James Dearest,   I was very glad to get <lb/>your letter this morn it cheered <lb/>me as I was feeling lonely not <lb/>feeling so well &amp; then Mother <lb/>living away fancy she never <lb/>wrote us since she left but asked <lb/>in a letter to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. S. did we get <lb/>her card. She is staying till <lb/>Monday but when that day comes <seg type="unclear">shell</seg><lb/>will stay until another I hope when <lb/>she does come I will feel fit to start <lb/>on that so much wished for visit <lb/>Hope you will excuse this short <lb/>note in answer to your nice letter <seg type="closer"> Your ever loving   May </seg> I met M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs.</hi></hi><seg type="unclear">Price</seg>Morgan today she wanted to know from Mrs. S— <lb/>was I the <seg type="unclear">one</seg><lb/>was engaged <lb/>to her <seg type="unclear">friend</seg><lb/>It was a <lb/><seg type="unclear">start</seg> to see <lb/>it had <seg type="unclear">legs</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">so soon</seg><lb/>good news <lb/>you know  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1245_img_434_2"/>
                J.E.Finn Esq.  39 Belgrave Sq.  Rathmines  Dublin    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>