<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5010">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter on behalf of Chief of Staff to All Divisional Commandants, 30 November 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Chief of Staff</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Typed copy if IRA circular U. O’D on behalf of the IRA Chief of Staff to all Divisional Commandants, 30 November 1921. A previous letter gave the false impression on that the IRA was being reconstituted as a new Army rather some commandants are simply being offered new commissions. This new interpretation was agreed by a joint meeting of the GHQ and Cabinet. 1 page. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/2/5/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5010</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0324">Chief of Staff</persName>
              <date>1921-11-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0366">IRA General Headquarters, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5010_img_None_1"  url="58dde83392162501be23cc2817325153.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5010_img_0_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">P41/2/5/5<lb/><lb/>COPY.</hi> <hi rend="underline">OGLAIGH na h-ÉIREANN.</hi>   General Headquarters, Dublin    30th. November, 1921.    To all Divisional Commandants.   Some time ago you have, I presume, received a communication<lb/>from the Minister for Defence offering you a Commission with rank<lb/>of Commandant General. It might be inferred from this document<lb/>that a new Army was being formed, but this is not really so - the<lb/>idea being to offer fresh commissions to certain Officers. The<lb/>whole situation has been examined into at a Joint Meeting of the<lb/>Cabinet and G.H.Q. Staff and an understanding arrived at.  You should write to the Minister for Defence accepting the<lb/>Commission.   Beir Beannacht    U.O'D.<lb/>For Chief of Staff.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>