<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2581">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Henry Gill SJ to Fr Thomas V Nolan SJ, 3 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry V Gill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr Henry Gill SJ (1872-1945), Irish Jesuit Chaplain,  to Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941). Fr Gill writes of the effect of the Easter Rising on Irish troops at the front, particularly those of the 16th Irish Division. He describes conditions at the front and the weariness of 18 months of war.

The son of H.J. Gill, head of the publishing firm, M. H. Gill &amp; Son, Henry was educated at Clongowes Wood College and University College Dublin. He possessed an acumen for mathematics and science and studied in Louvain and under Professor J.J. Thompson, Cavendish Laboratories, Cambridge (1906 - 1908). Fr. Gill had a special interest in seismography: &#39;Experiments with Spinning Tops to illustrate earthquake reactions&#39; was the title of a lecture given by Henry Gill at the Cavendish Laboratory, 16 June 1908. It is recorded that the hardship of four years as a chaplain in WWI, had a lasting effect on Fr. Gill. Fr. Henry Gill SJ was awarded the Military Cross and the Distinguished Service Order with the 2nd Royal Irish Rifles.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/25/47</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2581</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0012">Henry V Gill</persName>
              <date>1916-05-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0735">2nd Royal Irish Rifles, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1945</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2581_img_2008_1"  type="Letter"  url="bbd151292bf0c92148957ba5db9c3ae6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2581_img_2008_2"  type="Letter"  url="e238f0bc9aa71295921212f1e241e692.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2581_img_2008_1"/>
             CHPI/25/ 2 Royal Irish Rifles <lb/>B.E.F France   3/5/16   Dear Fr Provincial PC,   We cannot think <lb/>of anything else than the terrible things which have <lb/>been going on in Dublin. Please God it is over now <lb/> and that the authorities will use - as I am sure they will - <lb/> tact in dealing with it. We only see the accounts <lb/>in English, and French, newspapers. I hope none of our <lb/> people have suffered in the affair. Nothing has effected <lb/> Irishmen out here more than this. I have to doubt <lb/>things will soon be <seg type="unclear">righted</seg> again. But it has been a <lb/>big lesson. Many who ought have known better seem <lb/> to have been asleep. - But least said soonest mended. <lb/>I pity the poor young lads who got entangled into <lb/> so horrible an affair. I see the XVI Division have been in it. <lb/> We too have had a bad week, but being of an <lb/> Irish regiment lost in an English army corps we never <lb/>get any praise. Ground mines were sprung and rushed <lb/>by the Germans, but our boys got into them at <lb/>once and <seg type="unclear">grabbed</seg> them back.<seg type="unclear">It was most ticklish</seg> for <lb/>a bit, but they got more than they expected
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2581_img_2008_2"/>
            <lb/>It will be known some day. Personally I am well, but utterly <lb/>jogged out. <seg type="unclear">Last</seg> 18 months with hardly a free day is <lb/> a long strain, officially when there is the responsibility for <lb/> well near a thousand souls scattered over any number of units. <lb/> The few days leave are certainly no rest, but relieves me <lb/> of the responsibility for a few days. You can judge from <lb/> newspapers quite as well as we can as to the chances of <lb/> another year. It will be time enough to consider the question. <lb/> Of my going in a few months hence, but as things go now, <lb/> I certainly do not feel that I ought to. I long for a comfortable <lb/> rest. It is as by sense <seg type="unclear">centred</seg> I feelings and imagin- <lb/>ation that it is possible to keep going on. I know that a <lb/>chaplain can do just that as much or as little as suits him, <lb/>but I should be ytterly unhappy were I not able to do the work <lb/> which has to be done. I have not seen any of our people <lb/> since I saw Fr. Doyle some months ago, even he complained of <lb/> the physical fatigue! <seg type="unclear">You</seg> see I'm a rather bad bit of <lb/>the hive, when there was a <seg type="unclear">bout</seg> of fighting a year or <lb/>less ago. He has to walk over an old battlefield to get <lb/>to our trenches; but I cannot say where we are. Please <lb/> give my kindest regards to all. I believe the "Declaration" if any <lb/>is for the kings birthday list. The last declaration would be the <lb/> permanent possession if a blackcoat! Hoping all will soon <lb/> be quiet again, Believe me dear Rev Father.   Yours by   H.V. Gill 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>