<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2231">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Willis, 10 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to a Mr Willis. Originally a liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
In the letter, Montgomery discusses the threat of Home Rule in Ireland, stating that the Unionist MPs have accepted that John Redmond (1953-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, will gain some form of Home Rule in Ireland. The letter also states that this is even being accepted by radical Unionist newspapers who call for Ulster to be excluded from an Ireland with Home Rule. It goes on to state that Carson should be encouraged to to enter discussions to prevent Ulster being part of and Ireland with Home Rule. Montgomery also describes the granting of Home Rule following the Easter Rising as an act of lunacy, naming Walter Long (1854-1926) and Bonar Law (1858-1923), Unionist members of parliament, as being effected by the lunacy. The letter ends suggesting an emergency meeting should be held to discuss the matters and propose an amendment to the Home Rule Bill to prevent landlords from being ruined.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingbourne Papers, D/627/429/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2231</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-10</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Willis</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2231_img_1676_1"  type="Letter"  url="0fd003d64575fce01a5880f8ef880434.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2231_img_1676_2"  type="Letter"  url="449598c85d3e0abe0c91bec18341f85f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2231_img_1676_1"/>
            Copy <lb/><hi rend="underline">Private and Confidential</hi>  10th June 1916   My Dear Willis,   Thank you for your letter of 7th,   All you say is perfectly true, but our leaders have <lb/> made us acquainted at private meetings with an amazing and <lb/> alarming state of things which makes it impossible for us to take <lb/> the steps that most of us would like to take, and which, under <lb/> circumstances as presented by you we ought to take. It appears <lb/> that diplomatic complications of a very serious sort have convinced <lb/> the whole Cabinet, including the Unionist Members, that it is <lb/> necessary to give John Redmond some form of Home Rule to come <lb/> into operation at once. The whole Unionist Press with the <lb/> exception of the "Morning Post" has taken up the cry that the <lb/> Irish question must be settled out of hand. The majority of <lb/> the Unionist Members of the House of Commons are now of the same <lb/> mind in spite of all our friends can say. The only life-buoy <lb/> that is visible in this hostile flood of things is a provisio <lb/> which even most of the Radical papers make, that "Ulster must not <lb/> be coerced." The only question before us here at present is, <lb/> shall we authorise arson to enter into conference with Redmond <lb/> and Co. for a settlement on the basis of the exclusion of six <lb/> counties in Ulster, with regard to which Lloyd George professes <lb/> to have arrived at a preliminary tentative agreement. In the <lb/> present state of British public opinion it is clear that whichever <lb/> party refuses to treat on the basis of Lloyd George's proposals <lb/> will incur odium and diminish its chances of getting anything
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2231_img_1676_2"/>
            it wants  in the future . If Carson receives the authority of the Unionist <lb/> Council to treat on this basis it will, of course, be understood <lb/> that he will make the best bargain he can as regards details <lb/> and safeguards for the minority in the part of Ireland not <lb/> excluded from the Home Rule Act. The Unionist Council with <lb/> whom the decision in this matter rests is a very <seg type="del">diplomatic</seg> democratic  <lb/> body, and it will be impossible to raise landlord points there. <lb/> If the Unionist Council on Monday decide to accept the proposed <lb/> basis of negotiations Redmond will still have to get his supporters <lb/> to do the same, and to me it appears that the establishment of <lb/> Home Rule is still some way off.     Of course on the face of it, the mere <hi rend="underline">proposal </hi> that Home <lb/>Rule should be granted <hi rend="underline">now </hi> as a consequence of the Rebellion looks <lb/> like sheer lunacy. The reasons behind the curtain which have <lb/> induced Walter Long and Bonor Law  <seg type="unclear">Law &amp; &amp; a Chamberlain</seg>  to agree to this apparently <lb/>mad step must have been of extraordinary force. Of course if <lb/> the country was ruled by a Pitt instead of an Asquith a very <lb/>different course would have been pursued, but we must take facts <lb/> as they are. I think the landlords must sit tight for the present, <lb/> but I agree with you that as soon as it appears to be settled that <lb/> an Amending Bill to the Home Rule Act now on the Statute Book is <lb/> to be brought at once, we should have an emergency meeting <lb/>to see whether it is possible to get anything inserted in this <lb/> Amending Bill on the point you mention or others to save land <lb/>lords from ruin.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>