<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2697">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 10 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother Maria (1854-1954) informing her of her latest news from London. Celia writes about time spent with her sister, Dorothy, her trip to the theatre and a  number of soldiers from her ward who visited Buckingham palace to be entertained by the King and Queen.

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/31/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2697</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1997">3rd London General, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2697_img_2118_1"  type="Letter"  url="1d7a0c9ba75e532dcf29852cf1db0c21.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2697_img_2118_2"  type="Letter"  url="d649e66d24bb62e7cab0328402a776aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2697_img_2118_3"  type="Letter"  url="8a5efb69d29c6c2e68f60642f16d80b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2697_img_2118_4"  type="Letter"  url="8482e92d02cdc030317135d0d065f5be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2697_img_2118_5"  type="Letter"  url="0cdb62b9fe4bd6140efb6f19dae2245a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2697_img_2118_1"/>
            D2109/10/1/C<lb/>  3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> London General Hospital <lb/> March 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916 <lb/><lb/>  Dearest Mamma <lb/>  Thank you so much for posting <lb/>me the currant loaf, Gosse and I <lb/>have been thoroughly enjoying it for <lb/>tea and supper, but please don't send <lb/>me any more things, as I am very <lb/>rich at present, as I am drawing <lb/>£6-13-4<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> a month. Long may it <lb/>last!    I have just been meeting Dorothy this <lb/>afternoon. I joined her at S. Kensington <lb/>Station, and we called on M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> <lb/>Macleod, but found she had just<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2697_img_2118_2"/>
            gone out which was a pity. We then <lb/>journeyed on to the High St, and I <lb/>helped Dorothy to choose a new hat at <lb/>Barker's, rather a pretty pink sports' <lb/>one, and managed to have time <lb/>for a hurried tea before getting <lb/>back. I was lucky this week, <lb/>as matron gave us a full day instead <lb/>of a half day, and I was able <lb/>to go to Epsom while Dorothy was <lb/>there. I only spent the night really, <lb/>as I went up to town with Dorothy <lb/>next morning to see Lady Oliver at <lb/>St. John's Gate. We waited in the <lb/>big hall and studied all the <lb/>quaint portraits of the old grand<lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2697_img_2118_3"/>
            masters, nearly all wearing a large <lb/>St. John cross on their breasts. The <lb/>place seemed full of business. Lady <lb/>Oliver was very nice, quite young, <lb/>with a great row of medal ribbons <lb/>across her apron. It appears the <lb/>clerical staff must sign on for a <lb/>year, and only get £1 a week <lb/>and have to keep themselves, so it <lb/>doesn't seem much use D.D. <lb/>going in for that. I asked her <lb/>about going abroad, and she <lb/>said they had sent no new ones <lb/>since last December, and none <lb/>were to go except from home <lb/>hospitals on the recommendation <seg type="del">of</seg> <lb/>of the matron, so that if I left here <lb/>I wouldn't have a chance at all, <lb/>unless Papa can get me sent <lb/>through Lord Ranfurly. Lady Oliver <lb/>said the V.A.D's who were coming <lb/>back from Alexandria would most <lb/>likely be landed in France as they <lb/>would be more used to foreign <lb/>conditions. I wonder what is <lb/>hap-pening to Emma, I am anxious to <lb/>hear. France would be rather nice <lb/>for a change and she would <lb/>miss the desperate heat of Egypt <lb/>in summer.   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2697_img_2118_4"/>
            D2109/10/1/C<lb/>  afterwards, Dorothy and I met Uncle <lb/>Edmund at the Haymarket Stores <lb/>and had lunch there and Aunt <lb/>Fanny, with her usual goodness <lb/>gave us theatre tickets, and we <lb/>went to see "The Backer" at St James' <lb/>which was about the only Tuesday <lb/>matinee and was not good.    Genevieve Ward was an old Duchess, <lb/>and George Alexander was the hero, but <lb/>as he was trying to be funny he <lb/>was not much of a success.    I was shocked to see the tragic <lb/>death of Colonel Hill-Trever. Was <lb/>there anhy reason for it. It does 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2697_img_2118_5"/>
             seem a pity.  Some of the tommies in my ward<lb/>went to Buckingham Palace and<lb/>were entertained by the King and<lb/>queen, they were awfully pleased,<lb/>especially one whom King George<lb/>had chatted to, and admired his<lb/>capelline bandage.  I have been busy to- day and<lb/>am writing this in bed, so goodnight<lb/>to you.   Ever your loving<hi rend="underline"><lb/>Celia </hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>