<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0159">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Dalton to Richard Henry Wright, 7 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Dalton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from William Dalton (b. 1870) a staff clerk in the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction, to Henry Richard Wright (b.1865), the registrar at the chief secretary&#39;s office. Dalton requests the original papers concerning the case of the late Crawford Neill (1868-1916), an employee of the National Library who was shot on 25 April trying to prevent looting. The letter also refers to the assistance Dalton provided in helping a man named Moses O&#39;Connor receive a passport for travel to Canada.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7721/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/159</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0643">William Dalton</persName>
              <date>1916-08-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1024">Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Richard Henry Wright</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0159_img_1288_1"  type="Letter"  url="41e13d83046ea112ecd2a6d43684f81a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0159_img_1288_1"/>
                DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE  AND TECHNICAL INSTRUCTION  DUBLIN    7th August, 1916.   Dear Mr. Wright,   I am sorry to trouble you again about the papers <lb/> relative to the late Crawford Neill. Mr. O'Connor sent <lb/> me, a few weeks ago, copies of the statements made in the <lb/> case, but Mr. Lyster, the Librarian of the National Library, <lb/> is very anxious to get the <hi rend="underline">original</hi>papers if possible. <lb/>If, therefore, there be no official objection to the return <lb/> of these documents now we should be very glad if you could <lb/> let us have them back.  I wrote you from Malahide about a man named Moses <lb/> O'Connor who was waiting for a passport to Canada. The <lb/>passport came next day. I am sure you must have helped to <lb/>expedite the matter, and I am much obliged for the trouble <lb/>taken in the case. <seg type="closer"> Yours very faithfully,  William Dalton   R.H. Wright, Esq.,  egistrar,  Chief Secretary's Office.  </seg> 3 originals returned to Mr. Dalton accordingly  Asst. Under Secretary. <lb/> I see no objection to the return of <lb/> the 3 documents asked for by Mr. Lyster on <lb/>behalf of the late Mr. Neil's relatives. Do you approve? <lb/>WMC  8/8/16   I agree <lb/><seg type="unclear">EJ</seg> 8/8/16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>