<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4316">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Horace Plunkett, 5 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Sir Horace Curzon Plunkett  (1854-1932). Plunkett, Unionist MP, was an Anglo-Irish agricultural reformer, pioneer of agricultural cooperatives, supporter of Home Rule, and author.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4316</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0570">Horace Plunkett</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4316_img_3677_1"  type="Letter"  url="0859298a01ae9f05cc426cf318a1066a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4316_img_3677_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0a54d699bb6f5255d84c0083d0fa1d3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4316_img_3677_1"/>
             D1507/A/17/8  PAGE 1 OF 2  1/2 BAY 44  40   5 June 1916    My dear Plunkett,   I am sorry I am myself confined to bed at all events <seg type="del">for</seg><lb/>for to-day, but if I am well enough I shall call to see you<lb/>to-morrow. I am sorry to hear you are unwell. I doubt very<lb/>much whether there is any solution to which you and I could <sic>agre</sic><lb/>as we take very divergent views of the whole question and my<lb/>negotiations were carried on up to some days after my return <seg type="del">fxxm</seg><lb/>from Belfast without any hint of any kind from any of my late<lb/>Unionist colleagues in the Cabinet that they did not really<lb/>agree with Asquith's statement on the 25th. May, which alleged<lb/>that they were unanimous about a settlement. To withdraw, at<lb/>this stage, the offer which was carried by the Nationalists<lb/>in very grave difficulties would in my opinion probably render<lb/>the carrying on of the war from a Parliamentary view almost<lb/>impossible and all that would be secured would be another weak<lb/>executive in Ireland which would be challenged at every step<lb/>by disappointed and hostile Nationalists. To run these risks<lb/>for the sake of putting off till the end of the war the Act<lb/>which then automatically comes into force does not seem to me<lb/>to be a sound or statesmanlike policy and so far as Ulster is<lb/>concerned the settlement gives her all that we would have taken<lb/>at Buckinhgam Palace Conference, and personally I would    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4316_img_3677_2"/>
             D1507/A/17/8  view with horror the necessaity of native hostilities<lb/>in Ulster at the end of the war.   Yours ever, <lb/>The Rt. Hon. Sir Horace Plunkett 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>