<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0674">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Clara Mary Davidson, 3 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson expressing frustration at the delay in going to front. In spite of this frustration Davidson does note that they have been provided with comfortable billets and that he has been getting plenty of exercise visiting his troops who are scattered over several villages. Davidson then requests that certain items be sent from home, such as thick woolen socks, shirts, warm underwear, shaving cream and butter. This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642B/8/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/674</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0674_img_2167_1"  type="Letter"  url="d5d41da851d512be153a1019c0cca205.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0674_img_2167_2"  type="Letter"  url="91e4571ddac7e54aa7e33544ccbcaf99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0674_img_2167_3"  type="Letter"  url="a21bf56e97352c1256acda9047311117.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0674_img_2167_4"  type="Envelope"  url="aa5b691660596949c067f4f404e73e35.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0674_img_2167_5"  type="Letter"  url="b2aeb5ef37d2d3871a197e1363a14bc8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0674_img_2167_1"/>
                3/11/15   My dearest Mother   — It is just a week I <lb/>think since I wrote last, &amp;since then I have <lb/>received your letter of 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; one from <lb/>Kathleen dated 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Am so glad to hear that <lb/>she was keeping bright &amp; well &amp; hope that since <lb/>then there has been nothing to worry about. I am <lb/>expecting to receive the good news any day <lb/>now but I don't imagine you will be able <lb/>to let me know by wire as I understand none <lb/>are allowed to be sent out here.  I have scarcely any news to give you, for even <lb/>since we arrived here we have been simply <lb/>doing the same kind of work as at Seaford <lb/>with rather more Divisional Field Days &amp; we <lb/>are all heartily sick of it. It seems to me <lb/>that instead of doing the men good it is having <lb/>quite the reverse effect for the Units are scattered <lb/>over different villages &amp; discipline is apt to <lb/>become slack. The orders were of course <lb/> to begin with, that we were only to be here  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0674_img_2167_2"/>
              about a week &amp; then return to the trenches <lb/>to take over a part of the Line on our own <lb/>&amp; we were all looking forward to this for we <lb/>should have then been able to settle down to <lb/>some definite work, but for some reason <lb/>or other it was decided to send the 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Bde <lb/>instead of us &amp; it looks as if we might <lb/>now be here for weeks. The weather has <lb/>been too awful for words — torrents of rain <lb/>&amp; very cold — the only compensation is <lb/>that we are in rather comfortable billets <lb/>in a fine big Chateau &amp; after all that is <lb/>a good deal to be thankful for out here. <lb/>I have almost got rid of my cold &amp; am <lb/>really very fit. I have a lot of riding to <lb/>do as the Batts are at different villages <lb/>some distance apart &amp; the exercise does <lb/>me good. Saw Gerard today when I <lb/>was over with the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. He is quite fit &amp; <lb/>in very good form &amp; is also in fairly <lb/>comfortable quarters. He had heard <lb/>from Chas.M. within the last day or so  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0674_img_2167_3"/>
              &amp; told me that the latter had been given <lb/>another months leave as his throat was <lb/>still giving trouble. As regards clothing, <lb/>the last new socks that you sent me were <lb/>not so thick as I wanted though they have <lb/>suited quite well up to the present. For <lb/>the cold weather I shall want something a <lb/>good deal thicker, similar to my old ones <lb/>&amp; of nice soft wool. I got the last ones <lb/>in Lindsays &amp; they were very good quality. <lb/>They should have long legs so as to come <lb/>well up over the calf of the riding breeches. <lb/>The following is a list of things I would <lb/>like you to send out to me as soon as <lb/>it is convenient.  3 pairs thick socks <lb/>2 suits warm underwear <lb/>1 thick shirt <lb/>6 handkerchiefs <lb/>1 Tube shaving cream (Roger Gallets) <lb/>1 Tube Kolynos tooth paste <lb/>1 Muffler ( think there is a nice soft one <lb/>in one of my greatcoat pockets)  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0674_img_2167_4"/>
              I think this all I require at present <lb/>dear Mother &amp; when they arrive I will <lb/>send back a parcel of this clothing so <lb/>as not to increase my luggage.  There is one thing which is always very <lb/>acceptable &amp; that is butter. We find <lb/>it very hard to obtain any out here &amp; <lb/>tinned stuff has always a sniff. Our <lb/>Bde. Major gets some sent out from home <lb/>occasionally wrapped in oil paper &amp; <lb/>it arrives out in splendid condition so <lb/>if when there is any to spare you could <lb/>send me a few pounds it would be <lb/>very much appreciated. It is very <lb/>late now so must have done. Hoping <lb/>all are well &amp; with my fondest love <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  Jim </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0674_img_2167_5"/>
              On Active Service <lb/> Rcd 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Nov 1915    Mrs. S.C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  Ireland    J Davidson  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>