<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4343">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 5 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4343</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1360">Brooks&#39;s, St James&#39;s Street</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4343_img_3700_1"  type="Letter"  url="1a40e85d68c3d7b37a035b3b834f3cff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4343_img_3700_2"  type="Letter"  url="2369936db4052074fe7094f44df560e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4343_img_3700_3"  type="Letter"  url="83574237d57ceb1dddea6b9b098b0107.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4343_img_3700_1"/>
             <sic>Wedy</sic> night <lb/> 5 July   BROOKS'S, <lb/> S<hi rend="superscript">T</hi> JAMES'S STREET.   Dear Sir Edward.   My excuse for writing <lb/>you is the fact of <lb/>the <hi rend="underline">tremendous</hi> crisis <lb/>we are in.    It is one of life &amp; <lb/>death to us in the <lb/>S &amp; W. -    The North (six counties) <lb/>are comparatively safe <lb/>but, is not that so on
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4343_img_3700_2"/>
            <lb/>the grounds that the matter <lb/>is <hi rend="underline">permanent</hi>.   <hi rend="underline">You</hi> of all people have <lb/>the power of having <lb/>the true facts as to <lb/>this. May I with <lb/>all earnestness appeal <lb/>to you to do so ? <lb/>and, before the meeting <lb/>at the Carlton on <lb/>Friday.   If I am unreasonable <lb/>forgive me. but, Sir E. <lb/>Carson's name is being <lb/>bandied about in a <lb/>way that hurts me. I <lb/>am telling you the plain <lb/>truth. You have ever <lb/>been more than kind <lb/>to me, hence my feeling <lb/>that I can write thus <lb/>to you.   I have worked and struggled <lb/>for 30 years in the <lb/>cause of loyal Ireland, <lb/>is it to be said that <lb/>now, owing to what can
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4343_img_3700_3"/>
            <lb/>surely be merely an error <lb/>of Judgement, or a mis ap. <lb/>-prehension, that <hi rend="underline">because</hi> <lb/>the plain truth regarding <lb/>"permanent" or "temporary" <lb/>was not disclosed, that <lb/>the whole cause of loyal <lb/>Ireland, N.S.E.W., was <lb/>to be eternally and <lb/>irretrievably wrecked? <lb/>I can't &amp; won't believe <lb/>it.   My usual regards to Lady Carson.    Always <sic>Yrs</sic>   <hi rend="underline">J. Mackey Wilson</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>