<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1777">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Henry Grattan Esmonde to Augustine Birrell, 7 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Esmonde</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Thomas Henry Grattan Esmonde (1862-1935), a landowner and politician. The letter was addressed to the Chief Secretary for Ireland, Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Birrell was appointed chief secretary in January 1907. In 1916 Birrell resigned as he willingly accepted the political responsibility for the outbreak of the Rising in 1916. 
In the letter Esmonde states that John Robert O&#39;Connell (1868-1943) is qualified for the position of chief crown solicitor which has been left vacant.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1777</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0418">Thomas Esmonde</persName>
              <date>1916-04-07</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1935</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1777_img_1232_1"  type="NULL"  url="f1b2e1ec613e9de1b07048d6f1d168a1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1777_img_1232_1"/>
            date>7.4.16.   Dear Mr. Birrell   The office for Chief <lb/>Crown Solicitor for Ireland <lb/>being vacant <lb/>I have <lb/>pleasure in recommending <lb/>Sir John P. O'Connell of <lb/>34 Kildare St Dublin <lb/>for the post.   He is well qualified for <lb/> the duties of that office.   Ever Yours   Thomas H. Grattan Easmond 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>