<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1613">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. Marie Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM). In this letter from the theatre of war, Marie writes home to her mother to talk about her new posting in Malta. Marie explains quickly how her recent days have gone.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF116</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1613</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1613_img_1077_1"  type="Letter"  url="dfe4254a22f6cf864ed1826720c1b67d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1613_img_1077_2"  type="Letter"  url="3ee54ce81daab301fb3fbb1d464084c4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1613_img_1077_1"/>
             B/F/1/16  I am enclosing Photo we had taken about<lb/>a week ago on our way to Valetta it<lb/>is very good we all think &amp; I look very<lb/>fat in it. The centre one is Paul &amp; the<lb/>other Jenkins an Australian. I hope you<lb/>will like it—  There is a man going to England to-day<lb/>so I am going to give this to him to post—<lb/>I received your letter of the 21st Nov: last<lb/>night also Violets it was too bad you<lb/>had the trouble of <sic>coping</sic> Charlies letter<lb/>as Violet also sent me a copy, certainly<lb/>it was worth reading &amp; so <sic>cheerry</sic><lb/>&amp; bright—  Very many thanks for sending Gerald<lb/>a Plum Pudding it is much too good<lb/>of you to send one out to me, we<lb/>shall enjoy it I know—  I am longing for your photo—<lb/>It will be very nice to see Aunt Lily<lb/>&amp; hear all the home news  I tried the other day to get warm<lb/>Vest or Spencers <!-- a garment worn as a cardigan --> but failed, they are absolutely<lb/>no use also Silk Blouse as it is getting too cold<lb/>for cotton— I have had a horrible cold<lb/>this last week but am glad to say is<lb/>nearly well now &amp; has gone up to my<lb/>head— I must end now as it is time 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1613_img_1077_2"/>
            for duty—<lb/>  With heaps of love &amp; kisses,<lb/> Your loving daughter—<lb/><hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> <lb/>  The patient did not go to-day so open this again as<lb/> to add a few sensible lines — You will be glad to<lb/> hear I was <sic>innoculated</sic> against Para. Typhoid<lb/> so have the evening off &amp; need not go on duty<lb/>til after 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Dinner to-morrow so shall have a<lb/> good rest in the morning, it does not seem to be<lb/> <sic>effecting</sic> me in the slightest except my arm is<lb/> a bit stiff, I am also glad to say my cold<lb/> is quite gone to-night— I went for a lovely<lb/> walk after Tea with my Staff Sister into Sliema<lb/> &amp; back. She is a dear &amp; so kind to me—<lb/>   Well we were at last asked to sign on which<lb/> I have done for six months, for the present any-<lb/> how. I had a letter from Nellie to-day saying<lb/> they were off to Sicily, it would be nice to be<lb/> going with them. I am wondering how<lb/> A. Lily will like being out here, I am sure<lb/> she will find it very trying at 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> I hope<lb/> she will be lucky &amp; get under nice Sisters as<lb/> it makes all the difference whether you are happy<lb/> or not, they can either make it heaven or Hell<lb/> for the V.A.D's <!-- end of translation -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>