<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0022">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from S.M. Martina to Nancy O'Rahilly, 25 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>S.M. Martina</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from S.M. Martina to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). The writer apologises for not writing sooner, saying that, as a stranger, she didn&#39;t want to intrude too early on Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s grief. She praises The O&#39;Rahilly and and says that the sisters have been offering prayers. She mentions &#39;the boys&#39; and hopes they will be a comfort. Finally the writer requests a supply of mortuary cards and offers deepest sympathy. In a P.S. she invites Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly to visit the Convent.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at its founding in 1914. She was the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-styled as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916), who was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/44</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/22</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0005">S.M. Martina</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0796">St. Mary&#39;s Dominican College, Muckross Park, Donnybrook, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0022_img_1052_1"  type="Letter"  url="85f16b4cfabb85e9d8f5d36fdb757b6f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0022_img_1052_2"  type="Letter"  url="da0c34d5369c7096d5f54b182cc59218.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0022_img_1052_3"  type="Letter"  url="6816c7200743e4b10bfbf88fef41fd0e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0022_img_1052_1"/>
                St. Mary's Dominican College,  Muckross Park,  Donnybrook,  Dublin, S.    25th May 1916   Dear M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. O'Rahilly,    You must think <lb/>it very strange that I <lb/>never wrote a line to <lb/> offer you our deepest <lb/> sympathy in the biggest <lb/> sorrow of your life.   Believe me it was  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0022_img_1052_2"/>
              <lb/>through no want of <lb/>sympathy, but there are <lb/> times when a stranger's <lb/> letter might jar and <lb/> in a grief such as <lb/>yours I thought it <lb/>better to wait a little <lb/>before intruding. <lb/>May God comfort <lb/>your poor broken heart, <lb/>as He alone can. You <lb/>have the comfort of <lb/>knowing that your dear <lb/>husband was a good, <lb/> holy man and died <lb/>a holy, happy death. <lb/>We have prayed much <lb/>for him and you.   I hope the boys <lb/> will be a great comfort  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0022_img_1052_3"/>
              <lb/>to you now.   If you get any mortuary <lb/> cards of your dear husband <lb/> may I ask for a few. <lb/>We should like to remember <lb/> such a noble soul R.I.P. <lb/>Joined by the Sisters in <lb/> deepest sympathy, love <lb/>to my old Children.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely in J.C.  <hi rend="underline">S.M. Martina</hi> <lb/>O.S.D. </seg> P.S. When you <lb/>feel equal, we <lb/>should like to <lb/>have a visit <lb/>from you.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>