<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4237">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender, circa November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/75</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4237</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4237_img_3605_1"  type="Letter"  url="7271dd4632dbc25e9cdd83a989029e21.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4237_img_3605_2"  type="Letter"  url="778d48de9f091f6dc0a68809e622b785.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4237_img_3605_1"/>
             The enclosed from Mr <lb/>Crichton <seg type="unclear">Mahon</seg> is an extra <lb/>ordinary conglomeration of <lb/>mistakes. He too has been <lb/>taken in both by Redmond <lb/>&amp; the Germans. Fancy think <lb/>ing we have accepted Home <lb/>Rule, inclcuding Carson !!    Things thank heaven have <lb/>not come to that pass yet, <lb/>&amp; it will be again a case <lb/>of the strong hand in Ulster, so <lb/>perhaps it is as well that the <lb/>bw &amp; pr will not be enmeshed <lb/>in other snares.   I fear we shall hear of <lb/>a disaster in Service. If only <lb/>we had started 3 weeks earlier <lb/>when Carson wanted, but no...
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4237_img_3605_2"/>
            <lb/>When at last the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t </hi> does <lb/>dare to show a little strength <lb/>to Greece the effect is magical. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>