<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0701">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Seamus Fitzgerald to his aunt and uncle, 5 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Seamus Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from an interned Seamus Fitzgerald to his family, he thanks them for their welcome letter and describes Wakefield Prison as &#39;a rather dirty sleepy little manufacturing town, corresponding to practically what Carlow is in Ireland&#39;. He also describes the prison layout; four large halls each containing four wards with 40 to 60 cells, he is in C Hall, No. 1 ward, Cell No. 27. Main meals consist of black coffee &#39;very objectionable stuff&#39;, horseflesh with one potato, two tablespoons of beans and some soup, breakfast and supper dry bread but he comments &#39;still mind you it is better then what we got in Cork&#39;. He adds they were kept in Solitary Confinement for 23 1/4 hours each day for two weeks. He closes with remembrances to friends and a request for Miss Carroll to write.Seamus Fitzgerald (1896-1972) was a Cork politician who channelled his patriotism into day-to-day efforts to establish Ireland as a modern nation, especially in the economic sphere. He joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914. Following the Easter Rising, Fitzgerald was interned in Wakefield Prison in England.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork City and County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of Seamus Fitzgerald (1876-1972) PR/6/13, Papers of Seamus Fitzgerald (1876-1972) PR/6/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/701</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1323">Seamus Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-06-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1691">Wakefield Prison, West Yorkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0872">Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0701_img_2192_1"  type="Letter"  url="f690fa557202edeab99968387ae5f96e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0701_img_2192_2"  type="Letter"  url="3725048eed96d28eb2892a0079e01129.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0701_img_2192_3"  type="Letter"  url="f8bd66bfa42679f2dc868c023f8708af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0701_img_2192_4"  type="Letter"  url="f690fa557202edeab99968387ae5f96e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0701_img_2192_1"/>
              Address to reply to :- <lb/>  C1036 James Fitzgerald,  Irish Prisoner,  (Wakefield).  c/o Chief Postal Censor,, London    Mon. night 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916   My Dearest Aunt and 'Uncle',   Your<lb/> welcome letter reached me today, —<lb/> with stamps enclosed.l Before you<lb/> begin to read further just get <lb/> my letter to Patrick first and<lb/> read on after his, for I find<lb/> that to write to all I must<lb/> divide my news — or would you<lb/> rather call it experiences —<lb/> amongst you all, and you can<lb/> get all by reading the ones <lb/> I sent to Mother, Patk, Bob , and<lb/><seg type="del">yourselves</seg> then the one I am<lb/> just writing to yourselves.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0701_img_2192_2"/>
              Wakefield is a rather dirty,<lb/> sleepy little manufacturing town,<lb/> corresponding to practically what<lb/> Carlow is in Ireland — at least<lb/> this is what the nurse, or rather<lb/> one of the nurses who so<lb/> kindly visited me, told me. Of course<lb/> I don't know, having seen<lb/> nothing excepting perhaps the<lb/> station we alighted and<lb/> of course the edifice, which at<lb/> present holds me.  This noble pile consists of<lb/> four large halls as per figure<lb/> with a large block and<lb/> tower in the centre. <lb/> Each of these halls consists<lb/> of four wards numbered 1, 2,<lb/> 3, and 4. No. 1 ward is on the<lb/> ground floor, no. 2 on the next<lb/> ,and so on. Each ward<cb/> contains from 40 to 60 cells<lb/>. Thus I am in C Hall, no. 1 ward,<lb/> and in no 27 cell;— which<lb/> incidentally was also the number<lb/> of my cell in Cork, — thus you<lb/> can understand the 'Insignia'<lb/> C1/27 on the corner of the first page. <lb/> This is also the number on the badge<lb/> which we wear for distinguishing<lb/> purposes. Thus you can see<lb/> it is in reality a convict prison<lb/> like Kilmainham and others.   We dont get black tea to<lb/> drink as mother stated — it is<lb/> black coffee and very objectionable<lb/> stuff it is, too. She guessed<lb/> right, partly, when she stated dry<lb/> bread, for they manage to give<lb/> us margarine with it for our<lb/> supper. The meat for dinner<lb/> has been easily discerned to<lb/> be horseflesh which may be  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0701_img_2192_3"/>
              nice at times. One potato, two<lb/> tablespoonfuls of beans and some<lb/> soup make up the dinner proper. <lb/> The other course is dry bread again.<lb/> Still mind you it is better than<lb/> what we got in Cork, but of that<lb/> it will be sufficient to tell<lb/> you later on. For 12 days we<lb/> suffered what Dillon described<lb/> in Parliament recently. He<lb/> erred slightly in his numbers<lb/> '22' or '23'. To be strictly exact <lb/> we were 231/4 hours out of every<lb/> 24 in solitary confinement without<lb/> distraction of any kind.<lb/> However, the conditions are better<lb/> now as you can see by letter to<lb/> Mother.  To return to a nicer sphere; you mention<lb/> a Miss Carroll enquiring about me. Why<lb/> not ask her to write to me. I sure she <lb/> wouldn't refuse. Show her this. With remembrances<lb/> to all other kind friends, I conclude,<lb/> <seg type="closer"> Dear mom &amp; Lily, with love <lb/> from your loving nephew,  Jim </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S.Rem<hi rend="superscript">ees</hi> to Mother's   </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0701_img_2192_4"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> P.S. Convey thanks to Mr. Campbell and Mr. Grogan for what they've done </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>