<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4302">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 2 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4302</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-05-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4302_img_3664_1"  type="Letter"  url="35285ca2ed039abdedd24f673c8bf8bd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4302_img_3664_2"  type="Letter"  url="da55d189b80ad9920319eae710090ae1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4302_img_3664_3"  type="Letter"  url="390582a73fc37f765464a02951ec3015.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4302_img_3664_4"  type="Letter"  url="136cd4098e80f41ed48d475263e062fe.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4302_img_3664_1"/>
             II  D1507/A/16/3<lb/><lb/>11  PAGE 1 OF 4  1916   Dublin Rebellion<lb/>? from whom    2nd May, 1916.   Thank you very much for letter. Last week has been<lb/>rather a trying one for everybody up here. The moment we<lb/>heard of the disturbances in Dublin steps were taken by the<lb/>U. V. F. authorities to put guards on the armouries to prevent<lb/>any possibility of the Sinn Feiners making a raid and thereby<lb/>creating disturbance. General Sir George Richardson at once<lb/>put himself into communication with Hacket-Pain and placed the<lb/>services of the U. V. F. at the disposal of the authorities for<lb/>any purpose. The U. V. F. Motor Corps got Motor Cars together<lb/>and placed these at the disposal of General Hacket-Pain to<lb/>enable him to provide a flying motor column. Steps were taken<lb/>to get the U. V. F. Commanders together with a view of imprerssing<lb/>upon the the necessity or tightening up the U. V. F. so as to<lb/>maintain discipline among the rank and file, and prevent any<lb/>possibility of any outbreak by way of retaliation. This applied<lb/>particularly to the shipyards where there is a large number of<lb/>Roman Catholics employed. As a result of these precautions<lb/>which were taken, General Hacket-Pain was enabled to furnish<lb/>troops to Dublin, and practically dilute the City of Police. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4302_img_3664_2"/>
             D1507/A/16/13<lb/><lb/>PAGE 2 OF 4<lb/><lb/>12  -2-<lb/><lb/>Belfast, for the past week has, therefore, been in a unique<lb/>position. The commissioner of Police did not even consider<lb/>it necessary to close the pubs, and everything went on the<lb/>same as usual.  The War Office have authorised General Hacket-Pain to<lb/>enrol 5,000 of the loyal Volunteers (whatever that title may<lb/>mean). This is being done by the U. V. F. in the ordinary way,<lb/>and by the Shipyards (most of these men will be U. V. F. men). I<lb/>understand, in addition, the Nationalists are enrolling men for<lb/>use in their own particular district.  This, however, is only leading up to the question<lb/>which is at present before my mind, and that is, what action<lb/>the Government are going to take with regard to arms. I hear<lb/>to-day that the Government propose issuing a proclamation order-<lb/>ing all arms to be given up. If this is carried out in our<lb/>Districts, among the U. V. F., the Government will set back the<lb/>hands of the clock, and Belfast will revert to its old condition<lb/>of disorder. Strikes will result, and as regards the Belfast<lb/>Shipyards, the result will be that workmen may cease there for<lb/>months, and troops will have to be brought in to police the<lb/>city and country Districts. A more stupid or provocative<lb/>action could not possibly be imagined, if what I hear is true,<lb/>as order at the present time is maintained in Belfast by the<lb/>control which the men's selected leaders have over them. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4302_img_3664_3"/>
             D1507/A/16/3<lb/><lb/>PAGE 3 OF 4<lb/><lb/>13<lb/><lb/>-3-<lb/><lb/>but if the arms are removed, all such control is gone. At<lb/>the present time, the arms, or most of them in Belfast, are<lb/>in Armouries which are maintained by the U. V. F., and protected<lb/>by them. In fact, the arms are there to satisfy the men. They<lb/>don't want to use them, and Hacket-Pain is, as I have said<lb/>before, bringing a number of the U. V. F. men in as Special<lb/>Constables. Therefore, these men are subject to discipline,<lb/>and to that extent the Armouries are under the control of the<lb/>Government. Why can they not let them remain so? Let the<lb/>Nationalists by all means have proper Armouries appointed and<lb/>maintained by them themselves, open to Government inspection;<lb/>all other Armouries but these to be confiscated. This would<lb/>get over the whole difficulty and, as I said before, let the<lb/>U. V. F. and the Nationalist Volunteers respectively be recognised<lb/>as Volunteers, subject directly to the War Office, and not to<lb/>Dublin or any political faction. Let there be no sentimental<lb/>nonsense about mixing Nationalists with Unionists, which has<lb/>always been a failure.  I write to you to put the facts before you so that<lb/>you may use your efforts to avert what I may describe as nothing<lb/>short of calamity. If any other General than Hacket-Pain<lb/>had been in Belfast during the past week, the condition of<lb/>affairs here would have been very different. Let General<lb/>Hacket-Pain remain here in control.  I hope you will forgive me writing and bothering you 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4302_img_3664_4"/>
             D1507/A/16/3  PAGE 4 OF 4  14<lb/><lb/>-4-<lb/><lb/>about this matter, but it is very urgent, and I thought you<lb/>should know about the circumstances as they appear to me. I<lb/>will write you again about other matters; meanwhile, it is as<lb/>well that you should have this letter. Lloyd Campbell is<lb/>beleagured in Malahide, where he has been since before Easter.  In haste,<lb/>Yours ever, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>