<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4226">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 17 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/65</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4226</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-17</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4226_img_3596_1"  type="Letter"  url="ac0651423db712e7edb2691862472057.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4226_img_3596_2"  type="Letter"  url="2433ea660870c812e38af09bddb3f847.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4226_img_3596_1"/>
             Nov. 17' to 18' <lb/>Nov. 17'   Rather a growly wolf without his daily meal especially when <lb/> he knows Neptune is not the cause. Perhaps there may be 2 tonight <lb/> or a big one. However I know old thing you are having a pretty busy <lb/> anxious time of it &amp; that it is not <hi rend="superscript">always</hi> easy to write at 24.   I hope you are getting along all right. If you can, <lb/> manage to be home from 5.30 onwards. This is the time when Mater <lb/> most misses her visitors. In fact I think she likes being alone in <lb/> the mornings.    Perhaps tomorrow I shall hear better what you have decided, <lb/> to become a Dr ! to open a shop! or to culture microbes. One thing <lb/>I am glad about is that Mrs Borton if you recommend her is <hi rend="superscript">likely</hi> to be <lb/> a really efficient hellper to that commitee.   In the next few days the Nation <hi rend="superscript">also</hi> has to make its decision, <lb/> on National Service. Reading Asquith's statement one would read it to mean <lb/> a) that we shall call on all the men we want. <lb/> b) that no man married before 15 August will be called out till all <lb/> bachelors have been.   Consequently unless there are sufficient bachelors volunteering they <lb/> will be called out. This is so clearly how it reads, that I am quite <lb/> sure some other interpretation will be put on it when the time comes. <lb/> &amp; I would not mind betting that many married men wil be taken <lb/> rather than call out the bachelors, tho' the married men have put <lb/> down their names on that understanding. Remind me at Xmas time <lb/> if I <seg type="del">p</seg> seem wrong in my prophecy. There is always some misconception <lb/> of everything a Radical Minister says, &amp; they leave everyone in the <lb/> misunderstanding till the last possible minute, e g Carson whose letter <lb/> of resignation clearly showed that he misunderstood what Asquith <hi rend="underline">now says</hi>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4226_img_3596_2"/>
            was the situation.    It was the same with <lb/> Seely of whom I have thought of this motto <seg type="foreign">"Cum grano Seely's</seg> <lb/>Do you twig , the last <seg type="del">word</seg> syllable pronounced "is."    <hi rend="superscript">18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> I am very savage this morning over a very little thing. The news <lb/> has cut down it's papers to 1 Times &amp; 1 Morning Post in order to purchase rags <lb/> like the Bystander Tatler etc. The Gen' slept from 9 till MN with the Times <lb/> on his lap, &amp; <seg type="unclear">Singleton</seg> took the M P to bed with him &amp; neither were <lb/> available at Breakfast so that I don't see them till breakfast on <lb/> the following day. I said at mess a propos of some rather extra extravagance <lb/> that in another year we shall probably have to lead the simple life &amp; the <lb/> general view was that is was not up to us to be economical until <lb/> the Govt gave the lead ! ! We have a lot to learn yet.    By the way Castlefield has come out with an increased dividend &amp; I <lb/> think we shall be able to increase our subscription by another £100 <lb/> to the War loan, but I am again rather of opinion that it may be better <lb/>to hold back until the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> <seg type="unclear">have</seg> to put their house in order. Shilly Shally <lb/> Squiffy is again at it. // Such a nice budget of letters has come <lb/> including 2 long ones from a p v , &amp; very welcome ones too. I agree <lb/> old thing that I am glad the war did not come earlier in our <lb/> married lives. The absolute certainty in each other, &amp; in the other's love <lb/> would not have been the same then. As it is there is a feeling of <lb/> entire confidence which is exceedingly restful.   One thing is that I now know you have learnt most of my <lb/> faults &amp; yet are prepared to go on giving all your love to a b w in <lb/> spite of them. I can hardly wait for the next mails they <lb/> are so exciting but there ought not to be the same block again at any <lb/> rate for a while I hope.    Best love from your b w    WB Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>