<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1736">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 8 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). In this letter Marie thanks her mother for the news of the death of a family friend, Gerald. She mentions the attitudes of the injured men she takes care of and briefly talks about her brother, Charlie&#39;s (1895-1915) death. She thanks her mother for the parcels she sent and asks her to send on her regards to friends and family.

Marie was the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary. At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle until be called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/1/47/1916/07/08a</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1736</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1736_img_1193_1"  type="Letter"  url="8480a6289b691508341e6b5b2a8b0027.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1736_img_1193_2"  type="Letter"  url="c429695f1de233a68ea9af57c2a6bbe0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1736_img_1193_3"  type="Letter"  url="5cafc5e3a4ef9ca4cf197f4ae9361b44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1736_img_1193_4"  type="Letter"  url="26138498bc7bec5ce2619b2fe02f06f4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1736_img_1193_1"/>
             25<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> General Hospital <lb/><hi rend="underline">B.E.F</hi>   8<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi><hi rend="underline">July 1916</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   The news about Gerald <lb/>came as a great shock to me, it <lb/>was so sweet of you to write &amp; <lb/>tell me as I would have got a <lb/>terrible shock had I seen it in the <lb/>paper 1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> the wonder is I have <lb/>not as I get a daily Mail <lb/>every evening &amp; I am sure his name <lb/>has not been in the casualty list. <lb/>I do hope by the time this reaches <lb/>you, you will have heard something <lb/>more definite, as I am very anxious, <lb/>poor Gerald what a rotten time he <lb/>has had. I only wrote to him on <lb/>the 4<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> &amp; asked him why he had <lb/>not written since he went back. <lb/>I received your letter at 7 A.M. this
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1736_img_1193_2"/>
            <lb/>morning, just before going on duty. I <lb/>was never so glad in all my <lb/>life we were so terribly busy as it kept <lb/>my mind occupied, we are really very <lb/>very busy, convoy after convoy &amp; <lb/>some of them have such nasty <lb/>wounds, some with Gas Gangrene which <lb/>means immediate operation to get <lb/>free drainage otherwise it means <lb/>high amputation. All the time I <lb/>am writing this I hear nothing but <lb/>ambulance driving up at night it <lb/>is exactly the same — Really if I <lb/>only heard Gerald was alright &amp; <lb/>only slightly wounded it ought to <lb/>be a great relief to know that <lb/>he is out of it for a bit, no <lb/>matter how bad the men are they <lb/>all say how glad they are to be <lb/>away &amp; how lucky they are, they <lb/>are also very cheerful &amp; say it <lb/>will be over in <sic>october</sic>, I do hope <lb/>this is true — I hope you have <lb/>had good news of Tommy lately, <lb/>many thanks for sending on his letter
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1736_img_1193_3"/>
            <lb/>I really do not know what to think <lb/>about poor Charlie, if Fr Murphy <lb/>says we may believe that <sic>mans</sic> <lb/>story which in a way ought to <lb/>be a relief to know he died without <lb/>much suffering. I feel sure he went <lb/>straight to Heaven after all he went <lb/>through. I pray every night for you <lb/>&amp; all and hope we will all be consoled <lb/>soon by this cruel war ending.   Very many thanks for all the parcels <lb/>none have arrived yet if you do <lb/>not hear for a couple of days <lb/>don’t worry it is only because we <lb/>are so busy but up to this we <lb/>have been able to take our couple <lb/>of hours off every day except once — <lb/>but sometimes I feel too fed up <lb/>&amp; tired &amp; think it better to go out <lb/>for a walk than write—   I hope there is good news from <lb/>Gerald M. I often think of him <lb/>and wonder how he is, he is such <lb/>a nice boy—
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1736_img_1193_4"/>
            <lb/>Will you give my fondest love to <lb/>all at 20 Clyde R<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi> &amp; tell A. Sissy <lb/>I will answer her letter very soon — <lb/>I hope you are all keeping very well <lb/>at home, please thank Desmond for <lb/>his sweet letter tell Andrew I am <lb/>anxiously awaiting one from him — I <lb/>often wish they were both out here <lb/>what fun we would have on the sand. <lb/>Now I must end as I must <lb/>fly off to duty.   With heaps of love &amp; kisses <lb/>Anxiously awaiting your next <lb/>letter, should he be in Hospital <lb/>in Boulogne I shall try &amp; <lb/>manage to see him —   Your ever loving daughter,   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>   I have forgotten heaps I wanted <lb/>to tell you however it will do <hi rend="underline">again.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>