<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1166">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 3 April 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw to Father Provincial regarding the masses Francis M. Shaw had. Francis, or Frank, Shaw (1881-1924) SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/25, IJA/CHPI/54/25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1166</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-04-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1166_img_3843_1"  type="Letter"  url="8c34e89f52cb705446848a5ddaa57ca2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1166_img_3843_1"/>
                3 April. 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   There is nothing fresh to report; but the <lb/>weekly mails are much an improvement on the uncertain mails <lb/><sic>ofthe</sic> sea-faring life, that I like to take advantage of them.  I hope you got my last week's letter, with enclosure for F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley. <lb/>I was able to say 18 Masses for him in March. I shall probably <lb/>have the full number for April. This morning I rose with the <lb/>lark (we have larks in Mesopotamia â the real kind, not <lb/>Joe Gargery's 'Wot larks !') and <sic>trekked</sic> a couple of miles to a <lb/>siege battery just arrived in our district, and had Mass and <lb/>Holy Communion for the ten Catholics in the unit. The gunners <lb/>here as in France seem <sic>tobe</sic> neglected in the Chaplain line. <lb/>I shall do a like trek for another battery tomorrow or the <lb/>day after : it has about twenty Catholics.  F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frank Browne and F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Fitzgibbon will I am sure be <lb/>in the thick <sic>ofthe</sic> present German push. We are lucky <lb/>people in one sense who are in the wilderness. Some of <lb/>the people out here left Italy just before the banks <lb/>gave way there, and have practically no experience <lb/><sic>ofwar</sic>.  I am comforted every day by the appearance of <lb/>fresh familiar wild-flowers â dandelions, thistles, buttercups, <lb/><seg type="unclear">etc etc</seg>. Sometimes I can almost imagine <sic>Iam</sic> at <lb/>home. <seg type="closer"> I commend myself to your Reverence's prayers : <lb/>Yours very sincerely in Christ;  Francis M Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>