<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5016">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from H. McGrath to Charlie Daly, 4 February 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>H McGrath</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>H. McGrath to Charlie Daly, 4 February 1923. Sends her regards. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/2/12/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5016</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0220">H McGrath</persName>
              <date>1923-02-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5016_img_None_1"  url="6486f8e70d42fa4fbdad517b9d819aba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5016_img_None_2"  url="ef20edc753909098749861314989a6d5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5016_img_0_1"/>
             P41/2/12/1   P.S. I suppose the Censor is saying     to himself, as he has every     night to say, yes, written from a     padded cell!    The Dirty Port   Sunday   4.2.23    <seg type="foreign">A Cara</seg>   A few lines in answer to<lb/>your latest masterpiece. I think you should<lb/>have been made Govenor of the six<lb/>countys, you see, I wish you well such<lb/>an exciting time you would have. Anyhow<lb/>it would help to <seg type="unclear">???</seg><lb/>b<seg type="del">iting</seg> sarcasm of yourself and the famous<lb/>Miss Blake. I hope she told you that<lb/>I am a jam pot collector. You see I<lb/>must do something for a living and work<lb/>is scarce. If I could get back to my<lb/>home in Craig's Kingdom, but sure their is<lb/>no good in dreaming of things which may<lb/>never mature. Jimmy knows as well as<lb/>Miss Blake does that I am a cracked<lb/>mug without a handle, sporting the Belleek<lb/>Pottery trade mark. As I have ceased<lb/>corresponding with that lady. I would<lb/>like if you could see your. way to<lb/>become a medium for this time, and 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5016_img_0_2"/>
               8/2/23      <hi rend="underline"> Thursday </hi>  <hi rend="underline"> Forgot </hi> to     post this     on Monday.     Can you       f  or  give     hurried     <hi rend="underline">scrawl</hi>     <hi rend="underline">h</hi>   warn her to lie low, the reason for this<lb/>warning is the fellow who discovered the<lb/>tomb of Tutenkhamen, is supposed to be on<lb/>his way to <seg type="unclear">Gortahook</seg>, as he has good<lb/>reason for believing, that the animated<lb/>corpse of Tutenkhamen wife is living in<lb/>a cave near Cashels girl school. You might<lb/>also tell her, that the <seg type="unclear">anima</seg>she<lb/>lost in Bundoran last summer, was found<lb/>a few days ago, and that she can<lb/>have it, on applying to Mr <seg type="unclear">Pend</seg>down her way in the Summer, and<lb/>if you hear a rumbling sound, from<lb/>that direction, you are to understand, that<lb/>it is she arriving in no mans land.  Are you allowed newspapers. if so, I<lb/>could send you on our local rags.  I wrote to some Ballyshannon Boys,<lb/>who are in Newbridge, of Course they<lb/>never write to me but I don't blame them.  Tell Mr Larkin that I am going to<lb/>write him some day in the near future:<lb/>I am saying this with the name<lb/>that my best friends know me by.   Yes etc The Savage  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>