<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0103">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 18 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Helena Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin from a field hospital during the First World War. In the letter Marie writes to her mother that she is still safe and well. Marie also enquires about her Uncle Frank&#39;s illness and asks her mother to take care of herself.Marie served as a nurse in various field hospitals during the war. She worked for the British army in Malta, Leeds, and France. Later she would become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/1/69, B/F/1/69</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/103</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0618">Marie Helena Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-10-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1223">Monkstown, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0103_img_1185_1"  type="Letter"  url="e5d59258bce492a006fcfd109fafd877.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0103_img_1185_2"  type="Envelope"  url="999b757ca0ec4a4e22ea432da1eccfd0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0103_img_1185_1"/>
             B/F/1/69    18 Oct 1916   My very dearest Mother,   First a few lines to thank<lb/>you for your P.C. I am very sorry to hear<lb/>there is no decided change in Uncle<lb/>Franks condition we must only hope for<lb/>the best. I have just received <seg type="unclear">Phills</seg> letter with<lb/>a thousand thanks. <seg type="del">I</seg>but have not had<lb/>time to read it properly yet— as I<lb/>just got it this morning when I was<lb/>going on duty.  This is only a note as promised<lb/>to say I am very well I shall<lb/>write long letter this afternoon. I<lb/>hope you are taking care of yourself.<lb/>I feel so much for you as I know<lb/>all the worry Uncle Franks illness will give<lb/>to you. I hope you will get Tommy's<lb/>letter soon . It will cheer you up.<lb/>Must close now in great haste— <seg type="closer"> Your very loving daughter—  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0103_img_1185_2"/>
                Mrs Martin,  Greenbank  Monkstown  Co <hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi>  Ireland   Passed Field Censor 1563   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>