<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6672">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from WB Yeats to Russell, 14 March 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.B. Yeats</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 7. Folder: Letters 43 TL/copies to Russell, George William (7.8)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6672</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date>1921-03-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0747">4, Broad Street, Oxford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0970">George Russell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6672_img_None_1"  url="phpUAqO8J.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6672_img_0_1"/>
              4, Broad Street<lb/>Oxford    March 14, (1921)    My dear Russell   Yes I think you must be right. It is certainly a<lb/>distressing suggestion. I think by the way that the line is  Dust has closed Helen's eye  not eyes. At least I have always quoted it as eye. I cannot<lb/>look it up for I have no edition of Nash who I think wrote it.  I hope you will do that essay on Unity &amp; Culture. I<lb/>will send you the final chapter of My four years on the subject.<lb/>Your essay need not be finished for months &amp; need not be long.  My<lb/>sister will know when it should be done &amp; how long it should be.  I<lb/>will let you know.  If we can present this one idea from many sides<lb/>we might effect the future of Ireland!  In my essay I would go more<lb/>into details than I can in the last chapter.  You could start off by<lb/>referring to your essay in the Express &amp; so affirm the independence<lb/>of your thought.  In my Four Years it comes after chapters on Madam<lb/>Blavatsky,Morris,Macgregor,Henley &amp; so on &amp; will come as a logical<lb/>deduction.  The idea is much more obviously a deduction from all past<lb/>work of intellectual Ireland.  The idea has been forced again into<lb/>my mind after a long interval of apparent individualism by my present<lb/>philosophy.   I find something of the kind is stirring among the young<lb/>men here, --an indian called Mallik is having great influence --&amp; here<lb/>philosophy is now the one great intellectual influence,politics being<lb/>dead.  I do not yet understand the Oxford thought on the subject<lb/>except that it is more metaphysical than ours.  Mallik I have met but<lb/>I have not met him enough.  I hear also of an American who has left<lb/>I know some similar thought.  Macdougal was I think the first source.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>