<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1790">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Mangan regarding Sir John O'Connell, 3 April 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Mangan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by John Mangan as an endorsement of John Robert O&#39;Connell for the vacant chief crown Solicitor position. Mangan (1853-1917) was the Bishop of Kerry in 1916. Mangan writes that his chief experience of O&#39;Connell (1868-1943) was as a public man and that as such he contributed largely to the public good. Mangan believes that the south of Ireland is indebted to O&#39;Connell for his services. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1790</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1357">John Mangan</persName>
              <date>1916-04-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1790_img_1245_1"  type="Letter"  url="fce0ef7a4fb78f92befbfa46f953a425.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1790_img_1245_2"  type="Letter"  url="0f971c4d47b9946e3dc0a53523b37dd0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1790_img_1245_1"/>
            <lb/>people.   +John Mangan  <lb/>Bishop of Kerry.  <hi rend="underline">April 3<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rd</hi></hi> 1916</hi>   THE PALACE, <lb/>KILLARNEY.   I have experience <lb/>of Sir John R. oConnell <lb/>for some years <lb/>past both professionally <lb/>and in other respects.   In every way as <lb/> far as my knowledge <lb/> goes he has been
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1790_img_1245_2"/>
            very successful.   My chief experience <lb/>of him has been <lb/>as a public man <lb/>and as such he <lb/>contributed very <lb/>largely to the public <lb/>good. In the South <lb/>of Ireland we are <lb/>very largely indebted <lb/>to him for his excellent <lb/>services to the University <lb/>College at Cork.   I may say that he <lb/>has in very large <lb/>measure the respect and <lb/>confidence of the <lb/>best class of our
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>