<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2802">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 21 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p> A letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary.  James details how busy he is with paperwork despite the conditions in the trenches. Due to a change in the weather he asks that she send him light weight  clothing.

This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/49</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2802</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-05-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2802_img_2219_1"  type="Letter"  url="7432ce11c12ba9801985903b639b93f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2802_img_2219_2"  type="Letter"  url="e859c98d23b8076d02b50cec587ddc85.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2802_img_2219_3"  type="Letter"  url="8fb702cf67e8030b0ec852e290f1df18.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2802_img_2219_4"  type="Letter"  url="d7b6b72fc277ff443f2ace53ace46743.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2802_img_2219_5"  type="Envelope"  url="08491d481ec10c611711a7bf4fb74929.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2802_img_2219_1"/>
             21/5/16   My Dearest Mother    — I <lb/>have two letters of yours <lb/>&amp; two from K. to acknowledge <lb/>but am afraid I have <lb/>not time to send much <lb/>of a reply. The work <lb/>seems to increase every <lb/>day. Today Sunday <lb/>I have been since early <lb/>morning in Orderly Room <lb/>trying to get things up <lb/>to date but letters have <lb/>come pouring in all <lb/>day calling for further <lb/>reports &amp; returns <lb/>with the result that I <lb/>am very little further <lb/>forward. These never <lb/>ending returns &amp; <seg type="unclear">c</seg> <lb/>are heartbreaking
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2802_img_2219_2"/>
            when there is so much <lb/>important work waiting <lb/>to be done in the Trenches. <lb/>One would imagine that <lb/>at the front, this office <lb/>work would to a <lb/>large extent cut out <lb/>but it seems quite the <lb/>contrary.   The weather is now very <lb/>warm &amp; I was so glad <lb/>to change into my light <lb/>underwear. Would <lb/>you please send me <lb/>out 6 of my light khaki <lb/>shirts. I will post <lb/>my warm clothing <lb/>home some day this <lb/>week. The warm <lb/>lining for my waterproof <lb/>arrived safely, thanks
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2802_img_2219_3"/>
            ever so much dear Mother. <lb/>I suppose you received <lb/>my British Warm <!-- a woolen overcoat -->all <lb/>right from the officer <lb/>who took it for me <lb/>when going on leave. <lb/>Charlie Murland arrived <lb/>out here on Friday &amp; <lb/>has joined the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> again. <lb/>He stayed with us till <lb/>today &amp; as you can <lb/>guess we were all <lb/>very delighted to have <lb/>him. Have not <lb/>seen Gerard lately <lb/>but hear he is all <lb/>right, though he has <lb/>been in a rather nasty <lb/>part of the Line recently. <lb/>Personally I am <lb/>keeping all right — this
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2802_img_2219_4"/>
            warm weather agrees <lb/>with me — but I do <lb/>long for a few days <lb/>complete rest.   So far there is no talk <lb/>of being relieved though <lb/>indeed if we were not <lb/>going back some distance <lb/>I should prefer to remain <lb/>where we are.   I feel this is a very <lb/>uninteresting letter <lb/>Mother dear but there <lb/>is really no news — <lb/>that is to say — news <lb/>that I can tell you. <lb/>Will you thank K. for her <lb/>letters &amp; with fondest <lb/>love to all.   Your loving son   Jim 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2802_img_2219_5"/>
              On Active Service <seg type="unclear">Inserted</seg> 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>   26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May/16   Mrs S C Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor  J Davidson<lb/>   21/6/16<lb/> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>