<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0622">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Terence Duffin to his father Adam, 29 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terrence Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter was sent by Major Terence Duffin (1886 - 1936), to his father Adam Duffin (1841 – 1924). In the letter Terence writes that the weather has been making life in the trenches much easier, although he separates himself from the men as he acknowledges that he is living in ‘comparative luxury’. Duffin reports that they have just had a visit from Bishop Crozier (1853 – 1920), the primate, and Sir James Stronge (1849 – 1928). According to Duffin, their guests were fed with ‘caviar and game and oysters’ for dinner leaving them pleased with warfare feeding. However, it is not all comfortable living as Duffin writes about his fears about the frequent number of gas attacks reported in the last few days in their vicinity. However, Duffin goes on to state that the reports have so far come to nothing and instead tells his father of his riding exercises and a pony which has gone lame.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/A</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/622</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0936">Terrence Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0513">Adam Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1949">Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_1"  type="Letter"  url="c49fe58cbe49f4ad6544316c1c7fecea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_2"  type="Letter"  url="9ab3853556599690fb52529666e6c34c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_3"  type="Letter"  url="028e131ea237c2ef1b73602f39be32a5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_4"  type="Letter"  url="704e263b62d9ed711d34ca80d2c86b98.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_5"  type="Letter"  url="964366d813faab94feae7a7c8848d94c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_6"  type="Letter"  url="f2fb01256ea131c6fa083ef78e23542f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_7"  type="Letter"  url="6674c78ff0da2568e0d04f2fb7fa395d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0622_img_2044_8"  type="Letter"  url="08777c891b63da4f3161bddcfb382308.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_1"/>
                Dear Father,    We have had quite a <lb/> longish spell of dry weather and <lb/> consequently have been getting through <lb/> much more work in the trenches <lb/> and generally more comfortable <lb/> all round â When I say <lb/> 'we' I don't include myself as <lb/> I am still living in comparative <lb/> luxury. We are on the <lb/> move again â our original <lb/> Division is going to take our <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_2"/>
              place and we still remain on <lb/> with our present Divisn but <lb/> go back for a rest, somewhere.   We don't yet know for how <lb/> long or exactly where but anyhow <lb/> out if the danger zone â   Naturally we are all glad <lb/> that we are staying on with <lb/> the present Division but rather <lb/> surprised, as we were told only <lb/> 3 days ago that we were to <lb/> go back to the original one <lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_3"/>
              which would have been a <lb/> very unpopular move for all <lb/> ranks.   We have just had a visit <lb/> from Bishop Crozier (The Primate) <lb/> and Sir James Stronge â The <lb/> Primate was in great form <lb/> and really quite amusing <lb/> Sir Jas. Stronge, a stupid old <lb/> goat.They were fearfully <lb/> pleased at being allowed <lb/> to go round here â We did <lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_4"/>
              them proud â We had <lb/> caviar and game and <lb/> oysters for dinner, <seg type="del">which</seg> &amp; <lb/> sent him away quite pleased <lb/> with warfare feeding â   Day, who is a distant relation <lb/> of the Primates, took them up <lb/> some of the communicating <lb/> trenches and they were able <lb/> to visit a battalion Hd. Qrs.   Even then they got 2 shells <lb/> uncomfortably near! The <lb/>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_5"/>
              Primate should have found <lb/> subjects for sermons for months <lb/> to come!   I am sending you some <lb/> post cards of a shell battered <lb/> village quite close where and <lb/> which has become quite famous <lb/> on account of the Church, which <lb/> has been fairly well smashed <lb/> up but the spire is still standing <lb/> with an enormous figure <lb/> of the Virgin hanging down at <lb/>  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_6"/>
              an extraordinary angle and <lb/> apparently without support.   We took the Primate to see <lb/> it on his last day.   We have been much perturbed <lb/> during the last few days by <lb/> frequent reports of gas attacks <lb/> in the vicinity and warnings to be <lb/> prepared but so far they have <lb/> all come to nothing.   Very little else to tell you <lb/> at present - I keep in <lb/>  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_7"/>
              first rate form and have <lb/> snared one or two afternoons <lb/> for riding exercise lately as <lb/> work has not been quite so <lb/> heavy â One of my ponies <lb/> was lame but has now <lb/> recovered and mighty <lb/> fresh today when I had <lb/> been out for the first time â    I am some what stiff as <lb/> a result.   The <seg type="unclear">supernumerary</seg> Staff <lb/>  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0622_img_2044_8"/>
              Captain is lost to us again â <lb/> The officer from the 15 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> who took over when I was <lb/> on leave was re-called as <lb/> the Adjutant had been <lb/> wounded and so far <lb/> we have got no one in <lb/> his place.  <seg type="closer"> Best love to all <lb/>from your own    Terry </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>