<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0649">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to Ruth Duffin, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Olive Duffin to her sister Ruth. In this letter Olive discusses how her sisters Emma (1883-1979) and Dorothy are getting on, specifically travel arrangements and Dorothy’s new job with the admiralty. Olive also mentions a possible job for Marjorie as a female chauffeur. Olive offers to enclose the prospectus for the driving school with her letter.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who was a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/36</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/649</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0865">7 West Cliff, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1375">Ruth Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0649_img_2124_1"  type="Letter"  url="66b04d6b1f8a07e62697694bc0490d9d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0649_img_2124_2"  type="Letter"  url="70caf78a9f4175e176e4153f87a6d8cc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0649_img_2124_1"/>
                7 West Cliff.    31st March, 1916.   My dear Ruth,   I suppose Emma has got home by now but she must have had <lb/> an awful journey as the railways are still all blocked as the result of <lb/> the storm. We did not get the worst of it here, but it was bad enough <lb/> and I am thankful this morning it is much warmer and looks as if <sic>thar</sic><lb/> weather was really over and there might be a chance of Spring at last.  I heard from Dorothy this morning, poor thing she is I am sure in an <lb/> awful fright but I am so pleased to hear she happened by a bit of luck <lb/> to hear of the lady wanting a tenant for a room in her flat for it sounds <lb/> much nicer than a boarding house or hostel and is very cheap, and if <lb/> the other people turned out decent it would be some company.  Of course the hours and the pay are very bad and would really not be <lb/> worth keeping unless there was some chance of promotion, but it will be <lb/> a kind of trial trip and <sic>experienceand</sic> may lead to something else.  I've been making all enquiries I can for some time now , asking everyone <lb/> about work and pay and conditions and it is very discouraging, all the <lb/> hours are terribly long and pay not capable of being lived upon under <lb/> present conditions, rooms very hard to find.  <sic>Hve</sic> you any idea of what Marjorie thinks of doing? Or what she <lb/> would like to do. Do you think she would care to come to London and <lb/> take this course of training in motor mechanism and driving<seg type="unclear">?</seg> I enclose <lb/> the prospectus. I know she is interested in it and it might just be <lb/> an occupation for her for a time. I am awfully taken with it and would <lb/> love to do it , the fees are very low and the whole thing sounds most  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0649_img_2124_2"/>
              <lb/>businesslike. It <sic>semms</sic> that women chauffeuses are really wanted now <lb/>and it would be very useful to know. I think it is quite possible that <lb/>I could arrange with Miss Roberts to leave for a time even if not for <lb/>altogether, she can always get odd friends to come especially in the <seg type="del">summ</seg><lb/>summer and she likes nothing so much as a variety. May Darbyshire is <lb/>coming to her on the 15th for a fortnight so I shall be on the loose then.  I have <sic>alittle</sic> money in hand and then there will be the Â£50 and it <lb/>might not be a bad investment. Anyhow will you study the enclosed and <lb/>also sound Marjorie as to what she thinks , it might just be the distraction <lb/>she needs, but I have heard so little I <sic>dont</sic> know what her ideas may <lb/>be. Tell her I have also discovered a First Aid Yeomanry Nursing Corps <lb/>which sends members abroad in different capacities, paying a small sum for <lb/>themselves.  I am just off now to pick tow at the Depot, a very wearisome <lb/>job! Do you know what is a good speed at <sic>typeing</sic> I can do 1800 <lb/>an hour now but not with great accuracy? <seg type="closer"> Much love to all <lb/>Yours ever  Olive. </seg> P.S. Tell Emma I forgot she owed me ten shillings but I think she paid <lb/>some things I forgot about too. I wish you were having a little <lb/> change for your holiday.  Return papers <hi rend="underline">please</hi>.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>