<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0435">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 15 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (1866-1955). This letter is the second that Marie wrote to her mother during her second tour on 15 July 1916. This is a long letter in response to one she received from her mother. She discusses family news and hopes that her mother gets over her flu soon. She also mentions that she expects the tents to be full tomorrow with soldiers as she can hear convoy after convoy arriving.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>France Letters, B/F/1/51</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/435</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1543">Hardelot, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1257">Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0435_img_1770_1"  type="Letter"  url="45a098c3ddd2f1572ace76167f0c2c74.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0435_img_1770_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5fda04b956d81925a84e692fde7a5ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0435_img_1770_3"  type="Letter"  url="293e43c7d580a2cb462001d20e4001ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0435_img_1770_4"  type="Letter"  url="34766e43a8e820114d67fbe2cae99f8f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0435_img_1770_5"  type="Letter"  url="45a098c3ddd2f1572ace76167f0c2c74.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0435_img_1770_6"  type="Letter"  url="6289d43b472b936682ce9b9b0864e624.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0435_img_1770_1"/>
                15.7.16 9.30PM   My very dearest Mother   I have just received your<lb/> very nice long letter &amp;fell I could<lb/> not sleep without writing &amp; letting<lb/> you know how very sorry I am<lb/> to hear you have a touch of the<lb/><sic>flue</sic> how on earth did you get it<lb/> I hope by the time this reaches you<lb/> you will be quite alright again.<lb/><seg type="unclear">Reserve</seg> to go away for a change <lb/> as soon as you feel able. I was<lb/> so afraid before I came away that<lb/> you would get run down. that is <lb/> why I was so anxious you would <lb/> promise to go before O left — Are you <lb/> taking the boys with you they <lb/> will be company if you do —<lb/> Whatever you do take the greatest <lb/> care of yourself &amp; let me know how <lb/> you are feeling. I suppose you saw  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0435_img_1770_2"/>
              the family I hope &amp; got a good tonic<lb/> What a terrible <seg type="unclear">surprise</seg> for Ethel &amp; V.<lb/> I should have got the fright of my<lb/> life I can quite imagine poor<lb/> Violets feelings as I know it would<lb/> have been the first thing I would<lb/> have thought. I am very glad<lb/> he did not take any silver. it <lb/> was too bad about the money<lb/> but I am so glad he did not <lb/> worry you up stairs, it was not very <lb/> good for you with your cold. <lb/> I have just received another letter <lb/> from M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi><seg type="unclear">Garlton</seg> telling me Gerald<lb/> was wounded by <sic>scrapnel</sic> in the <lb/> arm — but <sic>seem</sic>a <seg type="unclear">bught</seg> &amp; still<lb/> in duty, she is in a terrible state<lb/> about him I really do wish he<lb/> had been a little worse &amp; got <lb/> out of it for a bit. We must<lb/> only pray &amp; trust in the Sacred<lb/> Heart. I was so glad to hear  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0435_img_1770_3"/>
              &amp; read that delightful long <lb/> letter from Tommy. What a brick<lb/> he is I'm afraid he felt A. <seg type="unclear">Bernards</seg><lb/> death R.I.P. very much &amp; he seems <lb/> to worry so about Uncle Frank<lb/> who I hope is something <seg type="unclear">better</seg> &amp;<lb/> going away soon. I sent Tommy<lb/> a cake from London I hope he<lb/> will get it.  It is nearly 10.30 when light go<lb/> out as I have had a great many<lb/><sic>interruption</sic> so must say good-<lb/> night. It looks like as if the<lb/> Hospital will be full up to-morrow<lb/> as I hear convoy after convoy arriving<lb/> it is so <seg type="unclear">interest</seg> as they<lb/> come straight from Albert.<lb/> I only wish you could come<lb/> out &amp;see my &amp;<seg type="unclear">tents</seg>. I am <lb/> very busy getting dressing, medicine  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0435_img_1770_4"/>
              <seg type="unclear">co-boards</seg> make out of all <seg type="unclear">roses</seg><lb/> &amp; them making curtains of pretty<lb/> chintz. it has not been opened<lb/> yet but expect it may to-<lb/> morrow, if you do not hear for <lb/> a couple of days don't worry<lb/> it is only we have an extra<lb/> push — I am feeling A.1 my<lb/> feet are <seg type="unclear">splinched</seg> not —<lb/> Give all the relations my love<lb/> &amp; tell them to excuse me writing —<lb/> Get Violet to write me a card<lb/> every day just to saw how you <lb/> are. They ought to get P. O'Kelly<lb/> to sleep with them whilst you <lb/> are away as Granny says a<lb/> man is a great protection —  With my fondest love &amp; anxiously <lb/> awaiting to hear you are alright  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0435_img_1770_5"/>
               able to go for a change take a good long<lb/> visit. How is <lb/> the cook working<lb/> &amp; all the others<lb/> With a<lb/> tiny good<lb/> night kiss.<lb/> Your loving<lb/> &amp; grateful<lb/> daughter.<lb/> Marie  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0435_img_1770_6"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> P.S. By the way a <seg type="unclear">Trooper</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">Boase</seg> of the London <sic>Yoemanry</sic> wrote &amp; asked if he could come<lb/> out to see me, he was a very nice<lb/> patient &amp; I think a gentleman. <lb/> Tommy any how I am sending <lb/> on his letter to you if you <lb/> think it wise ask him out <lb/> to tea. I nursed him for nearly <lb/> two months in Malta I think.  Good-night  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>