<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4437">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Bell to William Johnson, 1 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Robert Bell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Bell to solicitor William Johnson regarding previous correspondence about the removal of the remains of Mrs Campbell from one grave to another in the Burren burial ground.

William Robert Bell (1873-1930) was a clerk for Newry District Urban Council for Co. Down.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI/CSO/RP/1916/10801/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4437</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1422">William Robert Bell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1485">Newry, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0757">William Johnson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1485">Newry, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1930</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4437_img_3788_1"  type="Letter"  url="ae17f29e3112f7b74d253bae933318b9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4437_img_3788_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="9ca95ff1bd29b8b0a7358d4b7af66d99.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4437_img_3788_1"/>
             NEWRY No. 1 RURAL DISTRICT COUNCIL. <lb/>COUNTY OF DOWN. <lb/>Rural District Council Offices, <lb/>Workhouse, Newry.   1st. June 1916.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">Re Mrs Mary Campbell, Warrenpoint, Dead</hi>  Dear Sir,  <lb/>With reference to my letter of the 16th ult. and further <lb/>correspondence, I now send you a copy of a resolution adopted by the <lb/> Sanitary Authority, consenting to the removal of the remains of Mrs <lb/>Campbell from one grace to another in the Burren burial ground.  Yours faithfully,   William Bell  <lb/>Clerk of Council. <lb/>"That the Newry No. 1. Rural District Council, being the Sanitary <lb/>Authority for the district in which the Burren grave-yard is situated, <lb/>hereby consent to the removal of the body of Mrs Campbell from the grave <lb/>in which it is interred to another grave in the same burial ground."  Wm. Johnson. Esq., <lb/>Solicitor, <lb/>Newry. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4437_img_3788_2"/>
             WE, the Undersigned, Most Reverend Edward Mulhern <lb/>Bishop of Dromore and The Reverend Felix Magennis Parish <lb/>Priest of Warrenpoint and Clonallon being the Authority in <lb/>whom the Burren Roman Catholic Burying-ground County Down <lb/>is vested do hereby consent to the removal of the remains <lb/>of the late Mrs. Mary Campbell who died at Warrenpoint on <lb/>the 16th February 1916 being removed from the grave in <lb/>which it is interred in the said Burren Roman Catholic <lb/>Burying-ground and to the said remains being re-interred <lb/>in her Husband's grave in said graveyard.   Edward Mulhern   Felix Magennis   To the Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle, Dublin and <lb/>Messrs. James Kelly and John <lb/>Crawford Executors of Mary Campbell <lb/>deceased and all others whom it may concern.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>