<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2655">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to James Ryan from May Gray</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Gray</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to James Ryan from May Gray. Gray is a nurse in St. Vincent&#39;s and a friend of Ryan&#39;s. She gives him news of how people in his class got on in their exams and what they are doing now. She tells him that a friend of hers, Michael Collins, is apparently in the same prison as him, and that he should introduce himself to him as he is &#34;a jolly decent sort!&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>University College Dublin Archives P88/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2655</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0814">May Gray</persName>
              <date>1916-06-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1438">St. Mary&#39;s House, St. Vincent&#39;s Hospital, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2655_img_208_1"  type="Letter"  url="6d043bc1aede748e5d04e05ea84fd58a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2655_img_208_2"  type="Letter"  url="6f1fd96718fa915441ea8fb8af24a6e9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2655_img_208_3"  type="Letter"  url="8d4dae14dfb760d13481b970d2a4b26f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2655_img_208_4"  type="Letter"  url="2e25fcb20ab40f46fedb92216009dfda.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2655_img_208_1"/>
             P88/24(1)   P.S. Collins address<lb/>is the same as<lb/>yours except his<lb/>has 748    St. Mary's House,<lb/>St. Vincent's Hospital<lb/>Dublin    24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916.    My dear Jim -   I made various attempts since<lb/>Easter to find out your whereabouts<lb/>but till late last week got no definite<lb/>information. I hope you are better<lb/>of the neuralgia you complained of<lb/>Easter Saturday when I met you in<lb/>O'Connell St.? Probably the excitement<lb/>since charmed it away. I met Delaney<lb/>(sick Thrush) today &amp; he gave me your<lb/>address. I did not care to ask any<lb/>of the other chaps. I expect you are<lb/>kept pretty well up in the latest news.<lb/>In any case things are fearfully<lb/>quiet at present - O'Mahony &amp; Walsh<lb/>got through last week - O'Mahony is<lb/>to   the Kalki one of these days but<lb/>I think Walsh is going down to<lb/>Ballina to take up his brother's practice<lb/>the latter died rather suddenly about<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2655_img_208_2"/>
              a month ago. Leo Blake is gone<lb/>out to Verdun or somewhere in France<lb/>I dare say you heard Caulon got the<lb/>medal in Surgery &amp; O'Mahony in<lb/>Medicine - Michael Smith was working<lb/>hard for it but I think he funked it<lb/>at the end as he feared Caulon would<lb/>do him out - At present Smith is General<lb/>Surgeon to the Leeson St Homes - He nearly<lb/>lives there attending &amp; dressing Johnnie<lb/>patient. Courtney is still in  and,<lb/>of course, as important as ever, if not<lb/>more so. Andy Ryan is house physician<lb/>&amp; as far as I can observe he is knocking<lb/>Courtney out altogether. Purcell, Lawlor,<lb/>Cassidy &amp; a few more chaps are in at<lb/>present - very quiet &amp; good.<lb/>I am writing this in bed as I am<lb/>on night duty in 94 Leeson St - I am<lb/>finished with the wards   Hospital now.<lb/>We had our final exam - I got 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> in<lb/>Medical Nursing &amp; 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> in Surgical —<lb/>  got 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> in Surgical -<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg> got 1st in Surgical -   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2655_img_208_3"/>
             Dr. Meenan is off duty since Easter<lb/>practically - McGuinness is giving his<lb/>classes - I was talking to him today<lb/>he says he is going away for a few<lb/>months. Poor devil he looks rotten - The<lb/>heart was terrified out of him Easter<lb/>week. His house was under fire from<lb/>the Shelbourne for two or three days in<lb/>fact his windows were well pierced.<lb/>Needless to remark it was <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>Browne that was meant to be hit -<lb/>but we will pass over the merits of the<lb/>men behind the guns as good shoots.  By the way there is a friend of mine<lb/>a prisoner of war named Michael<lb/>Collins. He gave me rather a surprise<lb/>when he wrote to me from Prison - I<lb/>cannot find his note now but as far<lb/>as I remember he must be with you.<lb/>Look him up if you do not already<lb/>know him he is a jolly decent sort. I<lb/>think I told you about him last year.<lb/>He knew your sisters in London.        
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2655_img_208_4"/>
             I hope you are tolerably comfortable<lb/>there - will you drop me a line<lb/>&amp; say how you are &amp; give me all<lb/>news of yourself - I wish you were<lb/>a bit nearer home so that we<lb/>could see you - If it is your rotten<lb/>luck to be in till Aug or Sept I will<lb/>probably see you.  Bye bye and I am glad<lb/>to know you are alive, as somehow<lb/>for weeks after no one seemed to<lb/>know what happened to you.   I will look forward to a line<lb/>from you soon - Goodbye very best<lb/>wishes from<lb/> Yours V. sincerely<lb/>May Gray  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>