<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4289">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Turner Oliver Read to Edward Carson, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Turner Oliver Read</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Turner Oliver Read (1853-1938) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Turner Oliver Read served as the High Sheriff of King&#39;s County in 1899. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4289</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1480">Turner Oliver Read</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0426">Dungar, Roscrea, Co. Tipperary, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4289_img_3652_1"  type="Letter"  url="fba7a628d99c332dc8e527df876ecb68.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4289_img_3652_2"  type="Letter"  url="777f0ab4424aebe869e79b921a70f335.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4289_img_3652_1"/>
             Dungar, Roscrea <lb/>Ireland   12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Nov 1915   Dear Sir Edward Carson   I enclose a letter, which appeared in <lb/>the "Dublin Evening Mail" last night, copied from the <lb/>"Munster News", which speaks for itself. It will show <lb/>what we are up against, in recruiting in this Country &amp; <seg type="unclear">seems</seg> <lb/><sic>increditible</sic> that any man in a responsible position could <lb/>write such a letter, in the present serious condition of our <lb/>country — It was given as an excuse, for Certain classes <lb/>not joining the Army some time ago, that they could not be <lb/>spared from the agricultural pursuits, and now they can be <lb/>spared in hundreds, to emigrate to America, where they <lb/>are told they are not wanted, and I am <sic>creditibly</sic> informed <lb/>that they are well supplied with money. — I fear German <lb/>gold is doing its <seg type="unclear">devil</seg> work in Ireland as it has <lb/>done in other parts of the world. I see it has been <lb/>suggested that, what is called the "National Volunteers" <lb/>should be armed &amp; drilled for "home" defence, which it <lb/>is feared could be a dangerous experiment, with the <lb/>extreme section of that party, they wish to be armed &amp; <lb/>drilled, not for the defence of the Empire, but for <seg type="unclear">interior</seg> purposes, <lb/>which  it  is not difficult to guess, by those living amongst <lb/>the people. I have only two Sons, they are both <lb/>fighting for their country, and it is hard to see ones neighbour <lb/>whole families perfectly indifferent to their responsibilities
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4289_img_3652_2"/>
            in this great crisis of the Empire — I hope you will pardon <lb/>me for writing to you, being unknown to you, but my excuse <lb/>is that I appreciate what you have done for our Country, <lb/>and that I am deeply interested that we should succeed <lb/>in this terrible war &amp; that everything that is possible should <lb/>be done to secure that end. Of course in this part of <lb/>the Country, those that are opposed to Nationalist ideas, <lb/>cannot publicly express their Views with Safety; as for <lb/>a long time, loyally to the Empire has been discouraged <lb/>by our late Government &amp; the Country is now reaping <lb/>the reward of their actions.   I have the <sic>honor</sic> to be <lb/>Your Obedient Servant   T. O. Read   Sir Edward Carson   P.S. Please consider this Communication <lb/>private. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>