<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4515">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 15 May 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis M. Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw to the Father Provincial regarding Francis M. Shaw&#39;s journey to Port Said. He is still at Suez and reported his progress there. 

Francis M. Shaw worked in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. He was ordained on 31st July 1916 at Milltown Park in Dublin and in 1917 was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia, possibly due to his nationalistic views.

Fr. Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives </repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/44</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4515</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1425">Francis M. Shaw</persName>
              <date>1919-05-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2024">Suez, Egypt</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr. Thomas V. Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4515_img_3859_1"  type="Letter"  url="10da6d4176d8446625e21de93338a1bc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4515_img_3859_1"/>
             Suez   15 May 1919   Dear Rev. Father Provincial,<lb/>P.C.   We have orders to <lb/>proceed to Port Said tomorrow. <lb/>I cant say whether it means <lb/>immediate embarkation there <lb/>or another taste of camp life. <lb/>Shall continue to report progress, <lb/>as I have done so far.   I said 20 Masses in April for <lb/>F<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Farley (Item repeated from last letter), and <lb/>have said 12 in May already.   Dont know yet whether we go by sea, by <lb/>Marseilles, or by <seg type="unclear">Tarentum</seg>   FM Shaw S.J. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>