<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0827">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Roger Casement to Robert Monteith, 13 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Roger Casement</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by Sir Roger Casement to Robert Monteith about the visit of Fr. Crotty, a Dominican priest. Casement goes on to express concern for Monteith&#39;s welfare as Monteith left the previous night without saying goodbye and states that he will not rest easy until he sees Monteith again.Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916),was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. Casement believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany. He spent eighteen months in Germany, arriving first as an envoy of Irish-American leaders, attempting to encourage Germany to support Irish separatist aspirations by providing arms. Casement succeeded in securing limited German support but his attempt to form a brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps to fight against Britain was largely unsuccessful. When it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916.Robert Monteith (1879-1956) was a founding member of the Irish Volunteers. In 1915 he was selected by Thomas Clarke (1858–1916), a veteran of revolutionary politics, to accompany Sir Roger Casement to Germany to assist with the recruitment of an &#39;Irish Brigade&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br. Allen Collection, IE/AL/RM/1/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/827</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date>1916-01-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0605">Zossen, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0377">Robert Monteith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0827_img_2378_1"  type="Letter"  url="f100eeaa35e945a10494acf9ac272dcd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0827_img_2378_2"  type="Letter"  url="aec535731dd06a1276496e23a3891847.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0827_img_2378_3"  type="Letter"  url="cbe33aeb76d2cd6c36fcdd28b94a8e98.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0827_img_2378_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">Zossen</hi>    Jan 13. 1916.   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Monteith,   Fr. Crotty came &amp;<lb/> has spent the day with<lb/> me. We went out to<lb/> the Camp together &amp; he blessed<lb/> the men. Now he goes<lb/> in to Berlin to stay with<lb/> his Order (the Dominicans)<lb/> tonight &amp; will return  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0827_img_2378_2"/>
              to L. tomorrow evg.<lb/> They told me at the<lb/> Camp you were at the<lb/> Hotel S. so I send this there.  I was alarmed about <lb/> you yesterday when the <lb/> waiter brought me the<lb/> cigarettes &amp; said you had<lb/> gone. I ran out to<lb/> go with you &amp; down to<cb/> the station - I am so grieved <lb/><hi rend="underline">for</hi> you, and shall not<lb/> be easy till I see you here <lb/> again - and I beg you<lb/> to drop me from your<lb/> thoughts. The best way<lb/> to help me is to do<lb/> nothing perhaps - but come<lb/> back &amp; with the the help of  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0827_img_2378_3"/>
              God get the men straight<lb/> and off to Exercise &amp; I hope on to the front.  If only <hi rend="underline">that</hi> were sure<lb/> &amp; certain &amp; I knew their business<lb/> was going to prosper I'd have<lb/> a millstone - one - off my<lb/> neck. But I want to feel<lb/> Easier about you yourself - <lb/> I am grieving for you &amp; hoping to<lb/> see you soon - very soon.   Fr. Crotty's Order has their House up<lb/> in the Moabite. <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely,   Roger Casement .</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>