<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0624">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslai, 3 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley; 1881–1965) from his father, Patrick Langford Beazley. The letter discusses the impact that wartime paper shortages are having on newspapers. He also sends £1 to ease Piaras&#39;s financial difficulties.Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley) was an English born writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, journalist and a member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He wrote twenty plays between 1913 and 1939.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Piaras Béaslaí Papers, Collection List 44, MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/624</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-02-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0624_img_206_1"  type="Letter"  url="a94a21cc82a15a5ecfc82c1b26521903.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0624_img_206_2"  type="Letter"  url="e4cb32947dd35bf0cfb94ed7600b8da0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0624_img_206_1"/>
                'GLENGARIFF'  RUDGRAVE SQUARE,  EGREMONT,  CHESIRE,    3rd Feb.,1916.  .  My dearest Pierce,   I hope you are quite <lb/> well &amp; that everything is<lb/> going well with you. We<lb/> are quite well, thank God,<lb/> but have no news. We have<lb/> no visitors now. Dr. Walsh <lb/> has dropped off, coming only<lb/> at long intervals &amp; Carey<lb/> comes only in the shape of<lb/> occasional letters. It looks<lb/> as if this regulation restricting <lb/> paper supplies will tell<lb/> greatly against the news.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0624_img_206_2"/>
              papers. I don't know yet<lb/> how it will work out. I sup-<lb/> pose the daily papers, in-<lb/> cluding the evening sheets<lb/> will be best off, as being<lb/> best able to press their case. <lb/> The wealthier will probably<lb/> have to play a very small <lb/> second fiddle. I see that<lb/> the Freeman has already drop-<lb/> ped the Sunday edition &amp;<lb/> come down to three sheets. <lb/> I am afraid the outlook for<lb/> extra work is not at all <lb/> encouraging. However keep<lb/> up your heart. If any<lb/> convenient &amp; fairly com-<lb/> fortable post were within reach<lb/><cb/> I think you ought to try &amp;<lb/> get it. When times become<lb/> more flourishing you will<lb/> be able to choose your own<lb/> course according to your taste.<lb/> I feel very anxious lest you<lb/> should be in want of money. <lb/> Don't let anything prevent you<lb/> from telegraphing or at any<lb/> rate writing if you<lb/> do. I enclose a one pound<lb/> note which will be useful. <lb/> Do send a couple of words <lb/> acknowledging it. The air-raid<lb/> has caused a good deal <lb/> of talk here but of course people <lb/> were not alarmed. The raiders<lb/> did not come very near L'pool.<lb/> With fondest love from mother <lb/> and myself, <seg type="closer"> Ever affectionately,  Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>