<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0372">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Brown to Sir Robert Chalmers, 2 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Brown</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Robert Brown to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). The letter concerns a payment that Brown feels is owed to him. He writes to Chalmers to express his frustrations about not being paid in accordance to what he was promised by the police officials. In the letter, he asks if he could direct his claims, instead, to someone who would be able to process his payment.Robert Brown had appeared at as a witness at a trial. Robert Brown, the assistant manager at the National Margarine Company Ltd. Before the war, a middle-class British household tended to put butter on the table, and reserve margarine for cooking purposes. But because the rations for margarine were more generous than for butter, margarine worked its way out of the kitchen and into the dining room. Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, as the chief secretary following the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9471/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/372</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1431">Robert Brown</persName>
              <date>1916-06-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1991">10 Quality Street, Leith, Edinburgh, Scotland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0372_img_1619_1"  type="Letter"  url="f2dfa4f6491fb53b35183d3d19c49f8c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0372_img_1619_2"  type="Envelope"  url="f2689adba96d90c1d67d34e480819b8b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0372_img_1619_1"/>
              <lb/>The National Margarine Company <lb/>Limited.     10, Quality Street,  Leith    2nd. June 1916  <lb/>To The Under Secretary,   Dublin Castle,  Dublin.   Dear Sir,   <lb/>I am in receipt of your letter of 30th.inst for which <lb/>I thank you.   <lb/>I have read over your various letters and I am unable to <lb/>gather from them your reason for refusing to give instructions for <lb/> payment of the balance of my claim.   <lb/>You give different reasons in different letters and there <lb/>seems no valid reason why I should not be paid in accordance with t <lb/>the promise made by the Police Officials. If Mr. J.J.Taylor who <lb/> signs your <sic>leters</sic> has not the power to order payment then I shall <lb/> be glad if you will inform me to whom I should now submit my claim.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  Rob Brown </seg> <lb/><sic>Ack,</sic>, and state that T.E can only <lb/>report that they leave nothing to add <lb/>to the replies but to his previous applications <lb/>E.O.F. 5 — 6 — 16   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0372_img_1619_2"/>
              <lb/>If undelivered return to:-   THE NATIONAL MARGARINE CO., Ltd.,  10 QUALITY STREET, LEITH.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>