<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1914">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Julia Conroy to Lord Wimborne, c. May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Julia Conroy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Julia Conroy to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Churchill Guest (1873–1939), Lord Wimborne. The lord lieutenant or viceroy was the monarch’s representative in Ireland. Conroy is appealing to the Lord lieutenant as a last attempt to obtain a pension which she claims is owed to her. Conroy claims to have received an injury in work which has left her unable to carry out manual labour. Conroy is asking for Wimborne&#39;s help in getting her some form of benefit. This letter includes an enclosure of a doctors note, it states the injury and how it was obtained.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8064/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1914</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1048">Julia Conroy</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1682">Mountmellick, Queen&#39;s County (Laois), Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Wimborne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1914_img_1365_1"  type="Letter"  url="fe1a9dd35dbcac4ee25c947222ee8b8a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1914_img_1365_2"  type="Letter"  url="ba5363c823d064d5dd982a6f119f7f94.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1914_img_1365_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="c72a75819b7ac50d9ed6112ed4349d85.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1914_img_1365_1"/>
             I Ack simply. <lb/>II Inspectors of Lunatics <lb/>for report please J.J.T. 12/v/16   6 Cottage Garroon <lb/>Mountmellick <lb/>Queens County   To His <sic>Excellancy</sic> Lord Lieutenant <lb/>of Ireland   Your <sic>excellancy</sic>   I Julia Conroy <lb/>humbly petition your <sic>excellancy</sic> <lb/>to give kindly consideration to my <lb/>case at your <sic>earlist</sic> <sic>convenance</sic> I <lb/>feel reluctant to <sic>truble</sic> you at the <lb/>present crisis as I am well aware of the <lb/>strenuous work you are engaged in.   The facts of my case are briefly :- I <lb/>occupied the position of Female attendant <lb/>in Maryborough District Asylum for a <lb/>period of nineteen years. Some seven <lb/>years ago I met with a accident <lb/>in the execution of my duty and <lb/>although I recovered from the effects <lb/>at the time, I have since been <lb/>unable to do any manual work. as <lb/>I left the house on getting married some <lb/>time after the accident, I received no <lb/>pension nor did I receive any compensation <lb/> Benefits.   I applied to The asylum committee Some <lb/>time back and The <sic>unanimusly</sic> entertained <lb/>my application but I was statute barred as <lb/>I did not apply sooner. I did not like to <sic>truble</sic> <lb/>The committee previous to this as I thought I <lb/>would get alright, but as my arm has become <lb/> useless and my husband in delicate health, <lb/>I am compelled to seek redress I <lb/> would feel very grateful to your <sic>Excellancy</sic>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1914_img_1365_2"/>
            if you would kindly consider my <lb/>case and try to obtain some small <lb/>pension or compensation for me. <lb/>A great many of my relatives are in <lb/>the army and I have no one to look to <lb/>only Your <sic>Excellancy</sic>.   I remain <lb/>Your most humble Servant   Julia Conroy 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1914_img_1365_3"/>
             40 Moore St   6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dec 15   This is to certify that <lb/>I have attended M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Julia <lb/>Conroy for synovitis <lb/>of the elbow joint <lb/>&amp; periostitis off &amp; on <lb/>for the past 6 six years, <lb/>which originated in <lb/> a fall received in the <lb/>Maryboro Asylum.  <lb/>Signed  M.L. O'Brien M.D. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>