<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0869">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to Sir Robert Chalmers, 14 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Andrew Philip Magill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941) to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). The letter concerns minutes sent by the Home Secretary&#39;s office concerning the reinstatement of certain employees and how a man may be released by the military but be seen as unfit for service of the crown due to association or sympathy with Sinn Féiners.Andrew Philip Magill had a varied career in the Irish civil service; he moved to the Ministry of Home Affairs in Northern Ireland before resigning prematurely in 1925. As private secretary to Augustine Birrell, the Chief Secretary whose resignation was prompted by the 1916 Rising, Magill was well placed to observe the often bizarre workings of the pre-revolutionary Irish administration. His subsequent postings in Dublin and Belfast likewise made him an invaluable witness of conflicts associated with revolution and partition. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary following the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5618/12149/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/869</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date>1916-07-14</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0869_img_2431_1"  type="Letter"  url="a60195635835351a5ebd9218af956901.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0869_img_2431_2"  type="Letter"  url="21eb46e1d3c79b73e170251855fed1fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0869_img_2431_3"  type="Letter"  url="a60195635835351a5ebd9218af956901.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0869_img_2431_1"/>
                14/7.   Dear Sir Robert,   Please see <lb/>the Home Secretary's <lb/>minutes on enclosed <lb/>file. I shall be much <lb/>obliged if you can <lb/>return the papers with <lb/>the information for <lb/>which he asks and any <lb/>suggestions which <seg type="del">you</seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0869_img_2431_2"/>
               page 2 <lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0869_img_2431_3"/>
               Page 3 <lb/> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>