<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0644">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy to Maria Duffin, 25 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Dorothy Duffin to her mother, Maria. Dorothy writes to her mother about the frustrating search for work in London. She does not want to work long hours for small pay and her preference would be a job in the Admiralty. Unfortunately she has found that there is no point in applying without a letter of introduction. She has asked a Mrs. Arnold-Forster for such a letter but she hasn&#39;t received a reply.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/30</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/644</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0232">Ardeevin, Epsom, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0644_img_2115_1"  type="Letter"  url="b3fd6c1751607b769a0b89023875866d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0644_img_2115_2"  type="Letter"  url="58b01bd9cba69f365dc69f947892b065.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0644_img_2115_3"  type="Letter"  url="4b0ea026dbfc385960b16bf39d874f6d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0644_img_2115_4"  type="Letter"  url="c26f71ef0fcc4495b7d7056b337ad29e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0644_img_2115_5"  type="Letter"  url="22de2ac93598c65df7a17bc869556507.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0644_img_2115_1"/>
                March 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 16    Ardeevin  Epsom   Dearest Mamma   Your letter just arrived<lb/> I was so glad to get it. Please thank<lb/> Ruth &amp; Helen for theirs also.  I have just been writing letters about posts<lb/> but dont feel at all hopeful about them<lb/> &amp; I am disappointed at not hearing from <lb/> Mrs <seg type="unclear">Arnold</seg> Forster. I heard it was<lb/> useless to approach the Admiralty without<lb/> a letter of introduction to some<lb/> definite person as being on the list<lb/> counts for little so I wrote to her but<lb/> got no answer.  Yesterday I spent a nightmare day<lb/> going from <seg type="del">1</seg> one Bureau of Association to<lb/> another. Miss <seg type="unclear">Sharek</seg> started me with<lb/> two letters &amp; each seemed to send me<lb/> on some place else I started at Victoria<lb/> St then made my way into the heart<lb/> of the City then Baker St &amp; Oxford Circus<lb/> ending up at South Kensington. There<lb/> was some amusement in discovering <seg type="unclear">routes</seg><lb/> &amp; on the whole everyone was agreeable<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0644_img_2115_2"/>
              but such dreadful women all asking me<lb/> the same questions my shorthand speed<lb/> especially &amp; telling me to be willing<lb/> to start with little pay. I said I<lb/> would prefer a private residential<lb/> post but am told they are practically<lb/> nil since the War &amp; moreover it<lb/> was so much better to carve out<lb/> a <hi rend="underline">career</hi>(!) I have joined the<lb/> Association of Clerks &amp; Secs: &amp; various<lb/> people have written down my name<lb/> on forms &amp; promised to write but I<lb/> have not much hope of them &amp; have<lb/> a   feeling that I should detest<lb/> anything they offered me! I have<lb/> made up my mind that I will not<lb/> be an office clerk working from 9 —6<lb/> on small pay. I struck one<lb/> rather decent man in an office off<lb/> the Strand who gave me an address<lb/> of a Capt <seg type="unclear">Stil</seg> who wanted a<lb/> Secretary for a hospital at Camberwell  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0644_img_2115_3"/>
              and I have written to him  One of these official ladies told me so<lb/> many incompetent women had got <seg type="del">them</seg><lb/> into Admiralty work through influence<lb/> that the authorities are disgusted<lb/> &amp; probably most of them will be turned <lb/> out as incapable. I dont know<lb/> what they are <seg type="del">disposed</seg> supposed to do<lb/> exactly.  I was glad to meet Celia at South<lb/> Kensington <seg type="unclear">foreign</seg> offices typewriters!<lb/> We called on Mrs <seg type="unclear">Macleod</seg> but she was<lb/> away so we went to Pontings where<lb/> I bought a hat &amp; we   into<lb/> Bakers for tea. I shall meet Celia<lb/> again for a half day next week &amp;<lb/> expect to go to Eastbourne on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi><lb/> Celia is always cheerful &amp; uncomplaining.  Aunt Fanny &amp; Uncle Edmund are kindness<lb/> itself but you know how long days can<lb/> be but I smile cheerfully <seg type="unclear">at</seg> her<lb/> all day &amp; sing to him in the evening.<lb/> We had a wee dinner at the<lb/> Clubrooms where the women attempted  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0644_img_2115_4"/>
              to dress so were frozen in a miserably<lb/> cold room the men remained in morning<lb/> clothes smoked pipes all night till<lb/> I was nearly suffocated.  I have avoided walking into the town<lb/> with Aunt F this morning in order<lb/> to write to you but this afternoon we<lb/> are to have a good constitutional.<lb/> Baby is very well but her health<lb/> is almost entirely the only subject<lb/> of conversation. It is so funny<lb/> to see her dancing with her<lb/> grandparents. Uncle E kicking up his <lb/> heels. Aunt F hopping with a face<lb/> of intense misery. Uncle E looks<lb/> just the same &amp; is still talking<lb/> of his golf swing and of ' a<lb/> man I know'  Tomorrow we walk over to <seg type="unclear">Cormac</seg><lb/> Janet has been poorly &amp; so has Harry<lb/> but both are better. Janet has<lb/> come into money it seems.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0644_img_2115_5"/>
              The other day we went for tea at<lb/> the Bayshaws in the creepy underground<lb/> house. The drawing room chairs<lb/> were all covered with white calico.<lb/> Mrs B is so fat she cannot sit<lb/> down but she leans against a solid<lb/> seat. The <seg type="del">other</seg> visit was the <seg type="unclear">other</seg><lb/> of one I paid years ago &amp; was<lb/> asked exactly the same questions about<lb/> the <seg type="unclear">Souths</seg> &amp; Corrys as before. I felt<lb/> I was dreaming!  I am sorry about Charlie's training<lb/> being a farce it seems very stupid.<lb/> I would join Marjorie if she wanted me<lb/> &amp; come back to London. I'm glad<lb/> you have Ruth at home &amp; hope to<lb/> hear of Emma soon.  I feel my brains <seg type="unclear">cooking</seg> in this<lb/> little study. Epsom is the most bilious<lb/> place I have ever been in . I hope<lb/> you wont find it so &amp; that you will<lb/> make up your mind to come over. <seg type="closer"> Best Love Dear  Dorothy. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>