<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2639">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maria Duffin to Celia Duffin, 13 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

This letter was written by Maria Duffin (1854 – 1954) to her daughter Celia (b. 1888). In this letter Maria recounts events at home, such as the actions of Peter who is making himself ‘so dirty and disreputable’ through his socialising with different women. Maria writes about Celia’s sister Emma 1883 – 1979), who is also serving as a VAD. She writes that Emma was told by a man that none of their officers who went out were left. Maria also writes about an auction she will be attending and the difficulties she is having economising, especially without eggs, cream and butter.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B/6/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2639</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2639_img_2065_1"  type="Letter"  url="8447dcc6fde2f7ae635573ff9375b94c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2639_img_2065_2"  type="Letter"  url="3fdbb291f0086490414803da8b78d6c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2639_img_2065_3"  type="Letter"  url="66631af7163c4a981c567e23eb747cea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2639_img_2065_4"  type="Letter"  url="0d22a90cf2e21cfae3a61ffffcacb6fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2639_img_2065_5"  type="Letter"  url="eea09c575aa4b684191280dcb64a12dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2639_img_2065_1"/>
             Dunowen<lb/>Belfast.   Feb. 13. 1916    My dearest Celia   I was glad to<lb/>get yours of the 10th and<lb/>to hear that you did see<lb/>Olive even for a short time.<lb/>All the stupidity was pro-<lb/>voking.    I was at Danesfort yesterday<lb/>and heard that Marjorie<lb/>had arrived safely but<lb/>that the Hughes girl &amp; Dora were<lb/>at some other place outside<lb/>the town and that she<lb/>was with M. Perri, who has<lb/>quarrelled with the others<lb/>&amp; a Mrs Baresoft, which does   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2639_img_2065_2"/>
             does not sound exciting. Sam &amp;<lb/>Ivan went on Thursday.<lb/>Iris has had a son &amp;<lb/>all goes well. Great joy of<lb/>course.  Peter arrived on Monday &amp;<lb/>Dorothy took him to the Riddil<lb/>Hall on Tuesday. On Wednesday<lb/>he disappeared and we were<lb/>in great anxiety, but on<lb/>Thursday morning arrived<lb/>at Riddil Hall. Brought<lb/>back he ran off there again<lb/>on Friday. Again   claimed<lb/>he has again disappeared.<lb/>Is he looking for Sheelagh?<lb/>He was not <hi rend="underline">particularly</hi><lb/>attached to Ruth. It is an<lb/>unforeseen nuisance and he<lb/>makes himself so dirty and     disreputable.   Emma writes that she is on<lb/>night duty again just when<lb/>she wanted three days leave<lb/>to go to Cairo. The hospital is<lb/>nearly empty and she thinks<lb/>they may not be asked to<lb/>sign on again. I think it<lb/>would be really better for<lb/>her to go somewhere else in<lb/>the hot season.  No kittens yet but Julia &amp;<lb/>Peter quite friendly.  You seem to have had company<lb/>on the boat. Emma says<lb/>a Cheshire man told her<lb/>they had not one of the<lb/>officers who went out left.<lb/>I hope your soup turned out<lb/>well. If you will tell me 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2639_img_2065_3"/>
             what is the best. I will send<lb/>you some more when you want<lb/>it.  comparison so old has <seg type="unclear"></seg>   I can't think why Mrs  <lb/>told me I had got the <seg type="unclear"></seg> <lb/>&amp; the water colour neither of<lb/>which came to me. I am<lb/>bidding for a nice old bureau<lb/>and a little stand I had a<lb/>fancy (she for both)  for but am not<lb/>likely to get them. If sold<lb/>I shall try and sell the<lb/>one in the drawing room for<lb/>what I paid for it £7.    After all the money is the<lb/>most useful thing to have,<lb/>these times! the sale is to<lb/>be the 18th.  Your father and Ruth are lunching<lb/>with Aunt Margaret. She says 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2639_img_2065_4"/>
             she does not feel lonely but<lb/>I feel rather sorry for her in<lb/>that big house by herself.  We take tea at the farm<lb/>tomorrow to meet Helen Hultan.<lb/>I suppose as I hear she is<lb/>down. There is absolutely<lb/>nothing doing here.  The <seg type="unclear"></seg> goes on well and<lb/>is usually quite satisfactory<lb/>so domestic worries are reduced<lb/>to me. I am not a very good<lb/>hand at economising. I find<lb/>I can look after <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>but always want to <seg type="unclear"> </seg> butter,<lb/>eggs, or cream! Olive has 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2639_img_2065_5"/>
             sent me a little book of eggless<lb/>cookery but I have not found<lb/>anything very tempting in it.  I am reading a life of Jane<lb/>Austen by a nephew, gt nephew<lb/>&amp; gt-qt nephew, but they do<lb/>not inherit her talent &amp; are<lb/>far too minute and lengthy- Her<lb/>own letters are good.  It is almost luncheon time<lb/>so goodbye darling<lb/> your ever loving<lb/>Mammy  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>