<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0934">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Commissioner of the R.I.C. to the Major Geoffrey Drage, 15 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Commissioner of the Royal Irish Constabulary (R.I.C.) to the Chief Recruiting Office regarding David Max Cohen. According to the Commissioner Cohen is a Jew of Russian descent who has been residing in Ireland since the age of four. He is noted as a respectable man.Major Geoffrey Drage (1860-1955), politician, served from 1914 in the military intelligence section of the War Office. He was also the chief recruiting officer for Belfast.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5617, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5617</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/934</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-15T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1186">Commissioning Office, Royal Irish Constabulary, Belfast, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Geoffrey Drage</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0976">City Hall, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0934_img_2718_1"  type="Letter"  url="a60b6dff8cd39e5e56b837d3bf6cf178.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0934_img_2718_1"/>
                15 July 1916.  <lb/>Re David Max Cohen 27 Pacific Avenue <lb/>Now a British Subject <lb/> --------------***---------------  Sir,   The Home Office having granted a Certificate <lb/>of Naturalization of the above-named,and,being under <lb/>41.Years of age I have been directed to communicate <lb/>with you in case you should desire to invite him to <lb/>enlist or<hi rend="superscript">to</hi>attest.  Cohen is a Jew, born of Russian parents and in this <lb/>country since he was a child of four years of age. <lb/>He is a respectable man. <seg type="closer"> Your obedient servant <lb/>Commissioner <lb/>R.I.C.   The Chief Recruiting Officer  City Hall  Belfast.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>