<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5248">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 26, March, 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Expresses love for his father and gratitude for for an engagement present.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5248</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1920-03-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1905">1st Bn Royal Irish Rifles, Albany Barracks, Parkhurst, Isle Of Wight, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5248_img_None_1"  url="bf5c7ea6bb6e39342d2ea51c50529925.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5248_img_None_2"  url="fe678bf681b425bdbdaa365babead956.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5248_img_0_1"/>
              197 B ROYAL IRISH RIFLES    ALBANY BARRACKS    PARKHURST    1 OF W    <hi rend="underline">26/3/20.</hi>   My dearest Daddy,  Your letter of 24th with your most<lb/>generous cheque came tonight - Really you<lb/>are the very best and dearest that was lived<lb/>and I simplty can't thank you enough. You<lb/>have always always been to me the very<lb/>very best Father that any boy could<lb/>possibly have. and you have always been<lb/>far far too good and generous. Everyone<lb/>of you have always been doing things<lb/>and giving me things and I'll never<lb/>never be able to repay the half of your<lb/>kindness. All I can hope is that I will<lb/>always be a credit to you all. Even<lb/>when I'm married my home will always 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5248_img_0_2"/>
             be with you and we shall sepnd the<lb/>greratest part of our leave with you. And<lb/>we shall always look frward to <seg type="del">t</seg> our<lb/>leave too. And I specially look forward to<lb/>the time when we shall have a little house<lb/>of our own and you can all come and<lb/>stay with us. And I know Nellie is looking<lb/>forward to that too. She is always going<lb/>to consider you a 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Father. And we are<lb/>both going to be the very happiest two that<lb/>have ever lived. I do hope that you will<lb/>be able to come over for the 10<hi rend="superscript">th. </hi>I do so<lb/>want you to be there. I'm going to buy<lb/>something with that present that will really<lb/>last me forever &amp; ever. I haven't quite decided<lb/>yet what it will be but it will be<lb/>something very very nice.  John's present arrived tonight and I'm<lb/>writing to him. Also to Mrs Williams of Grange.  I'm back in Barracks again.   Very best love to all    Your most afficionate sone    Willie     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>