<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6245">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Daly to Charlie Daly, 29 January 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Susie Daly, [Our Lady of Mercy College, Crarysfort, Dublin, Ireland] to [Charlie Daly, [Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Donegal, Ireland]. Asks if he wants more books. Thomas was transferred to Mountjoy on Thursday. She heard rumours that Charlie had been moved from Drumboe. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/2/4/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6245</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0193">Susan Daly</persName>
              <date>1923-01-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1309">Our Lady of Mercy College, Carysfort, Blackrock, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1693">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Tirconail, Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1983</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6245_img_None_1"  url="bf9cc075a6fc8b7593bac13399f81237.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6245_img_None_2"  url="4e38fece27c24d8c79cf0930958cb4ef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6245_img_None_3"  url="80564ec778b60777b58fef334bfe2480.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6245_img_None_4"  url="9417d7b5822a1a7bbd2bc0b0843fbbde.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6245_img_None_5"  url="cfac7052d357941804387a748492ad12.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6245_img_0_1"/>
             3.  You must have found my last letter very<lb/>dry so I'll try to make up for it this<lb/>time by telling you all the news I can think<lb/>of about home. To begin with  Cornelie g ot<lb/>a fit of growing since you saw him last<lb/>and he is three or four inches taller now<lb/>than he was in the summer so you'll<lb/>hardly know him the next time you see<lb/>him. It might have been that he grew<lb/>with importance for being arrested. Poor Nellie<lb/>didn't grow a scrap and she still divides<lb/>her time between the collage and the Bung.<lb/>She stayed with Katie for the first week<lb/>after Josie left before Molly got holidays<lb/>I don't know how they'll run the Bungalow<lb/>at all without Josie. The few times I was<lb/>there Katie and Mollie were trying to do<lb/>the cooking and they weren't any better<lb/>than I would be at the job. Mollie's<lb/>fingers were all burned from trying to<lb/>bake a cake for Willie in the range<lb/>and Katie was vowing that she'd have 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6245_img_0_2"/>
             4.  to get a maid when Mollie's holidays<lb/>were over. She didn't get the maid yet<lb/>but she invites all her friends in<lb/><seg type="unclear">luin</seg>to stay a few days with her. When<lb/>my mother wrote last she had Ella O'Brien<lb/>over with her. Josie was delighted that they<lb/>found out what a loss she was in some<lb/>way. I hadn't any letter from her since<lb/>she left but very likely she won't write<lb/>until she arrives in France and very likely<lb/>she spent a few days in London with Nora.<lb/><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"> Sun </hi></hi>. As you can see from Mrs.<lb/>Browne's letter enclosed, Tomas is in<lb/>Mountjoy since Thursday. I didn't get this<lb/>letter until this morning and you may<lb/>have heard it from home before this.<lb/>I expect a letter from my mother very<lb/>soon. I wrote to Tomas today but it<lb/>was a pity that I didn't know he was<lb/>there when out yesterday as I could<lb/>have told the Mahony's and those.<lb/>I called to Whelan's yesterday - they were       
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6245_img_0_3"/>
             thinking that I hadn't come back at<lb/>all. Leo is just recovering from a<lb/>heavy cold. When I was in noboody but<lb/>Mrs. Whelan and Lizzie was up. After<lb/>going out on Sat week I didn't see Sheila<lb/>O'Brien - she had a very heavy cold and<lb/>was allowed see nobody but the doctor.<lb/>I don't think she was very bad tho. for<lb/>she sent me a card to call on her<lb/>yesterday.  Whelan's heard somewhere that you<lb/>were removed from Dromboe but as the<lb/>rumour wasn't confirmed I thought that<lb/>I'd write to the old address.   Beannacht Dé leat<lb/>Susie   P.S. Did you hear that <seg type="unclear">Pa </seg>nand <seg type="unclear">Dave </seg>Connor<lb/>were arrested? 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6245_img_0_4"/>
              Mr. Charles Daly,<lb/>Dromboe Castle,<lb/>Stranorlar,<lb/>Co. Donegal.        
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_6245_img_0_5"/>
             If not there, Please forward. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>