<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1926">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter McGinn to Robert Chalmers, 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter McGinn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Belfast based solicitor Peter McGinn (1864-) to Under-Secretary for Ireland Sir Robert Chalmers (1858–1938). After the Easter Rising Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), his chief secretary. In the letter, McGinn, who is representing Mr. Jones, enclosed a letter that he wrote to the National Health Insurance Company requesting money which is entitled to Mr Jones. However on each occasion McGinn&#39;s letter have gone unanswered, so he has written to Chalmers to see what is to be done about this issue.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI; Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8631/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1926</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1370">Peter McGinn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2083">151 Donegall Street, Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1926_img_1376_1"  type="Letter"  url="4c1bf941e29eae4550dbbc63ab7edf84.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1926_img_1376_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="64a706daf2fde36e0df76ed31544397c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1926_img_1376_1"/>
             20 May 1916   Dear Sir , <lb/> I enclose a copy of a letter I wrote the <lb/>National Health <sic>Insce.</sic> <sic>Com<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>.</sic> on the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April last <lb/>I wrote the said Commissioners for a reply on <lb/>the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> April, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> May and 12th May, but I <lb/>got no acknowledgement of any of my letters. <lb/>The Irish Transport and General Workers Union <lb/>was a society approved of by the National Health <lb/>Insurance <sic>Com<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>.</sic> Although controlled <seg type="unclear">beyond</seg> <lb/>men as the notorious Larkin and the rebel <lb/>Connolly recently shot. James is entitled to <lb/>10p per week and is without any means. He <lb/>is suffering from consumption and if he had <lb/>the money which the law says he is entitled <lb/>to it would soften and sooth his suffering. <lb/>I hope you will enliven the <sic>Nat<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>.</sic> Health <sic>Ins<hi rend="superscript">ce</hi></sic> <lb/><sic>Com<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>.</sic> as to their duties. Are employers still <lb/>bound to pay weekly into this Society, and if <lb/>they stop doing so will they be prosecuted?  Yours faithfully   P McGinn   The Under Secretary <lb/>Dublin Castle <lb/>Dublin 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1926_img_1376_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>  11 Donegal Street, <lb/>Belfast ,  11<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> April 1916  <lb/>re National <hi rend="underline">Health</hi> <sic>Insce</sic> Act<lb/>  Dear Sir,  <lb/><seg type="unclear">Alex.</seg> Jones 6 Dock Lane, Belfast has instructed <lb/>me to inform you that he gave his contribution <lb/>books and stamped cards to an agent in Belfast <lb/>of the Irish Transport and General Workers Union <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Jones is a member of that Union. M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Jones <lb/>has applied several times at their office in <lb/>Belfast for his Contribution book, but always <lb/>got the reply that his book was at "Libery Hall", <lb/>and would be got back for him in a day or two. <lb/>I have also applied several times for the book <lb/>and got <seg type="del">sev</seg> similar answers. I also wrote on <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Jones' behalf to the Secretary of the Union of <lb/>"Liberty Hall" Dublin but I got no reply from him <lb/>I will be obliged if the Commissioners will put <lb/>their powers in force and get Mr Jones his <lb/><seg type="unclear">contribution</seg> book<lb/>  Yours faithfully  P McGinn   The <sic>Secy</sic> <lb/>National Health Insurance Comp <lb/>Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>