<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0076">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Gavan Duffy to the Manager, 'Irish Independent', 22 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Gavan Duffy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In the letter George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951) requests that Blythe&#39;s copies of the Irish Independent newspaper be forwarded to him at Brixton Prison until further notice.George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising.Gavan Duffy had been acting for Ernest Blythe (1889-1975), organiser for the Irish Volunteers. Blythe had been arrested under the Defence of the Realm Act. He was released from prison in England before the Easter Rising but was rearrested there during Easter week 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD/45/3/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/76</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date>1916-05-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Manager, &#39;Irish Independent&#39;</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1726">Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0076_img_1145_1"  type="Letter"  url="58de0451e4fccbfcbb1a35a141d95687.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0076_img_1145_1"/>
               DUREAU OF MILITARY HISTORY 1913-21<lb/> DURO STAIRE MILEATA 1913-21<lb/> C.D. 45/3/11     22nd May 1916.    The Manager,  'Irish Independent'   Dear Sir:-   I write on behalf of Mr Ernest Blythe of <lb/>Abingdon, who lately subscribed to the 'Independent', <lb/> to ask you to address the paper to him in future, until <lb/>further notice, to Ernest Blythe, No. 3134 Brixton <lb/> Prison, Brixton, London, S.W. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully, <lb/> G. Gavan Duffy </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>