<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3667">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Ryan to The Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Joseph Ryan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Michael Joseph Ryan thanking the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) for their consideration of his case for reinstatement on the college&#39;s roll.  Ryan asks if the College would be willing to use their influence to persuade the General Medical Council to reinstate him on the medical register. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T46</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3667</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0627">Michael Joseph Ryan</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1795">Heathfield, 22 Chorley Old Road, Bolton Lane&#39;s</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3667_img_3061_1"  type="Letter"  url="2665c31e61b5ff613309e0e8c9242f26.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3667_img_3061_2"  type="Letter"  url="1d58b5b1537980a80dab134d249b5e12.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3667_img_3061_3"  type="Letter"  url="d10da59629a88061ad0bed4340f0e6db.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3667_img_3061_1"/>
             HEATHFIELD <lb/>CHORLEY OLD ROAD 22 <lb/>BOLTON Lane's.   November 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915.   The Registrar <lb/>Royal College of Physicians <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I beg to offer my sincere thanks <lb/>to the President and Fellows for their kind <lb/>consideration of my case in Oct 1914 <lb/>and for the resolution of the College to <lb/>re&amp;-instate me.   I now wish to ask them if they cannot <lb/>possibly bring their valuable influence to <lb/>bear to persuade the General Medical <lb/>Council to restore my name to the <lb/>Medical Register as, owing to the serious <lb/>shortage of doctors for the Army I wish to offer <lb/>my services to the War Office as early as possible <lb/>and I venture to think if the Medical Council <lb/>understood my case thoroughly they would <lb/>not refuse.   I have already suffered two years cruel <lb/>punishment and in the absence of my son who <lb/>is away on Active Service I have tried to <lb/>manage his business, but owing to his absence
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3667_img_3061_2"/>
            and the War it has had to be disposed of and <lb/>I am faced with financial ruin.   In doing that for which my name was re- <lb/>moved, I can truthfully and conscientiously <lb/>say I acted in perfect innocence and good <lb/>faith and had no intent to do wrong or <lb/>deceive, and, being guileless myself, I gave <lb/>others credit for being the same.   I gave credence to the statements of a man <lb/>who at that time commanded the respect <lb/>and trust of everyone in the town but who <lb/>afterwards proved himself to be a wicked <lb/>man and who made use of my believing <lb/>nature to induce me to fall into the <lb/>trap which he had carefully prepared for <lb/>me to further his own nefarious designs. <lb/>This fact was emphasized by M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Justice <lb/>Bailache at the Court of Appeal.   Knowing the urgent need for doctors, the <lb/>following gentlemen who are anxious that <lb/>I should be re-instated, have promised <lb/>me their support, - Colonel French, Sir <lb/>Thos Flitcroft, Alderman Seddon, (Mayor <lb/>of Bolton), and I can also refer you to <lb/>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Russell Solicitor 11 Wood Street Bolton <lb/>who has known me intimately for years. <lb/>One gentleman intended writing to the Med. <lb/>Council on my behalf but the meeting <lb/>took place earlier than he expected. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3667_img_3061_3"/>
             It has been suggested that an Emergency <lb/>meeting of the Council might be called <lb/>on my behalf under present urgent <lb/>circumstances.   I have been taught a severe lesson <lb/>which will make me more careful in <lb/>future and if re-instated I promise <lb/>that the Medical Council shall have no <lb/>reason to regret <seg type="del">this</seg> having performed <lb/>a generous and patriotic action and <lb/>also that I shall endeavour to uphold <lb/>the homour and dignity of the Medical <lb/>Profession.   I shall be glad if you will hand this <lb/>letter to the President without delay, <lb/>and I hope to have an early and <lb/>favourable reply.   Yours faithfully,   M. J. Ryan.   MacD.C. <lb/>3.XII.15 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>