<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2787">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 27 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.
James has been sick, in appalling weather conditions with 3 to 4 inches snow and the trenches in &#34;a terrible state&#34; so he is looking forward to spring in a few weeks time. James is upset that they will have to move shortly, so soon after getting &#34;things in hands here&#34;. Leave has been cancelled so he doesnt know when he will get off but things are quiet.
He thanks his mother for the French books and food parcels containing apples and butter etc. have arrived from home but reminds her to send on Cocpiles??  pills, quinine and iron tablets (as the Battalion doctor recommended them for him).
James thanks her for her letter of 17th and that of his father of 19th</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/31</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2787</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0606">Somewhere in the field, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2787_img_2205_1"  type="Letter"  url="78dac9b66e690a50f9997873069da5c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2787_img_2205_2"  type="Letter"  url="144f2d5096014c15f75ba12570193206.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2787_img_2205_3"  type="Letter"  url="64443092da83fa02ee1d0fcc59781f6c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2787_img_2205_4"  type="Envelope"  url="c6a49bb108da2d065bf20f3b688ec513.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2787_img_2205_1"/>
             27/2/16   My dearest Mother — I have been ill <lb/>for past 2 days - a chill with sore <lb/>throat headache &amp;c - but today <lb/>am much better &amp; able to be up so no <lb/>doubt in a day or so I shall be <lb/>quite all right again. The weather <lb/>has been awful &amp; the wonder is <lb/>that not more are laid up. Snow <lb/>sleet &amp; storm. At the present <lb/>moment the snow is about 3 to 4 <lb/>inches deep &amp; the trenches are in <lb/>a terrible state. It is a long <lb/>way the worst weather we have <lb/>had but it is some comfort to <lb/>think that in the course of another <lb/>3 or 4 weeks we should be having <lb/>a little spring sunshine.   After all the trouble &amp; worry we <lb/>have had in getting here &amp; taking <lb/>over, the latest news is that we
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2787_img_2205_2"/>
            are to proceed elsewhere in a <lb/>few days time. Whether we <lb/>shall be in the fighting line or <lb/>again in reserve remains to be <lb/>seen but it is very sickening <lb/>as we are just beginning to get <lb/>things nicely in hand. The <lb/>Coy's allotment of leave was <lb/>curtailed a few days ago from 2 <lb/>places per 4 days to 1 but now <lb/>even that has been cancelled so <lb/>dear knows when I shall be <lb/>able to get away. Things <lb/>here have been a good deal more <lb/>quiet recently &amp; beyond on <lb/>periodical straffes with the guns <lb/>there has been nothing exciting. <lb/>My trench boots arrived safely &amp; <lb/>are a great success, also refills <lb/>for the Little Kitchener, box of apples <lb/>&amp; parcels with butter &amp;c. Thanks <lb/>ever so much for them all. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2787_img_2205_3"/>
             I wonder if you remembered <lb/>to port me a large box of <lb/>Cockles pills. If not would <lb/>you please send with it a <lb/>bottle of Quinine &amp; Iron tabloids. <lb/>The Dr. of the Batt. billeted in our <lb/>village who has been looking after <lb/>me has recommended me to <lb/>take them for a week or so &amp; <lb/>of course they cant be obtained <lb/>out here.   Your welcome letter of 17th came <lb/>a few days ago &amp; I also had one <lb/>from Father dated 19th. Was glad <lb/>to hear such good reports of the <lb/>Pistol. Have not seen Gerard <lb/>since he returned but hope to do <lb/>so soon. Goodbye dear Mother. Dont <lb/>be anxious if you dont hear from me <lb/>for some days as when the move comes <lb/>there will be no time to think of writing.   Love to all your loving son    Jim 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2787_img_2205_4"/>
              Rtmd>March  4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>/16    Mrs S. C. Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor <lb/>Co. Down <lb/>Ireland   JS Davidson. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>