<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0476">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry J. Walker to the Lord Lieutenant, 30 June, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry J. Walker</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Henry J Walker to the Lord Lieutenant, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939). Walker writes as a candidate for the position of Clerk of Crown and Peace for Co. Westmeath. Further to his application he encloses two testimonial letters from J.P. Hayden (1863–1954) and Alexander Major Kelly, the Dean of Elphin.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/11171</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/476</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1152">Henry J. Walker</persName>
              <date>1916-06-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1888">Athlone, Co. Westmeath, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Lieutenant of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0476_img_1830_1"  type="Letter"  url="0e0ce6c43f8d58e8a9eed35259963281.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0476_img_1830_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="c469f8723c4d8c510c4abc3cbadbafe2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0476_img_1830_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="5b58bbf549d5b9e468e4ccdffbbd4f8f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0476_img_1830_4"  type="Letter"  url="2b3e2d32564ec99fedb29df2e8f00b1d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0476_img_1830_1"/>
                Henry J. Walker, B.A.  Solicitor  Athlone,    30 day of June 1916    To his Excellency the Lord Lieutenant  (or the Lords Justices)   May it please your Excellency   Referring to my letter of application for <lb/> the Clerkship of Crown &amp; Peace for County <lb/> Westmeath I now enclose letters from <lb/> 1. Right Rev Mgr Kelly DD Athlone (Dean of Elphin) <lb/> 2. J. P. Hayden Esq MP. <lb/> <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be <lb/> Your Excellency's most obedient servant   Henry J. Walker </seg> Ref. <lb/> Please annex the <lb/> separate file of application <lb/> C. W. S. <lb/><hi rend="underline">17âviiâ16</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0476_img_1830_2"/>
                29/6/16.   My Dear Harry,   Of course you are aware that I have always strictly adhered <lb/> to the resolution of the Irish Party in reference to official <lb/> appointments. I have not interfered on behalf of any candidate <lb/> for any position in the past and I am not doing so on this <lb/> occasion. However, this does not prevent me from expressing <lb/> the opinion that you are admirable qualified and that you would <lb/> give satisfaction to all concerned in the discharge of the duties <lb/> of Clerk of Crown &amp; Peace for Westmeath.  <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely,  John P. Hayden <seg type="unclear">C.M.S.</seg><lb/>  Henry J. Walker Esq.,  Solr.,  Athlone.  </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0476_img_1830_3"/>
                St. Peter's   Athlone    23 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> June, 1916     I have known <lb/> Mr. Henry J Walker <sic>Sol'r</sic><lb/> from his boyhood. I <lb/> am glad to give him <lb/> the highest character <lb/> as an upright and <lb/> conscientious young <lb/><seg type="unclear">man</seg>. He has been <lb/> highly distinguished <lb/> in the examinations <lb/> of the Intermediate Educa <lb/> â tion Board of Ireland. <lb/> He is a man of culiva <lb/> âred taste and literary <lb/> accomplishments. I  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0476_img_1830_4"/>
              strongly recommend <lb/> him for the position <lb/> he seeks in the legal <lb/> profession.  <seg type="closer"> Fr J Kelly, D.D. V.G  Dean of Elphin </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>