<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3959">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frongoch to William O'Brien, 14 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from a group of Irish prisoners in Frongoch to William O&#39;Brien. The letter concerns the rations received by internees in the camp. According to the prisoners some of the meat being served to prisoners is &#39;unfit for human consumption&#39;. The letter states that this is the third time this has occurred and asks O&#39;Brien to let in &#39;the light of public opinion on the matter&#39;.

Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; due to the influential effect it had on its inmates.

William O&#39;Brien (1852-1928) was an Irish nationalist politician serving as a Member of Parliament in the Britain from 1883 until he withdrew himself and his party in 1918. 

Among the signatories to this letter are Michael Staines (1885-1955), Thomas Sinnott (1893-1965) and Richard Mulcahy(1886-1971).

.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Art Ó Briain Papers, Collection List No. 150; Ms 8429/19-5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3959</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0235">Frongoch Prison, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1436">William O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0077">House of Commons, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3959_img_3334_1"  type="Letter"  url="1149e63d6e27f9711ac034a60188b011.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3959_img_3334_2"  type="Letter"  url="2fc554b46e3a4a8cdb7236c365aaeeeb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3959_img_3334_1"/>
             Irish Prisoners,<lb/>Internment Camp,<lb/>Frongoch.   14th Oct. 1916.    Al. Byrne<lb/>L. Ginnell   Wm. O'Brien Esq., M.P.<lb/> House of Commons.    Sir:-   We much regret the necessity which compel<seg type="del">e</seg>s us to send to you<lb/>additional complaints regarding the rations supplied to us by the<lb/>authorities. In accordance with the intention to refuse the ration<lb/>of herrings as indicated in the second para. of the third item of<lb/>our letter to you dated 11th inst., the Prisoners' Quarter Master<lb/>declined to take over the ration of herrings from the military<lb/>yesterday, and asked that some other food stuffs be supplied in lieu.<lb/>No other article of food would be issued in lieu; and yesterday's<lb/>(Friday 13th inst.) dinner, in consequence, cost the prisoners<lb/>£3: 15: 10., out of their private fund.   Item No2<lb/>14/10/16<lb/>B<lb/>V This morning when the prisoners ration party attended the<lb/>military stores for the purpose of drawing the daily meat ration, the<lb/>prisoners' Quarter Master complained to the Orderly Officer of the<lb/>day that the meat, in his opinion, was unfit for human consumption,<lb/>as the stench from it was very noticeable. The officer admitted that<lb/>the stench was bad, but that if it was washed with vinegar and water<lb/>the stench would disappear. The military butcher remarked, in the<lb/>hearing of the Quarter Master, that this meat was intended for the<lb/>Guard, but that they refused it, and were supplied with sausages in<lb/>lieu. In view of the order and directions of the Orderly Officer, the<lb/>prisoners' Quarter Master, had no option but to accept the meat for<lb/>the time being. On arriving in Camp, the attention of the Head Camp<lb/>Leader was drawn to the meat, and he called the doctor to the kitchen.<lb/>When he arrived in the Camp at 10 o' clock a.m. the military staff<lb/>sergeant on duty in the Camp, on becoming aware of this notified the<lb/>Adjutant, who came to the the prisoners kitchen shortly after the doctor,<lb/>and immediately tried, by his language and attitude, to brow-beat the<lb/>doctor, and was most insulting to the prisoners Quarter master. The 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3959_img_3334_2"/>
             doctor, in view of the Adjutant's attitude, considered it advisable<lb/>to call in his assistant, who at once condemned 176lbs. out of a<lb/>total 268lbs. as being utterly unfit for human consumption —<lb/>that is a proportion of nearly 2/3 of the total. The meat was then<lb/>changed.  You will agree with us that this is a serious state of affairs,<lb/>especially as it is the third occasion on which the meat had to be<lb/>condemned, as being utterly unfit, and we hope that you will<lb/>endeavour to seize an early opportunity of letting in the light<lb/>of public opinion on the matter.  We desire to remain, Sir,<lb/>Your obedient servants,   Michael Staines Head Leader<lb/>J.J. O'Neill (acting) Leader No1. Room<lb/>Edward A. Misken Leader No 2. Room<lb/>R.J.Mulcahy Leader No 3. Room<lb/>Thos. D. Sinnott Leader No 4. Room     <lb/>J.J. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>