<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4565">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr. Edward J. MacWeeney to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick, 2 February 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Joseph McWeeney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Dr Edward Jospeh McWeeney (1864-1925) was a Professor of Pathology in the Cecilia-street Medical School of the Catholic University. McWeeney did much work at the Fungi, especially of the Dublin area. His contributions appeared mainly in the Irish Naturalist. 

From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI/2/3/3/16/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4565</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0226">Edward Joseph McWeeney</persName>
              <date>1917-02-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1082">School of Medicine, Cecilia Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1207">11 Fitzwilliam Place, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1925</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4565_img_3907_1"  type="Letter"  url="5efdd019c79a4dd02e297a220fdf2f4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4565_img_3907_2"  type="Letter"  url="63929e1796d661f1c41642195bfa23a8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4565_img_3907_1"/>
            University College, Dublin.  Department of Pathology and Bacteriology, <lb/>School of Medicine, <lb/>Cecilia Street, Dublin.   2nd Febry. '17   Dear Kirkpatrick,   I see you have put the V.D. business down for dis- <lb/>cussion this afternoon, but I am sorry to say that I am prevented <lb/>by another engagement from attending the meeting of the College.   You will observe that in Belfast they have gone to far as to <lb/>hold a <hi rend="underline">public</hi> meeting on the subject, at which is was resolved to es- <lb/>tablish a branch of the National Council for Combating Venereal Dis- <lb/>eases. The principal speaker was Professor Lindsay, and he was sup- <lb/>ported by the Bishop of Down, Sir John Byers and Captain W.J. Wilson <lb/>(Lecturer on Hygiene, Q.U.B.) (See current number of B.M.J. page 134). <lb/>Whether the state of feeling among the <seg type="del">general public</seg>  people  in Dublin is <lb/>quite ripe for a <hi rend="underline">public</hi> discussion of so delicate a matter I do not <lb/>know. It seems open to question, though it is not exactly easy to <lb/>state in words why we in Dublin should not be able to take action <lb/>which has been successfully taken in Belfast and Liverpool.   The course of action that seems to me least open to ob- <lb/>jection would be <seg type="del">for</seg>  that  the two Royal Colleges and the two Universities, <lb/>as representing the Medical profession, should meet and send up a small <lb/>deputation to the Local Government Board, asking them to take steps
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4565_img_3907_2"/>
            similar to those already taken by the Local Government Boards of <lb/>England and Scotland. (See enclosed reference "A")  In order to facilitate the discussion I have drawn up a <lb/>series of references, showing the leading steps that have been taken <lb/>in this matter in England and in Belfast during the past seven months. <lb/>With one exception they are all from the B.M.J., so that if the <lb/>numbers are available, the references can be at once looked up.   I remain, <lb/>Yours sincerely,   Dr. Edward J. MacWeeney   T.P.C. Kirkpatrick Esqr. B.A., M.D. <lb/>11, Fitzwilliam Place, <lb/>Dublin. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>