<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1092">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick, 2 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sir Arthur Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1974) to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) addressing the concerns of the Board of Doctor Steevens&#39; Hospital regarding the proposal of the new College of Nursing scheme.Sir Arthur Stanley was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers. From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>TPCK-2-6-1-3, TPCK-2-6-1-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1092</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0219">Sir Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-02-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1092_img_3243_1"  type="Letter"  url="9a38bb8884d4b2de55dec27c81813489.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1092_img_3243_2"  type="Letter"  url="13f129b76227a43c781e975747d70eb7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1092_img_3243_3"  type="Letter"  url="a758a3f42896e1a41967611e0144feca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1092_img_3243_1"/>
                83, PALL MALL,  LONDON, S.W.    2nd February 1916   Dear Sir,   I beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter <lb/>dated the 31st ultimo. I will answer your questions <lb/>in the order in which they stand :—   1) The certificates of the proposed College will <lb/>be given only to the nurses who have under gone a satisfactory <lb/>course of Hospital Training and passed the requisite <lb/>examinations of the College.  2) The general opinion as to the minimum length <lb/>of Hospital Training required to qualify a nurse for <lb/>membership of the College is three years in a Hospital <lb/>of 100 beds and upwards; but I think that some provision <lb/>will have to be made for the possibility of women <lb/>becoming members of the College who have had two years <lb/>training or who have trained in a Hospital of <lb/>less than 100 beds. These points will have to be <lb/>settled by the Consultative Committee which we propose <lb/>to set up. No doubt everything will turn on the kind of <lb/>examination which these latter classes of nurses will be <lb/>required to pass, but from the opinion given to me <lb/>by those whose advise I have been following I do not <lb/>think that this is a point which is likely to present <lb/>any insuperable difficulty.   3) It will certainly be a part of the scheme to <lb/>establish <seg type="del">a</seg> local centres for teaching and examination  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1092_img_3243_2"/>
              of Irish, Scotch and Provincial Nurses.  The idea of this College is receiving far more <lb/>support than I expected and I sincerely hope that it will <lb/>be approved by the Governors of Doctor Steevens' <lb/>Hospital. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  Arthur Stanley. <lb/>Chairman.   T. P. Kirkpatrick Esq.,  11 Fitzwilliam Place,  Dublin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1092_img_3243_3"/>
               Letter from Mr Stanley <lb/>February 2 1916 <lb/>Re <hi rend="underline">proposed College</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>