<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2968">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 16 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Wilfred Spender to his wife in which he expresses the hope that Lillian can move into her &#34;burrow&#34; (her new flat) as soon as possible. He discusses the Irish Question, and speculates that the current British Government will fall on the question of whether Ireland should get special treatment in regards to recruitment and conscription.

This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Captain Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender née Dean, (1880-1968). The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.

Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914, and served as an officer of the Ulster Division until 1916. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund during the war, and a member of the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps.


</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/106</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2968</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2968_img_2373_1"  type="Letter"  url="1120a8a0e0182c68ff7b9562ea1ee2be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2968_img_2373_2"  type="Letter"  url="e85182703d86e06d00e8d5f97d9395c4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2968_img_2373_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/106   16. Dec 15 <lb/> When is<lb/>Carson coming<lb/>out. I should<lb/>like to be<lb/>home then <lb/> My <seg type="unclear"></seg>     I too hope you will get your burrow quickly. The idea of a<lb/>thin little   &amp; running about looking into a   thin &amp; a corner then<lb/>&amp; wondering whether they will do for a big wolf is too touching, &amp;<lb/>I hope for this &amp; sake will soon come to an end. There is<lb/>another reason in that, this b w may be pouncing upon the<lb/>  a little earlier than he thought possible before. We may know<lb/>tomorrow what the orders are on the subject. If the 3 months limit<lb/>is  not  informed I shall <seg type="del">probably</seg> possibly have  a chance of flying about the 11th<lb/>otherwise about the 18th of January. Of course the whole thing is<lb/>very unsettled and may be stopped by a man at any time but these<lb/>are possibilities.      <seg type="unclear">R</seg> is being left to himself &amp; seems to me to be<lb/>losing touch a little. The Gen has no use for others<lb/>except as instrumnets of his fingers &amp; this is not the right<lb/><seg type="unclear">point in for G301</seg> &amp; R perhaps lacks the personality or perhaps<lb/>feels the instincts of the <seg type="unclear"></seg>  make friction undesirable.    Bonar <seg type="unclear"></seg>   speech in Wednesday's paper has done a<lb/>marvellous thing. It has actually silenced my criticism. The man<lb/>is so obviously honest so ready to sacrifice himself for the country<lb/>that one cannot help following him, but I cannot see how he<lb/>can live much longer with his coleagues of whom many hold such  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2968_img_2373_2"/>
             different ideals. I should not be surprised if this govenrment eventually<lb/>go out over an Irish question, i.e<lb/>Whether Ireland is or is not to<lb/>get sepcial treatment in recruiting or not. It seems to me to be a<lb/>hopeless impasse. The 10th Div seems to have done well at the Dardanelles<lb/>but I very much question whether the regiments were composed largely<lb/>of Irishmen this you may trust Rednow to make out that they<lb/>are all Nationalists, when we know they are less than half RC at<lb/>any rate.  I am sending this to Amy's. Please thank them very much<lb/>from me for looking after you &amp; giving you a change.  Toothbrush &amp; powder arrived safely. Plenty of lather! Many<lb/>thanks for useful Xmas present. It would be a really useful present for<lb/>most people at Xmas or as a New Year's gift done up with pink ribbon.  Gin still thinks we do nothing — &amp; R has not been able to convince<lb/>him. It's a pity. By the way, Singleton is a composer &amp; is sending<lb/>his latest to you as author's copy. Very kind of him. I hope you<lb/>will like them, main . . .  He has composed before under the name<lb/>of Corbett. He thinks you can have  them. Perhaps you can on<lb/>your way to try his former compositions before you write &amp; thank him.    Conf' reports an going in on staff. I believe they are good, but<lb/>that Capt WB is too junior for higher employment (in other words is useful<lb/>when he is). If this is really this can I would give a lot to<lb/>see it &amp; would face this Gin' stright off but those pass through Singleton<lb/>&amp; and unless they are   one does not see them &amp; is not even supposed to<lb/>know of their existence so one is powerless. It is a curious world<lb/>how one gets tied up. A pushing strong man like Winston would break<lb/>through of course but not you poor BW.   <lb/> W.B Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>