<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0781">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender discusses the progress of the war (making reference to the Russian Brusilov Offensive), asks Lillian to send him toothpaste and shaving soap, and thanks her for her kindness in sending packages to Spender&#39;s brother Rex.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/369</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/781</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0781_img_2316_1"  type="NULL"  url="01e62dffdfa0d0428600658053903744.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0781_img_2316_2"  type="NULL"  url="8d75e2434abb0aff3d2310981e4730ef.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0781_img_2316_1"/>
                31 July   My Pr   No letter I expect owing to your <lb/> weekend. Perhaps 2 are accumulating? Anyhow <lb/>I have been spoilt lately. I enclose nice <lb/> letters from Sir George &amp; Jessie which I must <lb/>answer.    Things did not progress very well yesterday <lb/>but luckily the Russian news is a good backup. <lb/>What we are doing here no doubt helps on that <lb/> side, but I do not change my views that no <lb/>decision can be looked for on this front unless <lb/>the Germans are forced to withdraw  large numbers  to the other <lb/> &amp; that tho' we may advance a little &amp; very <lb/>painfully we must exert all the economic <lb/> pressure we can &amp; continue to work at <sic>munitious </sic><lb/> munitions at the greatest speed possible &amp; <lb/> without holidays &amp; relaxation. We have not yet <lb/>felt the full pressure of the <sic>appaling</sic> wastage <lb/>yet, but after the war then will be great <lb/>distress at first I'm afraid.  By the way can you send me soon some  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0781_img_2316_2"/>
              shaving soap Boots Salvisan is quite good <lb/>and another tube of toothpaste about which latter <lb/>there is no hurry. I'm afraid with my &amp; Rex's <lb/> commissions you may be a bit harried but I <lb/>know you will look upon his requirements as a <lb/>labour of love. It does make a difference to him <lb/>to know he has someone who is glad to <lb/>attend to his wants. Why I said 2 a week <lb/>parcels is because in the trenches one has to <lb/>rely on post for everything except rations, &amp; <lb/>you know what that means. I should think <lb/>Fish flake powder might be a pleasant <lb/>change for him.   I have a letter waiting for Sir Ralph <lb/>so don't forget his address - no I will let <lb/>you forward it.   2 letters just come ! I must try &amp; <lb/> send you another page but have such a lot <lb/>of letters to answer. I send you some. <seg type="closer">  Your  b w WB Spender  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>