<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3531">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Christine Magorrian to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 15 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Christine Magorrian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Christine Magorrian to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), Christine expresses her sympathies regarding the execution of Hannas husband, Francis. She encourages Hanna to have faith in God through the hardship she is undergoing.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3531</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0773">Christine Magorrian</persName>
              <date>1916-05-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1577">Brooklyn House, Lurgan, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3531_img_2935_1"  type="Letter"  url="d52353e9a6ad07bc35bd8f5f18652825.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3531_img_2935_1"/>
              Brooklyn House<lb/><seg type="unclear">-gan</seg><lb/>Co. Armagh     15 May 1916   Dear Mrs Sheehy -Skeffington<lb/>I offer you my most sincere<lb/>sympathy in your very had bereavement.<lb/>It is <seg type="unclear">terrible</seg> to think that cousin<lb/>Thank met with such a very sad<lb/>death, (B.J.P.) God almighty is merciful<lb/>+ you must not worry. Father is<lb/>awfully annoyed + he asked me to write<lb/>you;  I sincerely hope little <seg type="unclear">Willie</seg> + yourself<lb/>will <seg type="unclear"></seg>the terrible cross you<lb/>have to endure. I know it is very hard<lb/>but God almighty will assist you.   Your sincere friend<lb/>Christine Magorrian<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg> Gordon<lb/>delay in writing<lb/>C. M  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>