<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0186">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Daulat Ram Kalia, 6 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter to an Indian student Daulat Ram Kalia. The letter is both an apology and a promise that action will take place in Kalia&#39;s favour. The incident that merited a letter is an article that was published in a newspaper in Dublin called the &#39;Eye-Opener&#39;. The paper printed an article with the heading &#39;Black Peril&#39; which attacked Indian students and indeed all people of dark skin. The letter says that the lord lieutenant, Lord Wimborne (1873–1939), has told police to warn the people responsible that if any more insulting and offensive articles are published serious action will be taken.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5575/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/186</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-04-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0290">Daulat Ram Kalia</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0770">21 Synge Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0186_img_1322_1"  type="Letter"  url="b721ad219eb38f2bb09a5b4e5371d608.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0186_img_1322_1"/>
                6 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April, 1916    No. 5575  Sir,   With reference to the letter you addressed to <lb/> the Private Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant, I have <lb/> to inform you that your representations with regard <lb/> to attacks made upon Indian students in articles <lb/> headed 'The Black Peril' contained in a newspaper <lb/> called 'The Eye-Opener' were laid before the Lord <lb/> Lieutenant who greatly regretted that Indian subjects <lb/> of His Majesty should have been subjected to the <lb/> annoyance complained of.   His Excellency directed the police to warn <lb/> the owners, printers, and publishers of the period- ical <lb/> in question that if they persisted in making <lb/> scurrilous attacks upon any class of the King's <lb/> loyal subjects, action of a serious kind would be <lb/> taken.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Sir, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,    D. R. Kalia, Esq.  21, Synge Street,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>