<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3612">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide Hannay to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 24 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Adelaide Hannay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Adelaide Hannay (c. 1865-1933) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) offering her sympathies over the news of Francis&#39; murder, which she has just received the details of. She closes by offering her help to Hanna in any way should she need it.

Adelaide &#39;Ada&#39; Susan Hannay (née Wynne) was the wife of Canon James Owen Hannay (1865-1950), a scholar and writer working under the pseudonym of George A. Birmingham. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3612</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0252">Adelaide Hannay</persName>
              <date>1916-05-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0257">Mount Mapas, Killiney, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1933</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3612_img_3011_1"  type="Letter"  url="05bd40c543913fb6d188240025067a53.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3612_img_3011_2"  type="Letter"  url="282dbec4f95e6792cfe8a03a24706d81.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3612_img_3011_1"/>
             May 24, 1916   Mount Mapas,<lb/>Killiney,<lb/>Co. Dublin    Dear Mrs Sheehy Skeffington,   I hope letters are not a mere<lb/>nuisance to you &amp; that you<lb/>wont think of bothering to answer<lb/>this one. I do want to tell you<lb/>how much &amp; deeply I've been<lb/>sympathising with you. Words<lb/>quite fail one, but you know<lb/>you have the sympathy of every<lb/>Irish heart in this awful time.<lb/>Not only sympathy for you<lb/>but rage fills all our hearts —<lb/>My husband writes — just got<lb/>(being much delayed) the paper<lb/>with the whole of Mrs Sheehy Skeffington's 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3612_img_3011_2"/>
             statement. I don't wonder Dillon<lb/>ran amok in the H. of C. with<lb/>that story in his mind — well<lb/>he says a great deal more I'd<lb/>better not write.  I don't know if it can be any help<lb/>to you to know how much<lb/>every one is feeling for you &amp;<lb/>your little boy.   Yours very sincerely   A.S.Hannay 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>