<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3608">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mary Scarlett to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 7 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mary E. Scarlett</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Mary E. Scarlett (c. 1869-1948) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) sending her sympathies regarding the death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. She writes about the virtues of his life and his devotion towards the causes he stood for, saying she and others admired him greatly. .

Mary Scarlett was a schoolteacher and fluent Irish speaker. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3608</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1363">Mary E. Scarlett</persName>
              <date>1916-05-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0351">Ethel Lodge, Annaville, Ranelagh, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1948</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3608_img_3008_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc12577d4832475efbec0b98d6a1ed1d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3608_img_3008_2"  type="Letter"  url="fcc4b1b2a1e6b1ce7d4b09294fbdbf44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3608_img_3008_3"  type="Letter"  url="cbfd083076dea56e005c55fa0e9ba18e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3608_img_3008_1"/>
             May 7, 1916   White Lodge<lb/>  <seg type="unclear">Carnlough</seg>     My dear Mrs Sheehy-Skeffington   I hope you will<lb/>forgive my troubling you with<lb/>a few words just to say<lb/>that I am thinking of you,<lb/>and to offer you my deep<lb/>and respectful sympathy<lb/>in this time of supreme<lb/>trial.  I always admired your<lb/>husband and shall -<lb/>with very mane others here &amp;<lb/>elsewhere - always revere 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3608_img_3008_2"/>
            his memory for the life he<lb/>lived and the death he<lb/>died. He was so absolutely<lb/>fearless and devoted to the<lb/>causes for which he worked,<lb/>without even a thought of<lb/>personal advantage. Surely<lb/>such a life though not long<lb/>in years must have<lb/>accomplished much, and<lb/>will still continue to be<lb/>a force &amp; influence in those<lb/>who are left. In saying this about Mr.<lb/>Skeffington's work I know the<lb/> work was not his alone but<lb/>yours also, that you were<lb/>connected  in work &amp; interests<lb/>as few husbands &amp; wives were -<lb/>which makes your loss the more<lb/>peculiar.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3608_img_3008_3"/>
             I will not say more, as the<lb/>tragedy of things are present -<lb/>a tragedy which you are bearing<lb/>the full brunt of - is too great<lb/>for words.  But I have known you and<lb/>thought of you with friendship<lb/>for as many years I did not<lb/>like to be silent.  Yours in sincere sympathy<lb/>Mary E. Scarlett 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>