<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5251">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 3, December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Discusses plans for forthcoming leave. William Upton Tyrrell to bring Victoria Mary &#34;Minnie&#34; Tyrell to Moyvalley.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5251</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0190">Portobello Barracks, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5251_img_None_1"  url="2e57f2a81cd0ed3751389434d9cd1690.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5251_img_None_2"  url="8064927266824d815f3cb831ec35c008.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5251_img_None_3"  url="d1a6de03c61e16d2a0e46c167c57b523.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5251_img_0_1"/>
              Cortobello Barracks<lb/>Dublin    3 Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 1915    My dearest Daddy.   I can write you a more<lb/>sensible letter now.  I had a very nice letter<lb/>from Miss Reilly this morning<lb/>and she says I may bring<lb/>Minnie home with me.  I will get leave for four<lb/>days from Monday and will<lb/>be able to come down on<lb/>Sunday night. I flashed 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5251_img_0_2"/>
             for leave before Monday<lb/>I would have to go on Saturday<lb/>and come back on Tuesday so<lb/>I think we will get more<lb/>shooting the other way so you<lb/>see there is method in my<lb/>madness.  Of course I may not go<lb/>out for some time but it is<lb/>better to take leave now and<lb/>of course if I do not go till<lb/>after Xmas I will get a<lb/>couple of days there as well.  I was talking to Mr. White<lb/>yesterday and if you can<lb/>get the shoot on he will<lb/>come but I only asked him<lb/>provisionally (not thinking<lb/>of provisions). Also <seg type="unclear">hope</seg> would<lb/>probably be able to come down<lb/>for the day and so we<lb/>might take up a few guns.  I sent Bernie his parcel<lb/>yesterday afternoon and<lb/>enclose you Kavanagh's receipt<lb/>and post office receipt.  I could not get glove<lb/>needles anywhere though I<lb/>tried two other places.  I have got a full kit<lb/>and am quite ready 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5251_img_0_3"/>
             for any emergency now.<lb/>I had Capt. Graham's advice<lb/>about it and he gave it<lb/>from experience. You had<lb/>better send Miss Reilly a<lb/>wire when you <sic>gett</sic> this to<lb/>say you are satisified that<lb/>Minnie should come down<lb/>with me.  Unless you get further<lb/>word from me expect<lb/>both of us at Moyvally<lb/>on Sunday night by night<lb/>mail.   No news so with best love    Your most affec Son Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>