<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4362">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert Samuel to Edward Carson, 21 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert Samuel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Herbert Samuel (1870-1963) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.. Samuel, liberal politician, served as Home Secretary of the British Government 1916. During the Great War he initiated legislation which offered thousands of Russian refugees a choice between conscription into the British Army, or returning to Russia for military service. Samuel resigned as Home Secretary following Asquith&#39;s replacement by David Lloyd George.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/27</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4362</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1103">Herbert Samuel</persName>
              <date>1916-07-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1993">Home Office, Whitehall, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1963</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4362_img_3718_1"  type="Letter"  url="503f59b20b2741ba7b9f2514661e91cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4362_img_3718_2"  type="Letter"  url="762253f878bc9565cc62b4e202300fec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4362_img_3718_3"  type="Letter"  url="4deb1e40d1bf9a45d83a95b64b9558eb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4362_img_3718_4"  type="Letter"  url="8186ccd5eeda31b935824cb86dc16cbc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4362_img_3718_5"  type="Letter"  url="24f84d5db4108566fafb82ef28bfea06.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4362_img_3718_6"  type="Letter"  url="211870f5455155546b5db92e54016050.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4362_img_3718_1"/>
             Personal &amp; Private   Home Office, <lb/>Whitehall, <lb/>S.W.   July 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1916   Dear Carson,   If any alteration is made <lb/>in the terms of the clause <lb/>agreed to by Redmond and <lb/>yourself regarding the <lb/>provisional character of <lb/>the Irish Bill, the result <lb/>must be our immediate <lb/>support, and Nationalists <lb/>throughout Ireland will <lb/>claim that the failure
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4362_img_3718_2"/>
             2.  of the settlement is due to <lb/>their having been deceived as <lb/>to the terms to be embodied <lb/>in the Bill. It is obvious <lb/>that the task of maintaining <lb/>peace and order in Ireland <lb/>will be rendered far more <lb/>difficult if the work takes <lb/>place in such circumstances. <lb/>On the other hand the Cabinet <lb/>recognises that it is necessary to meet your point that it <lb/>must be made quite clear <lb/>to the Ulster counties that <lb/>they will not automatically <lb/>be swept into Home Rule <lb/>Ireland through any <lb/>failure to make an Order in <lb/>Council or for any other <lb/>reason, but that the re-union <lb/>of Ireland can only be <lb/>effected by the special and <lb/>deliberate action of the <lb/>Imperial Parliament. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4362_img_3718_3"/>
             The only way that I can <lb/>see to meet this situation <lb/>is to keep the sub. section <lb/>relating to the provisional <lb/>character of the measure <lb/>untouched, and to add to <lb/>it a <seg type="unclear">declaratory</seg> sub. section <lb/>that will embody your <lb/>point in specific terms. <lb/>I enclose the draft which <lb/> has drawn to effect <lb/>this purpose. Whether Redmond <lb/>will agree I do not know, <lb/>  but  before discussing the
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4362_img_3718_4"/>
            point with him or laying <lb/>it before the Cabinet I <lb/>should be glad to know <lb/>whether you concur. I hope <lb/>you will agree that if a <lb/><seg type="unclear">surprise</seg> is to come, it had <lb/>better be on a disagreement <lb/>on an additional declaration <lb/>such as this   because <lb/>of an alteration in the <lb/>wording of the agreed terms.
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4362_img_3718_5"/>
            The suggestion you made <lb/>to   as to the form of <lb/>the first clause can be <lb/>adapted without difficulty. <lb/>I enclose the re-draft. <lb/>I am not sending the whole <lb/>Bill because there is to be <lb/>a Conference on it this <lb/>afternoon with   &amp; <lb/>Sir H. Robinson, and further <lb/>alterations will no doubt be  made. <lb/> With respect to the name <lb/>for the six counties, I appreciate <lb/>your objection to the title of <lb/>"the excluded area." On the <lb/>other hand to call them <lb/>"North Ireland" will be taken <lb/>in the rest of the country <lb/>as hoisting the flag of a <lb/>permanent separation and as <lb/>the  definite  constitution of a <seg type="del">definite</seg> <lb/>new state within the Empire, <lb/>(which is not, I believe, what you have in view) <lb/>It must   so offend
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4362_img_3718_6"/>
            the sentiment of great numbers <lb/>of people as to intensify in <lb/>a high degree the opposition <lb/>to the whole scheme. I would <lb/>therefore propose to call <lb/>them in the Bill what we <lb/>are all now calling them <lb/>in these discussions "The <lb/>Six Counties." I sincerely <lb/>hope that you will not <lb/>dissent.   Yours very truly,  <lb/> Herbert Samuel.   P.S. The Cabinet <seg type="unclear">meeting</seg> for this mornings has been postponed till <lb/>tomorrow as <seg type="unclear">Ld</seg>George &amp; several others <lb/>had to be away to-day. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>