<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1695">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Lawson to Director General, Army Veterinary Service, 18 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Lawson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter of recommendation for Patrick Alphonsus Carroll.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Pat Carroll</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection, Carroll_Pat_8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1695</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0315">Henry Lawson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Director General, Army Veterinary Service</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1695_img_1152_1"  type="Letter"  url="d451c662d50fa90f54202c4c876b0944.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1695_img_1152_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="57ca0913951f6ccb69ef1a5d67a091c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1695_img_1152_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="e148a89387d2bfd76acb169ba3eb88ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1695_img_1152_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="b930f13e82dd77ff2de89eac12c2dc2a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1695_img_1152_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="b74b284a6ff6c75c61884e6a1ecd9dff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1695_img_1152_1"/>
             The Director-General, A.V.S., <lb/> War Office,<lb/> London, S,W.   With reference to your No. 1045/16 (V.D), <lb/> dated 11.1.16, herewith application of Mr P. A. Carroll, <lb/> M. R. C. V. S., Carlow, for a temporary commission in the <lb/> Army Veterinary Corps, which is recommended.   <seg type="unclear">E.J. Lawson</seg> , Major,  Lr. Castle Yard, <lb/>Dublin,   18.1.16  <lb/>D. A. B. V. S., Irish Command.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1695_img_1152_2"/>
             To His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for War.   I Patrick Alphonsus Carroll <lb/>of Carlow Ireland <lb/>being qualified to practice veterinary medicine and surgery, and being registered as <lb/>a member of the Royal College of Veterinary Surgeons, hereby offer to serve as a <lb/>Veterinary Surgeon to His Majesty's Forces, whether within or without the <lb/>United Kingdom on the following conditions:   1.The period of my service hereunder shall commence from the date of my <lb/>joining for duty, and shall continue until the termination of the War or until my <lb/>services are no longer required, whichever shall first happen.   2. My pay and allowances shall, for my first year of service, be the same as <lb/>as received by a Lieutenant, Army Veterinary Corps.   3. On completion of twelve months satisfactory service I shall, if my <lb/>services are further required, receive an advance of pay to 17/- a day together <lb/>with the temporary rank and allowances of a Captain, Army Veterinary Corps.   4. During the said period I will devote my whole time and professional skill <lb/>to my service hereunder.   5. In case I shall complete my service hereunder to your satisfaction In all <lb/>respects, I shall receive at the end of the said period a gratuity of sixty days. <lb/>full pay, in respect of each year or part of a year of service should my employment <lb/> be terminated during a year at the rate hereinbefore specified, but in case <lb/>I shall in any manner misconduct myself, or shall be (otherwise than through <lb/>illness or unavoidable accident) unfit in any respect for service hereunder, of which <lb/>misconduct or unfitness you shall be sole judge, you shall be at liberty from and <lb/>immediately after such misconduct or unfitness to discharge me from further 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1695_img_1152_3"/>
            service hereunder, and thereupon all pay and allowances shall cease, <lb/>and I shall not be entitled to any gratuity in respect of the year of service <lb/>during which such misconduct or unfitness occurs. <lb/>Dated this  18th day of January 1916   P.A.Carroll  (here sign) <lb/>Witness to the Signature of the said <lb/><hi rend="underline">Patrick Alphonsus Carroll</hi> <lb/><seg type="unclear">E.J.</seg> Lawson Major (Witness). <lb/>D.A.D.V.S. <hi rend="underline">L.C.</hi> <lb/>On behalf of the Secretary of State, I accept the forgoing offer. <lb/><hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">R. Pringle</seg></hi> <lb/>Director-General, Army Veterinary Service.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1695_img_1152_4"/>
            <!-- This is an application for a position in the Army Veterinary Services -->
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1695_img_1152_5"/>
            <!-- This is a medical certificate for the applicant to the position -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>