<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1373">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William O'Brien to Augustine Birrell, 26 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William O&#39;Brien</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by William O&#39;Brien (1881 - 1968), the president of the Dublin trades council, to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), chief secretary for Ireland. Birrell served as chief secretary from 1907 until his retirement in May 1916 in the aftermath of the Easter Rising, for which he accepted responsibility. William O&#39;Brien, was an active labour leader and trade union official. Although O&#39;Brien did not take part in the Easter rebellion of 1916 he was closely involved in its planning. and was interned in Frongoch for a month after its outbreak. Later in his career he became a Labour Party TD for Tipperary.This letter contains a resolution dealing with the control of shipping and protesting government inaction in allowing shipowners &#39;amass huge fortunes&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3733/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1373</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1436">William O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date>1916-02-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0657">Capel Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1373_img_726_1"  type="Letter"  url="401cf31afb0814f175b33eaea5da38dd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1373_img_726_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="9c57997920a847d1efbf1f41bed8ab4f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1373_img_726_1"/>
                Dublin United Trades Council  and  labour league  Trades Hall Capel S <hi rend="superscript">T</hi>.   Dublin    Feb. 26th. 1916.    The Right Hon. A. Birrell, M.P.,  Chief Secretary For Ireland.  .  Sir,   I am directed to forward you the inclosed resolution <lb/>dealing with the control of shipping.  <seg type="closer"> Faithfully yours,  W <hi rend="superscript">m</hi> O'Brien,  <lb/>Acting Secretary. </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1373_img_726_2"/>
              RESOLUTION X  That this Council, representing the workers of Dublin, <lb/>enters its strongest protest against the inaction of the <lb/>Government in allowing the shipowners to amass huge fortunes <lb/>by exploiting the necessities of the people, and declares <lb/>that the high freightage is almost entirely responsible for <lb/>the unprecedented increase in the cost of Food; that we demand <lb/>that the Government shall immediately take over the entire <lb/>Mercantile Marine, as the only method calculated to be effec- <lb/>tive in stopping this shameful robbery of the people, which <lb/>will continue so long as shipping remains a private monopoly. <lb/>That copies of the foregoing be forwarded to the Prime Minister, <lb/>the President of the Board of Trade, the Chief Secretary for <lb/>Ireland, Mr. J. E. Redmond, M.P., and Mr. G.J.Wardle, M.P.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>