<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5262">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 6, July, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell, who is quite partial to café au lait, mentions that Slade&#39;s triple cream is the best coffee he has &#34;ever tastes anywhere&#34;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5262</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-07-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5262_img_None_1"  url="db11334ca805aed1d6c8f40eeb42af61.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5262_img_None_2"  url="51f52002b7a51c4107f9796e233a7e5d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5262_img_0_1"/>
              6 July 1917    My dearest Mamy   Such a feast of letters as I<lb/>got just now from everyone. They<lb/>took a little longer than usual<lb/>but I think we are in a new postal<lb/>district which helps to explain.  They were all written on the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.<lb/>Yesterday I got your splendid<lb/>parcel. Really you are the very<lb/>best. I am glad my clothes<lb/>turned up. I was beginning to think<lb/>they had gone west. Before I forget<lb/>tell Aunt Alice that the Stead I<lb/>knew was wounded and I hear<lb/>is getting on well.  I went the other day to have a<lb/>look at the place where a great<lb/>battle was fought just over 500 years<lb/>ago. Things are fairly changed<lb/>since then I expect. I am off the cigs now s the signal officer is back. I have another job for 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5262_img_0_2"/>
             10 days or so now. I am acting<lb/>as <seg type="unclear">Junior</seg> Master while that most<lb/>important <seg type="unclear">personage</seg> is on leave.  It is an absurd thing to put<lb/>me on to as I know nothing about<lb/>it. I would much rather go to<lb/>my company where I have<lb/>something to do.  Weather is glorious again<lb/>now.  I am afraid Mrs Howe does not<lb/>know the Wallers. At least I<lb/>have never heard her mention<lb/>them and she told me she did<lb/>not know any one down there<lb/>at all.  I had a long letter from Mr. B<lb/>today too.  The toffee you send<lb/>me called Slades Triple Cream<lb/>is the nicest I have ever<lb/>tasted anywhere. No news<lb/>but will write again soon.   Best love<lb/>Willie     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>