<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4176">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Adam Duffin to his daughter Dorothy Duffin, 7 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Adam Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by Adam Duffin (1841 – 1924) to his daughter, Dorothy Duffin (b. 1881). 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4176</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0513">Adam Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4176_img_3549_1"  type="Letter"  url="f6d4c94498860919b3d19014f24aeeae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4176_img_3549_2"  type="Letter"  url="58f43ffcec1b4fb3516562b827210606.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4176_img_3549_3"  type="Letter"  url="a16a3f7a735430f9d514bcde764a6ee5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4176_img_3549_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/B   DUNOWEN, <lb/>BELFAST.   Sunday 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Nov. 1915   Dearest Dorothy   Your announcement of the <lb/>possibility, I may say <hi rend="underline">probability</hi> <lb/>of your marrying a man, so far <lb/>totally unknown to us, while full of <lb/>hope for your future happiness, still, <lb/>you can understand, makes me a <lb/>little anxious and I am glad <lb/> that you have entered into no bonds <lb/>irrevocable on either side, until <lb/>you have time to consider, even if <lb/>not <hi rend="underline">coolly</hi>, to consider the future &amp; <lb/>to become <seg type="del">pi</seg>  more  <seg type="unclear">completely</seg> <seg type="unclear">acquainted</seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4176_img_3549_2"/>
            <lb/>I am <hi rend="underline">sure</hi> you must have found <lb/>Mr <seg type="del">Horsbrugh</seg> a clean, straight man <lb/>and a gentleman, or you would not <lb/>have listened to him, and so am <lb/>confident that it will be all right <lb/>but I do wish we could see and <lb/>know him and learn something <lb/>of his family, surroundings. I am <lb/>enclosing a note to him <seg type="del">so</seg>which will <lb/>give him an opportunity of saying <lb/>something of himself &amp; his position, <lb/>as I have no doubt he will wish <lb/>to do. I wonder if he is connected <lb/>with the <seg type="del">Horsbrughs</seg> of Peebleshire, one <lb/>of whom married Sir Andrew Porter. <lb/>I was best man at his wedding, so many <lb/>long years ago.    I need hardly tell you, dearest child <lb/>how very, very glad I shall be to <lb/> see you united to a man who really <lb/>loves and is worthy of your hand I <lb/>shall miss you terribly at home, <lb/>perhaps more than any of the others. <lb/>I have always fancied that you <lb/>had most apprehension of all the <lb/>anxieties I have tried to keep to <lb/>myself &amp; had your silent sympathy.   I am glad to tell you that they <lb/>weigh less heavily on me now <seg type="del">than</seg> <lb/>they have done for years, &amp; I am <lb/>very happy in thinking how splendidly <lb/>you have <hi rend="underline">all</hi> come out &amp; made us <lb/>proud of you. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4176_img_3549_3"/>
             Now, dear, you will be wise &amp; I am <lb/>sure you know that your happiness <lb/>&amp; such assurance of the future as <lb/>is possible is the one thought of <lb/>all of us at home.   Your loving father   Adam Duffin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>