<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4387">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to her aunt, 18 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers; D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4387</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0733">3rd London General Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4387_img_3741_1"  type="Letter"  url="bc175bafa820fb68f54da6ac27a554a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4387_img_3741_2"  type="Letter"  url="197741f9508da4492ca0b0e915e5c92e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4387_img_3741_3"  type="Letter"  url="1ca3ac12201ff04eef5bb6ceaddd9200.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4387_img_3741_1"/>
             3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> London General Hospital   Nov. 18. 1915   Dear Auntie Cha:   Thank you ever so much for your <lb/>kind letter; I am quite alright again <lb/>and busy at work I am glad to say, <lb/>my neck got better quite quickly, though <lb/>it was rather uncomfortable at the time. I <lb/>think it was this cold frosty weather <lb/>coming on so suddenly, we have had <lb/>snow on the ground for two days <lb/>now. Thank you all ever so much for <lb/>offering to give me the sports coat, but <lb/>I have a nice warm woolen one <lb/>that I wear under my cloak when I <lb/>am out so I am quite well off <lb/>that way. It was kind of you to <lb/>think of it.   Thank Auntie B. And Aunt Ellen <lb/>for the verses they sent, I so seldom see
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4387_img_3741_2"/>
            the papers that I miss all the new things <lb/> that come out. I like Miss Maitlands' <lb/>especially; it is such a nice idea.   All the streets and houses are kept <lb/>so dark at night it is quite hard <lb/>to find one's way about. I went <lb/>to the S. Kensington Museum the other day, <lb/>just an easy bus ride from here, <lb/>and got so interested in all the things <lb/>to see there that I had to rush <lb/>back in a great hurry. They have <lb/>exhibits there now showing how food <lb/>gets infected by different germs and <lb/>how they attack grains etc, and telling <lb/>you how to get rid of them. I <lb/>discovered such a lot of weird animals <lb/>too that I had never even heard of <lb/>before.   The doctor gave me a tonic to <lb/>take and one of my patients, such <lb/>a funny little boy, was so delighted <lb/>that <seg type="del">I ha</seg> it was my turn to be <lb/>dosed too, that he always makes <lb/>me drink my medicine so that he <lb/>he can see that I take it properly.   It is very exciting news about Dorothy <lb/>and I am longing to see him. I do <lb/>hope he is really nice; I am sure <lb/>he must be. Di sounds so happy.    I am still in the same ward, <lb/>and we have been very full up <lb/>lately, so many come back deaf or <lb/>with bad ears from exposure. The <lb/>doctor is such a clever man, and <lb/>the head sister so nice to work under, <lb/>I think the men are well-looked after <lb/>but one feels one really must do <lb/>everything one can for them. It <lb/>was really sad this week, one poor
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4387_img_3741_3"/>
            patient who was being sent back to his <lb/>depot was so depressed that he tried <lb/>to poison himself. Fortunately the <lb/>bottle he took, although marked poison, <lb/>wasn't a very strong lotion and, <lb/>after making him very sick he <lb/>got alright and was being moved to <lb/>the detention ward. I was so sorry <lb/>for him - he was quite a nice man, <lb/>and I think being at the front had <lb/>upset his nerves a great deal.   Twenty-five Australian nurses have <lb/>just arrived to help, nice tall, capable <lb/>looking women. This place is wonderful <lb/>the way it grows and grows, it is <lb/>quite a little town now.   Best love to you all, I wish I could <lb/>fly over and see you all and have <lb/>a nice chat. Please thank Auntie D. <lb/>for the Strandtown Chrysanthemums.   Your loving   Celia 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>