<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1079">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eileen Coffey to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eileen A Coffey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Eileen Coffey, matron in Barrington Hospital, to Thomas Percy Kikrpatrick regarding the proposed establishment of a college of nursing. Coffey writes that she does not quite understand the proposal but fears it would not be in the best interest of provincial hospitals.From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-3-15-8, RCPI-2-3-3-15-8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1079</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0245">Eileen A Coffey</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1828">Barrington&#39;s Hospital, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1079_img_3224_1"  type="Letter"  url="35c17f41d0dd97af10e15930f8f01349.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1079_img_3224_1"/>
               BARRINGTON'S HOSPITAL,  LIMERICK.    <hi rend="underline">March 31 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi>   Dear D. Kirkpatrick,   In reply to your letter<lb/>re. College of Nursing. I do<lb/>not understand much<lb/>about it but I fear<lb/>it would not be for the<lb/>advantage of the<lb/>Provincial Hospitals. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly  E. A. Coffey<lb/>Matron  </seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>