<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1338">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 22 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.James talks of marriage plans and plans to visit in near future. Also mentions the Tullmore affair in the news.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1338</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-22T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1338_img_670_1"  type="Letter"  url="cabb33019178599513bb136ea32b3703.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1338_img_670_2"  type="Letter"  url="0a5cc69f2acb7eec5efb218b10d28f48.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1338_img_670_3"  type="Letter"  url="46cfca515b9026c191df5eb8a797515a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1338_img_670_1"/>
                39 Belgrave Square,  Rathmines,  Dublin.    22 March, 1916.   My dearest May,   I have started to write this <lb/>at home on Tuesday at very near midnight <lb/>and will finish it on Wednesday. The letter <lb/>I sent you toâday (Tuesday) was I fear a bit <lb/>abrupt at the end. Duffy (you remember meeting <lb/>him here) called in to go to dinner with <lb/>me and I had to close it up rather hurriedly. <lb/>If I left it over till the evening I would <lb/>probably have missed the post. About this watch <lb/>I am sorry that it is not giving satisfaction. <lb/>OâLeary in Hopkins told me  when I bought it  that all watches <lb/>of the kind are a bit flighty at the start and <lb/>he asked me to tell you to let him see this watch <lb/>the next time you were in town in order to <lb/>have it tested again. I shall call and see him  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1338_img_670_2"/>
              and tell him about it. If you like I could <lb/>take it back with me when returning to town after <lb/>my next visit (Saturday next I hope) and I could <lb/>bring it down to you at Easter. Please yourself <lb/>though in that respect. As it will be so short now <lb/>until you are here for good (my good) perhaps you <lb/>would like to wait till then. I donât see any reason <lb/>why it shouldnât keep good time all right because <lb/>it was tested beforehand for three days and was <lb/>then all right. Iâm glad to hear you are so fond <lb/>of it (I hope for my sake). You will see by my other <lb/>letter that I am anxious to go down either this <lb/>week end or next. If you decide to let me <lb/>come down this week end, I am half inclined <lb/>to come down on Saturday morning by the 9:15 from <lb/>Broadstone (11:15 at Castletown) so as to <lb/>have the day with you. The other train is later <lb/>and I have to change at Mullingar but perhaps <lb/>it would be inconvenient for you for me to come <lb/>on the early train as Saturday is generally a <cb/> busy day in every house and besides you might <lb/>be going to Mullingar and might prefer to <lb/>meet me there and be home with me. Iâll <lb/>leave it all to you as well as the decision <lb/>whether I come next Saturday or Saturday <lb/>week. If you say <hi rend="underline">next Saturday</hi> let me <lb/>know <hi rend="underline">by return</hi> which trains I am to come <lb/>on and whether I am to meet you at M'gar. <lb/>It will be delightful to have the details of the <lb/>marriage to talk over and to be able to settle <lb/>things once and for all. If you donât care for <lb/>Killarney itâs easy to go somewhere else. Iâll <lb/>make enquiries about other places down south <lb/>and we can go to one of them and perhaps <lb/>drop in at Killarney for a day or two on our way <lb/>home. I donât mind where I go so long as <lb/>you go with me. As regards the dress Iâm afraid <lb/>Iâm a poor guide as to either colour or make <lb/>although I could tell you all right whether I <lb/>liked a dress or not. I was at last Mass on  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1338_img_670_3"/>
              Sunday and we had a passable sermon (quite good <lb/>for Rathmines) on St Joseph but Iâm sorry to say I <lb/>didnât pass very particular remarks on it. If I had <lb/>thought of your interest in St Joseph I should have <lb/>been more attentive.   Judging by the papers, you had a nice row <lb/>down in Tullamore on Monday night. I suppose you <lb/>have heard all about it by this. There must be a <lb/>queer crowd of the rowdy element there when such <lb/>things can happen. I was at another concert last <lb/>night run by Cope for his choir. Nora is going to <lb/>him for singing lessons hence my presence at it. <lb/>Iâm sending you the programme in case you might be <lb/>interested. It was very good all round but nobody <lb/>we know was performing. Am spun out of news <lb/>now so will shut up with my warmest love <lb/>and devotion.  <seg type="closer"> Your loving and faithful husband soon  James </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>