<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4329">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Clements to Edward Carson, 21 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Clements</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles Clements, 5th Earl of Leitrim (1879-1952) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Clements commanded the Ulster Volunteer Force in County Donegal, and arranged to run guns into the county in his yacht, SS Ganiamore, in 1913. During the First World War, Clements was commissioned a major in the 11th Service Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4329</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0875">Charles Clements</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0064">Endsleigh Palace Hospital, 25 Gordon Street, Endsleigh Gardens, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1952</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4329_img_3689_1"  type="Letter"  url="2dba5cebe518bba364a14df533711053.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4329_img_3689_2"  type="Letter"  url="7cc5e83d5edf4a1c96ec7783c2e5805f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4329_img_3689_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="5a0abb3fabddeaa9cc6edcf648af03d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4329_img_3689_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="7bc8e376ddbe3872920de76e3cc44868.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4329_img_3689_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="2ae9b9004ec0c870caf24190ae4934f5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4329_img_3689_1"/>
             D1507/1/17/23  89   Endsleigh Palace Hospltal<lb/><hi rend="underline">W.</hi><lb/>Leitrim    June 21. 16.    Dear Sir Edward   I know many of<lb/>my friends in the six counties, besides<lb/>the three, distinctly understood, that<lb/>the Unionist members in the Cabinet<lb/>desired that the pledge should be<lb/>broken, on the grounds of Imperial<lb/>necessity — It was several times<lb/>mentioned to me, that it was an<lb/>extraordinary thing, that they sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi><lb/>do so, &amp; the fact that had<lb/>done so, undoubtedly carried<lb/>great weight in coming to the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4329_img_3689_2"/>
             90  decision to carry out the<lb/>negotiations—  As there seems to be<lb/>some doubt, as to whether this<lb/>was or was not the case,<lb/>I have written the enclosed<lb/>letter to Mr. Bonar Law —  Yours sincerely  Leitrim 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4329_img_3689_3"/>
             d1507/a/17/24   Copy    Endsleigh Palace Hospital<lb/>Euston   91<lb/>PAGE 1 OF 2   June 21.16.    Dear Mr Bonar Law   Please forgive me<lb/>troubling you with a letter, upon a<lb/>matter, w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> concerns me deeply —  For the last 21 months I have been<lb/>serving with the Ulster Division, <hi rend="superscript">h</hi> I<lb/>may say was mainly recruited, on the<lb/>strength of the Prime Minister's pledge,<lb/>that Home Rule would not be brought<lb/>up again during the war—  As the leader of the Unionist<lb/>party in the House of Commons, you<lb/>assisted in this pledge being given,<lb/>but you may not realise all that 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4329_img_3689_4"/>
             92  this pledge means to the men now<lb/>fighting — It does not only mean<lb/>the political significance of Home Rule,<lb/>but also means the deepest anxiety<lb/>upon the part of these men for the<lb/>safety of their homes —  Rightly or wrongly they believe<lb/>that there will be riots &amp; bloodshed<lb/>upon Home Rule being put into<lb/>operation, &amp; after what has happened<lb/>I think these fears are justified.  I well recollect at the<lb/>time of our recruiting meetings, the<lb/>Prime Minister's pledge, as well<lb/>as the Defence of the Realm Act,<lb/>were quoted to assure them 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4329_img_3689_5"/>
                D1507/1/17/24  93  PAGE 2 0F 2 that they should have no fears for<lb/>the safety of their homes, whilst<lb/>they were on service —<lb/><lb/>I cannot say how strongly<lb/>I feel, that you should hold<lb/>yourself in honour bound to<lb/>respect that pledge — You cannot overestimate<lb/>the value in w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> It is held, by those<lb/>men, who are now, many of them,<lb/><seg type="del">going</seg> about to sacrifice their<lb/>lives because it was given. — 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>