<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2858">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 17 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

In this letter, Spender very briefly discusses the business of his working day, the unfairness of recent moves towards Home Rule, and the weather. He also wonders how he will make it through the next three months without seeing Lillian.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/315</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2858</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-06-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2858_img_2270_1"  type="NULL"  url="58b4b048b5f5e98926a8fd444020194e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2858_img_2270_2"  type="NULL"  url="2fa424f40447fc5880da3caa7aeefc9d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2858_img_2270_1"/>
             Still<lb/> <lb/>your <lb/>BW <lb/>WB <lb/>Spender   17 June   Very sorry no letter was <lb/>possible today in time for post <lb/>&amp; equally impossible now <lb/>but I am very well <lb/>tho' very busy.    I was out with G'OC <lb/>to see my wolf hole &amp; <lb/>it was quite touching to see <lb/>how nice it had been made   I realized that it was not <lb/>quite useless having let the <lb/>RE know it was for me as <lb/>it has evidently been a little <lb/>labour of kind hearts &amp; is <lb/>much better that the GOC!! <lb/>which is of course a long <lb/>way back.   Farnham is back &amp; had
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2858_img_2270_2"/>
            hoped to give me definite news <lb/>today but it has not come.   George was not authorised to <lb/>make the proposals for a settle- <lb/>ment now (!) it was not to <lb/>come in till the end of the war, <lb/> &amp; then has been the dickens of <lb/> a row, &amp; he may not now <lb/>get the other job.   Nice weather again at last. <lb/>A jolly little note from Luddy <lb/>which I will answer later. I <lb/>hope.    The Rummies are to begin <lb/>a big push today I believe.   I am so sorry for such <lb/>a poor little scrap now but <lb/>you wouldn't blame me if <lb/>you were here I know.    Wolf has not yet quite <lb/>forgotten a little pr, but I <lb/>expect he will do so if he doesn't <lb/>see her for another 3 months.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>