<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0150">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Henry Caunt to Herbert Henry Asquith, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Henry Caunt</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from a William Henry Caunt (b. 1879) of Cheshire to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), then Liberal Prime Minister of Great Britain. Caunt writes to complain about the low level of security on the Irish borders, which he sees as a threat to national security. Caunt claims he is writing as someone who was trapped in Dublin during the Rising during which stray shots posed a constant risk to one&#39;s life and that he feared the rebels. As a solution Caunt recommends that a house to house search should be carried out and conscription introduced in Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7554/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/150</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1190">William Henry Caunt</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1269">33 Nelson Street, Crewe, Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1814">Downing Street, Westminister, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0150_img_1274_1"  type="Letter"  url="e0f476b3cef8e6c0cb24c0a6bc0da2dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0150_img_1274_1"/>
                33, NELSON STREET,  C R E W E  CHESHIRE.    May 4th. 1916   Sir,   I feel it my public duty to bring to your<lb/> notice the comparatively lax scrutiny which is being exercised<lb/> in the case of persons passing from as well as to Ireland, and which,<lb/> from the point of view of national safety, I am convinced is<lb/> nothing like as thorough as the present state of affairs in<lb/> Ireland demand. I speak as one of those luckless subjects of<lb/> His Majesty who, until Monday evening last, was prevented from<lb/> leaving Dublin during Easter week owing to the ill-gotten purposes<lb/> of republican Irishmen, suffering much inconvenience, fright, and<lb/> constant risk of one's life from stray shots which flitted about<lb/> from one side, then the other, and all the unexpected outcome of an<lb/> innocent visit for Easter Sunday and Monday. I do not complain<lb/> so much of the scrutiny on the other side, xx xxxx as of the fact<lb/> that at Holyhead no person's landing from the Dublin S.S. Coy's<lb/> Steamer 'Munster' was challenged wither by a representative from<lb/> the Army, Navy, or Civic Police Authorities. Personally I expected<lb/> the Kingstown examination was but a preliminary, and not a final<lb/> one. I can assure you, in the face of political assertions to the<lb/> contrary from Irish M.P.s in Parliament, that the rebels have so <lb/> large a body of open and secret sympathisers as to demand the strict-<lb/> -est scrutiny by the authorities at each port to and from Ireland. A<lb/> house to house search here is imperative where arms and treason abound,<lb/> and it would be interesting to know how many Alien or Sein Fein Clergy<lb/> are presently enjoying liberty and immunity from suspicion. Why not<lb/> after this, compel every Irishmen to do his bit who can be spared? <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully, <lb/> William Henry Caunt   To the Right Hon:  H.H. ASQUITH, M.P. , P.C.,  DOWNING STREET,  WESTMINSTER.  S.W.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>