<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6505">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Miss Miller 29, June, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell describes his situation in France and wishes Miss Miller and her family well.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6505</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-06-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Miss Miller</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1929">Salisbury, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6505_img_None_1"  url="f840cc17f720e74c85cb4787ae609eb0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6505_img_None_2"  url="5f7a2f1ec88579ec7ea60e69814c8ca4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6505_img_0_1"/>
              29/6/17   My dear Miss Miller  Just a line to tell you all is well<lb/>here and I hope all is well with you.  It is quite a long time since I wrote to<lb/>you now as I have been rather busy<lb/>lately. Times have been somewhat lively<lb/>but now we are away back from the<lb/>line resting and enjoying ourselves<lb/>thoroughly. Get any amount of<lb/>strawberries etc.  It is the best place I<lb/>have ever come across out here.  I was not actually in the advance on the<lb/>7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> as I was sent back as reserve. However I<lb/>went up a few days after and had a<lb/>most interesting exciting and occassionally<lb/>uncomfortable time. The last time in we<lb/>lived for 6 days in a lovely boche dug<lb/>out. The scenes are absolutely indescribable.  The weather is very hot with frequent<lb/>heavy thunder storms.  I do not think I am any where near    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6505_img_0_2"/>
             your brother yet. I know who he<lb/>is with I think; so I will know if I do<lb/>get any where near.  I hope that by now your sister<lb/>has quite recovered from her illness.  I do not know where you are now<lb/>but will address this to Salisbury.  I get great letters from Minnie and<lb/>Bobby from school. They seem to be<lb/>having a great time and Bobby gets on<lb/>very well I think.  I found the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Battalion the other day<lb/>and spent a very pleasant afternoon<lb/>with many old friends.  All crops are very early out here.<lb/>They are working away at the hay<lb/>now. It makes things seem very<lb/>homelike.  No news so will shut up with<lb/>best love <seg type="del">from</seg>   Yours very Sincerely <lb/><hi rend="underline">Will Tyrrell</hi>       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>