<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4151">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to his family, 8 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/50</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4151</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4151_img_3525_1"  type="Letter"  url="0d72bdf0270a58a928071a3568483397.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4151_img_3525_2"  type="Letter"  url="62487f293912d32b0fc7529e27e0abc5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4151_img_3525_3"  type="Letter"  url="0bb15cc8e56dda2ac61ca50044e0761c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4151_img_3525_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Mater</seg> <lb/>Mab <lb/>Edmund <lb/><seg type="del">Rex</seg>   <hi rend="underline">Please return finally to Lil</hi>   Nov. 8.   My Dear folks   I wish I could have joined the other 2 at the family <lb/>reunion at  No  24, but I hope this may not be impossible in 1916, <lb/>though certainly the present situation shows no sign of that being <lb/>possible yet. I wonder how Rex found his Bagley wood nest, <lb/>&amp; expect he found it as hard as any school boy to turn back after <lb/>his holiday. I am awaiting further news of him rather <lb/>anxiously, as I have heard rumours of a change in the command <lb/>of his battalion which if true I should regret. In fact I hope he <lb/>will then start the uphill work of training men in the new <lb/>19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> battalion.   I have been preety busy these last 3 days as Col Russell <lb/>has been ill, tho' I hope it is merely a bad cold, which however <lb/>he has succeeded in making me share - very annoying as I don't <lb/>feel as if I had caught one on my own.   Yesterday I went in his place with the general to the <lb/>conference of the Generals of our corps, which tho' like most confer- <lb/>ences in being rather round talking was of course very interesting to <lb/>me, &amp; brought me into touch with various senior officers whom I <lb/>had not previously met. One of them who was in command of <lb/>troops at Belfast 2 years ago a certain Count. He was less affable <lb/>than  2 of  the others <seg type="del">?</seg>, who strange to say were formerly both mentioned as <lb/>possible Commanders for this Division! 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4151_img_3525_2"/>
             We had a long drive back, but luckily got in just before Col <lb/>Hudson an old gunner friend  arrived , whom I got appointed at the War <lb/>office, &amp; who is now Col Gen' Staff of the present army.   We had a long talk, &amp; he has just been presented with the <lb/>Legion of <sic>honeur</sic>, for having acted as guide to the French <lb/>President during the Kings recent visit. I told him that <lb/>with his rosette in his button hole he will never have to <lb/>take a railway ticket again when travelling in France.   I have either got a sting or <sic>chiblains</sic> on my hands, I <lb/>think the latter which itch violently so I can sympathize <lb/>with 2 of the family who favour these unnecessary winter <lb/>luxuries.   I wish I had known about <seg type="unclear">Jessie's</seg> nephew in the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>Worcester's as this was the battalion I was with a fortnight <lb/>ago, but I hope to see them again &amp; will take the chance <lb/>of asking after him. I am glad he is in this part of <lb/>the country rather than in the lower wetter portion <lb/>elsewhere   I get long &amp; rather sad letters from my old gen' &amp; Col <lb/>Craig. The latter strongly hopes that our recruiting will not be <lb/>successful without National Service, as it may very possibly lead the <lb/>politicians to end the war by a compromise with Germany, in which <lb/>case our politicians would be very bad as national service would be impossible
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4151_img_3525_3"/>
            after the war whilst Germany would be busy training. Craig <lb/><sic>things</sic> such a compromise quite likely won soon   The rumours about Kitchener are rather disconcerting. <lb/>Unless he has gone to give a decision about <seg type="unclear">Serbian</seg> operations <lb/>it will look like his having left whilst the reorganisation of the <lb/>General Staff at home is being arranged, in which case he will <lb/>almost certainly not care to return as War Minister.   I see very little of the French people here. The village <lb/>we are in is exceptionally quiet &amp; nearly all the people are <lb/>in mourning. They don't seem particularly friendly, but <lb/>on the other hand they take very little interest in <seg type="del">th</seg> our <lb/>affairs tho' Douglas my servant takes a different view as to this, <lb/>since he always locks my door to keep out  my ancient  Madame who <lb/>likes to follow him &amp; talk, rather to his embarrassment, <lb/>&amp; as he can't talk French &amp; she no English I should have <lb/>thought conversation would soon have dried up,   I should like further news of Edmund as he only <lb/>told me that his company was in a very uncertain position &amp; <lb/>that they expected to move, since when nothing further has <lb/>turned up.   Best love   Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>