<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3177">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nicholas Hurst to Thomas Tyner, 24 November 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nicholas Hirst</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Captain Nicholas Hurst to Thomas Tyner (1856). Hurst writes an apologetic letter to Tyner about the death of his son, Goodwin (1896-1916), during the battle of Ginchy. According to Hurst, three officers, Hurst, Goodwin and Dalton, survived the initial attack on the 9 September. Early in the morning of the 10th, Goodwin was hit by a stray bullet and died of wounds at a casualty clearing station shortly after. 

The Tyner family moved from Cork to Wicklow but Goodwin was working in Cork prior to his signing up. Both Dalton and Hurst were awarded medals for their actions at Ginchy. Hurst would survive the war.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3177</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0137">Nicholas Hirst</persName>
              <date>1916-11-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1527">9th Royal Dublin Fus B.E.F , France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas Tyner</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3177_img_2600_1"  type="NULL"  url="c2c57569ce21a07952dd5af91e219fc1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3177_img_2600_2"  type="NULL"  url="a901f37b886db82042f2df0275bf5717.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3177_img_2600_3"  type="NULL"  url="af6b60d35d99a49b53e2ac47801d0a50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3177_img_2600_4"  type="NULL"  url="b3bc2c3acda43e7d5f0185f09b191ca6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3177_img_2600_1"/>
             9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> R Dublin Fus<lb/>B.E.F<lb/>France   24/11/16   Dear Mr Tyner   It is with the<lb/>greatest sorrow &amp; sympathy<lb/>that I write these few<lb/>lines to tell you something<lb/>concerning the death of<lb/>your son. The news<lb/>of Goodwin's death came<lb/>as a great blow to me,<lb/>and at first I could<lb/>not believe it.     After the capture 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3177_img_2600_2"/>
            of Ginchy on Sept 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> there <lb/>were only three officers <lb/>left unwounded with the <lb/>battalion — Goodwin, a chap <lb/>called Dalton and myself.    I was with Goodwin <lb/>during the attack in the <lb/>afternoon about 5 pm, and <lb/>we were together during <lb/>the night until relieved <lb/>by another regiment.    During the relief about <lb/>4 am on morning on Sept 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>he &amp; I were walking about <lb/>collecting our me in one <lb/>spot before marching out <lb/>when he got hit by a
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3177_img_2600_3"/>
            stray bullet in the right <lb/>thigh. I had him dressed <lb/>by the Stretcher bearers. He <lb/>appeared to me conscious and <lb/>cheery and spoke to me before <lb/>going back, but was naturally <lb/>very weak due to loss of <lb/> blood and little food that <lb/>day. I got the Stretcher <lb/>bearers to take him to <lb/>the dressing Station, but I <lb/>was horrified when the <lb/>told me later that he <lb/>died just on arriving there <lb/>about 4.30am.   I have just come <lb/>back from leave and was
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3177_img_2600_4"/>
            speaking to Mr Vickery who <lb/>had a letter from Rev Caldwell <lb/>asking for information about <lb/>Goodwin.    He and I have been <lb/>together in our military life <lb/>for the past 17 months and <lb/>were at Cork Kinsale and <lb/>Moore Park together and also <lb/>came to France the same day.   He is greatly missed in <lb/>the battln as he was a general <lb/>favourite with officers &amp; men.   Please accept my deepest <lb/>sympathy in your sad bereavement.    Yrs very Sincerely   Nicholas Hurst. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>