<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0951">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph E. Devlin to the Urban District Council, Longford, 11 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph E. Devlin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Joseph E. Devlin, assistant secretary to the Local Government Board, to the Longford Urban District Council concerning the Housing of the Working Classes (Ireland) Act 1908.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Longford County Archives Service</repository>
                  <collection>LUDC-1-3-1916-6-6, LUDC-1-3-1916-6-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/951</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0998">Joseph E. Devlin</persName>
              <date>1916-05-11T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1620">Local Government Board, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0870">Urban District Council, Longford</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0951_img_2766_1"  type="Letter"  url="a2cb870070d75bc890340f6d0e8e1e5e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0951_img_2766_1"/>
                Local for Board Dublin    11 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916    Sir   — Adverting to the Certificate forwarded <lb/>in the Board's letter of the 10 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ultimo, made in <lb/>persuance of the provisions of Section 5 of the Housing <lb/>of the Working Classes (Ireland) 1908, I am <lb/>directed by the Local for Board for Ireland, to <lb/>inform the Layford Urban Dist Council that a <lb/>sum of £6,133:13:4 in Standing to the Credit of the <lb/>Housing Fund on the 31 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of March last is available <lb/>for distribution in respect of £33.61:19:3 the <lb/>total liabilities of local authorities under the <lb/>section referred to —   The proportion amount of the Fund payable <lb/>to the Urban District Council in respect of the <lb/>liabilities incurred by them is therefore £62:14:3   Instructions have been given for the payment of that <lb/>amount to the Treasurer for the Local Authority.  <seg type="closer"> I am Sir <lb/>Your obed <hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Serv <hi rend="superscript">t</hi>  J E Devlin  Ass <hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Secty   The Clerk  Urban Dist Council  Longford  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>