<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1072">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph O'Carroll to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 1 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Francis O&#39;Carroll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Joseph Francis O&#39;Carroll (1856-1942) to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick expressing his misgivings about his capabilities to preform as President of the College should Dr Bewley choose to defer his term.From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T91-3, RCPI-2-3-1-58-T91-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1072</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0000">Joseph Francis O&#39;Carroll</persName>
              <date>1916-10-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0195">43 Merrion Square, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1072_img_3213_1"  type="Letter"  url="4b94191f67ece1254749d19f8ebb0393.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1072_img_3213_1"/>
                43, MERRION SQUARE,  DUBLIN.    1st Oct. 1916   My dear Registrar,   I hoped very sincerely <lb/>that D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Bewley would take the Residency, to <lb/>which the votes of the College would have elected <lb/>him unanimously as against any other single <lb/>Fellow of the College. If however he desires to <lb/>defer his term of office, I feel that it is my <lb/>duty to the College, as it is a very great homour <lb/>to myself, to allow my name to go forward <lb/>as a candidate at the final election. But I <lb/>am so little confident of my ability to fill the <lb/>high position of President according to the Standards <lb/>set by the Presidents to whom I have known that <lb/>I should not feel at all displeased if some <lb/>more worthy candidate would be found in the <lb/>meantime. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely  Joseph O' Carroll   T. Percy Kirkpatrick Esq  MD. F.R.C.P.I.  Registrar, R.C.P.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>