<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0940">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Slevin to the Longford Urban District Council [December 1915]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Slevin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Joseph Slevin, town surveyor for Longford, regarding maintenance of house along the back of St. Mel&#39;s Road in Longford town.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Longford County Archives Service</repository>
                  <collection>LUDC-1-3-1915-12-7, LUDC-1-3-1915-12-7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/940</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0938">Joseph Slevin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-01T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0940_img_2746_1"  type="Letter"  url="adc6ebf4958aa02ded3360e52e02468f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0940_img_2746_1"/>
               Mr Chairman &amp; Gentlemen   Some of your tenants brought <lb/> under my notice the decayed condition of the <lb/> window sashes in their houses on S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Mels <lb/>Road. It will be necessary to have them put in <lb/>order. The pits also require to be emptied <lb/>There will be gravel required for the front paths <lb/>and it would be well if an order was given <lb/>to the Town Sergeant that no carts, boxes or <lb/>any obstruction were allowed to remain on the <lb/> street or roads overnight.  There have been some houses disinfected <lb/>during the month <seg type="closer"> Your obedient servant  <hi rend="underline">Joseph Slevin TS</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>