<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4232">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 21 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to family. Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/69</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4232</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-21</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4232_img_3600_1"  type="Letter"  url="cba4935706ae7183f07e2d4c27b6cbb8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4232_img_3600_2"  type="Letter"  url="2f307052815ff1c4725182d7e4b912af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4232_img_3600_3"  type="Letter"  url="a62ab4346e43b18e9bdf80af06c5df57.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4232_img_3600_4"  type="Letter"  url="9e44ff37b8ca1e8987077f393e7fc45f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4232_img_3600_1"/>
             21 Nov.   My dear folks   I really have no <lb/>news of moment. <lb/>We expect to do a bit of <lb/>a move next week but shall <lb/>still be in much the same area <lb/>as we are at present, though <lb/>overlooking a river; but <lb/>you won't be much the wiser.   I believe we go to quite a <lb/>large chateau &amp; rather hope <lb/>that I may leave a quarter out, <lb/>as the French houses are usually <lb/>built with the rooms acting <lb/>as passages which is not very <lb/>convenient for those who go to bed <lb/>early. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4232_img_3600_2"/>
             Personally I prefer a room to <lb/>my own in a cottage rather than <lb/>a chateau King's chamber.   We now belong to a   <lb/>of which I must not give you <lb/>the number, but Gen' <seg type="unclear">Congrur</seg> <lb/>is the General &amp; his Chief <lb/>Staff Officer is Gen' <seg type="unclear">Grunly</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">an</seg> a Staff College <seg type="unclear">Contempor</seg>. <lb/>any of mine, whom I have <lb/>now to remember not to <lb/>call "Bob <seg type="unclear">Grunly</seg>". He took <lb/>rather a strong line on the <lb/>other side during the Ulster <lb/>business &amp; very nearly <lb/>retired when French left the <lb/>War Office in which case he <lb/>would only be a Major instead <lb/>of a General, but I am glad
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4232_img_3600_3"/>
            he did not do so, especially <lb/>as it was only a case of <lb/>disappointment at his future <lb/>prospects not a matter of <lb/>principle.   I hope this past disagree — <lb/>ment will not affect our <lb/>previous friendly relations!   I find it hard to write <lb/>patiently of affairs in General. <lb/>Carson is being proved right yet <lb/>once more, &amp; I can hardly <lb/>imagine a more fatuous <lb/>move than for our 5 old <lb/>men <seg type="unclear">Asquith Balfour its</seg> to <lb/>come over to France &amp; talk <lb/>on Military matters without <lb/>one single Military officer with <lb/>them. The papers have not <lb/>commented on this but surely.... 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4232_img_3600_4"/>
             Rex's commands seems to vary <lb/>from 15 to 700 &amp; I can quite <lb/>imagine he is a strong com — <lb/>pulsory service man now, so <lb/>as to know how he stands.   I must end with best <lb/>love to all dear folks <lb/>&amp; hoping <seg type="unclear">Mal</seg> had a very <lb/>happy time at Plymouth <lb/>&amp; a rest   Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>