<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5492">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ella Young to Alice Stopford Green, 9 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ella Young</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Ella Young  (1867–1956) to Alice Stopford Green (1847-1929). In this letter, written on 9 August 1916, she reports on the collection of signatures for the reprieve of Roger Casement (who was hanged for treason on 3 August, having been arrested on the eve of the Easter Rising) and includes a list of petitions by location. She comments that there could have been many more petitions circulated if there had been more slips and more workers available.


Ella Young, was a poet, republican, and mystic actively involved in the Celtic Revival. Alice Stopford Green was an Irish historian and nationalist. While not a supporter of armed rebellion, her house provided a space for leading nationalists to meet. Stopford Green had collaborated with Roger Casement on Congo Reform and, after the Easter Rising in 1916, she tried to save him from execution</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, List no. A15; Ms. 13,088 /9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5492</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0825">Ella Young</persName>
              <date>1916-08-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0618">The O&#39;Curry College, Carrigaholt, County Clare</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5492_img_524_1"  type="Letter"  url="b2d625541d4fd3ffc40a6dd923ebaab3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5492_img_524_2"  type="Letter"  url="d9f6654fdb8b550314a1545fd423ecbc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5492_img_524_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="6327cf021f769df8ce446a09a35f080f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5492_img_524_1"/>
             The O'Curry College, <lb/>Carrigaholt, <lb/>Co.Clare   9th Augt 1916   Dear Mrs Greene   I have just heard <lb/> from Miss Josephine Webb 12 Brighton <lb/> Square Rathgar Dublin that she <lb/> forwarded 3 petitions. I had <lb/> in my list only credited her <lb/> with one. So please add <lb/>two petitions (Dublin) to those <lb/> already given in the lists I <lb/> sent you yesterday. We could <lb/> I think give you a list of those <lb/> who signed the College petition &amp; <lb/> it might be possible to fwd only <lb/> some of those who signed the <lb/> Carrigaholt petition. I could
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5492_img_524_2"/>
            <lb/>find out the name of the man <lb/> who asked for signatures &amp; took the <lb/> petition through the district. He <lb/> would certainly remember who the <lb/> chief people were. I think too I <lb/> would give the names &amp; addresses <lb/> of those who worked the petitions <lb/> in each district. It is no <lb/> exaggeration to say that we could <lb/> have got hundreds of petitions <lb/> if we had printed slips&amp; a <lb/> greater number of workers &amp; more <lb/> time. There were just a few <lb/> of us here &amp; we had no <lb/> lists of addresses through Ireland <lb/> so had to work through people <lb/> we happened to know in a <lb/> few districts.   Sincerely yours   Ella Young 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5492_img_524_3"/>
             Lists of Petitions <lb/>Cross 2 <lb/>Kilkee 1 <lb/>Carrigaholt 1 <lb/>O'Curry College 1 <lb/>Kilbaha 1 <lb/>Limerick 1 <lb/>Galway 1 <lb/>Grange (sligo) 1 <lb/>Clare Island 1 <lb/>Achill 3 <lb/>Waterford 1 <lb/>Enniskerry 1 <lb/>Dublin 2 <lb/>Toomgrainey 1 <lb/>Foynes 1 <lb/>Killen 1 <lb/>Carlow 1 <lb/>Letchworth England 3 <lb/>Rotherfield (Kent) 1 <lb/>Tullow 1 <lb/>Rathvilly 1 <lb/>Munny (Co Wicklow 1 <lb/>Shillelagh 1   Clonmore 1 <lb/><seg type="del">Carlow</seg> <lb/>Dingle 1 <lb/>Cork 1 <lb/>Ring 1 <lb/>Mallranny 1 <lb/>Ballyferriter 1   Total 35  *{Killala <lb/> {Dundalk <lb/> {Ballycastle <lb/> {Rathlin   N.B. In all probability <lb/> these districts sent in <lb/> petitions but we have not <lb/> yet been informed that they <lb/> did so. Mr.C.Chavasse <lb/> furnished them with a <lb/>petition in Gaelic. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>