<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3305">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maura [Power] to James Ryan, 18 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maura [Power]</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.
The letter was written after Ryan had been released from Frongach. Ryan does not seem to have been able to get work in the same branch of a company as the writer but has secured other work. The letter refers to conscription to the British army, which was threatened in Ireland but never applied during the Great War, and the writer speculates that it will not be introduced. The letter also refers to friends and colleagues. The &#39;Mick&#39; referred to is probably Michael Collins.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/45</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3305</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1496">Maura [Power]</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3305_img_272_1"  type="Letter"  url="be47ea089dae9ec3f9e14e1c0442926f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3305_img_272_2"  type="Letter"  url="6ca8894b516613695ede0a6e465f3aa8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3305_img_272_1"/>
             P88/45   18/10/16    My dear Jim,   Even though you did take time to make<lb/>up your mind, sure like the other story Its better late than<lb/>never and besides I suppose with all your other<lb/>pressing engagement you find it difficult to get<lb/>sitting down to write letters. I hope the weather has<lb/>improved some it is so unpleasant to have it raining.<lb/>We are all doing fairly well, we have just repulsed<lb/>a strong attack of the Flu which was made in<lb/>great force on our position, we suffered some casualties.<lb/>I am glad to hear that you are working away<lb/>and I am sure you will get used to the<lb/>change, of course I am sorry we did not<lb/>have room for you in this branch, but the<lb/>firm might start transferring again and<lb/>sure one never knows their luck, I hope however<lb/>that in the meantime you will make good and<lb/>get over your Exams with flying colours. One<lb/>does not take long to get over six months and<lb/>the work at the rate of several hours a day will do<lb/>you a world of good, and as for the staying power<lb/>well if I am any sort of a judge I'll plump right<lb/>on it. Yes we are still on the   racket and<lb/>so long as the weather keeps fairly satisfactory we are<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3305_img_272_2"/>
             likely to keep on it. I do not think that there is<lb/>any likelihood of conscription <sic>bein</sic> enforced<lb/>so I reckon things are alright over there.<lb/>I often have a game of bridge ordinary bridge<lb/>you know but that is the only card game<lb/>we have, I must find out something of poker.<lb/>I don't remember have ever played it. I am glad<lb/>to hear of Jack M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donagh when you see him again<lb/>give him my kindest regards and tell him<lb/>I would like very much to hear from him.<lb/>Ginger and C. are both quite well I enjoy the<lb/>former immensely as his delight at being here<lb/>is unbounded and his description of the<lb/>place really wonderful, I am glad you hear<lb/>from the other branch I hope George is quite<lb/>well I hear Dick has not been having a<lb/>very <sic>plesant</sic> time but I suppose Mick gave<lb/>you all the news. Give them <hi rend="underline">all</hi> my kind<lb/>remembrance when you write them.  Well I reckon it's very little news I have<lb/>but I am glad you wrote me, Kindest<lb/>regards to all who may be enquiring<lb/>and best wishes to yourself.   Your Very   Maura     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>