<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3136">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, April 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother Maria (1854-1954) informing her that she is recovering quickly from her recent illness and letting her know her latest news. 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/B/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3136</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3136_img_2554_1"  type="Letter"  url="ccea1b3744700af99d0ac84bf0600b19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3136_img_2554_2"  type="Letter"  url="c806439ae23b3db69909951b593f94d8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3136_img_2554_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Thursday</hi> <lb/> Nov. 1915    Dearest Mamma   Just a line to say that I have <lb/>recovered very rapidly and my neck is <lb/>nearly well again, disappearing as <lb/> quickly as it came. It was a rheumatic <lb/>chill of some sort with a temperature <lb/>for two days. I am quite normal <lb/>to-day and as it was nice and sunny <lb/>here to-day, saw the doctor and have <lb/>been out for a walk. I am now <lb/>back in my own billetts and have <lb/>lit a nice fire.   I found a nice parcel from <lb/>malcolmson's waiting for me to-day,
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3136_img_2554_2"/>
            thanks so much, it has turned up at a <lb/>very opportune moment and I am <lb/>going to have a good tea.   I am afraid I have missed <lb/>my day off which I was going to <lb/>spend at Forest Will, but may <lb/>get it later instead unless this is <lb/>counted as a holiday.   I haven’t got your Sunday letter <lb/>yet, as two were waiting for me at <lb/>the hospital till last night when one <lb/>of the nurses posted them to my <lb/>temporary lodgings, so I have just <lb/>missed them again, but will call <lb/>for them to-morrow.   I saw Olive on Monday evening, <lb/>looking very well, but I am afraid <lb/>getting very bored with Eastbourne. She <lb/>and Hilda had been to the theatre <lb/>and H: was resting in bed afterwards.   I think I must have got my <lb/>chill going home in the underground.   Have you heard anything more <lb/>from D ? I am longing to hear all <lb/>news.   Thank you again for sending <lb/>the rug.   Best love <lb/>from   <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>