<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1402">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maurice Bonham Carter to Mr Hutchison, 17 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maurice Bonham Carter</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Maurice Bonham Carter (1880-1960) to a Mr Hutchison. It encloses a telegram received from Sir Edward Grey&#39;s private secretary. Grey (1862-1933), was British foreign secretary between 1905 and 1916. The message states that the Prime Minister, Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), cannot give an interview but he suggests that Sir John Maxwell (1859-1929) might do so. Bonham Carter sets out the procedure for the interview and suggests that Hutchison enlist the assistance of Berry (believed to be an American Correspondent staying at the Gresham Hotel). Carter wants to counteract the negative feeling in America (over the executions) and makes a number of suggestions as to what the journalist might include in the piece. Finally Carter refers to having met Daily Mail correspondent, Montagu Smith. The latter was very interested in the &#39;North King Street cases&#39; (fifteen civilians killed by British soldiers) and it is suggested that Hutchison meet up with Smith and a solicitor who acts for families of victims and who is calling for a public inquiry.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/512</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1402</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0316">Maurice Bonham Carter</persName>
              <date>1916-05-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1787">Vice Regal Lodge, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr Hutchison</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_1"  type="Letter"  url="2b79556d203914b1ce04a3818f7e9a59.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_2"  type="Letter"  url="dd0a5b1af252f930f9ff7b766ed20532.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_3"  type="Letter"  url="1134e184fbfc5c5ae765b39023d2ed36.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_4"  type="Letter"  url="920ceb5757eef71ac3f650d85217d361.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_5"  type="Letter"  url="b39ee830fc3c6d3e1b79abade55a29df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_6"  type="Letter"  url="7583aaa43d5d4d799fbadf924c9042f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1402_img_795_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="aa8757f2ee3c74a2b7b0e1bd47d964ea.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_1"/>
                VICE REGAL LODGE,  DUBLIN.    May 17. 1916   Dear Hutchison   I enclose a telegram which I <lb/> received last night from <seg type="del">the</seg> Sir E. Greys <lb/>Private Secretary. explains itself <lb/> The Prime Minister cannot give the <lb/> interview at this moment, but he <lb/> wishes me to suggest that Sir John <lb/> Maxwell might do so. As you may <lb/> not have had experience of such things <lb/> may I explain the procedure.  The actual interview is almost a <lb/> matter of from 10 minutes or a quarter <lb/> of an hour just to give the journalist <lb/> some slight acquaintance with his  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_2"/>
              subject. The substance of what is wished <lb/> to appear, is given to the interviewer in <lb/>the form of a written statement, which <lb/>he will translate into his own words <lb/>&amp; <seg type="del">then submit explain</seg> He will submit <lb/> the draft interview for revision -   The Prime Minister wishes me to write <lb/> to you to suggest that you might <lb/> prepare such a statement on the lines <lb/> generally indicated in the telegram <lb/>&amp; get Berry to put it into the form <lb/> of an interview.  I think that the final draft might <lb/> be <seg type="del">set</seg> sent over to me before publication <lb/> for the P.M to see. <seg type="del">I do not</seg>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_3"/>
              I think you will have no difficulty <lb/>in arranging this.  There is undoubtedly considerable feeling <lb/>aroused against us in America which <lb/> it is worth while endeavouring to <lb/> counteract.   If I may make a few suggestions. I <lb/> should say that the more impartially <lb/> the case in presented the better: <seg type="del">if</seg><lb/> if possible give instances &amp; <seg type="del">details</seg> numbers  of <lb/> unarmed officers men &amp; civilians shot <lb/> at the outset of the <seg type="del">casualties</seg> outbreak , point <lb/>out the wanton futility of the outbreak <lb/> how men's lives were sacrificed for no <lb/> object; how destruction of life &amp; <lb/> property began before the military force <lb/> came effectivedly on the scene. <seg type="del">This is</seg><lb/>what is needed is to counteract the idea  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_4"/>
              which is being spread, that our forces had <lb/> no provocation &amp; that the military were <lb/> responsible for most of the loss of innocent <lb/> life &amp; for the destruction of property, in <lb/> particular for the fires in Sackville Street. <lb/> It might be worth taking Berry round the <lb/> chief centres of fighting to show the <lb/> difficulties <seg type="del">of</seg> with which  our men had to contend, <lb/> the <seg type="del">exact</seg> obvious  one being the intermingling of <lb/> peaceful civilians with the rebels.  These are only suggestions for your consideration.  Will you put the proposal before <lb/> Sir John &amp; let me know what he <lb/> decides? I go to Cork Tomorrow &amp; <lb/> shall be back at Downing St on <seg type="unclear">Fri</seg><lb/> morning.  There is one other matter which is <lb/> perhaps worth mentioning. This is from <lb/> myself only, as I have not had an  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_5"/>
              opportunity of mentioning it to the <lb/> Prime Minister.  I saw tonight the correspondent of the <lb/> Daily Mail <sic>Montagu</sic> Smith. He is <lb/> quite a good man &amp; I think can be <lb/> trusted. He has been interesting himself <lb/>in the North King Street cases &amp; seems <lb/> to know a good deal about them.   He tells me that the solicitor who <lb/> represented  at the inquest  the families of men found <lb/>buried is a temperate respectable man <lb/> who honestly wants to prevent trouble <lb/> if possible. He wants to get <seg type="del">an</seg> a public  inquiry <lb/>undertaken into the cases &amp; that all <lb/><seg type="del">public</seg> inquests should be stopped. <lb/> He says that other cases will present <lb/> a worse appearance than the one which <lb/> has just <seg type="del">been</seg>been sat upon.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_6"/>
              I give you this for what it is worth <lb/>thinking that it may be worth while <lb/> for one of your people to see <sic>Montagu</sic><lb/> Smith &amp; perhaps the solicitor Larden <lb/> is his name I think.   I am very sorry for all of you who <lb/> have to bear the burden of this <lb/> pitiable business <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely  Maurice Bonham Carter </seg> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1402_img_795_7"/>
                Post Office Telegraphs    May 16th 1916    To { <hi rend="underline">Confidential</hi>  Bonham Carter  Vice Regal Lodge. Dublin   Following from Drammond:-   Irish executions are being used effectually against us <lb/> in America. Would Mr Asquith give short interview <lb/> to American correspondent. Berry is the <seg type="del">best</seg> most <lb/>suitable. He is at the Gresham Hotel. Interview should <lb/> emphasise clemency of Government comparing number of casualties inflicted by the <lb/> rebels &amp; how rebels killed innocent people at the beginning <lb/> of outbreak. Spring Rice telegraphs confirming this. <lb/> Sir E. Grey approves this telegram.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>