<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6674">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from WB Yeats to George Russell, 12 January 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>WB Yeats</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 7. Folder: Letters 43 TL/copies to Russell, George William (7.8)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6674</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0403">WB Yeats</persName>
              <date>1922-01-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0747">4, Broad Street, Oxford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0970">George Russell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6674_img_None_1"  url="phpNvp3De.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6674_img_0_1"/>
              4, Broad Street,<lb/>Oxford    Jan.12 (1922)    My dear Russell   Do not forget that you are to give me for the Cuala<lb/>press what portions you have ready, or what selections you wish<lb/>to make from it? The press is now ready but my sister would prefer<lb/>to print first a little paper covered edition of nine or ten poems<lb/>of mine. These however will not take her long, I would prefer that<lb/>you came next, there have been too many Yeats books. Are you ready.<lb/>If you are I will have it out with her. The increased price makes<lb/>their books rather profitable to the author -- my Four Years in her<lb/>edition has brought in £54. It is really an extra so does not inter-<lb/>fere with the ordinary edition.  I wonder how you feel about the new Irish Government,<lb/>I am by constitution a pessimist &amp; never thought they would get<lb/>as much out of Lloyd George &amp; so am pleased, nor am I distressed<lb/>to see Madam Markieviez and other emotional ladies among the non<lb/>jurers. I am to lecture in Paris at the new Government's exhibition<lb/>there. I expect to see Griffith, now that he is the universal target,<lb/>grow almost mellow, and become the fanatic of broad-mindedness and<lb/>accuracy of statement. Hitherto he has fired at the <sic>cocanuts</sic> but<lb/>now that he is a <sic>cocanut</sic> himself he may become <sic>milkey</sic>   Yrs. W.B.Yeats  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>