<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0070">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from P.S. O'Hegarty to George Gavan Duffy, 24 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>P.S. O&#39;Hegarty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from P.S. O&#39;Hegarty (1879-1955) to George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951). In the letter, written on the day the Rising began, O&#39;Hegarty welcomes the news of Ernest Blythe&#39;s (1889-1975) release and that the papers haven&#39;t mentioned the case at all. He also sends his share of the expenses. He comments on &#39;things at home&#39; and is concerned at the situation; he feels the enemy is &#39;trying to provoke something&#39;.Patrick Sarsfield O&#39;Hegarty, was an Irish writer, editor and historian and a former member of the Supreme Council of the Irish Republican Brotherhood. He worked in the Postal Service at a number of locations, including Welshpool, Wales. George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising. Ernest Blythe was an organiser for the Irish Volunteers. He had been arrested under the Defence of the Realm Act. He was released from prison in England before the Easter Rising but was rearrested there during Easter week 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD/45/3/11/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/70</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0784">P.S. O&#39;Hegarty</persName>
              <date>1916-04-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1815">Woodleigh, Welshpool, Wales.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0070_img_1138_1"  type="Letter"  url="a782f5836ee6bf501cc0068ee0fb3843.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0070_img_1138_1"/>
                Woodleigh  Welno    24 April 16   Dear Gavan Duffy,   Excellent.  I see the papers<lb/> have not mentioned the case at<lb/> all. I am sending you my <seg type="unclear">paper</seg><lb/> of the <seg type="unclear">times.</seg>  We have just moved into<lb/> a house, and are frightfully<lb/> busy. It's an awful job when<lb/> you can't afford to hire somebody<lb/> to do the work.  Things at home have been very<lb/> threatening, and I hope there<lb/> wont be a <seg type="unclear">crisis</seg>. It would<lb/> be criminal unless the enemy<lb/> do something definite and and general.<lb/> They seem to me to be trying to<lb/> provoke something <seg type="closer"> Remember me to Mrs Gavan Duffy <lb/><seg type="unclear">do chara</seg><lb/> P.S.Ó héigeartaigh </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>