<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0669">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 28 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary, writing on his return from the trenches. He thanks her for socks, gloves, soda bread and provisions and asks for smaller quantities more regularly, due to difficulties packing provisions when moving. The weather is cold, hard frost but no snow. He is now stationed near other battalions and his friends which pleases him. This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/669</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0669_img_2162_1"  type="Letter"  url="f43ed356da00f62be4ac40b0180935f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0669_img_2162_2"  type="Letter"  url="faa9d9470a1123e7718b3e923b66ce29.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0669_img_2162_3"  type="Letter"  url="5bd44a5ee885da0fd4819b973b00e6e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0669_img_2162_4"  type="Letter"  url="0791d5f8a76a8d592c761c52115d973c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0669_img_2162_5"  type="Letter"  url="2f335b36af5c53002654d40a7a0b3850.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0669_img_2162_6"  type="Envelope"  url="0eed243187f28fdbb03c2ebcf3cab4a6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0669_img_2162_1"/>
                28/11/15   My dearest mother   We have arrived<lb/> in our new area &amp; things are<lb/> rather upside down so excuse<lb/> a very rushed letter. Have<lb/> not been able to do any writing<lb/> for some days as there has been<lb/> such a lot to do. The Brigade<lb/> arrived back from the trenches<lb/> on Friday &amp; it meant such a<lb/> rush getting all the details sent<lb/> back to their various billets,<lb/> settling billeting <seg type="unclear">claims</seg> &amp; as<lb/> of course the least possible amount<lb/> of notice is given. Then the Units<lb/> were only allowed to rest 1 night<lb/> in their old billets before starting<lb/> for the new area so you can't<lb/> imagine how difficult it has<lb/> been for all concerned. This <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0669_img_2162_2"/>
              time we are in quite a big<lb/> town compared to what we<lb/> have been accustomed to &amp; it<lb/> is therefore a very welcome<lb/> change. What makes it all the<lb/> more pleasant for me is that the<lb/> 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> are billeted with the Bde. H.Q.<hi rend="superscript">s</hi><lb/> &amp; the other Batts are in neighbouring<lb/> places so it is quite like old<lb/> times to see all my old pals.<lb/> Saw <seg type="unclear">Gerard</seg> of course today. He<lb/> is looking well &amp; in quite good<lb/> form <seg type="del">after</seg> in spite of the very<lb/> severe weather they had in the<lb/> trenches. The Brigade was<lb/> very lucky this time as there<lb/> were no killed — only a few<lb/> wounded. I am afraid there<lb/> is little hope for poor <seg type="unclear">Courtenay</seg><lb/> Shillington who was in the 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> Bde. He was out with a patrol<lb/> at night, was fired on by a<lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0669_img_2162_3"/>
              large German patrol &amp; he was<lb/> seen by the others to throw up<lb/> his arms &amp; fall forward. When<lb/> a larger patrol was sent out<lb/> later his body could not be<lb/> found. Weather very cold at<lb/> present — hard frost but fortunately<lb/> no snow. One has to file out<lb/> as many clothes as possible<lb/> to keep warm. I had a<lb/> very bad billet last night but<lb/> found a much better place today<lb/> where I am quite comfortable.<lb/> We are evidently to continue<lb/> training here as before — I<lb/> wonder where we shall go next<lb/> time. Hope it wont be service.<lb/> And now dear mother I must<lb/> thank you for three letters which<lb/> have come since I last wrote.<lb/> Was so sorry to hear you had not<lb/> been very well for a day or so.<lb/><cb/> I expect it was those oysters.<lb/> So glad that K. &amp; Baby go on well<lb/> &amp; that father has been keeping<lb/> all right. Poor Mr Ward does <lb/> not seem in good health. I do<lb/> so hope he will soon be better,<lb/> things would be very difficult at<lb/> the works without him.  The socks arrived safely &amp; the<lb/> gloves. Thanks ever so much mother<lb/> dear. They were all perfectly<lb/> splendid. The tin of soda<lb/> bread also came &amp; was enjoyed<lb/> by all &amp; papers come regularly <lb/> so I dont think anything has gone<lb/> wrong so far. When sending out <lb/> any eatables in future however<lb/> it would be better to send only<lb/> small quantities &amp; more frequently<lb/> because when we move all personal surplus<lb/> store one may have, have to<lb/> be given away or left behind<lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0669_img_2162_4"/>
              unless one can find some means<lb/> of packing them up. What I mean<lb/> is that fo instance it would be<lb/> better to send say I lb of butter<lb/> each week rather than a box<lb/> of 5 or 6 lbs every month.<lb/> There is one thing I would <lb/> like sent out as soon as<lb/> possible &amp; that is my green<lb/> canvas kit bag. It requires<lb/> some overhaul I think at<lb/><seg type="unclear">Erskines</seg> — some of the eyelets<lb/> were a bit torn &amp; he could <lb/> put my name on it if that<lb/> was not already done. I of<lb/> course dont mean they should<lb/> put on Bde. H. Q but simply<lb/> Capt. J.S. Davidson. I did not<lb/> think I would have time to <lb/> write so much but must now <lb/> stop. With fondest love to all. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  James <lb/></seg> <hi rend="underline">over</hi>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0669_img_2162_5"/>
              I was almost forgetting to ask<lb/> you to send me out 2 more<lb/> suits of warm underwear<lb/> &amp; 1 warm shirt. This should<lb/> be sufficient meantime &amp; I will <lb/> send back my summer things <lb/> within the next few days. <seg type="closer"> James </seg> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0669_img_2162_6"/>
               On Active Service    2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>Dec /15   <lb/>  Mrs . S.C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland   JS Davidson   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>