<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3023">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Maurice de Bunsen to Sir Cecil Spring Rice, 17 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maurice de Bunsen</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Cecil Spring Rice (1859–1918), a British diplomat who served as British ambassador to the United States from 1912 to 1918.The letter was sent by Sir Maurice de Bunsen (1852 - 1932). De Bunsen was a British diplomat serving in Vienna as the assistant undersecretary in the Foreign Office from 1915 until early 1918. 

This letter concerns the Irish Relief Fund. In this letter de Bunsen agrees that the funds should be distributed using the St Vincent de Paul Society in order to avoid the misuse of the funds raised for political purposes. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5618/12620/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3023</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0899">Maurice de Bunsen</persName>
              <date>1916-07-17</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1238">Cecil Spring Rice</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1932</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3023_img_2423_1"  type="Letter"  url="3c376d3f18bf0c69ebddae907497bf5d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3023_img_2423_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi> (128255/45A)<lb/><lb/>No. 206   FOREIGN OFFICE    17th July 1916.    Sir,   With reference to your despatch No.559 of the 23rd<lb/>ultimo on the subject of the Irish Relief Fund, I have<lb/>to state that it seems clearly desirable that the rela—<lb/>tives of the men executed and others who may be in dis—<lb/>tress through the rebellion in Ireland should receive<lb/>the money that has been contributed in America for their<lb/>relief, and I agree with Your Excellency in thinking<lb/>that advantage might well be taken of the good offices<lb/>of Archbishop Walsh and the Society of St. Vincent de<lb/>Paul in order to secure the distribution of the Fund to<lb/>bona fide sufferers and to prevent the misuse of the<lb/>money for political purposes.  It is to be expected that the emissary whom Cardin—<lb/>al Farley intends to select to convey the funds to Ire—<lb/>land will abstain from any political activity while en—<lb/>gaged in the work of distribution.   I am etc.<lb/>(for the Secretary of State)<lb/>(Sgd) MAURICE DE BUNSEN    His Excellency<lb/>The Right Honourable<lb/>Sir C. Spring Rice G.C.V.O., K.C.M.C.<lb/>etc. etc. etc.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>