<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0681">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 12 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary. Davidson writes to thank his mother for sending parcels of food, clothing and medicine. He especially appreciates the home made soda bread and boxes of butter. He also asks her for cakes, sweets, dates, raisins and apples. He is homesick at the thought of being away from home for Christmas.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme..</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/681</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-12-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0681_img_2173_1"  type="Letter"  url="de7f6e3f7fb9ef5be54bfe603061434e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0681_img_2173_2"  type="Letter"  url="bf14271f854dc14253445cb22427f823.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0681_img_2173_3"  type="Letter"  url="82b1f7db70e7b4090f53ddef9be3839e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0681_img_2173_4"  type="Letter"  url="062b11973b5d1aed866657751b63f7d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0681_img_2173_5"  type="Envelope"  url="10d90c47645a0fe412d68c9caa14ea87.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0681_img_2173_1"/>
                12/12/15   My dearest Mother,   I have not much in <lb/> the way of news but as it is Sunday &amp; <lb/> not much doing I am taking the opportunity <lb/> to send you a wee line in case I might not <lb/> have time during the next few days. Was so <lb/> glad to get your letters of 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; to hear <lb/> that Kathleen was going along better. Do <lb/> hope the trouble, whatever it was, will soon <lb/> pass off completely. It was such bad luck <lb/> for her poor dear when all was going so <lb/> well. The handkerchiefs arrived safely <lb/> also box of butter, Soda Bread, parcel of <lb/> clothes &amp; today the packet of medicine <lb/> including a large bottle of Aspirin which I <lb/> think must have been sent by mistake as <lb/> it would last me for a year or more <lb/> however I am sure it will be useful, as others <lb/> may be short. Thanks so much Mother dear <lb/> for all these things &amp; would you please  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0681_img_2173_2"/>
              give Mary my love &amp; best thanks for the parcel <lb/> she sent me. We of course usually have <lb/> a very comfortable mess &amp; this is particularly <lb/> the case where we are now as Madame in <lb/> the house where we have our mess does the <lb/> cooking for us, but the little extras make <lb/> a great difference. Butter is one of the <lb/> things we appreciate most for the ration <lb/> butter is usually rather awful. We also <lb/> enjoy any home made bread, — soda or <lb/> brown — &amp; an occasional cake or box <lb/> of sweets, or dates or raisins about complete <lb/> the list. As regards clothes please don't <lb/> send any more for the present as I have <lb/> all I require &amp; my kit is already very <lb/> bulky. We all enjoy the apples very <lb/> much but is is better to send only a small <lb/>packet at a time as a case takes such <lb/> a long time to come. When I wrote <lb/> a few days ago I thought we would <lb/>probably be on the move by now but  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0681_img_2173_3"/>
              <lb/>so far there have been no orders &amp; perhaps <lb/> after all we may spend our Xmas here. <lb/> I certainly hope so for we could not be <lb/> in better billets. The weather has been <lb/> awfully wet — downpours of rain practically <lb/> every day. The country is in a terrible state <lb/> of mud &amp; it makes our work most un <lb/>pleasant &amp; difficult but after all it is <lb/> nothing compared to the conditions in <lb/>the trenches. The poor fellows there at <lb/> present are having a very bad time of it. <lb/> Have not seen Gerard for the last few <lb/> days as I have out most of the time looking <lb/>after M.G. ranges but he is very well as <lb/> are also all the others in the 13<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We <lb/> shall all be glad to see Charlie Murland <lb/> back again. He hopes to get a clean <lb/> bill of health next month. Did I tell <lb/> you that Capt. Burroughs had been invalided <lb/>to the Base Hospital. I think it is very <lb/>doubtful if he will be able to return.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0681_img_2173_4"/>
              The latest report of Courtenay Shillington <lb/> is that he is wounded &amp; a prisoner. <lb/> What a relief this will be to his wife. <lb/> You mention in your last letter that <lb/> Kyle had been ringing up for my address. <lb/> I dont know why they should want it <lb/> as I have not ordered anything from them. <lb/> Goodbye Mother dear. <seg type="closer"> With love to all <lb/>your loving son  Jim </seg>  It is hard to believe that Xmas will be <lb/> here in about 2 weeks. I wonder if we <lb/> shall still be fighting when the next one <lb/> comes round. At present the end seems <lb/> as far away as ever. <lb/>Jim   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0681_img_2173_5"/>
              <lb/>On Active Service Dec 18th Dec/15 RUBBER STAMPED PASSED BY CENSOR NO. 2515   Mrs. S.C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland  <lb/>Js Davidson 12/12/15  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>