<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4225">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 17 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his family. Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/64</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4225</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-17</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4225_img_3595_1"  type="Letter"  url="948c68f81bcf6b46073b0016001f373f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4225_img_3595_2"  type="Letter"  url="8c79018a12b4517b1a3246e40e80d83f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4225_img_3595_3"  type="Letter"  url="b1489b6fdfa4222a121dd07a20376543.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4225_img_3595_4"  type="Letter"  url="40b627c4e8b75300b6130aa72990c5d7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4225_img_3595_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Mater</seg> <lb/> <seg type="del">Rex</seg> <lb/> <seg type="del">Edmund</seg> <lb/> <seg type="del">Mab</seg>  <hi rend="underline">Please return finally to Lil.</hi>  17.Nov.   My dear folks   I am a little nervous <seg type="del">of</seg><hi rend="superscript">that</hi> the effect of these <lb/> constant letters <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">but this one I think can well be reserved <lb/> for "one" of the folks</seg></seg> <hi rend="superscript">may lead some of you to expect them later, when I am more busy</hi>. No mail again &amp; I am not surprised <lb/>as the roads must be like glass as after a bit or a thaw <lb/> it is freezing hard. Mail came with nicest letter from old Mab &amp; one <lb/>from Mater in which I expected to find another but..   Our move to Z is likely to be postponed <lb/> a little as the storm must have delayed <seg type="del">our</seg> the  journeys of <lb/> others on whom our move <seg type="unclear">depends</seg>to some extent.   There is a bit of staleness in the air. The GOC <lb/> does not encourage one to do much in the way of training <lb/>with troops so that Richardson &amp; myself get far less of <lb/> this than we did at Seaford, &amp; tho' we could certainly <lb/> not have learnt what we have picked up here, had we <lb/> remained in England, we could have put it into practice better. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4225_img_3595_2"/>
             I think on the whole I am glad to have a move tho' <lb/> I fear it is to be to another valley where there is a hilltop <lb/> asking us to come to it.   I fancy our position is to be somewhat like it was <lb/> just before we left England ready for anything that may <lb/> turn up. The men who have been getting ready their <lb/> winter quarters will I'm afraid not believe it worth while <lb/> to begin it again for the third time for other people to <lb/> get the advantage perhaps, &amp; yet this ought to be the spirit <lb/> of the army so that all may help each other, but it seems <lb/> agin nature, &amp; I wonder if the Ulstermen can give a <lb/> lead in this form of Self Sacrifice.   If only the English could hold the view that <lb/> outsiders like the Greeks &amp; Swedes really think that Germany <lb/> is going to win they would make any sacrifice, but our <lb/> island home has the advantage of making us rank <lb/> optimists. There is no reason for pessimism if we face <lb/> the facts, but our wild optimists prevent our doing so. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4225_img_3595_3"/>
             Every one of us ought to be ready to give up half his <lb/>capital &amp; to face the future with that prospect. Everything <lb/>is relative &amp; I see nothing terrible if all ones' fellows do the <lb/> same.   Carson has again given the lie to the Government &amp; <lb/> I can't now believe that Grey is the honest man we have <lb/> thought him. He declares <hi rend="superscript">1)</hi> that the Government did not <lb/> come to a decision <hi rend="superscript">about Serbia</hi> before Carson's resignation when there is <lb/> no doubt that it did, tho' there is probably some technical <lb/> qualification which he can pretend sustains him, &amp; his <lb/> explanation of Britain's unqualified support of Serbia <lb/> which he pledged in what to the plain man is as <lb/> clear as daylight is the lamest thing I have ever seen.    He is tarred with the same brush &amp; I can't <lb/> help fearing that Bonar Law &amp; Balfour are learning <lb/> tho inwilingly the tricks of their associates.   If things get really black I believe we shall go <lb/> in for a government of 2 men K &amp; Carson &amp; they will <lb/> pull us through.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4225_img_3595_4"/>
             Tomorrow &amp; the following day I shall be <lb/> fully busy &amp; may only be able to write scraps.   I am sorry Walter is going through the unsettled <lb/> stage. It is bound to come some time, &amp; probably next <lb/> year he will be as keen about his school as we all <lb/> became in time. I will try &amp; find time to write <lb/>him a letter later after I have been up at the front <lb/>again, but he will not appreciate one from the back of the front.    I return Mab's jolly letter for circulation &amp; <lb/> hope others may be as particular !   Best love.    Wilfrid BS 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>