<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1160">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, End of December 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s patients in India.Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/19, IJA/CHPI/54/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1160</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1917-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0786">Bombay, India </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1160_img_3837_1"  type="Letter"  url="f55f385c72dd766ee5d772f8431c1738.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1160_img_3837_1"/>
                End of December 1917   My dear Reverend Fr Provincial P C    I have nothing to write about, but <lb/>as we touch land again in a day or two I re-open <lb/>communications. I struck a bad patch on this return <lb/>journey, as about eighty per cent of our patients are <lb/>Mahommedans, and nineteen per cent Hindu. Of the <lb/>remainder not all even belong to me. I have four to <lb/>take care of! On of the Mahommedans wants to become <lb/>a Christian. I shall get him in touch with the Bombay <lb/>priests.  As far as we can judge at present the early part <lb/>of our Christmas day will be spent at sea, the second half <lb/>in harbour. (Later I said my 3 Christmas Masses at sea. In harbour 5.30p.m.)  I am hoping for a large Irish post when we land. <lb/>Fr O' Mahony if he is still in these parts will be able <lb/>to keep.  Hoping all are as well as I am, I recommend myself <lb/>to your Reverence's Masses and prayers <seg type="closer"> Your obediently in Christ <lb/>Frank Shaw SJ </seg> <hi rend="underline">P.S.</hi>Fr Farley 17 Masses November <seg type="del">20</seg>18 Masses December  <hi rend="underline">P.S. ii </hi>There is a home mail in harbour, I believe, but as the outward mail closes tonight I cannot wait to <lb/>see if there is anything from Ireland. F.S.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>