<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1797">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Harty, Archbishop of Cashel, to Sir John Robert O'Connell, 30 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Harty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by John Harty (1867-1946), the Catholic archbishop of Cashel. Harty was a strong supporter of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was a supporter of John Redmond and in 1916 wrote a letter denouncing the Easter Rising and congratulating the people of Cashel for abstaining from the insurrection.
In this letter Harty recommends Sir John Robert O&#39;Connell for the position of chief crown solicitor and hopes that he is chosen for the position.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1797</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1260">John Harty</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0595">John Robert O&#39;Connell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1946</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1797_img_1251_1"  type="Letter"  url="0f050ac4c6936da668299deb7b6daf1c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1797_img_1251_1"/>
             The Palace, <lb/>Thurles.   30th March 1916   My Dear Sir John,   Showing your legal quali- <lb/>fications and also the many benefits <lb/>which you have conferred on University <lb/> Education especially in connection with <lb/>University College, Cork, I sincerely <lb/>hope that you will be appointed to <lb/>the office of Chief Crown Solicitor for <lb/>Ireland. Your appointment would give <lb/>pleasure to many who know your merits.   Yours very faithfully,   +JM Harty   p.s. You may make whatever use you please of <lb/>this letter. +JMH 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>