<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4408">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward Roe to Under Secretary, 22 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Roe</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward Roe to Sir Robert Chalmers requesting the names featured on the list for next year&#39;s High Sheriff Office. 

Colonel Edward Roe (1841-1920), a retired Army Medical Officer, was serving as the high sheriff for Cavan in 1916. The High Sheriff of Cavan was the British Crown&#39;s judicial representative in County Cavan, Ireland from the 16th century until 1922, when the office was abolished in the new Free State and replaced by the office of Cavan County Sheriff. 

Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was appointed under-secretary of Ireland in 1916, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI/CSO/RP/1916/10616</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4408</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0804">Edward Roe</persName>
              <date>1916-06-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1119">Cavan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1920</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4408_img_3760_1"  type="Letter"  url="a765269a4492b780656e28412158ec7a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4408_img_3760_1"/>
             Sheriff's Office <lb/>Cavan,  22nd June 1916   Shrievalty   Sir   I shall be obliged if you <lb/>will let me know the names of <lb/>the two gentlemen who were on <lb/><seg type="del">last</seg> this year's list along with mine.   I want to know these names so <lb/>that I can furnish list for the coming year.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obdt. Servant <lb/>E.A.H. Roe, <lb/>High Sherriff   The Under Secretary <lb/>The Castle, Dublin   Inform Col Roe that the names of the <lb/>undermentioned gentlemen were <lb/>returned  in addition to his own  at Summer Assizes  1915 as <lb/>eligible to serve the Office of the High <lb/>Sherriff during 1916, viz:— <lb/>Joseph Arthur Benison, Esq., <lb/>Slieve Russell, Ballyconnell. <lb/>Theophilus Edward Lucas-Clements, Esq., <lb/>Rathkenny, Cootehill. <lb/><seg type="unclear">ChoS.</seg> <lb/> 26-6-16    Done   27/6    desp'd <lb/>  27/6  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>