<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5500">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty to Sir Roger Casement, 8 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from the Dominican priest Fr. Thomas Crotty (d. 1930, born James but took the name Thomas after he joined the order) to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written during Casement&#39;s eighteen month stay in Germany, where he was attempting to gain German support for an Irish rebellion against British rule. The letter refers to Casement&#39;s attempts to create an Irish Brigade of Irish-born British army soldiers who were then held as prisoners of war in German camps. It was the camp at Linberg, in the Lahn valley, that was designated for the project. Fr. Crotty was one of the priests who administered to the men in the camp at Limberg. The project was, however, largely unsuccessful and only fifty-six men signed up. The letter refers mainly to Crotty&#39;s so far unsuccessful attempts to secure funds to pay for his time administering to the Irish prisoners of war. He also mentions proposals to request that all Irish prisoners be transferred to the same camp and to a letter that he has sent, without reply, requesting permission to visit all camps with Irish prisoners.
Casement was later arrested in County Kerry having returned to Ireland in a submarine to try and prevent the Easter Rising from taking place as he felt German support was insufficient. He was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,085 /20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5500</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0444">Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</persName>
              <date>1915-12-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0529">Limberg, Lahn, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0605">Zossen, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1930</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5500_img_532_1"  type="Letter"  url="9795a10e08298f977c3da9a42eb93e08.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5500_img_532_2"  type="Letter"  url="c01fe077e2736aeaf7729d0f27772eca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5500_img_532_3"  type="Letter"  url="61bb33fd6c336d5c247386342b5ad601.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5500_img_532_1"/>
             Limburg a/ Lahn <lb/>Germany   8. Dec. '15   R in Zossen <lb/>9 Dec/15   My Dear Sir Roger   <hi rend="underline">Your very kind note to hand, for which <lb/> I am extremely grateful. A word to our <lb/> friend M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Meyer, may relieve me of the <lb/> necessity of accepting your generous offer. <lb/>My appeal for funds was made to be <lb/> able to meet the account which is due to <lb/> the Missionhaus Fathers with whom I <lb/> lodge. I asked or at least reminded Mr. Meyer <lb/> of this in my letter to him now more than <lb/> one month ago. I shall beg you to do me <lb/> the favour of reminding him : he may have <lb/> forgotten all about my letter owing to the vast <lb/> amount of business he has in hands.</hi>   <hi rend="underline">I need hardly say I appreciate highly your <lb/> suggestion to let you know my present needs, but <lb/> I shall not encroach on your generosity while <lb/> there is a hope of having a favourable reply from <lb/> the Auswaertiges Amt.</hi>   <hi rend="underline">I propose to await a line from you, to say</hi>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5500_img_532_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">if you have mentioned this matter to M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Meyer. <lb/> In case of receiving an assurance of being heard <lb/> I shall await patiently.</hi> If on the other hand I get <lb/> an unfavourable reply I shall write to the Ambassador <lb/> to the Holy See at Lugano, through the Cardinal <lb/> Nuntius of Munich, and explain the necessity of <lb/>having funds to pay for lodging and travelling. <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Since the Prisoners were taken to the farms I <lb/> have travelled much to visit them, and had <lb/> always to stay with them a part of two days. I <lb/> did ask for a free pass on the Railways just as <lb/> other Pastors have, but I was not given that.</hi> I <lb/> left my house in Rome without any money and <lb/> I mean to return there in the same financial <lb/> state. I merely desire that my expenses be <lb/> paid, and I am sure my Superiors in Rome shall <lb/> willingly suffer the loss my absence from <lb/> there means to them. To put that at the lowest <lb/> figure it would amount in a year to over 1000 <lb/> Lire.   Rumour has it that a move is being made <lb/> in England to appeal to the Prussian Government <lb/> for the bringing together of the Irish Prisoners <lb/> of War. I hope it is not true, and; that such a <lb/> report is the outcome of the imagination of some <lb/> of those <hi rend="underline">thinking</hi> people in the Camp here. The <lb/> Nuntius agreed with me that my wish to have <lb/> all the Irish brought together again, or at least <lb/> to have permission to visit all the Camps where <lb/> there are any Irishmen was quite just, and <lb/> from political and diplomatical motives the <lb/> best thing to be done.   <hi rend="underline">I explained how favourably impressed <lb/> were the people at home when the notice appeared <lb/> in the Press that Priests were sent to look after <lb/> the Irishmen, and that all Irish Prisoners were <lb/> to be concentrated in one Camp to have the <lb/> aid of their ministration. I have a letter <lb/> from an Irish Bishop who expresses him- <lb/>self much pleased at what was done. His <lb/> words are - "We in Ireland owe much to the <lb/> Holy Father and to the Kaiser for what they <lb/> have done for our countrymen". Is it not then <lb/> a pity that anything should happen to inter- <lb/>-fere with such an impression, as to lessen in any <lb/> degree the sense of obligation which the people <lb/> in Ireland feel for what has been done?</hi>    <hi rend="underline">In the event of the refusal of funds during my <lb/> stay, I shall write to my relatives in Ireland <lb/> who are blessed with much of this world's goods,and <lb/> will ask them to pay for my stay as Spiritual <lb/> Guide of my dear countrymen. This of course would <lb/> be the last resource, &amp; one which I should not pur- <lb/>sue unless driven to extremities, for I fear though <lb/> my relatives should keep the secret, yet somehow <lb/> or other such things leak out, and that would not do.</hi> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5500_img_532_3"/>
              I regret to hear that you feel so much depressed <lb/> at times. There are good times coming, and let us <lb/> look forward to them with confidence. With you <lb/> I pray that an end may soon come to the awful <lb/> carnage that is <seg type="unclear">destructing</seg> Europe.   Kind regards to all the boys. I am glad to <lb/> learn of their welfare. I wish you and them <lb/> all the blessings and joys of Xmas   Yours v. sincerely    <hi rend="underline">J.T Crotty O.P.</hi>   P.S. <lb/>I should say I have received the <lb/> Papers which you Kindly sent, and <lb/> handed them over for the boys. Thanks. <lb/><hi rend="underline">J.T.C.O.P.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>