<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3728">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Elizabeth McCracken to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 23 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Elizabeth McCracken</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Elizabeth McCracken (1876-1944) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), thanking Hanna for her previous letter and her interest. Elizabeth writes that she hopes that Hanna will be able to influence Birrell, the chief secretary for Ireland. She goes on to write about a variety of current events and closes by wishing Hanna good health.

Elizabeth A.M. McCracken was an Ulster suffragist and member of the Women’s Suffrage Society and the Women’s Social and Political Union. She is the author of The Feminine in Fiction and wrote under the pen name L.A.M. Priestly McCracken.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,604/13-14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3728</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0679">Elizabeth McCracken</persName>
              <date>1915-11-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1715">Seafield House, Bangor, Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1944</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3728_img_3117_1"  type="Letter"  url="da95edda11e88bb8eabc1913a012a286.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3728_img_3117_2"  type="Letter"  url="4d31b82957a53027d9bccf86497246de.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3728_img_3117_3"  type="Letter"  url="08e4f2239ae0d38320617b4a99734562.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3728_img_3117_4"  type="Letter"  url="86eb32306f0dd28979020b01faf54cec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3728_img_3117_1"/>
             Seafield House,<lb/>Bangor,<lb/>C. Down.   <hi rend="underline">23 Nov. 15</hi>    MyDear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington.   Many thanks for your<lb/>very kind letter. &amp; your<lb/>practical interest<lb/>in this <seg type="unclear"></seg>  as it<lb/>concerns my husband. There<lb/>have been so many<lb/>rumours about it (&amp;<lb/>  are in connection<lb/>with such appts : ) that   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3728_img_3117_2"/>
             one hardly knows what<lb/>to believe. It is interesting<lb/>however to see the<lb/>cuttings you kindly enclosed.<lb/>I have found from last<lb/>year's experience that   <seg type="unclear">Tirrill</seg><lb/>is awfully hard to get at,<lb/>or influence, &amp; everyone seems<lb/>to agree that he is<lb/>the one who decides this<lb/>post. I can quite see  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3728_img_3117_3"/>
             it w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> be wiser not to<lb/>intervene <hi rend="underline">openly</hi> on<lb/>our behalf, but anything<lb/>you could do through<lb/><hi rend="underline">others</hi> to <hi rend="underline">influence</hi> <seg type="unclear">Hanney</seg><lb/>to <hi rend="underline">influence</hi> <seg type="unclear">C Sirrell</seg> w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi><lb/>be fine, &amp; we should<lb/>be so grateful.  I hope M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Skeffington<lb/>will get home safe &amp;<lb/>well &amp; surely the<lb/><seg type="unclear">Cat</seg> will keep off<lb/>it's old game. Did<lb/>you not see Christabel 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3728_img_3117_4"/>
             in <seg type="unclear"></seg>   last week,<lb/>or Sir Edward Grey? It's<lb/>a wonder the gout doesn't<lb/>resent that sort of tack!   I hope your little boy is<lb/>well again, also your<lb/>maid, &amp; that you are very well yourself.  Yours sincerely,<lb/><hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">Eli</seg> M.Mc.Cracken</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>