<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5748">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn 16 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
May writes of James&#39; cousin getting engaged
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5748</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-04-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5748_img_848_1"  type="Letter"  url="d274b20a154e8a918334c4e69f6222e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5748_img_848_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5b1b762899e9ae67cccdf91423a8a7b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5748_img_848_1"/>
             Togherstown   16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>April 1916    My dearest James,   I got your letter yesterday<lb/>&amp; today you were very good to write I have<lb/>only a minute to write Paddy is going to<lb/>Loughnavallup besides I have no news only that<lb/>Louis was down seeing his girl &amp; all is<lb/>settled Louis is out and delighted with her <seg type="unclear">saying</seg><lb/>she <hi rend="superscript">is</hi> the best of them etc. Johnnie has heard<lb/>nothing since he is gone to Mullingar today<lb/>with the D<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> &amp; <seg type="unclear">Tommel</seg> the latter is gone to bury<lb/>John Allen with who's people he has the greatest<lb/>sympathy.  Last night Mrs P. called for mother &amp; both<lb/>went to see Jim Donellan he does not seem to<lb/>have got out of his trouble very much yet<lb/>his sleep is still effected it seems to have gone<lb/>very hard on him he was glad to see them.<lb/>I hope <seg type="unclear">JW s</seg> will take P. Moran as but now in good<lb/><seg type="unclear">parts</seg>I am pitying Nora &amp; Moll if they have<lb/>weather anything like what we have today the <hi rend="superscript">wind</hi> would<lb/>shave you as well as frequent showers of rain 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5748_img_848_2"/>
             Perhaps they have<lb/>better weather tho'<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Kiernan sent<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> George a letter<lb/>she got from<lb/>cousin Mary Kelly<lb/>Ctown. Three large<lb/>sheets like this<lb/>I wish I could fill<lb/>a few pages of a<lb/>nice letter now for<lb/>my dear little man<lb/>but no such luck<lb/>as to be able to give<lb/>that much pleasure<lb/>so I need not try<lb/>but I will send you lots<lb/> of love and kiss<lb/>from your loving <lb/> <hi rend="underline"> May </hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>