<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0911">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Vincent Coyle to John F. McGuinn, 23 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Vincent Coyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter (copy of original) from James Vincent Coyle (1864-1948) to John F. McGuinn (1893-1916), on 23rd March 1916. McGuinn was serving with the 2nd Irish Guards in the Ypres area at the time. Coyle writes of family matters, monetary concerns and news at home. John worked in the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction, Dublin. Five young men in the Department also joined up with John in September 1914 to fight in the British Army in the Great War. John was hit by an artillery shell and killed on 27 March 1916. This letter was among his belongings that were returned to his mother in Sligo some weeks after his death. He was aged 23.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/911</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1516">James Vincent Coyle</persName>
              <date>1916-03-23T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0734">Department of Agriculture and technical Institution, Dublin, Ireland. </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John F. McGuinn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0911_img_2550_1"  type="Letter"  url="c65b84daba984cce4bca687ced42a412.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0911_img_2550_2"  type="Letter"  url="1517380d10ef78c51e95bc7bdcc7790a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0911_img_2550_3"  type="Letter"  url="1a2dfed9b5bb7024a0e14a2741e94f94.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0911_img_2550_4"  type="Letter"  url="8c94069b6f7c5193267a1ee04174de54.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0911_img_2550_1"/>
                Department of Agriculture  and Technical Instruction  Dublin    23 March 1916   Dear McGuinn   Enclosed came <lb/>here yesterday but as I was kept <lb/>at a Board meeting until after <lb/>post time &amp; as I wanted to write a <lb/>note to you when forwarding it <lb/>I could not write until today.  I hope you are keeping <lb/>fit. don't forget to let me <lb/>have a p.c. by early next <lb/>week to show the a/c <seg type="unclear">for</seg>  By the way I have heard <lb/>on an absolutely unimpeachable  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0911_img_2550_2"/>
              source that Ms.Meyrick <lb/>is engaged to be married &amp; <lb/>I learned subsequently that he <lb/>is somewhat perturbed <seg type="unclear">lost</seg><lb/>the news should reach my ears <lb/>&amp; induce me to start some joke <lb/>on him. Well I don't intend to <lb/>disappoint him in the latter <lb/>respect but while I am thinking <lb/>out the details you might <lb/>write to congratulate him <lb/>but don't disclose the identity <lb/>of your informant though he will <lb/>of course guess who it is. I  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0911_img_2550_3"/>
              have not spoke to him on the <lb/>subject so far a I have not yet <lb/>decided on the form of the joke <lb/>part. I am very glad —; sincerely <lb/>so —; that he is taking this step <lb/> I trust that he will have as <lb/>happy a married life as I <lb/>thank God, have had.  Nothing new here except <lb/>that there is talk of an increase <lb/>in the taxes on incomes, tea &amp;c.  Yesterday, I received from <lb/>the P.O. an Enchequer 5% Bond <lb/>Book in which is recorded the <lb/>investment of £10 which I made on <lb/>your behalf. I propose whenever <lb/>the <seg type="unclear">balce</seg> to your <seg type="del">cheque</seg> credit  reaches  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0911_img_2550_4"/>
              £7, to invest £5 automatically <lb/>in these 5% bonds this would <lb/>leave say £2 or £3 loose for <lb/>sudden call. Of course should <lb/>you at any time anticipate <lb/>the necessity for having a larger <lb/>sum at call on your letting <lb/>me know I will arrange accordingly. <lb/>My object is however, not to let the <lb/>bank have the free use of too much <lb/>of your money bu to see that it is <lb/>bearing interest for you. Junior <lb/>(i.e Vincent) in his last letter from <lb/>Clongowes asked to be remembered <lb/>specially to you. He is doing well both <lb/>at work &amp; football. Cecil is seemingly <lb/>kept going pretty hard at the front. We <lb/>feel it a bit lonely at home now with <lb/>only Desmond who is just 4! <seg type="closer">  With all good wishes <lb/>Yours   Vincent Coyle </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>