<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0694">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Daniel Roche SJ to his Father Provincial, Thomas V Nolan SJ,, May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr Daniel Roche</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Daniel Roche SJ (1882-1961) to his Father Provincial, Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941), May 1916. Roche writes an exciting account of surviving through a high explosive bombardment while conducting a burial detail. Roche also writes of his daily routine in the salient he and his men now occupy in the British front line.Daniel Roche was born in Castleisland, county Kerry in 1882 and died in 1961 in Limerick. He attended the Intermediate School in Tralee, county Kerry and the Jesuit boarding school, Clongowes Wood College. He entered the Jesuits in 1899 and was ordained in 1915. He volunteered as a military chaplain and was accepted in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/53/10, IE IJA/CHP1/53/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/694</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0294">Fr Daniel Roche</persName>
              <date>1916-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0038">97th Field Ambulance, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0694_img_2186_1"  type="Letter"  url="56c0da53024cb86ab40b4b1144ef1521.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0694_img_2186_2"  type="Letter"  url="c0651c44c483d75156dc1b5181ae5bfa.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0694_img_2186_1"/>
                97<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ( C. P. ) Field Ambulance B. E. F. France   Dear Fr Provincial P.C.   When I was changed to this Ambulance I dropped you a card <lb/>letting you know and giving the address and presume you got it.  I am now attached to a Brigade tho' attached to the Field <lb/>Ambulance for billets &amp; rations. I find it a much more interesting and <lb/>profitable job than my last. I have come on with and intend to stay <lb/>with the advanced dressing station here till we go back for rest. <lb/>I do not know if you have yet guessed where I am but it is not <lb/>far from Greystones or Killiney. We occupy a <seg type="unclear">pronounced</seg> salient in the <lb/>line and it is a very hot spot. There is a very good Church here which <lb/>is at our disposal — the civil population and <seg type="foreign">Cure</seg>having gone. I say 'our' <lb/>because I have run against Fr Sandford of the English Province here and <lb/>we run the district between us. We have daily mass for a small congregation <lb/>of soldiers at 7.00 to 7.30 and Holy Devotions every night. Then during the <lb/>week we try to do scattered units and on Sundays we <seg type="unclear">climate</seg> and get <lb/>in quite a large area. During the short time we have been up here it <lb/>has been <seg type="unclear">bourne</seg> in on me that, if attached to a Brigade like mine where <lb/>the Catholics are in a proportion of about 1 in 10 and some battalions are <lb/>in trenches and some 'at rest' (?) and these latter scattered in various <seg type="unclear">labour</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">parties</seg>, the two things necessary are good physical staying power and <lb/>to know the ropes. The latter is not so easy. The work, then, is a mixture <lb/>of drudgery and excitement and I have been treated to a little of both. <lb/>I just escaped a bombardment by high explosion some days ago by <lb/>a 100 yds and 30 secs. I had been up at the line to conduct a burial <lb/>and was talking to an officer for a few minutes when the shells began to <lb/>fall about 100 yds away. As it was getting dark and I had to make <lb/>my way alone back along the trenches I set out for home. I met <lb/>the Colonel on my way and he told me to wait awhile till the shelling <lb/>was over and told me that my trench was the one which was being <lb/>shelled! I had lost all idea of the direction in which I had come  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0694_img_2186_2"/>
              <lb/>and had I not met the Colonel I should have been into it in my ignorance <lb/><seg type="del">I have</seg> The trench was blown in in several places and large branches <lb/> of trees brought down in it. I have been very near shell fine on various <lb/>occasions but this was my narrowest escape. We were roused out of bed <lb/>here a few nights ago by a night alarm and spent several hours in <lb/>the cellar but only a few shells came into the place and these not <lb/>very near. We are fully prepared for a bad time when anything big <lb/>is on and expect this place to get a bit of a pounding. However we are <lb/>in very good not to say excellent form despite it all.  I am out now more than ten weeks and am commencing <lb/>to look forward to my first leave. Whether I shall get it or not I cannot <lb/>say but at any rate I expect to put in for it. If the push comes on <lb/>I might have to wait rather too long. <seg type="closer"> Hoping you will remember me in your Masses &amp; <lb/>prayers <lb/>Yours sincerely in Xt  D Roche SJ </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>