<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5536">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Monteith to Roger Casement, 1 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Monteith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Monteith (1880-1956) to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) in February 1916. Monteith was the commander of the Irish Brigade, appointed by Casement. 
Casement had spent over a year in Germany attempting to secure German support for an uprising in Ireland and raising an ultimately unsuccessful brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps. By April, Casement had become disillusioned with German assistance and marginalized from the plans for the Rising. He believed there should be no rising without sufficient German support and when he realised that it was going ahead with only a small supply of German arms, he traveled to Ireland to prevent it from taking place. The Germans supplied a submarine to transport Casement, Monteith and Beverly to Ireland but Casement and Sergeant Beverly (Daniel Bailey) were captured after they landed in Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Casement was hanged for treason in London in August 1916.
Monteith writes that he had received Casement&#39;s last two letters and is glad he is improving in health. He encloses letters from others for Casement, including one from Zerhusen, a German officer. He also writes that Casement should not worry about their moving, &#39;I can&#39;t worry the H.Q. people more than I am doing, God knows we all want to get away from this awful place as quickly as possible&#39;, despairs that he had no communication from America yet and no one to confide in and mentions a letter from Count von Papen, the military attache.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sir Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15; Ms. 13,085/24/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5536</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0377">Robert Monteith</persName>
              <date>1916-02-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0605">Zossen, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5536_img_631_1"  type="Letter"  url="7a8d745c02663e6b4e07021235a2b08d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5536_img_631_2"  type="Letter"  url="b69b340fdbb0cef2420ae94ecf774824.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5536_img_631_1"/>
             R at M <lb/>3 Feb. 1916   Zossen   1.2.16.   Dear Sir Roger,    Your two letters received, glad to know you are improving <lb/> in health &amp; if I read your letter rightly in spirits. I am enclosing some <lb/> correspondence from Golden Lion, and a pamphlet, also a letter from <lb/> Zerhussen - together with the article from the Times which you <lb/> asked, The "Glories of Ireland follows by parcel post. —     I am afraid you are going to start writing again &amp; if <lb/> I was sure of it I would  not  send on these things, a spadeand a <lb/>garden rake would be better — Please do not worry Sir Roger about <lb/> our moving — I can't worry the H.Q. people more than I am doing, <lb/> God knows we all want to get away from this awful <lb/> place as quickly as possible —     I wish I could see you &amp; talk with you. I have <lb/> no one to confide in - and I have not had a letter from <lb/> America yet — will it be possible for me to see the friend <lb/>from the U.S.A?    I knew the Emersons had gone to C, I called to <lb/> see them but they had already gone. Perhaps I did not <lb/> tell you in my last letter that I had seen Capt Von Papen <lb/> at the War Office, he had no news except that things had <lb/> taken a decided turn for the better in America —    I do not understand you as regards Miss M.F. and <lb/> <hi rend="underline">funds</hi>. I am afraid she is in trouble with the Consulate, as <lb/> far as I can fathom they are after her passport —    Beverly has received a very fine artist's outfit and is <lb/> busy, witness some of her work on top &amp; side of this paper. I have had
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5536_img_631_2"/>
            the misfortune to touch one of his brushes, so you must pardon <lb/> the smear —    I think I have said all now, so will end with best <lb/> wishes   Faithfully Yours   R.<hi rend="underline">Monteith</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>