<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1334">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 8 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) teasing May about her sentimentality and informing her on the progress of her gift.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1334</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1661">National Health Insurance Commission, Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1334_img_660_1"  type="Letter"  url="d55d71dbc2d23135ad3571108212cf46.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1334_img_660_2"  type="Letter"  url="9b3b4c8822b755d0e15959b9b687e5a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1334_img_660_1"/>
              wristlet watches which I thought <lb/>would suit. O’Leary, the manager, <lb/>recommended both strongly and said <lb/>he would get them going for a <lb/>day or two to see which one was the <lb/>better. They are at present racing <lb/>against each other under his <lb/>supervision and he will let me <lb/>know on <hi rend="underline">Friday</hi> which I should <lb/>take. I shall send the watch <lb/>on <hi rend="underline">Friday evening</hi> so that you may <lb/>have it in good time for Sunday <lb/>or if you like I can get him <lb/>to send you a selection of two <lb/>or three on approval. Let me <lb/>know would you prefer this. <lb/>I shall probably not write <lb/>tomorrow but will wait <lb/>until I send watch <lb/>on Friday. No news at <lb/>all except that I am <lb/>getting back into harness <lb/>very well and am quite <lb/>happy knowing that you <lb/>love me. Thanks ever so much <lb/>for the kisses which I return <lb/>even more heartily than they were <lb/>given. With all my dearest and <lb/>warmest love and blessings to <lb/>my darling from your future husband, <lb/>James. <lb/>Give my warmest regards to our mother. Hope Christy is getting better <lb/>x x x x x x x   Beginning of letter    NATIONAL HEALTH COMMISSION (IRELAND),  PEMBROKE HOUSE,  UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN.    8th March,1916.   My dearest love   I was delighted and pleased with your letter this <lb/>morning. It has kept my heart ringing all day up to the present <lb/>for it is clear all through it that you are not quite the superior <lb/>“sensible” sort of girl that you were trying to humbug me into <lb/>believing. It is the greatest possible comfort and happiness to me <lb/>to know that my dear girl thinks of me so much and so highly. <lb/>I suppose it’s heartless to be glad to hear that you had recourse <lb/>to tears on Monday night. Is this the superior girl that never <lb/>cried and who was so contemptuous of me for being “silly” <lb/>when I thought I was only affectionate? Well I am glad to <lb/>see that you were moved to tears on my account and I love you <lb/>all the more dearly (if that is possible) for it. For my part, <lb/>I’m not a bit inclined to cry these days. In fact I feel quite <lb/>pleased with myself and inclined to shake myself by the hand <lb/>— almost indeed to stand myself a drink — because I have been  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1334_img_660_2"/>
              so lucky as to get such a treasure as your love. The thought of <lb/>it warms and comforts me so that I can almost feel something <lb/>warm and singing within me all day long. I didn’t have <lb/>any pancakes for tea yesterday evening so I’d have done better in <lb/>more ways than one if I had been able to help you to eat <lb/>yours. I suppose everyone forgot it at home and indeed I forgot <lb/>it myself till I got your letter this morning. That’s one of the <lb/>advantages of being young like you; you don’t forget the pleasant <lb/>customs of the children. Sorry to hear Mrs Seery has been worrying <lb/>you over your secrets. I don’t know why she should think you <lb/>have any. The only thing between you and me is that we love <lb/>each other dearly and I expect everyone can guess that pretty well <lb/>(in my case any how) without being told it. I’m not surprised that <lb/>she thinks you pretty clever although I hope she doesn’t think you <lb/>“smart” in the bad sense. I have certainly always thought you a <lb/>young girl of remarkable character and intelligence and <lb/>goodness, far beyond your very youthful years, and I am all <lb/>the more delighted that I hooked the prize. What a dear sweet <lb/>clever little <hi rend="underline">wife</hi> I shall have one of these fine days! Well my dearest <lb/>love, about the watch, I called into Hopkins yesterday and selected a couple of  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>