<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5712">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 1 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
James&#39; boss Gallagher is leaving for London the next Monday, which he declined, there have been Zeppelin raids in England, the weather is balmy.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5712</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-04-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1427">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5712_img_814_1"  type="Letter"  url="6208e481965d280ddb9ff8761348ecc8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5712_img_814_2"  type="Letter"  url="9feb19ad353e38396f8050fd552acc7f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5712_img_814_3"  type="Letter"  url="9232aad8d3337533bc564eb2f0179e95.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5712_img_814_1"/>
              fag of tramping up to<lb/>Loughnavalley for me. It is<lb/>dear and good of you but<lb/>I hope you won’t be putt-<lb/>ing yourself about on my account. Y<lb/>ou must be getting to be a<lb/>great walker when you can<lb/>do that walk every day without<lb/>being tired. How is the poor<lb/>ankle getting on? I suppose well<lb/>or you wouldn't be able to<lb/>walk so well. Give my<lb/>love to all and with<lb/>fondest and most enduring<lb/>love to my dearest<lb/>and best girl<lb/><lb/>Always your loving &amp; devoted<lb/>James    39 Belgrave Square,<lb/>Rathmines,<lb/>Dublin. <lb/><lb/> 1st April 1916    My dearest darling May, <lb/>I hadn’t the least<lb/>expectation of getting a letter from<lb/>you and so I was all the more delighted<lb/>to have it. I guessed the last few days<lb/>that you probably had to do your own post-<lb/>and for that reason I didn’t think you’d<lb/>write yesterday. I know very well it is awfully<lb/>good of you to write to me so often and I<lb/>had it on the tip of my pen to say so yesterday<lb/>but I was interrupted as I am very frequently<lb/>and forgot it afterwards. About the<lb/>race if it is a choice for me between seeing 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5712_img_814_2"/>
             you at the races and seeing you in town<lb/>I prefer the latter of course but I was hoping<lb/>that I might have both pleasures. If however<lb/>I can only have one of the two, I plump for<lb/>you coming up for a few days rather than<lb/>seeing you for an hour or two in a crowd<lb/>at Mullingar. I have been talking the matter<lb/>over with my mother and she will leave it<lb/>to yourself when you come up. Nora and<lb/>Moll will probably be going away this<lb/>day week for about three weeks and will<lb/>be back shortly after Easter and perhaps<lb/>you would like to have either of them here<lb/>at the time. They would be useful to you<lb/>if you were buying things or anything of<lb/>that sort and besides you will probably get<lb/>tired of my dull company after a while  and might like for a change to have someone<lb/>younger than my mother to speak to. It<lb/>will be an awful disappointment to me not<lb/>to be able to see you until Easter if you<lb/>decide not to come up before then but I<lb/>suppose it can’t be helped. I hope your<lb/>mother won’t be vexed at me for dragging<lb/>you away from home during the spring hurry. I’m<lb/>sure you’ll all be very busy now for the<lb/>next couple of months for things look now as if the<lb/>spring was at last starting in earnest. The last<lb/>few days have been perfect here and today is<lb/>like a Summer day. Hadn’t I the devil’s own<lb/>luck not to go down this weekend instead of<lb/>last. It would have been so pleasant to be<lb/>rambling about with my own dear girl, but I<lb/>can’t complain even so for I had her all<lb/>to myself in the house if I couldn’t go outside 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5712_img_814_3"/>
             and what more could I want. In any case<lb/>I expect to have a lovely time at Easter when<lb/>I shall probably be free for at least a week<lb/>and of course I’m burning for it to be here now.<lb/>I hope you will be extra sweet and nice and<lb/>good to me then and if you do I’ll bring you<lb/>an extra large Easter egg so now be a “dood<lb/>ittle dirl” and you’ll see what you’ll get. I’m<lb/>afraid I have no pleasant news of any sort to<lb/>tell you. My chief, Gallagher, is going off to<lb/>London on Monday morning and although he pressed<lb/>me again to accompany him I declined so your<lb/>poor little man is safe for the present. I don’t envy<lb/>him his job especially as they have had another<lb/>Zeppelin raid in England and in any case he will<lb/>have a lot of very troublesome and exacting work to<lb/>get through which I know very well without blowing<lb/>horns that I could handle better myself as I am<lb/>much more familiar with the particular job being<lb/>dealt with. I don’t expect a letter tomorrow so<lb/>I hope, love, that you won’t give yourself the 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>