<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0324">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to Mary Martin, 13 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). In this letter Marie writes that she has been appointed to a committee to represent the Red Cross VADs. She asks her mother to thank Bee for her last letter and mentions that Gerald has returned to the trenches. Marie also asks her mother to send her on a small prayer book.Marie Helena Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/1/48, B/F/1/48</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/324</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-13</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0361">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0324_img_1548_1"  type="Letter"  url="28c08e9e23bee3f89d795b15f96e0856.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0324_img_1548_2"  type="Letter"  url="4f0ed6fa29aaf4963f77ffe0b57ba219.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0324_img_1548_3"  type="Letter"  url="b88d5f7f8cbd5eb2c301c4dc725097f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0324_img_1548_4"  type="Letter"  url="dfd16efde6e1e3fa0aa5422feb454445.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0324_img_1548_5"  type="Envelope"  url="f569c5ea63007ec94acdbb5230f46329.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0324_img_1548_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">13.7.16Â­Â­Â­</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   It is very late now but<lb/> I do not want to let to-day<lb/> pass without writing to you, as<lb/> I shall not be able to write<lb/> till Thursday. not because we are<lb/> so busy in the wards, we have<lb/> just the usual work and out 3 hours<lb/> off every day but I have <sic>be</sic><lb/> put on the Committee to represent<lb/> the Red Cross V.A.Ds â All the Sisters<lb/> &amp; Nursing Staff are giving<lb/> a Tea to the Orderlies (180)<lb/> on Tuesday &amp; Wednesday next<lb/> so for the last few days in my<lb/> off time I have been at Committee<lb/> meeting &amp; yesterday I had a<lb/> whole day off but spent mostÂ­<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0324_img_1548_2"/>
              in <hi rend="underline">Town</hi> buying things for it &amp; the<lb/> next few days we will be<lb/> busy preparing â We are going to<lb/> give them a Tipsy Cake you can<lb/> imagine whipping up Ideal<lb/> Milk for it. I hope it will be<lb/> a success &amp; that they will enjoy<lb/> it. I think it ought to be quite<lb/> a good spread â It takes some<lb/> working in a place like this<lb/> especially when convoy are beginning<lb/> to come in again â   Please thank Bee for her very<lb/> nice long letter I shall answer it<lb/> as soon as this is over â Tell her<lb/> she was quite wrong about the<lb/> letter, it was such a nice one<lb/> from Sister Trower who has<lb/> had a very rough<seg type="del">t</seg> time since<lb/> she left Malta â I also had a<lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0324_img_1548_3"/>
              letter from Eveleen who is <sic>suppose</sic><lb/> to be off to drive M. Ambulance<lb/> in Russia with the Scottish women<lb/> on the 9th of Aug. She says<lb/> Gerald is back again in the <lb/> trenches and was <sic>recommend</sic> as C.O.<lb/> but another man unknown to them<lb/> all was sent up from Headquarters.<lb/> I do hope he is alright. <lb/> Is there any news of Gerald M. <lb/> I must try and write to Ethel <lb/> to-night also Aunt Mary B. <lb/> who I hope is keeping very <lb/> well â I think of her every night<lb/> poor thing.  I wonder if you would get me <lb/> a nice small prayer book, I <lb/> do not know where A. Sissy<lb/> got that one she gave me, I<lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0324_img_1548_4"/>
              think they cost a shilling, they<lb/> are very nice for a manâs pocket.<lb/> I want one for such a nice boy<lb/> &amp; he has not got a prayer book<lb/> Minnie F. is so good and sending<lb/> me out such a lot of stuff<lb/> &amp; going to so much trouble<lb/> over it â  Well, I must end as I<lb/> am falling to sleep â<lb/> Fondest love to everyone <lb/> I hope Desmond is quite <lb/> alright â <seg type="closer"> Love and good-night X  Marie </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0324_img_1548_5"/>
                Mrs Martin  Greenbank  Monks town  Co Dublin  Ireland    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>