<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1761">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Augustine Birrell to Edward W. Mooney, 5 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Augustine Birrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), the chief secretary of Ireland, to Edward W. Mooney (b. 1846), an Irish Catholic priest. The letter acknowledges and thanks Mooney for a previous letter he sent recommending Charles P. O&#39;Neill (b.1867) an Irish solicitor and member of the Irish Parliamentary Party for the position of  chief crown solicitor due to the death of former solicitor Malchy Kelly (1850-1916).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5729/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1761</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date>1916-04-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0266">Edward W. Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0051">St. John's Priory, St. John's Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1933</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1761_img_1217_1"  type="Letter"  url="80473e974c3504134d906b1fcb5b49ef.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1761_img_1217_1"/>
             5th April, 1916.   Reverend and Dear Sir,   Thank you for your letter of yesterday's <lb/>date written on behalf of Mr. Charles P. O'Neill, an <lb/>applicant for appointment to position of Chief <lb/>Crown Solicitor. I am much obliged to you for <lb/>the trouble you have taken.   Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Rev. Edward W. Mooney,  St. John's Priory, <lb/>St. John Street, W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>