<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4474">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 12 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to Father Provincial Thomas V. Nolan SJ (1867-1941) informing Nolan about his recent movements. Doyle writes that their accommodation is comfortable but cold, yet despite the ad weather they are keeping in good spirits. Doyle also comments that despite the battalion being nearly all Irish there are only five Catholics out of thirty-four men. Despite this Doyle believes there is a lot of good work to be done as overall he has 3,000 men to look after.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.

Fr. Thomas V Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War. During the Rising Nolan was based at St Francis Xavier’s, Upper Gardiner Street and, alongside Rector Fr John Fahy SJ, risked his life in aiding the wounded and supplying local areas with food and milk.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-CHP1-14-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4474</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1707">Whitley Camp, Surrey, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V. Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4474_img_3820_1"  type="Letter"  url="3983008757627be896c5c379005e0337.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4474_img_3820_2"  type="Letter"  url="f33e247faf6cad57db4e804a90d83c67.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4474_img_3820_3"  type="Letter"  url="a786beba0e426ceb1d1acd2d17af2593.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4474_img_3820_4"  type="Letter"  url="aeb933bcbb1447e1183ceed02f713ee0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4474_img_3820_1"/>
             CHPI/14(I)  <!-- letterhead: Royal Irish Fusiliers <lb/> 8<hi rend=\'superscript\">th</hi>(Service) Batt<hi rend=\'superscript\">n</hi> --> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>R.I.F.<lb/>49<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Brigade<lb/>Whitley Camp<lb/>Surrey    12/12/'15. <lb/><lb/> Dear F. Provincial,    I should<lb/>have written to your<lb/>Reverence before this<lb/>only I had no very<lb/>definite news to give.<lb/>We came here from<lb/>Wohing <!-- Woking --> last Saturday  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4474_img_3820_2"/>
             and remain till<lb/>the 22<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">nd</hi></hi> when we move<lb/>to Bordon Camp, Surrey<lb/>to join the other three<lb/>battalions of the 49<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>Brigade and remain<lb/>there till we sail for<lb/>France, which will<lb/>not be till Jan, I<lb/>believe.  We are living in<lb/>wooden huts, which are<lb/>comfortable enough<lb/>though rather cold as<lb/>there is no means of  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4474_img_3820_3"/>
             heating them <seg type="unclear">nor</seg>at<lb/>Wohing. In<lb/>additon it has been<lb/>raining almost in-<lb/>cessantly for the past<lb/>fortnight which does<lb/>not tend to make<lb/>things more pleasant,<lb/>but for all that we<lb/>are in the best of<lb/>spirits, the officers being<lb/>a very nice set of<lb/>fellows, practically all<lb/>Irish, though only<lb/>five Catholics out of<lb/>34.  There is abundance of  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4474_img_3820_4"/>
             good work to be done<lb/>among the men as<lb/>my companion, F. Kelly<lb/>from Cashel, and myself<lb/>have the best part of<lb/>3,000 men to look after,<lb/>but neither of us will<lb/>be sorry to go on to<lb/>the Front.  Asking a remembrance<lb/>in your Reverece's <seg type="unclear">Name</seg>,<lb/>Believe me<lb/>Yours obediently in  <lb/>W. Doyle. SJ    Kindly give enclosed<lb/>note to Fr <seg type="unclear">Farley</seg>.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>