<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0131">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Denis Mangan to Anna O'Rahilly, 11 August 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Denis Mangan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Denis Mangan (1894-1981) to Anna O&#39;Rahilly (d.1958), offering his condolences upon the death of her brother Michael. In the letter Denis, who is on a mission in Africa, comments on the Rising, stating that it was a hopeless affair but that he believes the rebels had the best intentions and that hopefully some good can come from the sacrifice. Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/122/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/131</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0091">Denis Mangan</persName>
              <date>1916-08-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0866">Kamuli, Busoga, Africa</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0131_img_1221_1"  type="Letter"  url="856e37daddb4a2566cd57bd0035a825c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0131_img_1221_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">Aug 11th, 16</hi>    R. C. Mission  Kamuli  Busoga  B. E. Africa   My Dear Anna   The sad news has<lb/> reached me of poor Michael's tragic<lb/> death and I feel I must send<lb/> a word of condolence to you &amp; Nell.  It is a long way from Central <lb/> Africa to Ballylongford but my thoughts<lb/> have travelled back there many times<lb/> since I heard of Michael's death.  That rising was, indeed, a foolish<lb/> and hopeless affair, but no doubt,<lb/> those who took part in it, did so with<lb/> the best intentions. Let us hope that<lb/> some good may come from the sacrifice <lb/> of so many noble-minded fellows.  You and Nell must naturally<lb/> feel the death of your only brother and<lb/> therefore I wish to say that I feel for you<lb/> in your bereavement. <seg type="closer"> With kindest regards<lb/> I am<lb/> Yours very sincerely <lb/> D. M. Mangan </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>