<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0117">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to Mary Martin, 18 Sept 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892–1975) to her mother Mary Martin. In the letter Mary thanks her mother for a letter dated from 15 September, writing that she is glad everyone is well. She goes on to write of the weather and explains that she is on her own as many of the sisters have left while she has few patients, however she does have spring cleaning to do. The letter tells of enormous casualties on the front, however it accounts the taking of 9 miles of territory with few casualties the previous day. She commends the Irish who fought at the battle of Ginchy (9 Sept 1916). The Caterpillar that Marie refers to on page 3 is most likely the British Mark 1 battle tank.Marie was a born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the out break of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Medical Missionaries of Mary, B/F/1/62/1916/09/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/117</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1915-09-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0361">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0117_img_1200_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc0d120578cd64d6745632e411ca5d43.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0117_img_1200_2"  type="Letter"  url="a27247318f356dff94d159787a355cb9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0117_img_1200_3"  type="Letter"  url="4fa1ac199b619f66a041e960b7964e39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0117_img_1200_4"  type="Letter"  url="6b55d1e2636bf822db2d601f172a9f8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0117_img_1200_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">18-9-16</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   A 1000 thanks for your <lb/>letter dated Sep. 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I am so <lb/>glad to hear you are all well. <lb/>&amp; also to hear Tommy is alright <lb/>again, it is a great relief to <lb/>hear he is not in the fighting. <lb/>Yes the Combination have arrived <lb/>&amp; I think ought to be quite <lb/>warm enough because when it <lb/>gets really cold <sic>Ihave</sic> wool <lb/>bodices <sic>Ishall</sic> put on. I like <lb/>Tommy want to be on the safe <lb/>side <sic>the</sic> have had some days <lb/>here since Sep: came in terrible <lb/>cold &amp; as I just get odd touches <lb/>of stiffness <sic>Ithink</sic> it better to be  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0117_img_1200_2"/>
              very careful. The Southwestern just <lb/>arrived in time it absolutely <lb/><sic>pouring</sic> to-day with a terrible <lb/>gale, <sic>Iam</sic> afraid this will <lb/>be a very exposed place in the <lb/>winter.  I am on my own again the <lb/>Sister has been taken away <lb/>at present <sic>Ihave</sic> no patients <lb/>but we expect to fill up <lb/>any day now I have <lb/>plenty of spring cleaning <lb/>to do but I am just taking <lb/>my time over it as we <lb/>will want all our energy <lb/>when the rush startsâ <lb/>The casualties are enormous <lb/>but we are certainly doing  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0117_img_1200_3"/>
              very good work all round. <lb/><sic>Ithink</sic> yesterdays was the best <lb/>when we took 2 miles on a <lb/>six mile front with the <sic>Catapillers</sic> most likely tanks <lb/>&amp; <sic>Iam</sic> glad to say we had <lb/>very few <sic>casualities</sic> in taking <lb/>them. Yes certainly the Irish <lb/>Div: was magnificent in the <lb/>taking of Ginchy a battle of the Somme, however, the history books say the main battle was on the 9th September in which there were high casualties, Marie must be referring to the advances after that date &amp; <sic>Iam</sic><lb/>glad to say the 16<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> Div: is <lb/>absolutely Irish â no English <lb/><sic>req</sic> to make up their <sic>strenght</sic>. <lb/>Well <sic>Imust</sic> close now as <lb/>I am writing this on duty <lb/>but want you to have a line <lb/> from me.  <sic>Iam</sic> frightfully distressed <lb/>to hear about poor Uncle <lb/>Frank &amp; will pray hard for  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0117_img_1200_4"/>
              his recovery <sic>Imust</sic> write to <lb/>him to-day â &amp; poor A. Maysie. <lb/><sic>Ihad</sic> a long cheery letter from <lb/>Granny yesterday.  Ask Nana if she ever sent <lb/> that corset <sic>ofmine</sic><sic>tobe</sic><lb/>cleaned &amp; settle as the one <lb/><sic>Iam</sic> wearing is in ribbons <lb/>if not will you send it into <lb/>Switzers &amp; have it <sic>down</sic><lb/> With fondest love to all. <seg type="closer"> Your ever<seg type="del">y</seg> loving &amp; grateful <lb/>daughter  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>