<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2594">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Diarmid Coffey to Jane Coffey, 16 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Diarmid Coffey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from Diarmid Coffey to his mother. Diarmid Coffey (1888-1964) joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914 and became secretary of the Irish National Volunteers after the organisation split in 1915 (it was the other group who participated in the Rising). He later served as assistant clerk of the Seanad.
Jane Coffey (née l&#39;Estrange) (1857-1921) was born into a Protestant family but married Catholic George Coffey and became a member of the National Literary Society.
The letter describes his time in Cork and refers to political matters, particularly the threat of Irish conscription in to the British army. Coffey notes that the people he has spoken to are all willing to fight conscription and suggests that it would take half a million troops to enforce it in Ireland.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Coffey &amp; Chenevix Trench Papers, Collection List No 153; Ms. 46,304/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2594</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0284">Diarmid Coffey</persName>
              <date>1916-10-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0609">Glengarriff, Co. Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0106">Jane Coffey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1823">Bath, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1964</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2594_img_202_1"  type="Letter"  url="48bb6f42661dae1e2cb8f5ed07fe4724.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2594_img_202_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0ba1d5e069cd820ba13d48a5597e75a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2594_img_202_3"  type="Letter"  url="22ff0e63a702450768b6f022fbeac203.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2594_img_202_4"  type="Letter"  url="36ac64e371e0d33034b73a677aa72d62.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2594_img_202_5"  type="Envelope"  url="9ee1ec3f639915583697533185d64372.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2594_img_202_1"/>
             Glengarriff, <lb/>Co. Cork.   Oct 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916.   Dear Mother,   Your notes have certainly been short. <lb/>I was interested in the cutting from the <lb/>"Daily News". There was a big anti-conscription <lb/>meeting at Limerick under Linden M.P. in <lb/>which he called on all the young men of <lb/>Ireland to rally around Redmond to resist <lb/>conscription &amp; to be prepared to resist it <lb/>in their thousands.   There are two very nice young Irish <lb/>officers in the Eccles with very sensible <lb/>views, almost as good as R.B's. It <lb/>is a comfort to think that a year in <lb/>the army has not made them imperialists. <lb/>I gather that they are by no means misguided.   I have talked to a good many of <lb/>the country people round here. The one <lb/>thing that interests them is conscription <lb/>&amp; they   all say that if they have to die
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2594_img_202_2"/>
            they'll die in their own country so that I <lb/>think it would take <hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi> a million men to <lb/><seg type="unclear">conscribe</seg> us and whatever they got of us <lb/>would only wait their chance to <seg type="del">go</seg>shoot <lb/>their officers &amp; any other English troops <lb/>that came handy. Take it all in all <lb/>I hardly think the gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> will be insane <lb/>enough to try &amp; there is always the off <lb/>chance of trouble here turning the   <lb/>in America &amp; Australia. If they <lb/>bring in conscription, I look forward, <lb/>should I survive it, to seeing the end <lb/>of the English.   I had a pleasant day yesterday. <lb/>Sailed in the morning &amp; tea on Garnish <lb/>in the afternoon. There are a <lb/>rather curious crowd at the Eccles. <lb/>The two officers I mentioned &amp; two others <lb/>one a rather nice little Rhodesian. <lb/>The stiff V. a rather nice woman <lb/>as   (I forget her name), a Lady Theodora D— ? and her daughter <lb/>the former a <seg type="unclear">decent</seg> stick the latter a <seg type="unclear">minx</seg> <lb/>&amp; a Miss —? who seems nice. Then      &amp; Lord Frederick Hamilton. I rather <lb/>like the latter but he is inclined to think himself amusing <lb/>when not trying to be funny he <seg type="unclear">talks</seg> very interestingly &amp; has seen a lot of the <seg type="unclear">Wouldings</seg> he has been in every country.    Yours   Diarmuid 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2594_img_202_3"/>
             Wed   I leave here for the Stockleys tomorrow <lb/>&amp; on to M<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> T. on Sat. I did <lb/>not go to Lynsaghts because L told <lb/>me that he would not be at home <lb/>this autumn. I only heard <lb/> through you that he might be there. <lb/>I had arranged with Stockleys to <lb/>go on Thurs (tomorrow) &amp; did not <lb/>like to change without reason or <lb/>to propose myself to them for more <lb/>than 2 nights.   I hope you will come home <lb/>for the winter. I shall be <lb/>back in Dublin the end of next <lb/>week &amp; shall go to L.P.A. until
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2594_img_202_4"/>
            you come but would not like to <lb/>stay there long.   I had a good Irish lesson <lb/>today.   Your   Diarmid   I am at Casey's Hotel. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2594_img_202_5"/>
             Mrs. Coffey <lb/>C/O Emily Lady Lawrence <lb/>Langridge <lb/>Near Bath      
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>