<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4369">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Strachey to Edward Carson, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Strachey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John St Loe Strachey (1860-1927) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.. Strachey was a British journalist and newspaper proprietor.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/19/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4369</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0792">John Strachey</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1526">Newlands Corner, Merrow Downs, Guileford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2022">5 Eaton Place, S.W., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4369_img_3724_1"  type="Letter"  url="120aa085017e400580d78bd9dd2d6eaa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4369_img_3724_2"  type="Letter"  url="29d6f678226f9ac07c7af73edb9a5898.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4369_img_3724_3"  type="Letter"  url="f20389a90d7b19b02027890aa0de579d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4369_img_3724_1"/>
             PAGE 1 OF 3   NEWLANDS CORNER, <lb/>MERROW DOWNS, <lb/>GUILFORD.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">Private &amp; Confidental.</hi>  Saturday, October 7th, 1916.   My dear Sir Edward,   I want, if you will kindly give it to me, your <lb/><hi rend="underline">direction and advice</hi> on a matter which I think is if some moment. <lb/>Last week when dealing in 2The Spectator" with the proposed appli- <lb/>cation of compulsory service of <lb/>making the following suggestion. "  Why should not the six county <lb/>area, which has again and again proved its Imperial spirit, in- <lb/>struct <seg type="del">you</seg>    Sir Edward Carson  as its spokeman in Parliament, to tell the House of <lb/>Commons that it desires to be placed under the Compulsory Service <lb/>Act, and that is  would  rrgard it, not as a burden, but as a privilege <lb/>to be allowed to di its full share in the work of guarding the <lb/>Empire and the mother country? The fact that they have urged <lb/>and victoriously maintained the claim to remain a part of the <lb/>United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, even if the rest of <lb/>Ireland secedes from the Union  ,  and occupies a position of politi- <lb/>cal isolation, makes it imperative upon them to demand that the <lb/>homogeneous area of the six counties, recodnised in the negotaitions
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4369_img_3724_2"/>
             PAGE 2 OF 3  <lb/>with Mr. Lloyd George, shall stand side by side with the rest of the <lb/>United Kingdom. Whether it would be practical to carry out the <lb/>applications of complsion to the six county area, I don;t know; <lb/>but I feel quite sure that the demand would not merely greatly em- <lb/>barrass the Nationalist politicans, who are now making so miserable <lb/>a show, but would also immensly strengthe the position of the men <lb/>of North East Ulster.   Such an offer as I have sketched would, it seems to me, <lb/>make it impossible <hi rend="underline">for all time</hi> forany statemen to dare to go <lb/>back upon the exclusion of the sic county area. It would in fact <lb/>do what for the last five years I have been seeking to do, that is, <lb/>to build up the idea of an invio<seg type="del">ate</seg>  able  area -an area with an inde- <lb/>feasible right to remain in the Union, and incorporate under the <lb/>Parliament of Westminister with the rest of the United Kingdom, <hi rend="underline">un-</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">less and until</hi> that area voluntarily expresses its wish to leave <lb/>the Union. Your negotiations with Lloyd George practically <lb/>achieved this; but an offer of the king i  we  suggest your making on <lb/>the floor of the House of Commons would put it beyond all possible <lb/>shadow of a doubt.   But though I cannot myslef are any objection to my saying <lb/>this is "The Spectator", I feel that there may be objections which <lb/>are hidden from me, and that in some way or other which I don't
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4369_img_3724_3"/>
             Page 3 of 3  <lb/>perceive the proposal in "The Spectator" might prove embarrassasing to <lb/>you. In that case of course I should not dream of making it. You <lb/>have, I feel, a complete right of vote in a matter of this kind, and <lb/>I should not presume to question that veto. At the same time I can <lb/>see, even if you did not think it advisable for you to raise the <lb/>matter in Parliament, there might be no harm in having the sugges- <lb/>tion ventilated in the press.  In view of these circumstances, would you be so very kind <lb/>as to let me have a line to say whether or not you forbid the banns? <lb/>If you do, I will not write. If on the other hand you say you have <lb/>no objection, I shall probably write on the subject next week. <lb/>I should like to know not later than by the first post on Wednesday, <lb/>at the Spencer Office, 1 Wellington Street, Strand, W.C. If I <lb/>hear nothing, I shall assume that you have at any rate no objection <lb/>to my writing what I like on the matter.   Yours very sincerely,   <hi rend="underline">John Strachey</hi>   The Rt. Hon. <lb/>Sir Edward Carson, K.C., M.P., <lb/>5 Eaton Place, S.W.    PS. Of course  I write  I shall meet the point that it would <lb/> not be safe to disman the six county area while <lb/> <seg type="unclear">faithless</seg> &amp; Disloyal Ireland retained all her men. <lb/> If the compulsory service was "by request" applied to N.E. Ulster <lb/> the Government must give a special pledge to afford the amplest <lb/> military protection to that part of Ireland which was willing to <lb/> fight for the Union of the Empire. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>