<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0586">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Chief Secretary’s Office to George K. Sherlock, 10 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Chief Secretary’s Office to George K. Sherlock, Sessional Crown Solicitor for County Cork, West Riding. James Campbell (1851-1931), Attorney-General for Ireland, 1916 This letter advises Mr. Sherlock that the Attorney-General has approved his application for leave of absence, nominating his partner in practice as his substitute.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13783</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/586</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-08-10T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None"> George K. Sherlock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1765">Bandon, County Cork, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0586_img_1989_1"  type="Letter"  url="9dc70c508538fde320fef8c0bced62d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0586_img_1989_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="987103a5b0e03bf441384bd456375917.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0586_img_1989_1"/>
                10th August 1916  <lb/>Leave of Absence  Dear Sir,   The Attorney General consents to your having the leave asked <lb/>for. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  <seg type="unclear">Grattan</seg>  K Sherlock Esq,   S.C. Solicitor,  Bandon  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0586_img_1989_2"/>
                Law Chambers  Bandon    <hi rend="underline">8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> August 1916</hi>    I George K. Sherlock, Sessional <lb/>Crown Solicitor for County Cork, <lb/>West Riding beg to apply for leave of absence <lb/>from the 18 <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> day of August 1916 to the 20<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><lb/>day of September 1916. <seg type="closer"> George K Sherlock <seg type="unclear">Leas Mooreson</seg><lb/>WR Co. Cork   To The Right Honourbale,   </seg> Proposed Substitute <lb/>Robert Webb Sherlock <lb/>Solicitor.  Qualification <lb/> Is my partner. Was sworn in <lb/>as a solicitor in 1889 and he <lb/>has for several years back acted <lb/>for me as a Substitute with the <lb/>consent of the Attorney General <lb/>at vacation time.    Crown case pending on which the <lb/>Sessl. Crown solicitor has been ordered to take <lb/>charge of which may possibly come on during his absence.   Title of Cause Nature of Case <lb/>Nil  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>