<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0645">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Patrick Morris SJ to Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ, 24 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr Patrick Morris</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Patrick Morris SJ (1882-1966) to Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941) written from the Officers’ Mess at 2/8 Battalion, L.F., Sobraon Barracks, Colchester, England. Morris claims he has survived an attack by two Zeppelins. One has been downed and “is lying a wreck in a field seven miles from here”. He cycled over and found it “just like an enormous skinned crocodile … all of Essex turned up in vehicles of every description … The crowd was very quiet”. He adds that “Airships are flying about all day in every direction”. He “is very happy here …. I am treated with the greatest kindness at the Mess and feel very much at home”. He expects he will be “packed off soon” but “is in no hurry to go”. He feels he is “in the Lord’s hands”. Patrick Morris attended the Model school in Enniskillen, where his father, Charles was the first headmaster in this multi-denominational school. Finishing his education at St MacCartan’s Seminary, Monaghan, Patrick entered the Jesuits whereupon he went to Australia and spent six years teaching at Xavier College, Kew. On returning from Australia, he was a chaplain for three years. He spent a year at the front before been sent back to England in November 1917, suffering from ‘clinical dysentery.’ After recuperation, he was stationed at Retford and Clipstone Camp in Nottinghamshire. In 1919, he taught at Mungret College and moved on to Belvedere College in 1924 where he spent 12 years, some as Rector. Further years were spent in Emo and then in 1943, Clongowes Wood College.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/43/3, IE IJA/CHP1/43/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/645</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0357">Fr Patrick Morris</persName>
              <date>1916-09-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0497">Officers’ Mess at 2/8 Battalion, L.F., Sobraon Barracks, Colchester, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0645_img_2116_1"  type="Letter"  url="747fb450b7cc08d05923a38f454d78b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0645_img_2116_2"  type="Letter"  url="46e02717d33a62759fc387b2b906f49f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0645_img_2116_1"/>
                Officers' Mess,  2/8 Batt. L. F.  Sobraon Barracks,    September 24, 1916.   My Rev and dear Fr. Provincial,     â P.C. <lb/>  Just a few lines to let you <lb/> know that I am still alive in spite of the fact that two Zeppelins <lb/> flew over us last night. One of them is lying a wreck in a field <lb/> seven miles from here. I cycled out with two of the officers <lb/> to see it this afternoon - it is just like an enormous <lb/> skinned crocodile. The crew are prisoners here in the <lb/> military lock - up. Cycling was very difficult on the way back,<lb/> as all Essex turned up in vehicles of every description to see <lb/> the 'Zepp..' The crowd was very quiet. Airships were flying <lb/> about all day in every direction and one landed here <lb/> beside the barracks in search of petrol. We all turned out <lb/> to see it off again.   I am very happy here at Colchester. I am treated <lb/> with the greatest kindness at the Mess and feel very much <lb/> at home. Fr. Bloomfield, the Rector of the Church, could not <lb/> be more hospitable. He has been connected with the army <lb/> for fourteen years and has been extremely useful to me <lb/> on several occasions. On weekdays I say Mass at eight <lb/> o'clock in his church. On Sunday I have two Masses, <lb/> the first for the Manchesters at Wivenhoe Camp at 8.30 <lb/> the second, the military Mass for about 500 soldiers in <lb/> Colchester Church - Fr. Bloomfield's. The number of  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0645_img_2116_2"/>
              Australian soldiers are stationed at Brightlingsea some <lb/> ten miles from here, among them an Old Xavier boy, <lb/> whom I taught in Melbourne eight years ago. I see him <lb/> every Sunday and sometimes I cycle during the week <lb/> to their billets in B'sea. Nearly every evening I have <lb/> some of the soldiers up to see me and I have two converts <lb/> on hand. I had a third, but I think, in fact I am sure <lb/> he was not sincere - he merely wants to be a Catholic in <lb/> name to secure some Catholic girl and I am pretty <lb/> certain he would not bother much about his religion, once <lb/> the marriage ceremony was over. However he may come<lb/> on again. One of the other two is an exceedingly fine <lb/> young fellow, very clever, and will know his Catechism <lb/> well in a very short time. I hope to be able to hand him<lb/> over to Fr. Bloomfield at the end of next week.   I suppose that when I have just got to know <lb/> the men well here I shall be packed off somewhere else. <lb/> I am in no hurry to go, I feel I could go further and <lb/> fare much worse. However I am in God's hands and <lb/> I always hold myself ready for the road. - I am having <lb/> a little difficulty in securing the allowance (Â£10) for the <lb/> portable - altar. Colonel France (at headquarters here) discussed <lb/> the matter with me the other day and referred me to the head<lb/> Chaplain. Lt - Col Roberts (my immediate Superior) told me <lb/> he had no powers in the matter. I don't think there will be <lb/> any difficulty finally, as I can assert that I cannot get on <lb/> without it.  <seg type="closer"> Commending myself to Your Reverence's Holy Sacrifices <lb/> and prayers, I remain, Very Rev. and dear Fr. Provincial,<lb/> Yours sincerely in X-,   Patrick J Morris SJ.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>