<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2790">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Rev Robert Kelson to Mrs. Burns, 10 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Rev Robert Kelso</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a next  of kin letter  from Rev Robert Kelso, Principal Chaplain&#39;s Dept,Bologne Base, B.E.F. France to Mrs Burns whose son died in the Canadian Hospital, Bologne.

He advised Mrs Burns that her son had appeared to be recovering well from his wounds, was in good spirits but then suffered a sudden relapse and died. He expressed his shock at the unexpected death, offered his deepest sympathies and gave details of her son&#39;s burial in France in grave number 4039. 

He added that her son&#39;s life and great sacrifice must surely be pleasing to God.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Kelso Papers, D3019/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2790</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0766">Rev Robert Kelso</persName>
              <date>1916-10-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1130">Chaplain&#39;s Dept, Bologne Base, B.E.F. France </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs. Burns</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0755">74 Paisley Rd., Renfrew, Scotland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2790_img_2208_1"  type="Letter"  url="47b42c005461bad0edf63aaca960600f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2790_img_2208_1"/>
             Mrs Burns <lb/>74 Paisley Rd. <lb/> Renfrew <lb/>Scotland   Serg. Geo. Burns (8641) <lb/>2nd Canadians   Principal Chaplains Dept <lb/>Boulagne Base <lb/>B.E.F. France   9.10.16   Dear Mrs Burns   I am sure you will have heard the <lb/>bad news of your son's death &amp; I feel I must write to say <lb/> how much I feel for you in your loss. After my last <lb/> letter to you he was so much better that he said he <lb/> had written you himself so I did not do so. I thought <lb/> he was on the sure road to recovery &amp; I was terribly <lb/> disappointed when he suddenly became worse &amp; passed <lb/> away. He was in such good spirits &amp; so confident <lb/>of recovery that the relapse was - to me - as unexpected <lb/> as it was sudden. He was buried in the military <lb/> cemetery here - on 8th <seg type="del">Sept</seg> Oct. - with full military honours <lb/> &amp; the number of his grave is - 4039. The authorities <lb/> will send you a photo of the grave on application to <lb/> "Director of Graves Registration &amp; Enquiries, War Office <lb/>Winchester House, St James Sq. London S.W." but <lb/> it may be a little time before they can reply to you. <lb/>Will you please accept my sincerest sympathy &amp; believe <lb/> me when I say that everything possible was done for your <lb/> son's comfort &amp; welfare while in Hospital. He has <lb/> made the great sacrifice &amp; such a life &amp; death as his must <lb/> surely be well-pleasing in the sight of Him who saith <lb/> greater love hath no man than that a man lay down <lb/> his life for his friends.   Sincerely Yours    R Kelso 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>