<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3886">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 25 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to his father, Hugh Doyle, regarding his activities before being sent to the front. Doyle informs his father that their deployment date has been delayed due to an outbreak of sickness. However, Doyle believes this may be for the best as soldiers from the 16th are being sent back from France for more training. Doyle writes about spending several days in London and convincing Fr Bernard Vaughan to come to the camp to give a talk.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3886</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-01-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1503">Bordon Camp, Hampshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1210">Melrose, Dalkey, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3886_img_3265_1"  type="Letter"  url="65a95efe8a66bc5af0446646573abb15.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3886_img_3265_2"  type="Letter"  url="bc7c5657a16402fb812bd0019cbb8ffe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3886_img_3265_3"  type="Letter"  url="dba2235bcaddfbcf16e2912b42423ad3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3886_img_3265_4"  type="Letter"  url="2f77bbc8626932a8314bc95c9fe59cb9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3886_img_3265_5"  type="Letter"  url="d584c8df84046920e799f2ec19e4c131.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3886_img_3265_6"  type="Letter"  url="0a9af76f6b7cfdd823363319d8bdd163.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3886_img_3265_1"/>
             J2/83 (20)   Borden Camp.    25/1/'16.   ROYAL IRISH FUSILIERS<lb/>8th (SERVICE) BATTALION.   My dear Father,    <seg type="foreign">L'homme</seg><lb/>propose but the Lord<lb/>knocks the skittles down —<lb/>another version of the old<lb/>proverb. Everything was<lb/>arranged for us to leave<lb/>for the Front on Mon:<lb/>31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> when some sickness<lb/>broke out in Camp &amp;  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3886_img_3265_2"/>
             2.<lb/>now we do not know<lb/>when we are going. Perhaps<lb/>after all it does not<lb/>make much difference<lb/>as the War Office has<lb/>at last discovered that<lb/>soldiers, officers especially<lb/>cannot be made in a<lb/>day and that other<lb/>things besides bravery<lb/>count at the Front.<lb/>The result is that a<lb/>large number of the<lb/>new troops, including<lb/>the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division, have<lb/>been sent back to<lb/>the base in France  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3886_img_3265_3"/>
             3.<lb/>to do more training, so<lb/>that though we are<lb/>all a bit put out<lb/>through so many false<lb/>starts and disappoint—<lb/>ments we are jolly<lb/>glad to remain here<lb/>instead of being<lb/>stuck in a French<lb/>camp away from all<lb/>the fun (?).  I have been away in London<lb/>for three days, a welcome<lb/>break from the deadly<lb/>monotony of camp life.<lb/>I had some little business<lb/>to do which I combined  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3886_img_3265_4"/>
             4.<lb/>with a generous <seg type="unclear">measure</seg><lb/>of pleasure and sight<lb/>seeing. While at <seg type="unclear">Farm St</seg><lb/>I asked Fr Bernard Vaughan<lb/>if he could manage to<lb/>come down &amp; give my<lb/>men a talk; he very<lb/>kindly promised to do<lb/>so and gave us a<lb/>most amusing and in—<lb/>teresting talk last Sunday,<lb/>quite a distinguished<lb/>gathering being present,<lb/>including the General,<lb/>who was very gratified<lb/>by the honour done his<lb/>Brigade. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3886_img_3265_5"/>
             J2/83 (21) 5.  ROYAL IRISH FUSILIERS<lb/>8th (SERVICE) BATTALION.  Your welcome letter has<lb/>just reached me; for<lb/>which many thanks.  I must congratulate<lb/>you on being made an<lb/>S.J. — I <seg type="unclear">presume General</seg><lb/>of the Irish Province —<lb/>That being so I shall be<lb/>deeply grateful if you<lb/>will see that all future<lb/>£5 find their way in<lb/>this direction and are<lb/>not mopped up by the<lb/>Rev <seg type="unclear">Limerick shark</seg>! 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3886_img_3265_6"/>
             6.<lb/>I am sorry I must<lb/>cut this letter short<lb/>as I am called away<lb/>and may not have a<lb/>chance of writing for<lb/>some time. If any<lb/>news comes of our departure<lb/>I shall let you know<lb/>in good time.  <seg type="foreign">Au revoir. </seg>Excuse haste<lb/>Ever your loving<lb/>Will. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>