<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0808">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 27 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender discusses Lillian&#39;s holiday arrangements and family issues. He mentions a meeting with an acquaintance, the continuing failure of the Gazette to announce his promotion, and his hope that his brother Rex will be promoted to captain. He suggests that his superior&#39;s alterations of Spender&#39;s dispatch was so poor that the correction required correction. He finishes the letter with details of his visit to the trenches, declaring that he will never again go with the same companion if he can help it; said companion officer violated Spender&#39;s &#39;first superstition&#39; by claiming that any trench he had been in was never shelled, and also refused to crawl in a one-foot-deep trench, though in full view of the enemy.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/399</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/808</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0808_img_2350_1"  type="NULL"  url="6020ddcc39330993d1725c052c3f261d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0808_img_2350_2"  type="NULL"  url="15de87e40d6494c7ae5d467c85a9494d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0808_img_2350_3"  type="NULL"  url="70459d99c548cf8786228d4eb858c8ee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0808_img_2350_4"  type="NULL"  url="e2e8bb5f2f0d81bca9523ee495ec16ca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0808_img_2350_1"/>
                27 Aug   My pr   I write a short letter now as I <lb/>may not have any time tomorrow as I <lb/>am going up to the line for the day.  I shall be <hi rend="underline">delighted</hi> to let you carry out <lb/>your suggestion about the family holiday. There <lb/>is only one difficulty, that mater if she heard <lb/>of it might not understand. I agree with you <lb/>in doing things in the days of our prosperity <lb/><seg type="del">and</seg> though we shall not be able to do <lb/> them later, I know, and anything which will  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0808_img_2350_2"/>
              make your holiday a real one. I am so <lb/>glad to hear of <seg type="unclear">Mrs</seg> Hussey's offer. It is kind <lb/>but I think it is up to one of the others to <lb/>take a turn. It is good of the Mother to <lb/>come &amp; help. I am sure she is very useful, &amp; <lb/>I hope not too much of a tax on her. I rather <lb/>think it may be good for her &amp; also for the <lb/>Pater that she shall have a little outside <lb/> interest tho' this does not distract from her <lb/> help. You will follow my meaning.  I find Withard  GS02  of the XV Corps was a <lb/>contemporary of Edmund's at Radley I was <lb/>with him today &amp; go up I hope with him <lb/> tomorrow. It is curious that my <seg type="unclear">gazette</seg> is  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0808_img_2350_3"/>
              <lb/>so long in coming. I wonder if there is a hitch. <lb/>I wish they would make Rex a Captain. From <lb/>his last letter I judge that he is settling in a bit <lb/>now.  I got off a letter to Mater really a good <lb/> bw, &amp; rather scolded her for her scolding. I hope <lb/>you will see her when as soon as she returns from the <lb/><seg type="unclear">Rundle's</seg> &amp; invite yourself to dinner. If you could <lb/>stop there a few days before you settle into <lb/>your new home it would be nice but don't <lb/> tire yourself with her deafness. It will mean <lb/>many extravagant taxies to the Palace ahem!  Did I tell you that K's correction to my draft <lb/>was so bad that I had to correct his correction <lb/>quite a lot. Today mine was passed with only one  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0808_img_2350_4"/>
              â Sunday â <lb/>line alteration. Tomorrow morning's won't be <lb/>mine so I hope you won't think it above the <lb/>average. Sunday morning 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> It looks like a wet <lb/>day and I am waiting for my orderly who wants to <lb/>go with me.  Just back after rather tiring and quite exciting time <lb/>but I will not go with Withard again if I can help it. He <lb/>went against my first   by saying they never <lb/>shelled him, and later when we found ourselves in a trench <lb/>1 foot deep within full view of the enemy he seemed inca- <lb/>table of crawling. It got rather on my nerves when I began <lb/>thinking of how we were to get him back. He was distinct- <lb/>ly done up but even so he ought to have gone slower if <lb/>necessary. However, we got through all right after some un- <lb/>pleasant shaves, a lot of mud a torn new mackintosh <lb/>and plenty of exercise.  Barge was with us. Mrs Barge has a little son I <lb/> was to be sure to tell you. If little p r had come now <lb/>the Ulstermen would have suffered so perhaps it is better for <lb/>one to come later. <seg type="closer"> Your bw  WB Spender. </seg><seg type="postscript"> I think it very <lb/> good marks for writing to me again &amp; <seg type="unclear">my pr</seg> but not if you were really tired.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>