<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2638">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 8 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

In this letter Celia writes a chatty letter to her mother. She writes about her of her nursing duties in London General Hospital, her uniform, meeting with people from Antrim and family members.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Collection D2109/10/1/A/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2638</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1291">3rd London General Hospital, London England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2638_img_2064_1"  type="Letter"  url="c170b05a433b640b56e6e1f33c36f739.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2638_img_2064_2"  type="Letter"  url="d3820120630791432ef5012ccaab8524.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2638_img_2064_3"  type="Letter"  url="74bff3d9d593b6fa4699cc1c49d8d70f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2638_img_2064_4"  type="Letter"  url="254ba1de16cebbfd3f4ad74029bd9495.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2638_img_2064_5"  type="Letter"  url="4a159150bf839459fe2a89beb520f08b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2638_img_2064_1"/>
             3<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rd</hi></hi>London General Hospital.   <hi rend="underline">Friday. Jan 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>   Dearest Mamma   I wonder how everybody at home is, <lb/>I hope the Christmas chills are all over. <lb/>I just got a wire from Terry as I <lb/>came on duty  to night saying that he <lb/>had arrived and asking me to lunch <lb/>with him. It had been sent off in <lb/>the morning but as I was <seg type="del">a</seg> in bed in <lb/>my billets all day, I never got it <lb/>till too late to get at him in any <lb/>way, but perhaps I may be able <lb/>to see him on his way back if I <lb/>hear in time. Unfortunately <lb/>had just had my night off the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2638_img_2064_2"/>
            day before. I went to St. Sidwell's <lb/>and had a nice visit there. The <lb/>two elder sisters were there for <lb/>Christmas with their husbands, two <lb/>greek brothers called Constandouros <lb/>who were not very attractive. One <lb/>of them had two dear little boys, <lb/>very good looking, and the other a <lb/>young baby, still in arms, with a <lb/>great thatch of brown hair. A young <lb/>doctor came to see baby while I <lb/>was there and I discovered afterwards <lb/>he was Peggy Beagley's husband and <lb/>that the Tellings had been at the <lb/>Beagley wedding and had met Hilda <lb/>Finlay.   Winnie was in town when I arrived, <lb/>and had booked seats for a matinee <lb/>at the Haymarket. After lunch, <lb/>I motored up with Mrs Constandouros, <lb/>met Winnie, and saw Henry <lb/>Ainlee in "Who is the?"The plot is <lb/>based on Mrs Bellue Loundes grue- <lb/>some "Lodger", if you remember it, <lb/>but is really quite different as the <lb/>play is a comedy and really <lb/>most amusing in parts.The lodging <lb/>house keeper was simply perfect, <lb/>and Henry Ainlee most amusing as <lb/>the lodger. Marjorie wouldn't <lb/>come as she had broken her arm <lb/>out riding and was afraid of
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2638_img_2064_3"/>
            getting it knocked as she can't use <lb/>it at all yet. We called at <lb/>a war work depot where Mrs <lb/>Tilling was working and I found <lb/>Peggy Beazley (as was) there, who was <lb/>most surprised to see me. I imagine <lb/>the Tillings must have made their <lb/>money pretty lately, everything in the <lb/>house is so modern and new. The <lb/>big hall is very pretty with a <lb/>huge fireplace and comfortable <lb/>sofas and chairs all round.   Emma's parcel for me arrived safely <lb/>to-day, what a quaint Eastern <lb/>little bell, it is really very <lb/>pretty.   I have just been looking at
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2638_img_2064_4"/>
            French's despatch, it is desperate reading, <lb/>What an utter waste the whole thing <lb/>seems to have been. The men seem <lb/>to have been extraordinarily brave. Most <lb/>of the ones in this ward seem to <lb/>have come from Anzac, very often <lb/>after they arrive here, they keep <lb/>starting up and calling out in <lb/>there sleep.   There is a chance I may get on day <lb/>duty again next saturday, if not <lb/>I shall have another fortnight to <lb/>do.   I went to St. John's Gate the other <lb/>morning to get my shoulder <seg type="unclear">tilles</seg>, <lb/>such a quaint old place in
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2638_img_2064_5"/>
            in a most unrespected part, with old <lb/>towers and winding stone stairs. I <lb/>wandered about and peeped into a <lb/> good many of the rooms. It is <lb/>built over both sides of the street <lb/>with an old connecting archway. <lb/>I didn't see Mrs Oliver as she <lb/> hadn't arrived yet, but one of <lb/>the ladies helping looked up my <lb/>name. We each have a separate <lb/>file apparently with an account <lb/>kept of our doings.I saw Emma's <lb/>there too.   I must order my new caps, they <lb/>are like large white handkerchiefs <lb/>tied tightly round the head with the <lb/> tails hanging down behind. Only <lb/>the pretty girls look nice in them, <lb/>as all the hair is covered up, <lb/>and the ones with ugly features look <lb/>very plain.   Please thank the others for all <lb/>their nice letters.   Lots of love to you <lb/>from   <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi>   I wore my new blouse at the Tillings, <lb/>it fits beautifully and looked <lb/>awfully nice. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>