<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2938">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 23 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1916 served at Advanced General Headquarters, his duties mainly involving the writing of reports for the cabinet, for the Press, and for posterity. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian  was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund during the war, and a member of the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps.

In this letter, Spender briefly discusses a visit Lillian made, a number of stamps he received from her, the health of a fellow officer&#39;s wife, and his mother&#39;s complaints that she has heard very little of him. He refers to the imminence of Devolution in Ireland. He mentions that he is suffering from hay fever, and in a postscript writes that it is all for the best that his brother Rex believes that his mother is the origin of all the parcels he has been receiving.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/395</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2938</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2938_img_2345_1"  type="NULL"  url="b364c0e580a8e1aff357a0e38cfc77df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2938_img_2345_2"  type="NULL"  url="a0756784a565202cbd751de117c41214.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2938_img_2345_3"  type="NULL"  url="d15f3cf2a6a8e4c6b76b5638c04adca4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2938_img_2345_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/395   23rd Aug    My pr   Your visit to Clyff Hall does seem<lb/>to have been a success but unless I get definite<lb/>news tomorrow I am not quite clear if you are<lb/>going to pay another this week-end.  Yes, your stamps did come. I thought it was<lb/>pr's birthday present (?) sent a little in advance. As a<lb/>matter of fact b w was rather good not to crow - one of<lb/>this  strange animal's  many accomplishments - before then pr had had a chance<lb/>to explain. It was touch and go with the stamps.  Mater needs a visit badly &amp; complains she<lb/>is getting no news of me. I must try to write to her,<lb/>but if you can invite yourself to a meal soon.    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2938_img_2345_2"/>
             Brice writes no leave in the Ulster Div but Rich<lb/>Andrews has got home as his wife is not well I am<lb/>sorry to say.<lb/>Well we must leave our Japanese travels alone at<lb/>present but they might be possible only what about<lb/>my directorates etc. there and Ulster? <seg type="unclear">Lord Sullivan's​​</seg><lb/>letters strikes me as the most illogical one I have<lb/>ever read, but seems to indicate that some form<lb/>of Devolution is certain - as far as I can make out<lb/>mainly because of the Sinn Fainers rebellion. One<lb/>would imagine that Carson and Redmond are going<lb/>to form a party!! I suppose Ivy brought back<lb/>no political news. I am visiting the Reserve<lb/>and IV army   this afternoon but don't expect<lb/>to see Gough. In any case we were not as<lb/>sympathizers as J'G &amp; I were. I have a    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2938_img_2345_3"/>
             fighting cold ! or hay fever &amp; rather suspect the<lb/>latter. So much in hand just now that<lb/>I must not attempt my usual 4 pages.  Just as much your C W as ever tho'  (poor C W )   Wilfred B Spender   PS I believe Rex thinks all parcels are from<lb/>Mater - <seg type="unclear"></seg>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>