<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5953">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur Eagleston to the Under Secretary for Ireland, 8 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur John Eagleston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Arthur Eagleston (1870-1944) to the under secretary for Ireland regarding the appointment of Charles C. Broy as the Vice Consul for the United States in Dublin.Arthur John Eagleston was a civil servant who served as assistant secretary of the British Home Office from 1913-1932.At the time this letter was written Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was serving as the under secretary for Ireland. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as the replacement for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916-9773</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5953</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0023">Arthur John Eagleston</persName>
              <date>1916-06-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0856">Home Office, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5953_img_2655_1"  type="Letter"  url="4914a45472505b4e8a58e5cebb038ded.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5953_img_2655_1"/>
               HOME OFFICE,  WHTEHALL.    8th June, 1916.   Sir,   The United States Ambassador<lb/>at this Court having notified to His Majesty's Government the appointment<lb/>of Mr. Charles C. Broy, of Virginia,<lb/>as Vice Consul for the United States<lb/>at Dublin, I am directed by the Secretary<lb/>of State to request that you will give directions to the proper authorities, at<lb/>your earliest convenience, to recognise that Gentleman in the capacity to<lb/>which he has been appointed, if there should be no objection to that course,<lb/>and that you will inform the Secretary of State whether such directions have<lb/>been given. <seg type="closer"> I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,   A.J.Eagleston   The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle.  </seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>