<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5246">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from 'Kit' to 'Billy', [1923]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kit </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/26/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5246</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0036">Kit </persName>
              <date>1923--</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Billy </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5246_img_None_1"  url="e28cac37949210195d3a760c009955bf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5246_img_None_2"  url="96d6f9b353418f43cfc29ee3a8ca89a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5246_img_None_3"  url="a82e0527a47fc0bc7b21d63461734618.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5246_img_0_1"/>
              P41/26/1    Dear Bill,   I was very pleased to get your<lb/>letter a few days ago. Really I am ashamed<lb/>for having neglected writing for such a long time<lb/>but “ when I am bad I am very bad “ you know.<lb/>All here are quite well. I suppose you have<lb/>heard that Kathleen did not come back to Kerry<lb/>after the summer holidays , so now I have to<lb/>keep a maid. She is from Mollie's place<lb/>and on the whole she is quite all right. I was<lb/>at <seg type="unclear">Cferg</seg> on Sun. last. They are all first class<lb/>there. We met the whole family except the<lb/>agricultural Dick. He was on holidays somwhere<lb/>as usual. He is as big an idler as ever.  Mick got married on Tuesday last. He had<lb/>a big turn out - something like fourteen motors    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5246_img_0_2"/>
             ? ? got ?<lb/>the wedding I _______ the ___<lb/>day, but I didn't see him. I'm sure he is as<lb/>fat as ever.  Ciss went off on Wed. last, but I haven't heard<lb/>a word since. In fact I haven't seen her for<lb/>nearly three months. Oh by the way, there<lb/>was a great round up here to day don't<lb/>get excited - it was only the dogs this time.<lb/>The Civic Guards made a swoop on <seg type="unclear">B . . .</seg><lb/>&amp; found umpteen dogs without a licence - three or<lb/>four at Griffins, &amp; horses, two at Denbys, one at<lb/>Julie Egan's &amp; one at  ?  Sheehy's. I don't know<lb/>how Mrs Sullivan fared. They have eleven in all<lb/>&amp; I'm sure they paid only for four. Mrs Fluffy<lb/>has lost an eye. You should see her now. She<lb/>is uglier than ever. Libby is in greta form. Its<lb/>well that she needn't go on the run. She is the<lb/>nicest little dog of the whole bunch.  Your mother hasn't yet got that <seg type="unclear">. . .</seg> bill<lb/>I'd love to get one &amp; I shall send you the thread 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5246_img_0_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">3</hi>  the first chance I get. I heard that you have<lb/>a picture frame for me. I hope you don't let<lb/>it go astray. What skilled workers you'll be<lb/>when you come home.  Susie hasn't yet got a permanent place<lb/>but I'm sure one will turn up soon. Nellie &amp;<lb/><seg type="unclear">. . .</seg> have grown very tall &amp; Nora is a<lb/>real stack. She was very pleased with your<lb/>little medal. I gave her a cuffing ?<lb/>for not writing to you. Mrs Maurice went to<lb/>Dublin this morning. She took Mickie to a doctor<lb/>again. The poor kid wasn't too  l  well lately.  There is nothing strange here. The<lb/>folks around often enquire for you &amp; wonder<lb/>when you'll return.   With all best wishes from<lb/>your fond cousin Kit   <hi rend="underline">ps</hi><lb/>I shall send on a cake to morrow or<lb/>after. I had no letter from Jim.<lb/>K 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>