<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0266">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Stanislaus Murphy to Robert Chalmers, 10 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Stanislaus Murphy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Stanislaus Murphy (b. 1870), the secretary to the Commissioners of Education in Ireland, to Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), Under-Secretary for Ireland. The letter is regarding the Report by the Commissioners of Education for the year of 1915, which is enclosed. Murphy states that due to the destruction of many buildings in Dublin as a result of the Easter Rising, only one copy could be provided. The enclosed report discusses the position of various schools, discussing such things as expenditure and income for the year of 1915.Chalmers became Under-Secretary for a brief period following the resignation of Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who relinquished his position following his administrational failure during the 1916 Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5611/8013</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/266</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1428">Stanislaus Murphy</persName>
              <date>1916-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1308">6 Grafton Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0890">Dublin Castle</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_1"  type="Letter"  url="07bdf35d6249f85907fbab15e11636a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="6ed3da41c3a58f88a560cb726eab3833.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="b2fa4d6735a238861d08428a6e3ec70b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="9c07afdd508b0f4777070531dab8f2d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="282fc8248cb08c53277f47190a954c33.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="21b09efaef0833ece2d26f4d1aa841b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="d6c2be376043ff5a6faed056f309eec3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="4f0d51fe858e19defb87f976dfcc9f1b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="c75c99e77856c126d775af00f3f2fe82.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_10"  type="Enclosure"  url="c195ac4ea53e87341b1c656fa795fd1c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_11"  type="Enclosure"  url="3b0a43d6ca411a898b48b16b65316595.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_12"  type="Enclosure"  url="578591bd9e8faea8077c2a890b832961.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_13"  type="Enclosure"  url="0dda07ef8a1cbce136e264c1feadd7b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_14"  type="Enclosure"  url="5df3f844b774066fef3011d56afe8c15.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0266_img_1452_15"  type="Enclosure"  url="35a81c39dc328f9377f5e31ce4d4436f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_1"/>
                THE COMMISSIONERS OF EDUCATION IN IRELAND,  6, GRAFTON STREET, DUBLIN,    May 10, 1916.   S I R,   Herewith I beg leave to enclose three<lb/> presentation copies of the Report of my Commissioners<lb/> for the year 1915, the original whereof was forwarded<lb/> to you on the 12th ult.  In former years it has been the custom to<lb/> forward five presentation copies, but owing to the<lb/> destruction of property by fire which has recently<lb/> occurred on the premises of the Government Printers, no<lb/> further copies will be available for some time. <seg type="closer"> I am,<lb/> Sir<lb/> Your obedient Servant,  Stanislaus Murphy<lb/> Secretary,<lb/>  The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle.  </seg> I Ack. this letter<lb/> II Irish Office<lb/> with <seg type="unclear">deputies</seg> for presentation<lb/><seg type="unclear">enough</seg><lb/><hi rend="underline">23-v-16</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_2"/>
              53 GEO. III., CAP. 107; 3 GEO. IV., CAP. 79;<lb/> 48 &amp; 49 VIC., CAP. 78, SCHEME NO. 34.<lb/> EDUCATION (IRELAND),  1915.  ANNUAL REPORT<lb/> of the<lb/> COMMISSIONERS OF EDUCATION in<lb/> IRELAND.<lb/> FOR THE YEAR 1915.<lb/> Presented to both houses of Parliament by Command of his Majesty.  London:<lb/> PRINTED UNDER THE AUTHORITY OF HIS MAJESTY'S STATIONARY OFFICE<lb/> By A. THOM and CO. (LTD.), 87,88, and 89, ABBEY STREET.<lb/> To be purchased, either directly or through any Bookseller from<lb/> E. PONSOBY, LTD., 116, GRAFTON STREET, DUBLIN; or<lb/> WYMAN AND SONS, LTD., 29, BREAMS BUILDINGS, FETTER LANE, E.C., and 28, ABIGDON STREET,<lb/> S.W., and 54, ST. MARY STREET, CARDIFF; or<lb/> H.M STATIONERY OFFICE (Scottish Branch), 23, Forth Street, Edinburgh; <lb/> or from the Agencies in the British Colonies and Dependencies,<lb/> the United States of America and other Foreign Countries of<lb/> T. FISHER UNWIN, LONDON, W.C.<lb/> 1916  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_3"/>
             <seg type="head">TABLE OF CONTENTS</seg> REPORT OF THE COMMISSIONERS - - - - - - Page 1-5  Ulster Royal School Endowments, - - - - - - Page 2-3<lb/> Schools, Numbers, Efficiency, Premises, 'Qualified Schools,' - - - - - - Page 3<lb/> Alteration of Scheme, - - - - - - Page 3<lb/> The Local Boards, - - - - - - Page 3  Other Endowments--<lb/> Preston, - - - - - - Page 3<lb/> Carysfort, - - - - - - Page 3<lb/> Leamy, - - - - - - Page 4<lb/> Viscount Limerick;s Endowment, Dundalk,- - - - - - Page 4<lb/> Banks Endowment, Eyrecourt,- - - - - - Page 4<lb/> Diocesan School Funds and Banagher Endowment,- - - - - - Page 4<lb/> Limerick Diocesan School, - - - - - - Page 4<lb/>  Estate Management, - - - - - - Page 4<lb/> Rentals, - - - - - - Page 4<lb/> Arrears, - - - - - - Page 4-5  APPENDICES— Appendix A.-Accounts, - - - - - - Page 6-9<lb/> Appendix B.-Report of Inspection, - - - - - - Page 10-12<lb/> Appendix B.-Names and Attendance Rolls of Commissioners and Standing Committee, - - - - - - Page 10-12  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_4"/>
              ANNUAL REPORT <lb/> of the <lb/> COMMISSIONERS OF EDUCATION IN IRELAND <lb/> FOR THE YEAR <lb/> 1915 <lb/> TO HIS EXCELLENCY IVOR CHURCHILL BARON WIMBORNE <lb/> LORD LIEUTENANT GENERAL AND GENERAL GOVENOR OF IRELAND <lb/> May it please your excellency,<lb/> We the commissioner of education in Ireland beg to submit the following <lb/> General Report of our proceeding during the year 1915   Commission- it is with deep regret that we report the death of Very Reverend J. <lb/> M. Hamilton. D.D. M.A., which occurred on January 17, 1915. Doctor Hamilton <lb/> gave long and useful service to the Board. His appointment dates back to December <lb/> 1892 and he had frequently been elected to the office of chairman, in discharging <lb/> the duties of which his business capacity and impartiality were always much appre-<lb/> ciated. By warrants dated February 4, 1915. Your Excellency appointed Reverend <lb/><seg type="del">John</seg> L. Morrow, M.A.,in the room of doctor Hamilton and William Alexander <lb/> Goligher, Esquire, M.A Litt.D. F.T.C.D., in the room of R.Y. Tyrrell, Esquire, <lb/> Litt.D., S.F.T.C.D., who died in this previous year. At the close of 1914 the <lb/> Fermanagh Protestant Board of Education elected as their representative for the <lb/> succeeding year Reverend Canon Webb, M.A., in the room of Major Falls, M.A, on <lb/> active service   The names of the Commissioners and of the members constituting the Standing <lb/> are given on page 13. Five Board meetings and sixteen standing committee<lb/> Committee Meeting were held during the year, the attendance at which are also given on page 13.   Accounts.- on pp. 6-9 we give summaries of our accounts which have been <lb/> certified as correct by the Auditor of the local government board.  Income and expenditure.- Our total income, including the balance brought <lb/> forward from the previous year, was £8,550 5s. Id... and our expenditure, <lb/> £6,592 18s 1d, leaving a balance of £1,957 7s 0d available for the current year. <lb/> As compared with the previous year both income and expenditure show an increase <lb/> the former of 3295 14s 3d and the later of £288 18s 9d. the increased income <lb/> is due mainly to extra dividends - the result of a new investment in 3 1/2 per cent. War <lb/> Loan Stock and of a conversion of Consols into 41/2 per cent. War Loan Stock - and <lb/> to a payment in respect of an old debt on the Cappaloughlin estate; while the extra <lb/> expenditure is accounted for by increased grants for educational purposes. The <lb/> following Tables give a summary of income and expenditure.   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_5"/>
             <seg type="head">2 ANNUAL REPORT OF THE COMMISSIONERS OF EDUCATION IN IRELAND</seg> Table of figures  Capital.—Our capital account has undergone two changes during the year:—<lb/> (1) by the investment of £300 in £318 2s. 10d. 31/2 per cent. War Loan Stock, and<lb/> (2) by the conversion of 36,801 2s. 1d. Consols into £4,534 1s. 4d. 41/2 per cent. War<lb/> Loan Stock.  Ulster Royal School Endowments.  General.—We believe that, on the whole, the Schools sharing in these endow-<lb/> ments continue to be efficiently conducted. Of the twelve 'selected' Schools only<lb/> one failed to qualify under the Scheme, and this one is a School of small resources<lb/> which has never yet fulfilled the prescribed conditions. The return dealing with<lb/> the other eleven schools, their rolls, educational results, and the condition of the<lb/> School premises are, speaking generally, of a satisfactory character. For par-<lb/> ticulars on these points we would refer to the report of our Secretary, who, as Lord<lb/> Lieutenant's Inspector, visited the various Schools in September last. This report<lb/> will be found on pp. 10-12.  Numbers,—The total number of pupils on the rolls for the year 1914-15 was 686,<lb/> which is exactly the same as that for the previous year. It is to be noted, however,<lb/> that in 1913-14 twelve Schools were included, while in the returns for 1914-15 only<lb/> eleven Schools are dealt with. Taking the same eleven Schools for the two years<lb/> we find that the total roll had been a constantly diminishing<lb/> quantity—820 in 1909-10 having fallen to 686 in 1913-14. It should be mentioned,<lb/> too, that the whole increase registered for 1914-15 is due to boarders.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_6"/>
             <seg type="head">Annual Report Of The Commissioners Of Education In Ireland</seg> The number of pupils presented for the Intermediate Examinations in 1915 <lb/> was 390 out of a possible 461, or 84.5 per cent. of the Intermediate Roll. This compares<lb/> unfavourably with the 88 per cent. of 1914, and is the lowest since 1909-10, when the <lb/> percentage fell to 83.   Efficiency. —Tested by the Intermediate Examinations, the efficiency of the<lb/> Schools, taken as a whole, is creditable. Out of 390 presented for examination 271<lb/> were successful, that is the percentage of Passes is 69, as against a general percentage<lb/> for the whole country of 62. In 1914 the percentage of Passes was 68 for our special<lb/> Schools,and 59 for Irish Intermediate Schools generally.  School Premises. — The work of necessary upkeep received attention during the <lb/> year and the condition of the buildings in the case of ten of the Schools is good. In <lb/> the eleventh case, namely Cavan Royal School, it can only be said to be fair. The <lb/> grounds of St. Michael's School, Enniskillen, and of St. Patrick's Academy, Dun-<lb/> gannon, present a neglected appearance.  Qualified Schools. — We are satisfied that eleven of the twelve Schools selected by <lb/> the Local Boards of Education qualified under the Scheme, and we accepted as<lb/> evidence of this qualification the certificate of the Lord Lieutenant's Inspector (see <lb/> p. 12). The twelfth School, namely Ladies' Collegiate School, Enniskillen, failed<lb/> to qualify, and never having received a grant, it was not inspected.  Alteration of Scheme. — By an Amending Scheme, dated March 24, 1915, the<lb/> Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests, on our application, altered<lb/> the Scheme by reducing the necessary number of passes in the Intermediate Exami-<lb/> nations from seven to five. We considered this a desirable change in view of the<lb/> discontinuance of the Preparatory Grade Examinations.  Local Boards. —In accordance with Section 48 of the Scheme we received reports<lb/> from the various Local Boards of Education as to their proceedings during the<lb/> School year 1914-15. These reports were generally of a satisfactory character.  OTHER ENDOWMENTS.  Preston Endowment. —The gross income of this endowment was £1,154 17s 3d.<lb/> as compared with £925 6s 3d for the previous year, the principal cause of the <lb/> variation being a payment in respect of an old debt on the Cappaloughlin estate. <lb/> After payment of the necessary outgoings, the following allocations were made to <lb/> the Governing Bodies of the three Schools named:—King's Hospital, Oxmantown, <lb/> £196 19s 4d; Preston School, Navan, £483 1s 1d; and Preston School, Abbeyleix, <lb/> £373 1s 8d.  Preston School, Navan.—The number on roll is 17—8 boys and 9 girls, and the<lb/> number in average attendance is 143. Six pupils were presented for the Inter-<lb/> mediate Examinations and one passed. The Lord Lieutenant's Inspector reports:—<lb/> 'The Preston School has been doing good work during the past year under the present <lb/> Headmaster. He has, however, resigned the post, and the new Master will soon be <lb/> appointed.'  Preston School, Abbeyleix.—The Lord Lieutenant's Inspector reports that <lb/> although the Intermediate results are poor, the educational efficiency of the School <lb/> is fairly satisfactory. Only four pupils were presented for examination, and of <lb/> these but one passed. The number on the roll was the same as that of the previous<lb/> year, namely, 20, of whom 6 were boarders. The financial position is much <lb/> improved, and it is safe to anticipate a steady and substantial reduction in the debit<lb/> balance.   Carysfort Endowment.—The Schools sharing in this endowment are Sheana,<lb/> Ballinatone, Ballycreen, Aughrim and Mucklagh National Schools, the two first <lb/> named being under Protestant, and the remaining three under Roman Catholic <lb/> management. A sum of £137 was divided equally between the two denominations. <lb/> No change has taken place in the unsuitable condition of the Mucklagh premises. <cb/> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_7"/>
             <seg type="head">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE COMMISSIONERS OF EDUCATION IN IRELAND</seg> The leamy Endowment Limerick - During the year we distributed between the <lb/> Leamy Local Boards of Education a sum of £254 18s. 5d. The roll of the High<lb/> School under Protestant management was 536. Judging by the reports of the Lord Lieu-<lb/> tenant's Inspector both Schools continue to be efficiently conducted.  The Viscount Limerick Endowment, Dundalk.— Three Schools established their<lb/> claim to share in this Endowment, namely :-St. Mary's College, Dundalk, for<lb/> 13 pupils, the Educational Institution, Dundalk, for 18 pupils, and Christian<lb/> Schools, Dundalk, for 1 pupil. We divided the sum of £53 4s. Od. amongst them<lb/> in proportion to these numbers.  Banks Endowment, Eyecourt.— During the past year, for the first time since<lb/> the Scheme came into operation, the Trustees of the endowment found themselves in<lb/> a position to submit a plan for its application. A School having been opened at <lb/> Eyrecourt under the management of Very Reverend Dean Aldridge, it was suggested<lb/> that the fund should be devoted to the teaching of Shirtmaking, Knitting, etc. in<lb/> that School. This suggestion was approved and a sum of £15 12s. 2d was paid in<lb/> furtherance thereof.  The Diocesan Schools and Banagher Royal School Endowments.— In accordance <lb/> with the plan adopted some years ago we paid the following sums on behalf of<lb/> pupils attending Schools in the districts named: — £12, Dioceses of Leighlin and <lb/> Ossory; £26, Dioceses of Meath and Ardagh; £28, Dioceses of Tuam, Killala and<lb/> Archonry; and £30, King's County. A sum of £40 was offered for competition in<lb/> the last named district— £24 for boys and £16 for girls. As only one girl qualified<lb/> receiving a £6 prize, the balance of £10 has not yet been applied. We also disti-<lb/> buted a sum of £56 as grants towards the better equipment of eight Secondary<lb/> Schools in the King's County.  Lattone School. Anne Hall Endowment.—The portion of the income of this<lb/> endowment applicable to Lattone School continues to be devoted to the reduction of <lb/> the debt incurred in repairing the enlarging the Schoolhouses. These are now in<lb/> good condition and are used not only for ordinary School purposes, but also for giving <lb/> instruction in Wood-work, Poultry-keeping, and Cooking and Domestic Hygiene.  Limerick Diocesan School Endowment. — A sum of £79 16s. 0d., accumulated <lb/> income, was invested in £84 12s. 6d 3<hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi> per cent. War Loan Stock, and a sum of<lb/> £63 1s, 6d. Consols was converted into £42 1s. 0d. 4<hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi> per cent. War Loan Stock.<lb/> No expenditure was incurred during the year, and on December 31st last the property<lb/> in our possession, in addition to the School buildings, consisted of the two lots of <lb/> War Loan Stock just mentioned. £310 12s 6d. Railway Stock, and £24 9s. 4d. cash. <lb/> the income for the year being £39 19s. 11d.  ESTATE MANAGEMENT  On pp. 8-9, we give Summaries of our Rentals for the year 1913-1914, together <lb/> with our Agents' Accounts for the corresponding periods.  Rentals.— As compared with last year, the gross rental on the present occasion<lb/> shows an increase of £12 5s. 0d., the figures being £1,835 12s. 2s. now, as against<lb/> £1,823 7s. 2d. in 1914. The rental of Caryfort estate remains unchanged: Tyrone <lb/> Rental Proper is decreased by £9— a rent having been reduced by £4, and possession<lb/> having been taken of two holdings for non-payment of rent, the rental of the two<lb/> holdings amounting to £5: the Tyrone Bog Rental, which varies from year to year,<lb/> and which suffered a diminution of £29 17s. 6d. last year, is increased by £21 5s. 0d.  Arrears. — The general condition of the arrears compares very favourably with<lb/> that of last year, the total sum outstanding having decreased form £1,629 4s. 4d. to <lb/> £1,522 13s. 2d. Taking the estates separately, Carysford, at the date the account<lb/> was rendered (May 1, 1915) showed that less than a year's rent had been collected<lb/> and that the former arrears of £35 had risen to £42 19s. 2d. This is the highest<lb/> figure reached since 1906, and the Agent's attention having been called to the fact, he<lb/> asked for authority to take proceedings where more than six month's rent was due.<lb/> This was granted. It is satisfactory to add that within a month from the rendering of <lb/> the account a sum of £33 14s. 2d. had been collected. On the Tyrone Estate the net   
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_8"/>
             <seg type="head">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE COMMISIONERS OF EDUCATION IN IRELAND.</seg> result is the substantial decrease of £114 10s. 4d in the arrears - £114 0s 7d on the<lb/> Rental Proper, and 9s. 9d on the Bog Rental. We note this pronounced improvement<lb/> with satisfaction, and it is to the Agent's credit that in 31 cases he collected more<lb/> than a year's rent, thereby reducing the arrears by £140 1s. 5d. Further, this is<lb/> the seventh consecutive year in which a greater or less reduction has been effected.<lb/> All this is in the Agent's favour, but we must point out that in eight cases absolutely<lb/> no rent was collected -notwithstanding the instruction repeatedly issued that all<lb/> tenants should be made pay at least something each year - and in one case less than<lb/> a year's rent was collected. New arrears to the extent of £28 0s. 10d.were thus<lb/> allowed to accrue. Again on the Bog Rental, out of 264 lettings, no rent was<lb/> collected in 49 cases. As this is a large proportion of defaulters, we asked the Agent<lb/> for an explanation and he replied to the following effect:-r (1) Rental Proper. That<lb/> two tenants, the sum of whose rents amounts to £4 5s.3d., had paid since the returns<lb/> were furnished; that four he expected to pay soon; that one had promised to pay the<lb/> arrears with the next rent; and that in one case an Ejectment Decree had been<lb/> obtained. (2) Bog Rental: - That the tenants promised but did not pay in time to<lb/> be included; that several had paid since, and that he hoped for further payments<lb/> shortly.  We have again expressed to the Agent our opposition to the growth of new<lb/> arrears, and we have issued special instructions with regard to the Bog Rent which<lb/> should result in a more effective collection.  All which we have the honour to submit to Your Excellency as our Report in<lb/> the premises.  Sealed with our Common Seal at a Meeting<lb/> held this 12th day of April, 1916, and<lb/> forwarded for submission to Your Excel-<lb/> lency on the same date.  Present when the Seal was affixed -  James H Stronge Chairman  PJ Byrne<lb/> M A <seg type="unclear">Goligher</seg> Commissioners<lb/> J C Mac <seg type="unclear">Gisiley</seg><lb/> Arthur Webb<lb/> J L Morrow<lb/> Stanislaus Murphy <lb/> Secretary  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_9"/>
              List of appendices.  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_10"/>
              List of Accounts.  
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_11"/>
              List of Receipts.  
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_12"/>
              List of Accounts.  
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_13"/>
              School Rolls.- The total number of pupils on the rolls for the year just closed is 686,<lb/> which is exactly similar to that for the previous period. But it is to be remembered that on the<lb/> present occasion that returns include only eleven school as against twelve last year, and, consequently,<lb/> if we are to institute a proper comparison the number credited to the twelfth school in 1913-14<lb/> should be deducted from the total. The result is that the total (686) for the eleven school in<lb/> 194-15 shows the substantial increase of 39 on the total (647) for the same schools in 1913-14.<lb/> This is all the more satisfactory, and indeed remarkable, in view of the fact that during the four<lb/> previous years a constant diminution had taken place, the total of 785 in 1909-10 having fallen to<lb/> 647 in 1913-14. That the shrinkage has been arrested is good; that the loss has been partially<lb/> recovered is better. And just as it was difficult to account for the reduction of former years, so<lb/> too it is not easy to furnish an explanation for the improvement on the present occasion, more<lb/> especially as that improvement is altogether due to the increased number of boarders. Under<lb/> existing circumstances one would scarcely have been surprised had the number of boarders been<lb/> fewer; and the reduction, had it occurred, would probably have been attributed to the war. How-<lb/> ever, theory must give way to facts, and the facts in the present instance are all to the good.<lb/> Analysing the returns we find that boarders are increased by 40, and day pupils reduced by 1;<lb/> while if we distinguish between the sexes, the boys are more numerous by 37 and the girls by 3.  The most important variations in individual school rolls are increases in St. Patrick's Cavan<lb/> (24), St. Patrick's, Dungannon (13), St. Eunan's, Letterkenny (8), Royal School, Cavan (4);and <lb/> decreases in Raphhoe Royal School (5), and Enniskillen Royal School (5).  The number on the Intermediate Rolls, that is tose available for the intermediate Examina-<lb/> tions, was 461, as against 427 last year. Of the 461 possible candidates, 390 were presented<lb/> for examination, that is 84.5 per cent. This percentage is not only lower than that of last year,<lb/> When 88 per cent, of the possible candidates were examined, it is also the lowest since 1909-10,<lb/> when the percentage fell to 83. It is submitted that this drop is to be regretted and that it is<lb/> in the interest of the pupils generally- more especially the backward ones- that as many as possible<lb/> should have the incentive of preparing for the public ordeal. In this connection it is pleasing<lb/> to note that St. Marcarten's Seminary, with the characteristics thoroughness, sent forward absolutely<lb/> every pupil within the prescribed ages. Of the school in which the smallest proportion of pupils<lb/> was examined, viz., Royal School, Enniskillen, it is only fair to say that work was disorganised<lb/> during the year through changes in staff, particularly in the Headmastership.   Educational Efficiency. — Tested by the results of the recent Intermediate Examinations, the <lb/> schools, taken as a whole, have done well. The successful candidates number 271, out of 390<lb/> presented for examination, that is the percentage of 'Passes' is 69 as compared with 68 last year. <lb/> This is perhaps not a very substantial improvement, and it will appear even more insignificant<lb/> when we consider that the general results for the country as a whole show improvement, and<lb/> that, too, to a greater extent, the general percentage being 62 now as against 59 in 1914. <lb/> Accordingly, the special schools with which we are dealing still maintain a higher percentage of<lb/> 'Passes.' but on the present occasion their superiority in this respect is presented by a per-<lb/> centage of 7 as compared with one of 9 last year. Taking the sexes separately in our particular<lb/> schools, the boys have done much better than the girls, the percentage of 'Passes' being 70<lb/> and 63 respectively. On the other hand, in the general results for the whole of Ireland the girls<lb/> have shown themselves superior, their percentage of 'Passes' being 64, while that of the boys<lb/> is 61.  Of the eleven girls schools inspected six can boast improved results. Further, whether judged by<lb/> high percentages, by the number of subject taken, or by the few failures in individual papers,<lb/> those results are eminently satisfactory. In this connection special mention should be made of <lb/> Royal School, Armagh, St. Patrick's College, Cavan and St. Eunan's, Letterkenny, whose percen-<lb/> tages of successful candidates range from 70 to 84, and all of which include at least three<lb/> languages in addition to English in their curricula. Cavan and Raphoe Royal Schools have justified <lb/> the confidence placed in them last year by 'qualifying' on the present occasion, while of the five<lb/> schools which have suffered reverses, it is only necessary to say that these reverses are for the most <lb/> part trivial, and that no serious set-back is noticeable.  A close analysis of the results obtained by the various schools goes to show that English was <lb/> particularly successful, that in other languages some weakness betrayed itself in the Junior Grade,<lb/> and that Mathematics were responsible for the majority of the failures.  Buildings, Equipment, etc. — The buildings, taken as a whole, are now in very fair condition.<lb/> The same may not be said of the equipment, except that in some few cases desks and blackboards have<lb/> reached the limit of their service, and call for renewal. Effective painting and colouring have<lb/> been carried out in the Royal Schools of Armagh, Raphoe and Dungannon, and in St. Patrick's<lb/> Cavan, while the damp spots in the new wing of St. Patrick's, Armagh seem to have been success-<lb/> fully treated. Further, the roof of Enniskillen Royal School has received much needed and generous<lb/> attention, the substantial sum of £120 having been expended on the work.  In connection with the premises the following points were noted: —   Armagh Royal School.— The condition of the outdoor w.c's. might be better. Raphoe Royal School.— The roof of gymnasium is still slightly defective.<lb/> St. Ennian's Letterkenny, — Plaster has fallen from the walls in some places.<lb/> St. Macarten's Monaghan. — Flushing of outdoor w.c's. leaves something to be desired.<lb/> St. Michael's, Enniskillen.— Playground very neglected.<lb/> Dungannon Royal School.— Plaster at back of main building requires renewal.<lb/> St. Patrick's, Dungannon. — When the new railing has been completed the grounds will<lb/> need attention.  
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_14"/>
             <seg type="head">THE COMMISSIONERS OF EDUCATION IN IRELAND</seg> Health, etc. -In the early Spring two of the schools suffered from an epidemic of influenza, <lb/> and in one case its ravages were so serious that two trained nurses had to be requisitioned, and <lb/> eventually the school had to be closed down for a period of three weeks. Otherwise the schools<lb/> generally present a clean bill of health. Except where interfered with by the influenza the attend-<lb/> ance was creditably regular. In nine of the eleven schools instruction is given in drill. Discipline<lb/> is, for the cost part, well maintained.  Free Places. — All the schools provided free education for at least two pupils, although is one <lb/> case it does not appear that the fact was advertised as required by Section 59 of the Scheme. In <lb/> five school there was no competition, the number of applicants being either less, or only equal <lb/> to, the number of places offered. The proportion of candidates to places was largest in the cases <lb/> of St. Patrick's, Cavan, and St. Macarten's, Monaghan, and in the latter, the most successful <lb/> candidate scored 90 per cent.  Local Boards. — The various Boards have discharged efficiently their duties the Scheme,<lb/> and their Minutes and Accounts are carefully kept. The improvement in the attendance of lay <lb/> member, noted last year, still continues.  Schedule I. Qualified Schools. — I am satisfied that eleven schools mentioned on the first<lb/> page of this report as having been inspected have fulfilled all the necessary condition, and I beg <lb/> to report the compliance of each of these schools with the requirements of the Scheme in respect of <lb/> the school year ended August 1st, 1915.  The matters which call for attention, and to which I have alluded above, will be made the <lb/> subject of further reference in my detailed Report to His Excellence the Lord Lieutenant.  Stanislaus Murphy<lb/> Inspector.<lb/> October 5th, 1915.<cb/>  
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_0266_img_1452_15"/>
              Appendix C  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>