<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3775">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Clara Davidson, 23 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Davidson, informing her of life at the front. Davidson&#39;s company have returned to the front line but have had difficulty with the terrible weather. Despite the difficult conditions Davidson writes of his exciting engagement with the Germans the previous night. While suffering no casualties himself he hopes that the British guns inflicted many on the other side. 

This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers, D3642-B-8-45</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3775</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2119">Seacourt, Bangor, CO. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3775_img_3160_1"  type="Letter"  url="a9f16480ce0a346403005be4e79de299.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3775_img_3160_2"  type="Letter"  url="79f9b7ef916751a0278a21f0ea84cfe3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3775_img_3160_3"  type="Letter"  url="320be35cb1b7a8145d3bf74ce840ac72.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3775_img_3160_4"  type="Letter"  url="966866e343692f856f3389e268c68f8b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3775_img_3160_5"  type="Envelope"  url="7b2d90341bd986d82e33ee5db426fd76.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3775_img_3160_1"/>
              April 23, 1916     My dearest Mother     I have not been <lb/> able to wirte any letters for some <lb/> dayes as there has been so much <lb/> to attend to &amp; now I have several <lb/> to answer so excuse a rather <lb/> hurried line.   We are back again in the Line, but this time <lb/> we have only taken over part of what <lb/> we held before &amp; unfortunately <lb/> for my Comp we have not got that <lb/> same comfortable billet. None <lb/> of any kind were available so <lb/> we were put into tents in a <lb/> wood from which we can just <lb/> see the German Lines.    We moved <lb/> up on Thurs. &amp; were lucky enough <lb/> to get a fine day, for the ground <lb/> was in an awful state &amp; <lb/> it was not till late in the evg.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3775_img_3160_2"/>
            that the tents were pitched &amp; we <lb/> were able to get some food cooked, <lb/> while in addition we had of course <lb/> to take over the gun positions &amp; c. <lb/> Since then &amp; for days before it has <lb/> rained incessantly &amp; we know <lb/> had a very miserable time of it. <lb/> Tthe trenches too were in a <lb/> horrible condition. This is the <lb/> first day I have had dry feet &amp; <lb/> clothes since we left our billets. <lb/> It was impossible to get anything <lb/> dried - even the tents leaked - <lb/> but thank goodness today is <lb/> fine &amp; we have been able to <lb/> spread things out to dry.   I think I may be permitted to <lb/> tell you that we had a fairly <lb/> lively demonstration against <lb/> the Germans last night. My <lb/> guns were very busy &amp; it
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3775_img_3160_3"/>
             was a sight I shall never forget. <lb/> I was at the point with 2 guns <lb/> where I could see most of the <lb/> ground.   We were standing in <lb/> water &amp; it was pouring but the <lb/> excitement of it all made me <lb/> forget all discomforts &amp; I <lb/> would not have missed it for <lb/> anything.    I had no casualties <lb/> but hope the guns made a good many    With this move <lb/> mails have been a little disorganised <lb/> that is to say as regards parcels <lb/> but I expect they will begin <lb/> to arrive again tomorrow. <lb/> Would you please tell Malcolmson <lb/> to repeat the trimmed bacon they <lb/> sent in our parcel.    It was <lb/> excellent, in fact I think you <lb/> might tell them to include a <lb/> bit in each parcel.    I got
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3775_img_3160_4"/>
             your letter of 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yest but am <lb/> afriad dear Mother I must <lb/> acknowledge that I could not <lb/> read the part you crossed.   A phone message had just come from Bde. &amp; I must <lb/> go off at once.  Sending love to all <lb/> your loving son    James.    A letter just came from <lb/> K. but have not time to <lb/> read it now.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3775_img_3160_5"/>
             On Active Service    dated 23 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Wed. of May 1916   Mrs. S.C. Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor <lb/>Co Down <lb/>Ireland 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>