<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5183">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Minnie Daly to Susan Daly, 25 May 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Minnie Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/6/3/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5183</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1430">Minnie Daly</persName>
              <date>1923-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1561">Keelslough, Gortatlea, Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Susan Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5183_img_None_1"  url="3aadc1111b63a6069009819788e332c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5183_img_None_2"  url="4538b7809036f715f39b037635316950.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5183_img_None_3"  url="1483d09e14410afb65bf0b8131cdbecc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5183_img_None_4"  url="7b561440049a415ce4cd7c549f03ae7d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5183_img_0_1"/>
             P41/6/3/7  Keelslough    Gortatlea    26.5.25    Dear Susie   it is about time I<lb/>thought of answering your letter<lb/>I lost the address so there is<lb/>my excuse for you. I was very<lb/>sorry to hear you were sick<lb/>so far from home too and<lb/>then about poor Charlie was'nt<lb/>terrible the poor fellow after all<lb/>his time. I suppose you must<lb/>have felt it very much I knew<lb/>you did not know it for a<lb/>long time after it must be<lb/>a great shock when you heard<lb/>it as it was to everyone and<lb/>we though he was quite safe<lb/>They bore it great at home 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5183_img_0_2"/>
             be there for three or four wks<lb/>more. Hanna Connells mother<lb/>was buried since too there is no<lb/>one there now but John Joe and<lb/>Hanna it is very lonely for them.<lb/>They told me behind that you<lb/>would be coming home in June,<lb/>I hope Miss you will pay us a visit<lb/>and not spend all your time <hi rend="superscript">at home </hi>like<lb/>before whatever the attraction will do<lb/>Tomorrow is Molahiffe fair do<lb/>you remember the time we went<lb/>there long ago that Nellie told<lb/>everything after coming home<lb/>I suppose there will be nothing<lb/>there this year. Of coarse you<lb/>heard about the rifles being<lb/>got in the dump behind and<lb/>the dug-out burned informers<lb/>again of coarse how greatly<lb/>they are everywhere. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5183_img_0_3"/>
             considering the great shock it<lb/>was to them but your poor mother<lb/>would grave the stones there is<lb/>about half of her there and<lb/>your father too feels it very bad.<lb/>Kathleen Barrett was here for<lb/>a few days I went back to Knockane<lb/>Sunday with her and stayed that<lb/>night<hi rend="underline"> ever</hi>yone there are fine the<lb/>same as ever May does not go up<lb/>to the road atal now I left Kathleen<lb/>behind after me she is out a<lb/>month now from home and she<lb/>got another for<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>night pon my word<lb/>she is like one on the run she<lb/>was at Kilfalney Oakpark Bally-<lb/>gree and here and now she is at<lb/>Knockane. Mackie McQuin is in<lb/>Dublin at present she is after<lb/>going under and operation she is<lb/>the Richmond hospital and well 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5183_img_0_4"/>
             I hope the weather will clear up<lb/>before you come home it is a<lb/>fright it is so cold here I suppose<lb/>its the same in Dublin. I know<lb/>you heard about our Cha. being<lb/>arrested and Cronin <seg type="unclear">going</seg> in for<lb/>him and Cronin and Herlihy being<lb/>arrested after so I wont your<lb/>head telling it again to you<lb/>There was no raid here now a<lb/>good bit not with over six weeks<lb/>I have no more to say hoping to<lb/>hear from you soon though indeed<lb/>I dont deserve any letter<lb/>Remember me to Vera Fleming<lb/>everyone here sends you their love   I remain<lb/>your fond cousin<lb/>Minnie Daly  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>