<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0800">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender, 18 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letter discusses the progress of the war and the strain of the Battle of the Somme, which has so far lasted seven weeks. He complains of those officers who bring visitors to the front, wasting army resources and giving civilians a too &#39;sudden&#39; impression of modern war and one &#39;too graphic and false&#39;. Spender discusses the work he is currently undertaking, specifically the practise of sending out telegrams beyond German lines to expose the &#39;lies&#39; of the German government, and his responsibility to inform the chief of the Imperial General Staff of those aspects of the war which cannot be made known to the Press. Spender emphasises the confusion of war, and also the need to let the public know the truth of the situation while necessarily &#39;paint[ing] certain portions of the picture in brighter colours&#39;. Spender finishes by regretting the discomforts his brother Rex faces in the trenches, and wishing he could share a few of his superfluous comforts with him. The letter is is part of a series of correspondence which date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/389</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/800</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_1"  type="NULL"  url="b3092a1701d473ea8960eb01a036f282.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_2"  type="NULL"  url="2370a00b0db8741050edd7021d38f221.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_3"  type="NULL"  url="2154518efa2727dcdd9eda2a5bbf12e5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_4"  type="NULL"  url="f5d93b36d5ed11c7ba43600315970be8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_5"  type="NULL"  url="44e578546ad9c20fa7fe6b9b9227a8aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_6"  type="NULL"  url="cdb4fc3522b930d06401a929193273ea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_7"  type="NULL"  url="31b06b88a687a89a6abede5cbea5179b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0800_img_2340_8"  type="NULL"  url="bfd612503680408730a5e3573623443d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_1"/>
                18 Aug   My dear folks   I ought not to be writing as I have a lot of work in<lb/> hand but as Gen. Sir L. Kiggell told me yesterday that<lb/> I had 'done a lot' I am rather<lb/> presuming on the fact! It does<lb/> not seem like a month since <lb/> Rex came out, yet it is very<lb/> nearly that since I saw him and left the Ulstermen! I<lb/>am going up to the front  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_2"/>
              this afternoon the first time for a<lb/> fortnight so that I feel very much<lb/> less a soldier than old Rex.  I am not surprised that Edmund's<lb/> visit out here has been delayed till<lb/> the winter though in many ways<lb/> I am sorry. It is a very severe<lb/> strain on every one to go on with<lb/> this battle which has already lasted<lb/> 7 weeks, and various people-such <lb/> as Sir S.Hughes ! - seem to think<lb/> it is a Commander in Chief's business <lb/> to entertain them &amp; as many<lb/> friends as they care to bring-and <lb/>their private photographers &amp; cinema-  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_3"/>
              -tograph performers! - Although Edmund<lb/> and probably the majority of those who<lb/> came with him would realise this and<lb/> not expect much, yet when every room<lb/> within 6 miles of the front is crowded <lb/> with fresh troops or wounded every<lb/> additional personage means an extra<lb/> strain, &amp; I am afraid no one else but <lb/>Edmund would show much consideration<lb/> as to be content with a blanket<lb/> under a tree &amp; such food as he can<lb/> carry. Besides I do not think the<lb/> battle field is any place for visitors<lb/> who will get too sudden and therefore<lb/>too graphic and false an impression of modern war, and even the guiding<lb/> of spectators round means a lot of<lb/> arranging and fuss for the already  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_4"/>
              overworked staffs. If Edmund could<lb/> have come out as a single visitor &amp;<lb/> stopped in my room &amp; kicked his heels<lb/> about 10 miles behind the lines for 3<lb/> days out of 4 &amp; then  have  been content<lb/> with an occasional hasty glimpse<lb/> at war conditions it would be al<lb/>l right, but even Rex I expect would<lb/> hesitate to <seg type="del">wish</seg> invite him to<lb/> his dug out tho' he would doubtless<lb/> welcome him and give him that<lb/> hospitality which the men in the<lb/> front seem able to provide, though<lb/> every ounce of food and every bottle<lb/> of water has to be carried by hand<lb/> through slippery winding trenches  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_5"/>
              by men who are already loaded<lb/> very often with their ordinary<lb/> kit which weigh I think over<lb/><seg type="del">70</seg><lb/>60 lbs. I do feel that I, living in <lb/>the lap of luxury, have no right <lb/>here, but I expect that I shall <lb/>go to a division again before<lb/> very long and am therefore<lb/> putting on fat like a horse!  One of my tasks of sending<lb/> German wireless telegrams out<lb/>so as to try and give them some<lb/> idea of the lies in their own<lb/> press is very interesting and gives  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_6"/>
              me a reason to read the papers<lb/> which I could not otherwise find an excuse for otherwise. A less<lb/> congenial task is to let the<lb/> chief of the Imperial Guard Staff<lb/> have a cipher account of all the events<lb/> which one cannot well put in the<lb/> papers. If Edmund knew<lb/> of the difficulties-how the French<lb/> cry if we bombard one of their<lb/> villages, or if we bombard the<lb/> enemy's line and he replies on<lb/> one of their villages behind our lines,<lb/> &amp; how conflicting all the reports  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_7"/>
              are, &amp; especially how careful one has to be in not giving the Simonites<lb/> an excuse for exaggerating our<lb/> set-backs he would I think forgive<lb/> the <seg type="del">rather</seg> baldness of the<lb/> official communiques. Every day<lb/> a new pitfall crops up, &amp; all<lb/> one can do is to see that the British public is told the truth<lb/> about the situation even tho' one<lb/> has to paint certain portions of<lb/> the picture in brighter colours<lb/> than others. However, all <seg type="del">that</seg> the picture painting is <lb/>the work of the correspondents.  A lot of my work is very secret  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0800_img_2340_8"/>
              so you will know nothing about it<lb/> till the war is over but one is very<lb/> much at the hub of the wheel seeing<lb/> everything that is going to be tried<lb/> as well as all that has been done<lb/> by our wonderful troops.  I send all letters on to Rex<lb/> promptly, but the man in the trenches certainly deserves much<lb/> more than me. I do wish I could<lb/> share his discomforts &amp; let him<lb/> have a few of my superfluous<lb/> comforts.  Best of love. I hope that<lb/> the youngsters won't have to work<lb/> all their holidays tho' I know they<lb/> find it a joy to be so useful. <seg type="closer"> Wilfred B Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>