<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3983">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Count George Noble Plunkett to Arthur Patrick O'Brien, 22 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Noble Count Plunkett</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from George Noble Plunkett arranging to meet Mr O&#39;Brien on the former&#39;s forthcoming trip to London

Count Plunkett was a nationalist and a papal count. He had been sworn in to the IRB by his son, Joseph Mary Plunkett (1887-1916), before the Rising and arrested afterwards. Count Plunkett was elected as an MP in 1918 and was a member of the first Dáil. 

In the wake of the 1916 Rising, Arthur Patrick O&#39;Brien founded the Irish National Relief Fund in London to
provide assistance to the families of Irish rebels.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>MS8434:18-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3983</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0468">George Noble Count Plunkett</persName>
              <date>1916-09-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0839">21 Wellington Square, Oxford, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arthur Patrick O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1948</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3983_img_3370_1"  type="Letter"  url="bc11822633f8bafa1727fefc11101563.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3983_img_3370_1"/>
             24/9/16   21 Wellington Square<lb/>Oxford,   22nd September 1916 <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr O'Brien,  <lb/>I shall be in<lb/>London early next week, and<lb/>I will call on you then: I have<lb/>arranged to see a friend on<lb/>business, and he has to decide<lb/>whether we meet on Tuesday or<lb/>Wednesday. I would call on<lb/>you at about half past two; I<lb/>hope this hour would not be<lb/>inconvenient for you.  With kind regards from<lb/>my wife and daughter, and<lb/>myself,   Yours sincerely,<lb/>G. Mount Plunkett  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>