<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0667">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of a letter from Serjeant Alex Sullivan to George Gavan Duffy, 4 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Serjeant Alex Sullivan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of a letter from Serjeant Alex Sullivan, Rosscarbery, Co. Cork to Gavan Duffy (1882-1951), in which he conveys his condolences on the execution of Roger Casement (1864–1916). States that &#39;these asses (the English) can learn nothing. They have made a martyr most stupidly, while abstaining from their hysterical performance would have been a good move for their own ends.&#39;George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>George Gavan Duffy Papers, P152/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/667</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0451">Serjeant Alex Sullivan</persName>
              <date>1916-08-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1972">Rosscarbery, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0667_img_216_1"  type="Letter"  url="3eb4aabc8e961f0de5ad4c06597069c4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0667_img_216_1"/>
              Letter from Serjeant Sullivan to G. Gavan Duffy.    Rosscarberry  Co. Cork.    4.8.16.   My Dear <sic>Gorge</sic>,    I am exceedingly sorry for the disappointment <lb/> and worry that you have suffered. These asses can learn <lb/> nothing. They have made a 'martyr' most stupidly <lb/> while abstaining from their hysterical performance <lb/> wd. have been a good move for their own ends.   Come down to me and have some rest and <lb/> relaxation. Brooding over this business will do you <lb/> no good .....   I am at last resting ... I shall do <lb/> no work for a month at least.  <seg type="closer"> Kindest regards to you both <lb/><hi rend="underline">Yrs ..</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Alex</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>