<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3848">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 1 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) informing Kirkpatrick that the proposed college of nursing has been established. I addition to addressing the next steps to be taken Stanley encloses a lost of the council members relating to the newly established college.


Sir Arthur Stanley was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.

From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-3-15-12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3848</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1166">Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-04-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3848_img_3229_1"  type="Letter"  url="7be9feb554c2414559c39016659825ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3848_img_3229_2"  type="Letter"  url="23ff5fa7642a393725854cf5ac7c1fa7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3848_img_3229_3"  type="Letter"  url="b0b1d16d889bf6459fcb742282cccd9c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3848_img_3229_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="41dbbdbe7d6b6a25296e7a88fdd50424.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3848_img_3229_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="8a0e621d4d364f892b099b1136ea8d65.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3848_img_3229_1"/>
             RCPI/2/3/3/15/12   83,   MILL.<lb/>LONDON, S. W.     1st April, 1916.    Dear Sir,   In reference to my letter dated the 30th December,<lb/>I have now the pleasure to inform you that the College of<lb/>Nursing has been duly established.  As it has been decided after careful consideration to<lb/>register the College with the addition of the word Limited,<lb/>as a Company not for profit and limited by guarantee, the<lb/>signing of the Memorandum and the Articles of Association<lb/>became practically a mere matter of form and the first Council<lb/>has been appointed by the Signatories as <seg type="unclear">under:—</seg>  Miss Ballie. Matron, General Hospital, Bristol.<lb/>Miss Cox Davies, R.R.C., Matron, Royal Free Hospital,<lb/>Principal <seg type="unclear">Matron</seg>, T.F.N.S.<lb/>Miss Gill, R.R.C., Lady Supv. Royal Infirmary,<lb/>Edinburgh.<lb/>Miss Haughton, Matron, Guy's Hospitaal, Hon. Sec.<lb/>Guy's Nurses League.<lb/>Miss Hughes. General Inspector, Q. V. J. Nurses.<lb/>Miss Lloyd Still, Matron, St.   Hospital,<lb/>Head of Nightingal Training<lb/>School<lb/>Miss Melrose. Matron. Royal Infirmary, Glasgow<lb/>Miss Ray, Matron. King's College Hospital.<lb/>Miss Sparshott, Matron., Manchester Royal Infirmary.<lb/>Miss Swift, R.R.C., Matron in—Chief. Joint War Com—<lb/>mittee, British Red Cross and<lb/>Order of <seg type="unclear">St. John</seg> of Jerusalem.<lb/>Miss Jane Walker, M.D.<lb/><seg type="unclear">Coryns</seg> Berkeley Esq. M.A., M.D., M,C. Cantab F.P. CpP.<lb/>Lond.<lb/>Sir Cooper Perry, M.D., F.R.C.P.,<lb/>Hon. Arthur Stanley, M.P.,<lb/>H. G. Turney Esq., M.D., F.R.C.P.,  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3848_img_3229_2"/>
             —2—  These ladies and gentlemen have consented to act,<lb/>and they have power to appoint other persons to be Members<lb/>of the Council to a maximum number not exceeding Thirty.  The Council will proceed shortly to the appointment<lb/>of the Consultative and Examination Boards and hope to have<lb/>the advantage of any assistance that your Hospital may be<lb/>able to afford them in coming to sound conclusions on the<lb/>various weighty matters which will shortly engage their<lb/>attention.  It is proposed to hold a Meeting of Representatives<lb/>of all Hospitals and Training Schools. and of representatives<lb/>of Societies of Trained Nurses, who are in general agree.<lb/>with the scheme of the College, at St. Thomas's Hospital,<lb/>Friday, April 7th., at 3 p.m. and I shall be glad if you will<lb/>send representatives to that meeting, with a view to discussing<lb/>the formation of the Consultative Board in such a <sic>wat</sic> as to<lb/>make it representative all interests.  Thanking you for the courtesy extended to my previous<lb/>communication.  Believe me,<lb/>Yours faithfully,   <hi rend="underline">A Stanley</hi>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3848_img_3229_3"/>
             Letter from Mr Stanley <lb/> April 1, 1916  <lb/>Council of College <lb/>List of names 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3848_img_3229_4"/>
             THE COLLEGE<hi rend="underline"> OF NURSING</hi>, LIMITED. <lb/><hi rend="underline">COUNCIL</hi>   Chairman. The Hon. Arthur Stanley.   Miss A. B. Baillie, R.R.C., Matron, Royal Infirmary, Bristol. <lb/>Mr. Comyns Berkeley, M.C., F.R.C.P. <lb/>Miss E. Barton, Matron, Chelsea Infirmary, S.W. <lb/>Mr. J. Cantlie, F.R.C.S. <lb/>Miss R. Cox—Davies, R.R.C., Matron, Royal Free Hospital, W.C. <lb/>Miss Gibson, Late Matron, Birmingham Infirmary. <lb/>Miss A. W. Gill, R.R.C., Lady Superintendent, Royal Infirmary, <lb/>Edinburgh. <lb/>Professor Glaister, M.D., Glasgow University. <lb/>Miss L.V. Haughton, Matron, Guy's Hospital, S. E. <lb/>Miss A. Hughes, General Superintendent, Q.V. J. Nurses. <lb/>Miss A. Mc.Intosh, Matron, St. Bartholomew's Hospital, E.C. <lb/>Miss J. Melrose, R.R.C., Matron, Royal Infirmary, Glasgow. <lb/>Miss E.W. Mowat, Matron, Whitechapel Infirmary, E. <lb/>Miss E. M. Musson, Matron, Birmingham General Hospital. <lb/>Sir Cooper Perry, M. D., F.R.C.P., Hon. Secretary. <lb/>Miss M. E. Ray, R.R.C., Matron, King's College Hospital, S.E. <lb/>Miss M. E. Sparshott, R.R.C., Lady Superintendent, Royal Infirmary, <lb/>Manchester. <lb/>Miss A. Lloyd Still, Matron, St. Thomas's, Hoaspital, S. E. <lb/>Miss S. A. Swift, R.R.C., Matron in Chief, Joint War Committee. <lb/>Dr. H. G. Turney, F.R.C.P. <lb/>Miss C. E. Vincent, R.R.C., Lady Superintendent, Royal Infirmary, <lb/>Leicester. <lb/>Dr. Jane Walker. <lb/>Miss C. Seymour Yapp, Matron, Union Hospital, Ashton—under—Lyne. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3848_img_3229_5"/>
             Council of College<lb/>[Questionable reading.] 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>