<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2579">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Willie Doyle SJ to Provincial Thomas Nolan, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to Father Provincial Thomas V. Nolan SJ (1867-1941). In  this letter, Willie Doyle gives his reaction to the &#39;dreadful riots&#39; in Dublin, details casualties, gas, leave, Holy Communion and other happenings.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. Within days of his arrival at the Front his bravery was a talking point among officers and men. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. Although there are differing opinions on his date of death (whether the 16 or 17 August 1917), he was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.

Fr. Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War. Dring the Rising Nolan was based at St Francis Xavier’s, Upper Gardiner Street and, alongside Rector Fr John Fahy SJ, risked his life in aiding the wounded and supplying local areas with food and milk. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>J2/83/62</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2579</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0642">British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1015">Melrose, Dalkey, County Dublin Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_1"  type="Letter"  url="8fb80f9fb007d73e4f167fded37430fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_2"  type="Letter"  url="3e34da0c68e86c0caaebe690d90d6804.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_3"  type="Letter"  url="6508d2f62a08dd24eb846f4959c1f2cf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_4"  type="Letter"  url="4333b63e112bb77c17ebc5cd4079fed3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_5"  type="Letter"  url="6edd7974bb17569a9e009d8632e0c63b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_6"  type="Letter"  url="31e129913f304be1436e51151f74bb71.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_7"  type="Letter"  url="e2a4bde956f9b242054949c73a27baa0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_8"  type="Letter"  url="c9b8b04458c9f9515ca966a01b928260.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_9"  type="Letter"  url="de2b175bf89d3c7029e6a5122be0303b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2579_img_2006_10"  type="Letter"  url="107e84a2cd6dcebd8f64639c47b2c62e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_1"/>
             Many thanks to <lb/>dear Lena for <lb/>her letter.   B. E. Frorce <lb/> France   13/5/'16   My dear Father,    I was on the <lb/>point of writing to you <lb/>when your ever welcome <lb/>letter reached me. A thousand <lb/>thanks for it (you cannot <lb/>imagine how welcome your <lb/>letters are) and also for <lb/>the papers giving an account <lb/>of the dreadful riots in <lb/>Dublin. I am glad I <lb/>was safe in the trenches
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_2"/>
            during that time, for <lb/> apparently the Bosches <lb/> cannot hold a candle <lb/> to the Sinn Feiners. <lb/> One good result will <lb/> follow from what has <lb/> happened: the ridding <lb/> Dublin of a most <lb/> undesirable element which <lb/> was doing much harm <lb/> among our ignorant <lb/> people. Incidentally I <lb/> am chuckling to myself <lb/> over those who said <lb/> that "Retreats for Workingmen" <lb/> were not needed in <lb/> Ireland, and I hope <lb/> the project will be <lb/> helped by those sad scenes. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_3"/>
             Since I wrote last we have <lb/> been back here some <lb/> miles from the firing <lb/> line as the men always <lb/> get a rest after a spell <lb/> in the trenches. This time <lb/> they wanted it badly, poor <lb/> chaps, having had a hard <lb/> time of it, an experience <lb/> none of us are likely to <lb/> forget. Once again we <lb/>have had all the luck, <lb/> even with our share of the <lb/> fighting, for though one <lb/> regiment of the Brigade <lb/> is reduced to 200 men
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_4"/>
            the casualties of the <lb/> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Fusiliers only came <lb/> to a little over 100.     As result of our stay <lb/> here things have been <lb/> singularly <sic>uneventfuly</sic> &amp; <lb/> quiet. They say a war <lb/> is going on somewhere <lb/> but it is not easy to <lb/> realize that at present. <lb/> I was not sorry to get <lb/> a little time of rest, <lb/> for the beastly gas took <lb/>more out of me than <lb/> I thought, but I am <lb/> feeling fit and well <lb/> again now, thank God, <lb/> ready for another spell <lb/> before my trip to <lb/> "Blighty". 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_5"/>
             I paid a visit recently to <lb/> another wonder of the <lb/> war, the church of <lb/> Vermelles. Little remains <lb/> of it now, for the town has <lb/> been held in succession by <lb/> the Germans, French and <lb/> ourselves and every yard of <lb/> ground was lost and won <lb/> a dozen times. The church <lb/> is just a heap of ruins; <lb/> the roof has been burnt, the <lb/> tower shot away, while the <lb/> statues, stations <seg type="unclear">etc</seg> are smashed <lb/> to dust, but hanging <lb/> still on one of the
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_6"/>
            broken walls is a large <lb/> crucifix absolutely <lb/> untouched. The figure <lb/> is a beautiful one, a <lb/> work of art, and the <lb/> face of our Lord has <lb/> an expression of sadness <lb/> such as I have never <lb/> seen before. The eyes <lb/> are open, gazing as it <lb/> were upon the scene <lb/> of desolation, and <lb/> though the wall upon <lb/> which the crucifix hangs is <lb/> riddled with bullet holes <lb/> and shell splinters, the <lb/> image is untouched <lb/> save for one round <lb/> bullet hole just through
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_7"/>
            the heart. The whole <lb/> thing may be only chance <lb/> but it is a striking sight <lb/> and cannot fail to impress <lb/> one, and brings home the <lb/> fact that if God is scourging <lb/> the world as it well deserves <lb/> He is not indifferent to <lb/> the sorrows and sufferings <lb/> of His children.     Sunday 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>I was not able to <lb/> finish this yesterday <lb/> as the men keep me going <lb/> scraping their kettles". (I wish <lb/> mine was half as clean <lb/> as some of theirs) Between <lb/> 600 &amp; 700 men were at
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_8"/>
            Holy Communion this <lb/> morning, the last probably <lb/> for many of them for <lb/> we are due back in the <lb/> trenches tomorrow, though <lb/> the part we are going to <lb/> is quiet compared to the <lb/> last position we held. <lb/> One cannot help feeling proud <lb/> of our Irish lads, everyone <lb/> loves them — the French girls , <lb/> naturally, that goes without <lb/> saying, as poor Aunt Polly <lb/> would have written; the shop- <lb/> keepers love them for their <lb/> simplicity in paying about <lb/> five times the real value <lb/> of the goods; Monsieur le <lb/> Curé would hug them each <lb/> and everyone if he could, <lb/> for he has been simply <lb/> raking in the coin these <lb/> days, many a one putting <lb/> three and five franc notes <lb/> in the plate to make up,
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_9"/>
            I suppose, for the trouser <lb/> buttons of the knowing <lb/> one, and surely our Blessed <lb/> Lord loves them best of all <lb/> for their simple, unaffected <lb/> piety which brings crowds <lb/> of them at all hours of <lb/> the day to visit Him in <lb/> the Tabernacle. Need I add <lb/> that the Padre himself has <lb/> a warm corner in his <lb/> heart for his boys, as I <lb/> think they have for him, <lb/> judging by their anxiety <lb/> when the report spread <lb/> that I had got knocked
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_2579_img_2006_10"/>
             out in the gas attack. <lb/> They are as proud as punch <lb/> to have the chaplain with <lb/> them in the trenches; it is <lb/> quite amusing to hear <lb/> them point out my <lb/> dug-out to strangers as they <lb/> go by: "That's <hi rend="underline">our</hi> priest," <lb/> with a special stress on <lb/> the <hi rend="underline">our</hi>.    Let me end up this note <lb/> with a little bit of news <lb/> which I mention because I <lb/> think it will please and <lb/> gratify you: I have just <lb/> been told (unofficially) that <lb/> my name has been sent <lb/> on to the Commander-in-Chief <lb/> for "Mention in <sic>Despatches</sic>." <lb/> I hope the Angels have done <lb/> their work as well and that <lb/> I shall get a little corner in <lb/> their report to Head Quarters above. <lb/> This is only for yourself.  Your loving son   Willie. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>