<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5572">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 19 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

This is a very emotional letter, however the letter that inspired it seems to be missing. He writes of the beginning of their courtship.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5572</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5572_img_668_1"  type="Letter"  url="f59ef15b6cb921a12086b3ec31aff886.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5572_img_668_2"  type="Letter"  url="8d1a82b809d9fdbcb7a37da5b1629bb1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5572_img_668_3"  type="Letter"  url="fb2f153fc2e2f81a38004dd8cdb03a88.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5572_img_668_1"/>
              and what I long for<lb/>every hour and every<lb/>minute almost. Do you know<lb/>you are the last thought at<lb/>night and the first in<lb/>the morning? Well it's true<lb/>anyhow whether you suspect<lb/>it or not. I have no news<lb/>at all this time so I will<lb/>close up with the warmest love<lb/>and devotion to my dearest girl from<lb/> her ever faithful and loving<lb/>James     39 Belgrave Square,<lb/>Rathmines,<lb/>Dublin.    19th March, 1916.    My dearest May,   You have sent me many<lb/>letters that I rejoiced at but none was<lb/>half so good as your dear letter of this<lb/>morning. I have been thinking and wondering<lb/>about it ever since and the more I think the<lb/>more I fail to understand what in God’s<lb/>name ever put a thought of me in your<lb/>sweet mind. Recently I have been comforting<lb/>myself with the thought that you did<lb/>like me a good deal but I never suspected<lb/>that you had such hidden depths of<lb/>affection as the incident of the rose reveals.<lb/>Good Lord! when I think what a fellow I am 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5572_img_668_2"/>
             and have been, I feel like the dirt<lb/>when I have to imagine it possible that a<lb/>girl like you that a prize such as you are<lb/>could ever love me. I remember the roses you<lb/>wore that day very well as I remember your<lb/>dress and everything you said and did but I<lb/>have only a very faint recollection of having picked<lb/>up the rose for you. Probably I did it mechanically<lb/>as an act of politeness without thinking there was<lb/>any special significance in it. If you had given<lb/>me the rose instead of my restoring it to you, I<lb/>could have remembered it forever. The clearest<lb/>thing I remember about the whole day is that I<lb/>was furiously jealous of Ray (the best man) all<lb/>day especially as you laughed and joked with him.<lb/>I remember thinking that it was only natural you<lb/>should prefer a man younger and better looking<lb/>than me and I half made up my mind there<lb/>and then to throw up the prize. That was  while we were up the hill. Later on when we<lb/>were playing the cards you sat beside me and I<lb/>plucked up a bit of spirits again but on the whole<lb/>thinking over the whole day’s events afterwards<lb/>I was inclined to think my chances were very<lb/>poor. One or two little things that happened<lb/>during my holidays in August gave me hope,<lb/>once or twice you allowed your hand to remain<lb/>in mine when we shook hands and more especially<lb/>your handshake the day I said goodbye that<lb/>time. I was bursting to speak to you then but<lb/>I got no chance and I never had so bad a<lb/>heartache as leaving you then, not knowing whether<lb/>to hope or despair. All that is over and done with<lb/>now, thank God, and I need hardly say how I<lb/>will cherish your dear sweet gift and mark of<lb/>love. You needn’t tell me not to do away with it.<lb/>Do you think I’m mad to do such a thing? I<lb/>doubt very much if you will ever get it back<lb/>again unless you insist on it. Don’t think that<lb/>is said as a joke or to flatter you. As I hope for 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5572_img_668_3"/>
             final forgiveness, it is true and I love and<lb/>revere my dear and darling all the more if<lb/>possible when I know that nearly a year ago<lb/>she had already a regard for me. As to<lb/>your being a cool customer as you say, I know<lb/>very well now from what you tell me that you<lb/>are not. I’m glad to hear that you are<lb/>thinking of the races. Mrs Seery was asking me<lb/>would I come down for them but I said I<lb/>wasn’t sure, not thinking that you would<lb/>be likely to go. I hope you will go and<lb/>maybe you’d think of inviting me too. I know<lb/>Mrs S would be only too delighted to give me<lb/>lodging for the few days if you wouldn’t be<lb/>too hard-hearted  to refuse  to let me come down. Please<lb/>do let me come down to see you then. I’m breaking<lb/>my promise already not to speak about coming down<lb/>again until you mentioned it so I won’t say<lb/>any more now. You know very well what I want 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>