<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4305">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from D.P. Barton to Edward Carson, 5 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>D.P. Barton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from D.P. Barton to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4305</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0438">D.P. Barton</persName>
              <date>1916-05-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2127">Ulster Club, Belfast, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_1"  type="Letter"  url="d32624a2bee3dac91e18f691fd987867.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_2"  type="Letter"  url="753fb45a2128a8294695b0e4a5d20b1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_3"  type="Letter"  url="1ce77d5f959b64b809fae16421078773.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="842de5469756a38e43ad5f97acc28dd6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="477a0eb44fa360557d1c95f1149059a8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="e277480f5942b6cd346e2b96ab4b8ed7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4305_img_3667_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="a14b5ca5f6618fb7c092a4240be25d89.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_1"/>
             5/5/16   Ulster Club, <lb/>Belfast.   My dear Ned   I think you may be interested to <lb/>hear the impressions of a friend who <lb/>was "held up" in the North. I was <lb/>at Newcastle Co. Down until Friday, <lb/>and have been in Belfast for <lb/>a week.   There was some unrest in the <lb/>outlying border counties, but, otherwise, <lb/>Ulster and Belfast have been <lb/>absolutely tranquil — without 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_2"/>
             any signs of excitement except an <lb/>occasional rush for newspapers.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">Tranquility</hi>  This has been due in, my opinion, <lb/>mainly to three causes. First there <lb/>is absolute confidence in your <lb/>leadership — and, when the ship's <lb/>company have confidence in the <lb/>man at the wheel, they are <lb/>able to be cool and collected.   Secondly men like  <hi rend="superscript">Colonel</hi>  Shannon <lb/>Crawford and Wallace have <lb/>used their influence actively <lb/>and successfully with good <lb/>results. — Thirdly General <lb/>Hackett-Payne and the <lb/>Police Commissioner Smith <lb/>have both made excellent <lb/>arrangements and have <lb/>worked well together.   I have no doubt that the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_3"/>
             Nationalist leaders used good <lb/>influence— but I had no <lb/>opportunity of discussing it—   I never met Smith before. <lb/>He seems to be a capable man <lb/>with firmness and discretion— <lb/>two qualities badly wanted <lb/>just now in this distrustful country.   I return to Dublin today. — <lb/>I liked your speech about Birrell. <lb/> It was  generous and big-hearted to <lb/>a fallen foe.   Yours ever  <lb/>D P Barton 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_4"/>
            <!-- Newspaper article -->
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_5"/>
            <!-- Newspaper article -->
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_6"/>
            <!-- Newspaper article -->
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4305_img_3667_7"/>
            <!-- Newspaper article -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>