<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1884">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William M. Nolan to Matthew Nathan, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William M. Nolan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the Town Clerk of Limerick William M. Nolan (1855-1941) to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) the under-secretary for Ireland. Nathan was under-secretary until the 1916 Rising after which he offered his resignation. The letter deals with the resignation of a Mr Reidy and particularly the amount of an allowance he will receive. The letter states that the council are considering a sum of £94:0:8 per year.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5711</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1884</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1399">William M. Nolan</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0904">Town Clerk&#39;s Office, Town Hall, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1884_img_1336_1"  type="Letter"  url="8507d084b24c802d1530038ab7a11cca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1884_img_1336_1"/>
             Town Clerk's Office, <lb/>Town Hall, <lb/>Limerick.   31st March, 1916.  <lb/>4810. <hi rend="underline">re <sic>Superranuation</sic> of Mr. Patrick Reidy.</hi><lb/>  Sir,   I am directed by the Limerick County Borough Council to state <lb/>in reply to your letter of the 20th instant herein, that they <lb/>desire to award a retiring allowance of £94:0:8 per annum to Mr. <lb/>Reidy. This figure represents 31/60ths of the salary of £3 per <lb/>week, which he enjoyed, as general Foreman of the Gas Works, from <lb/>1897 to 1913, and of his emoluments ( " house, coal, and light" valued <lb/>at Ten shillings per week.   There will be a meeting of my Council on Thursday next ,  the <lb/>6th prox. ,  and it would facilitate matters if I was in a position to <lb/>inform the Council that their proposal to grant an allowance of <lb/>£94:0:8 per annum to Mr. Reidy had the sanction of His Excellency ,  <lb/>The Lord Lieutenant.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,    W. M. Nolan  <lb/>Town Clerk.  The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>