<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4199">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Shaw to James Shaw, 23 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Samuel Shaw to his father,  James Shaw, requesting that his father send him some cigarettes as they are running low and the French ones are too strong. Samuel supposes that the town must be empty now as may of the Port boys seem to be coming out in a draft from the 13th Battalion.

Samuel Henry Shaw (1896-1967) was a sergeant with the 10th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers. He volunteered for active service in September 1914. Before enlisting Samuel was a member of the Portstewart Company, Coleraine Battalion, North Derry Regiment, Ulster Volunteer Force. Samuel served in France, and was wounded during the Battle of the Somme in July 1916 and again in early 1917 and in 1918. Before the War he was employed as a ironmonger&#39;s assistant. James Shaw was a local fisherman in the town of Portstewart.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4199</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0493">Samuel Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-01-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1967</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4199_img_3570_1"  type="Letter"  url="8f54e213a2764bc7c6a41e3021394379.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4199_img_3570_1"/>
             Same Address   <hi rend="underline">23 — 1 — 16</hi>   My Dear <lb/>Dad   Just a few lines to let you know <lb/>I received your letter all right. I would be <lb/>much obliged to you if you would send <lb/>me some fags. They are very scarce out <lb/>here just now. And the French fags <lb/>would kill you at 500 yards. I am <lb/>glad to hear that the fishing is still <lb/>keeping good. I suppose the harbour <lb/>is dull now with all the boys away.   I believe this is a lot of the <lb/>Port boys coming out here in a draft <lb/>from the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Batt. Tell Mr Mc Auley <lb/>I was asking for him. Tell him <lb/>there are no halls out here like the <lb/>Institute.   From Your <lb/>Loving Son   <hi rend="underline">Sammie</hi>   (P. S. Love to all)    P. S. Send me a tin of <lb/>cocoa. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>