<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5573">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 21 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

James has been very busy and unable to write, May has sent him a lockof her hair and a photo. He has seen a concert with Miss O&#39;Connor.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5573</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5573_img_669_1"  type="Letter"  url="db58d88fd3e3eec94740c6c234c3e3f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5573_img_669_2"  type="Letter"  url="ce9740f24176ad0297ad408635644d26.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5573_img_669_1"/>
              Let me know in your<lb/>next about the date of the<lb/>races and if it is later<lb/>than the 3rd April please<lb/>let me come down  <hi rend="underline">next</hi><lb/>Saturday. Will write you<lb/>again tomorrow. I send<lb/>you my warmest and<lb/>dearest love.   Your ever loving<lb/>James   National Health Commission (Ireland),<lb/>Pembroke House,<lb/>Upper Mount Street,<lb/>Dublin.  21/3/1916 My dearest and best, I feel horribly sick with myself because of having disappointed you this morning. I had firmly intended writing you a line yesterday just to show you that I think of you always but I never got as much as a minutes respite yesterday. I came in at ten yesterday (which was very early for me) and never lifted my head till 7 yesterday evening. Imagine I never got as much as a minute for dinner and had to snatch a cup of tea about 4 o’clock to help keep me going. I have had more than a few pretty hard days in this department since I joined it but I can honestly say I never had one a bit worse than yesterday. Don’t think I’m telling you all this mainly in order to “throw flowers at myself” or to enlist your sympathy (though that is always a pleasure to me) but I want to show you that it wasn’t my fault that I failed you yesterday. I have been very hard run the last few days. Sunday night I was up till at work. I bought it home on Saturday and of course left it on the long finger till Sunday evening. Last night I went to confession and got rid of a load of trouble with the result that both last night and Sunday night my mind was a bit too active going to bed for sleep with the inevitable result that I got on to the usual topic- yourself- and didn’t get to sleep till all hours. However my sleep was very pleasant both nights. I imagine sometimes that you are watching over me at night and that your prayers and your sweet spirit keep and sustain me. Indeed just to show you that I think it’s true I’ll let you into a little secret of my confession. The priest in Clarendon Street (you remember we were in it one Sunday together at Mass 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5573_img_669_2"/>
             told me that he thought there was somebody praying for me. I suppose he was surprised that such a bad egg would ever otherwise have the courage to go to confession. So I think<lb/>you’re going to be my guardian angel for I’m sure the poor chap that got that thankless<lb/>job when I was born has given up on me in despair long ago.  I was delighted to get your letter this morning and especially with the contents.<lb/>The lock of hair is going with the other treasures. As regards the photo I’m sure I can’t<lb/>imagine who the very plain looking girl with the baby is. I don’t think I could have<lb/>ever seen her anyway. The poor thing will be quite offended if she hears that you<lb/>have been sending her photo all round the country for strange men to make remarks<lb/>about her (bow-wow). I’ll keep the photo anyhow for a few days and will give<lb/>it back to you (if you want it) when I see you. Perhaps by that time I will<lb/>have discovered the identity of the lady!! As regards going down to see you<lb/>I’d prefer next Saturday to any other because for one thing it would break the<lb/>miserable wait till Easter more evenly than going later on but if you want to<lb/>go to the races I could defer it till then or preferably I could go down then also.<lb/>But if the races are on the 10th or 17th April I’d rather go now. I wouldn’t<lb/>mind deferring my visit till the 3rd April if the races were then but if they are<lb/>later I want to go now. For one thing I want to see you so much and for<lb/>another I’m a bit cleaner in spirit than the last time I saw you and could<lb/>look you in the face and kiss you with less compunction than on my previous<lb/>visit. The concert was a huge success as I told you. The Miss O’Connor who played<lb/>the harp was not one of the O’Connors you met. We must go and hear the harp<lb/>played some time a good player is performing. She wasn’t much so you didn’t miss<lb/>a lot. About Killarney I don’t care one way or another and the same as regards the<lb/>day” Thursday for losses” doesn’t bother me. I’d face anything with you by my side,<lb/>my darling girl, and the only thing I shouldn’t like is “no day at all” .Will you 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>