<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4239">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 27 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/77</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4239</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4239_img_3607_1"  type="Letter"  url="6219fba9cd6e33d384e22758fae2090f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4239_img_3607_2"  type="Letter"  url="16c5ff5c38cb464c3f26c8d4bcb32281.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4239_img_3607_3"  type="Letter"  url="22e41426aafc4d70ec77496aab654da0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4239_img_3607_4"  type="Letter"  url="5ae7294635cb43a3ec259b0095974f5e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4239_img_3607_1"/>
             27<hi rend="superscript">.</hi> Nov.   I am sending a general <lb/> letter tho' your last deserves <lb/> a direct reply.   I am beginning to wonder <lb/> what will be left for your <lb/> committee by Lady R &amp; Mrs <lb/> B , but can see that at pres- <lb/> ent you have useful work in <lb/> <hi rend="underline">keep</hi>ing the peace &amp; explaining.    I think your committee <lb/> will have to take up the <lb/> "Agency" work in self defence <lb/> &amp; in any case you can hard- <lb/> ly do harm by making <lb/> arrangements for it now in <lb/> case , or rather in getting all <lb/> the information you can in <lb/> case they decide to do so.   I wish I were a little happier <lb/>about Rex's future. I am not
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4239_img_3607_2"/>
            sure I ought to have got him <lb/> a commission in the Inf!    I have answered the enclosed <lb/> from Hugh.   Many thanks for Castlefield <lb/> extracts, I want to see if we <lb/> ought to <seg type="del">wan</seg> sell out, but <lb/> prices of shares still keep very <lb/> low compared with dividend <lb/> prospects. These in spite of the <lb/> drop of /3' per lb are extraordin- <lb/> arily good for this year, &amp; in <lb/> fact for the next 6 months <lb/> the PR will be able to think <lb/> she has really married according <lb/> to the bait held out to her.   She will certainly find later <lb/> however that it was bait not <lb/> daily meal, I'm afraid, but <lb/> according to <seg type="del">her</seg> our bargain <lb/> the motor ought to <sic>motorialise</sic> <lb/> tho' I don't quite know how it
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4239_img_3607_3"/>
            would be kept up later, &amp; <lb/> in any case our first duty <lb/> is to the country.   I don't know what <seg type="unclear">O</seg> <lb/> should do if you were really <lb/> the extravagant litlle ani- <lb/> mal I once thought you. <lb/> Certainly not let you see <lb/> my passbook, but probably <lb/> give you an allowance <lb/> &amp; a very strict one too.    General Powell seems <lb/> to have been fairly well. I <lb/> am glad some of your fami- <lb/> ly should have met him as <lb/> it will probably be clearer to <lb/> them that the p r &amp; b w <lb/> did work which was really
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4239_img_3607_4"/>
            good, even tho' <seg type="del">non</seg> not   appreciated <lb/> by the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, quite as by <lb/> a p r which is much more <lb/> important.   Gaiters have arrived <lb/> I shall not unpack them <lb/> yet 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>