<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1144">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Neazor to Augustine Birrell, 6 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Neazor</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is a complaint from James Neazor, a retired excise officer in Limerick, to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), Chief Secretary for Ireland. Neazor writes that he had been improperly held in the local lunatic asylum for over six years. He writes that a &#39;conspiracy&#39; by the priests and a local doctor led to him being declared &#39;insane&#39; and committed. The doctor continued to write reports that Neazor was insane as, Neazor claims, he was happy to keep receiving payment for keeping him. Neazor criticises the doctor and the asylum system in detail for allowing this to happen and asks Birrell to conduct an enquiry.Augustine Birrell served as the Chief Secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish educational system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Birrell offered his resignation on May 1.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, CSO RP/5596/1916/742/2-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1144</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1146">James Neazor</persName>
              <date>1916-01-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1420">Ballycahane, Palliskenny, County Limerick</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1144_img_378_1"  type="Letter"  url="4d0d42a060524b1281d5041a9fac10ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1144_img_378_2"  type="Letter"  url="7836863ad3ceca81eb7317bb14736a41.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1144_img_378_3"  type="Letter"  url="ef5b688db579f10f932ddb3f02660f16.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1144_img_378_4"  type="Letter"  url="a1e1bbce1e04a4938326d42ff296ad22.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1144_img_378_5"  type="Letter"  url="d1db43beddcd42d2ff71a6b09d84cc17.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1144_img_378_1"/>
              Ask the Inspectors of Lunatics <lb/> what they know of this man     Ballycahane,  Pallaskenry,  Co.Limerick,  <seg type="unclear">District 15</seg> Honourable Sir,   As the Chief Secretary for Ireland, I beg to direct your <lb/> attention to the following circumstances: I was detained in the <lb/> Limerick Dt. <sic>Asylumn</sic> for over 6 years under the lying pretext <lb/> that I was insane. I am a superannuated Officer of Excise. When <lb/> I was in the Excise Service, the RC Priests slandered me at all the <lb/> places in Ireland and England at which I resided, as numerous <lb/> persons can testify, and amongst others W. Waller Esq. J.P.,D.L., Castle- <lb/>town, Pallaskenry, Co.Limerick; Dr.Ling, Medical Missionary, Thomas St., <lb/> Limerick; Rev Wm Langley, Rector of Narborough, Near Leicester; Rev <lb/> Wm Croome, Vicar of Syston, near Leicester; the Collector of Excise, Lei- <lb/>cester; Mr John Tierney, Officer of Excise. I had no knowledge when <lb/> I was in the Excise Service that the R.C. Priests had slandered me <lb/> behind my back. The R.C. Priests said I had committed Secret <lb/> Sin before entering the Excise Service; but it was only after I <lb/> was superannuated in 1892, and after I had come home here,  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1144_img_378_2"/>
              where the slanders were repeated, that I learned what the Priests <lb/> had been doing. I wrote letters to several people at the different <lb/> places at which I resided, complaining of the misconduct of <lb/> the R.C. Priests slandering me while while I was in the Excise Service. <lb/> At last the R.C. Priests of Pallaskenry pretended to believe that I <lb/> meant to inflict corporal chastisement on them and they express- <lb/> ed their apprehensions to the police. A conspiracy was got up against <lb/> me, headed by the R.C. Priests, and the local Doctor said I was suf- <lb/> fering from Delusions, meaning of course insane Delusions. For <lb/> I assure you I was never insane in my life, nor had I ever at any <lb/> time insane Delusions. Dr Hoey, an asst. Doctor in the Limerick <lb/> District Asylum, said to me in the presence of Several persons,' I <lb/> always told Dr O'Neill, Resident Medical Supt., that I thought there <lb/> was nothing the matter with your mind'. Nevertheless O'Neill <lb/> filled up certificates every 3 months, and sent them to Somerset <lb/> House, stating I was insane, in consequence of which the Excise <lb/> Authorities gave £28 per annum out of my Pension, who did  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1144_img_378_3"/>
              not claim me out because he was getting this money. I charge <lb/> O'Neill with filling up false and lying certificates about me <lb/> every 3 months for 6 years and sending them to the Excise Auth- <lb/> orities in London. There seems to be no check on the arbitrary <lb/> and dishonest conduct of O'Neill, who kept me for 6 years in <lb/> the place, although not one in the place believed there was <lb/> anything the matter with my mind. In England, as you know <lb/> there are visiting Magistrates who visit the <sic>Asylumns</sic> every 6 <lb/> months , in order to see that sane persons are not kept in them <lb/> against their will, but there is no similar magisterial Inspection <lb/> in Ireland, not do the <sic>Asylumn</sic> Committee trouble themselves <lb/> to see whether sane persons are unjustly detained in the <sic>As- <lb/>ylumn </sic> or not. The Government if the Limerick Dist.. <sic>Asylumn</sic><lb/> appears to me most scandalous in that no check is imposed <lb/> on the arbitrary conduct of O'Neill. I am profoundly convinced <lb/> that <sic>Asylumn</sic> Doctors will keep all the people they can in <sic>As- <lb/> ylumns </sic>, in order to keep up the numbers, so that they may have  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1144_img_378_4"/>
              an excuse for asking for an increase of Salary, and that if <lb/> they are not properly supervised,either by magisterial visitation, or <lb/> by the Governing Board, gross abuses are certain to arise, and sane <lb/> persons will be unjustly detained in <sic>Asylumns</sic>. Some months <lb/> since I wrote to Dr Dawson, one of the Inspectors of Lunacy, in <lb/> which I informed him of the slanders of the R.C. Priests, and of <lb/> the illegal and dishonest conduct of O'Neill in filling up lying <lb/> certificates, and keeping a sane person in the <sic>Asylumn</sic> for <lb/> over 6 years, but I received no reply from him. As President of <lb/> the Irish Local Govt. Board, I request you will order an inquiry <lb/> into my case, as it is one of gross injustice and illegality, and <lb/> a public Scandal. It is most scandalous that a public official <lb/> should be allowed to break the Law, and to detain a sane person <lb/> in an <sic>Asylumn</sic> for several years, because his friends were benefii- <lb/> ing by having him there, and because the R.M. Superintendent <lb/> wanted to keep up the numbers. Unless <sic>Asylumns</sic> in Ireland <lb/> are to fall into general and deserved disrepute, it <hi rend="underline">is desirable</hi>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1144_img_378_5"/>
              that some persons should not be detained in them against their <lb/> will. I am profoundly convinced that unless <sic>Asylumn</sic> Doctors <lb/> are properly Supervised they will want to run those Institutions <lb/> for their own benefit, and not for the benefit of the public which <lb/> pays them. I mentioned my case to Inspectors Sir Ed O'Farrell and <lb/> Considine, who both failed to see that justice was done to me. <lb/> As this is a bona fide case of fraud, injustice and illegality and <lb/> a scandal to the Government under which such things  take place  I request <lb/> you will have an inquiry instituted into it.  <seg type="closer"> I am Honourable Sir, <lb/> Your Obedient Servant   James Neazor   Rt.Hon Augustine Birrell Esq. K.C M.P.,  Chief Secretary for Ireland  </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S. I prefer to bring this matter before yourself in the first <lb/> instance to having a question asked about it in the House of <lb/> Commons.J.N.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>