<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5519">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Count Georg von Wedel to Roger Casement, 1 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Georg von Wedel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a cover letter from Count Georg von Wedel (1862-1943) of the German Foreign Office to Roger Casement enclosing a letter from &#39;John McGoy&#39; which was delivered to the German Legation. The two numbers at the back of the letter are his &#39;control-numbers&#39; as a member of the Irish Revolutionary Union. McGoy is possibly a pseudonym for Joseph McGarrity (1874-1940) who was one of the first to contact Germany with regards to securing arms for an Irish rebellion. The letter from &#39;McGoy&#39; is enclosed

The cover letter and letter are taken from a collection of letters, poems, articles and other documents of Roger Casement and his family. Covering his career in the British Diplomatic Service and activities in the Irish Revolutionary movement, 1889-1945.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sir Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15; Ms. 13,085/27</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5519</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0300">Georg von Wedel</persName>
              <date>1915-12-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0840">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0141">Roger Casement </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5519_img_616_1"  type="Letter"  url="b2f81493ad08c8528d9dc38c949ba5d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5519_img_616_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="843ca268eec1c99a8c1a1bd1410f6c69.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5519_img_616_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="8fbab385538b3225ea621db296bf8829.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5519_img_616_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="5bef654bde9230b33368def87abb38af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5519_img_616_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="db98e9b89e98d18314eecf5c7b5b39ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5519_img_616_1"/>
            Auswärtiges Amt.  Berlin   1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> december 1915.   KW Berlin <lb/>3.12.15   Dear Sir Roger,   Mr. John Mc.Goy delivered the enclosed letter at <lb/> the German legation at Copenhague with the request <lb/> to transmit it to you by safe messenger.    He further stated that the two numbers, written <lb/> with pencil on the back of the letter, were his <lb/> "control numbers" as member of the "Irish revolutio- <lb/> nary Union."   Believe me, dear Sir Roger, <lb/>Yours sincerely    G. Wedel 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5519_img_616_2"/>
             a leaflet in the package will explain how the trick <lb/> can be done oh if our friends could only realize <lb/> what a successful delivery would mean to both and <lb/> especially to our friends they would not have neglected <lb/> so long the harvest is ripe the reapers are there but <lb/> no sycles, our friends have them in abandoned the attempt <lb/> to deliver would cost so little and might mean so <lb/> much. <hi rend="underline">can nothing be done</hi>. let the package be <lb/> examined by proper parties and sent they will <lb/> not be impressed I feel they will let the new <lb/> comer seek for material among all units where <lb/> the children of the old woman might be found <lb/> the new comer will understand them and vice versa   I and friends are continuing mining operations <lb/> with fair success but much time will be required <lb/> to produce the amount you named but I am quite <lb/> confident it will be done but most of it must go <lb/> to the old woman as she is in greater need than <lb/> any of the other relatives and callers on her <lb/>will be very few in future <sic>onaccount</sic> of restriction <lb/> the landlord so in a panic and will allow no <lb/> friend near her least there would bring her message <lb/>or help. I can make no promises as to what <lb/>may happen here to help our friends but if the <lb/> old woman got a small gift it will not be my <lb/>fault if it is not quickly repaid <hi rend="underline">in acts I mean</hi>
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5519_img_616_3"/>
            <seg type="unclear">I relate</seg> we have done all we were asked to do, <lb/> done the thing you told us was most important to do, <lb/> done more effective work along all <seg type="unclear">lines</seg> but one <lb/> than all the forces when were at work for <lb/>our friends. I know what I am talking about <lb/> the work we done free could not be <seg type="del">achieved</seg> accomplished  by <lb/>millions of money nor by any other funds but <lb/>ourselves unless the matter terminates quickly <lb/>remember and let our friends remember that our <lb/>usefulness is by no means <seg type="unclear">outlived</seg> and greater <lb/>blows may be struck than are expected by <lb/>our friends. Ask them to give the old woman <lb/>a chance to keep the children now and for <lb/>every one she can retain thirty others will be kept <lb/>from <seg type="unclear">injuring</seg> our friends which in itself is worth <lb/>this risk she does not want so much and <lb/>if she gets a little I promise to proudly endeavour <lb/>to repay our friends in the way you said in your <lb/>previous letter She wished things done many a <lb/>long delay we have already caused the enemy I believe <lb/>the only delays that were caused were the result <lb/>of our work outside of certain material which <lb/>was purchased by our friends directly and <lb/>with that we had nothing to do 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5519_img_616_4"/>
             before this reaches you we will know whether other packages <lb/>can reach. I doubt very much if they can but the <lb/>one now on its way may have such results that <lb/>others will be unnecessary. For yours and all of our sakes <lb/>I hope so.   I my poor girl I sympathise with you in <lb/>your torturous wait and at times lack of knowledge <lb/>so necessary for the work on hand. But be brave <lb/>and <sic>dont</sic> forget that a new spirit has been <lb/>breathed into the old woman by you that will <lb/>endure until the dawn comes. How proud I <lb/>was to read in an enemys sheet that the mention <lb/>of your name in the heart of <seg type="unclear">Irland</seg> was <lb/>heard by thousands.   Are own friends going to make the mistake <lb/>of looking to the East only and neglect the <lb/>source of most of their trouble. If they do <lb/>what fools <sic>the</sic> are. Your dearest friend is <lb/>well and will not be neglected. Look to your <lb/>health and may God bless and keep you <lb/>and bless your labours and crown them with <lb/>success.    Your friend   VW 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5519_img_616_5"/>
            Zi-96
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>