<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0381">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Roger Casement to George Gavan Duffy, 30 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Roger Casement</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) to George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951).Casement urges Gavan Duffy to recover, from the High Court of Justice or the Home Office, documents and papers contained in a canvas portfolio that he had brought from Brixton Prison to give to him (Gavan Duffy). The portfolio contained documents dealing with Casement&#39;s trial, and Casement was eager for them to be read only by Gavan Duffy. Casement also writes that he has ‘been &#39;wrongfully and most untruthfully assailed&#39; in the course of proceedings by the crown witness. He goes on to thank Gavan Duffy and his other supporters, and requests that his correspondence be copied and passed to friends.Sir Roger Casement was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. Casement believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany, and when it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916. George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>George Gavan Duffy Papers, P152/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/381</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date>1916-06-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1220">Pentonville Prison, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0381_img_164_1"  type="Enclosure"  url="23e331fc785e53702a6921a20d58e115.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0381_img_164_2"  type="Letter"  url="d1d0baf667c005f5d55aa455fe749dc5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0381_img_164_3"  type="Letter"  url="ac254ef8a8f1c034cf1406735e2f30f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0381_img_164_4"  type="Letter"  url="ff6a1dac86b5e9bce81993df241933ad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0381_img_164_1"/>
              In replying to this letter, please write on the envelope:-<lb/> NUMBER 1270 NAME R.D. Casement<lb/> Pentonville Prison.<lb/>  The following regulations as to communications, by Visit or Letter, between prisoners<lb/> and their friends are notified for information of their correspondents. <lb/> .......................................................................  The permission to write and receive Letters, is given to prisoners for<lb/> the purpose of enabling them to keep up a connection with their respectable friends<lb/> &amp; not that they may be kept informed of public events.  All letters are read by Prison Authorities. They must be legibly<lb/> written &amp; not crossed. Any which are of an objectionable tendency, either to or<lb/> from prisoners, or containing slang, or improper expressions, will be suppressed.  Prisoners are permitted to receive &amp; to write a letter at intervals,<lb/> which depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry &amp; good conduct ;<lb/> but matters of special importance to a prisoner may be communicated at any time by<lb/> Letter (prepaid) to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof, if expedient.  In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving &amp; writing a Letter<lb/> may be forfeited for a time.  Money, Books, Postage Stamps, Food, Tobacco, Clothes &amp;c., should<lb/> not be sent to Prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received<lb/> at the Prison for that purpose.  Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce<lb/> any article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine and imprisonment, &amp; any prisoner<lb/> concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.  Prisoners' friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorised persons, to<lb/> send Money, &amp;c., to them privately, under pretence that they can apply it for the<lb/> benefit of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such persons endeavour<lb/> to obtain money for themselves. Any Letter containing such application, received by<lb/> the friends of a prisoner should be, at once, forwarded by them to the Governor.  Prisoners are allowed to receive Visits from their friends, according<lb/> to rules, at intervals which depend on their stage.  When Visits are due to prisoners notification will be sent to the friends<lb/> whom they desire to visit them.  No 243<lb/><hi rend="superscript">(8254â20-4-00)</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0381_img_164_2"/>
                30th June 1916   My dear Gavan Duffy,   I particularly wish you to recover from<lb/> the rooms of the High Court of Justice where I was detained<lb/> the canvas portfolio of papers dealing with my<lb/> case I had brought in from Brixton prison in the<lb/> morning to hand over to you. They are all papers &amp;<lb/> documents dealing with my trial, &amp; it is very<lb/> important for me that they fall into no<lb/> hands but yours. Please apply to the<lb/> Lord Chief Justice for them â with them were<lb/> two books.   xAll have <lb/> been found<lb/><seg type="unclear">PSGov.</seg>  <lb/> (1) Life of Columban<lb/> (2) John Bulls Other Island<lb/> with inscriptions to my cousins.<lb/> (1)Gertrude and <hi rend="superscript">(2)</hi> Elizabeth Bannister  In 'John Bulls other Island' was a clipping<lb/> from the Daily News of 10th May with letter of G.B.<lb/> Shaw on Irish affairs â This also to go to<lb/> my cousin Gertrude â it is her property as well as the book.  If the portfolio of papers is not found<lb/> or recovered will you please try through<lb/> Home Office or Brixton Prison Governor to<lb/> get it - &amp; when recovered place all its<lb/> contents along with the other papers dealing with my<lb/> trial in your possession for the purposes already<lb/> communicated to you.  I also wish you to apply to the<lb/> Home Office for the recovery of my personal<lb/> effects seized by the police â &amp; the<lb/> restoration of all books and documents  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0381_img_164_3"/>
              they may have extracted therefrom. I beg that formal<lb/> application may be mad for the complete<lb/> restoration of all this property and its delivery<lb/> to you as my legal representative. You are<lb/> already acquainted with the manner in which I<lb/> wish my private effects disposed of â &amp; the whereabouts<lb/> of important papers I wish to be secured after<lb/> my death, &amp; when peace comes for the<lb/> country of my heirs.  I further beg of you as a last<lb/> wish â or as if it be a last wish â,<lb/> to make absolutely clear from my<lb/> letters and private papers in your hands<lb/> &amp; from the other sources of information <seg type="del">Pu</seg><lb/> to you wherein I have been wrongfully &amp; <hi rend="underline">most</hi><lb/> untruthfully assailed in the course of this prosecution<lb/> by the crown witnesses. You are acquainted<lb/> with the facts &amp; I leave the vindication<lb/> of my personal honour thus aspersed<lb/> &amp; falsely charged in 'your hands &amp; others'<lb/> of my friends. This covers not only the matter of the pension Knighthood to it- but still more<lb/> the testimony of the soldier witnesses which was as<lb/> you know from my statements capable of being<lb/> completely upset had I chosen to defend myself.  It may be that you cannot do this till after the war is<lb/> over, <sic>altho</sic> something of it may be done today.  I want to thank you &amp; your wife and all those<lb/> who stood around me at the last so faithfully, so<lb/> bravely and so loyally and to say that my last<lb/> thoughts will be of the devotion shown to me â <seg type="del">and</seg><lb/><seg type="del">of the</seg> Please have what I said at the last  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0381_img_164_4"/>
              carefully preserved and a copy of it given<lb/> someday to my many friends in Ireland.  Also the leter that was handed to me<lb/> in the Jack which I gave back to you-   God bless the writer whoever she was.<lb/> Further - a last wish - write for me to that<lb/> lady who wrote to me in the Tower, the one<lb/> who said she had travelled with me from<lb/> Berkshire up to London in 1898 &amp; who<lb/> sent me the cigarettes. If I had had her address<lb/> I should have written to her from Brixton.   I was greatly touched at her remembering me<lb/> &amp; her chivalry â if one may use the word of a<lb/> woman - I think one mayâ, for the noblest, bravest<lb/> &amp; most chivalrous friends I have found in<lb/> these last days, have been women.  To Mark Ryan too &amp; Father Ryan.<lb/> I shall not be able to write often to you<lb/> &amp; when you come again to see me it<lb/> can only be on my legal affairs.  Remember â I left it you &amp;<lb/> those other friends to protect my name after<lb/> all was over â &amp; you know why I kept<lb/> silent &amp; why I did not refute many<lb/> things as I might have done.  I shall bear your friendship with me as<lb/> one of the precious gifts of God, given by Him<lb/> to those whose hearts are faint &amp; broken â for<lb/> it was you, &amp; your help &amp; courage<lb/> that gave me courage to the End &amp; now that<lb/> it is all over, I am happier than you can possibly<lb/> conceive - with heart &amp; mind &amp; soul too<lb/> at peace - &amp; reconciled with all men &amp; all things. <seg type="closer"> Ever yours <lb/> Roger Casement. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>