<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0892">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Atkins Chirnside &amp; Co. to The Shareholders Messrs. Woodford, Bourne &amp; Co., 4 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Atkins Chirnside &amp;amp; Co</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Atkins Chirnside &amp;amp; Co to the shareholders of Woodford Bourne. It is an addendum to its yearly report and balance sheet. Woodford Bourne was one of the icons of business in Cork City for many generations, occupying one of the premier sites on the corner of Patrick Street and Grand Parade.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>UCC Library Special Collections and Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Woodford Bourne Collection BL_BC_WB_24_6, Woodford Bourne Collection BL_BC_WB_24_6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/892</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0076">Atkins Chirnside &amp;amp; Co</persName>
              <date>1916-10-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1350">39 South Mall, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0892_img_2469_1"  type="Letter"  url="d957624b5fd2f036977b2a53e566d3f7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0892_img_2469_1"/>
                39 South Mall,  Cork.    4th October, 1916.  <lb/>To The Shareholders, <lb/>Messrs. Woodford, Bourne &amp; Co. Ltd.  Gentlemen,   In addition to our report appended to the Balance Sheet, <lb/>we beg to report as follows:—  <hi rend="underline">1</hi>. During the year debts amounting to £1662. 3. 5. were <lb/>written off. The Debts now appear to be in much better <lb/>order. We would however point out that there is now no <lb/>reserve against the Debtors.  <hi rend="underline">2</hi>. No provision has been made for depreciation of Premises, <lb/>Fixtures, etc. or depreciation in the value of Investments.  <hi rend="underline">3</hi>. The amounts owing by Directors now amounting to £6502.11.9 <lb/>has increased £103. As we have before reported the only <lb/>security for these Debts is a lieu on the Company's Shares.  <hi rend="underline">4</hi>. The value of the Stock has been certified to us by two <lb/>Directors.  <hi rend="underline">5</hi>. A difference in the year's accounts of £26.13. 1. has <lb/>been written off. <seg type="closer"> We are, Gentlemen, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  Atkins Chirnside &amp; Co. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>