<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3707">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from C.H. Wheeler Ryan to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>C.H. Wheeler Ryan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from C.H. Wheeler Ryan to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), Wheeler Ryan offers their sympathy in regards to the murder of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. Wheeler Ryan writes telling Hanna to please ask if she requires anything, specifically to assure her that if she visits England they would be happy to put her up. Wheeler Ryan recounts their days together in the Field Naturalists Club and closes with a final expression of sympathy.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/2-18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3707</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1013">C.H. Wheeler Ryan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0157">79 Alderley Road, Merseyside, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3707_img_3098_1"  type="Letter"  url="86e26fe7e575a36594e1ef0609a87320.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3707_img_3098_2"  type="Letter"  url="445104fb58a536ece284cdbe74aaf95c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3707_img_3098_3"  type="Letter"  url="5dabb4a7ecbcedf75accad3d169e2edf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3707_img_3098_4"  type="Letter"  url="64eb94b4299dffa17119b8d4bd675b17.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3707_img_3098_1"/>
             79, Alderly Road<lb/>Hoylake   May 13 '16    Dear Mrs Skeffington   Will you allow me<lb/>to offer you my heartfelt<lb/>and respectful sympathy<lb/>in your tragic sorrow<lb/>. Also that of<lb/>my sister. and to<lb/>say also how much<lb/>we admire your<lb/>own fortitude and 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3707_img_3098_2"/>
             self-restraint in<lb/>this black agony.  I cannot attempt<lb/>to say what I<lb/>would but I should<lb/>take it as a<lb/>great <seg type="unclear">favour</seg> if<lb/>you would let me<lb/>know at once<lb/>are you in need<lb/>of money and if<lb/>there is <hi rend="underline">anything</hi><lb/>I can do.  If you should 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3707_img_3098_3"/>
             have to come to<lb/>England or your sisters<lb/>I hope you would<lb/>let us put you up.  We met you and<lb/>your <seg type="unclear">always?</seg> one over<lb/>and over again at<lb/>the <seg type="unclear">Fierd <!-- old word for army --></seg> Nationalists<lb/>Club in there <!--correctly spelled their -->happy<lb/>far off days — I am<lb/>sure that in some<lb/>way his martyr's<lb/>crown will be a<lb/>crown. A joy for<lb/>Ireland — Do let 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3707_img_3098_4"/>
             me be of a little<lb/>use if it is at<lb/>all possible. and<lb/>believe that we<lb/>share your grief<lb/>and mourning.  <lb/>God bless you and<lb/>comfort you   Your sincere friend<lb/>Sympathies<lb/>C.H Wheeler Ryan.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>