<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1364">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lord Wimborne to Sir John Maxwell, 3 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ivor Churchill Guest</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939) to Sir John Grenfell Maxwell (1859-1929). The letter was written in the aftermath of the Rising and on the day of the first executions of the leaders. It primarily concerns the issue of martial law. Wimborne had introduced martial law on 25 April, the second day of the Rising, and writes that the original documentation allowed it to be continued for one month. He notes that it would be possible to extend this if necessary. In a postscript Wimborne refers to the attorney general and the &#39;laudable task&#39; of seizing arms from volunteer organisations (such the Irish Volunteers and the Ulster Volunteers Force). Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918. Sir John Henry Grenfell Maxwell was appointed commander in chief of the British forces in Ireland after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. Before 1916, Maxwell briefly held command of British troops in Egypt, where he successfully organised defences against a Turkish attack in February 1915 and presided over the huge expansion of his command as Egypt became a major British imperial military base. In March 1916, having been superseded as general officer commanding in Egypt, he was recalled home when the Easter Rising broke out.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera papers, P150/512</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1364</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date>1916-05-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1364_img_716_1"  type="Letter"  url="d9a521f207c5393da5b7a94eb83e227b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1364_img_716_2"  type="Letter"  url="c535a1a51be8d40a21bc3728d13489f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1364_img_716_3"  type="Letter"  url="6b5b7304e219adbf3ee3f93984d75758.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1364_img_716_4"  type="Letter"  url="98b7a3197c081159d5f61be69408dd67.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1364_img_716_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">May 3<hi rend="superscript">rd 16</hi></hi>   Dear Sir John Maxwell   The proclamation which extended <lb/> Martial Law to all Ireland was modelled <lb/> on my first proclamation of the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ultimus <lb/> applying it to Dublin and County.  This was drawn up by the Law Offices. <lb/>I have telephoned to Mr Campbell who <lb/> informs me that the Statute provides <lb/> that a definite time <seg type="del">should</seg> must  be stated  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1364_img_716_2"/>
              <lb/>in the proclamation, and that the state <lb/> of affairs on the 24 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> served to him <lb/> to point to one month as the period <lb/> to be specified.  Then is nothing to prevent an <lb/> extension of this period at any time, <lb/> but he is of opinion that this would <lb/> come better, if thought necessary, <lb/> at a later stage in the specified period  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1364_img_716_3"/>
              <lb/>I am writing to the Prime Minister <lb/> and will ask him his instructions <lb/>Will you represent to him your <lb/> opinions or shall I say that you are <lb/> concerned at the month limit?  I am much obliged to you for <lb/> keeping me informed of the progress <lb/> of events  Please let me know if I can be <lb/> of any assistance to you <seg type="closer"> Yours v sincerely  Wimborne </seg> <hi rend="underline">OVER</hi>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1364_img_716_4"/>
              The Attorney General proposes to leave <lb/> Ireland in the laudable task of <lb/> securing by agreement the disarmament <lb/> of <hi rend="underline">all</hi> volunteer organisations in <lb/> Ireland  I do not know whether he might <lb/> not be wanted here. Points might <lb/> arise on which you might wish to <lb/> consult him  I have told him that he should <lb/> have your written instructions <seg type="closer"> W </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>