<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6706">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frank P. Walsh to William Bourke Cockran, 19 December 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frank P. Walsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Frank P. Walsh (1864-1939), was an American lawyer and political reformer. He was one of the chief architects of the legislative struggle against industrial exploitation of children and an advocate of Irish and anti-imperialist causes. He also fought for civil liberties and was a labour partisan and staunch New Dealer. Walsh was a member of the Irish-American delegation (along with Michael J. Ryan and Edward F. Dunne) who were appointed to represent Ireland at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919. On 10 April 1919 the delegation arrived in Paris. The men returned to America in July 1919 where Walsh began working with the Dail External Loan (Bond Drive). William Burke Cockran (1854-1922) was born in Sligo. He completed his education in Summerhill college, Sligo and the Marist College in Lille, France. In 1871 Cockran immigrated to America. While working as a teacher he studied law at night. In 1876 he passed the bar; he practiced in Mount Vernon for two years before moving to New York to practice law. His legal career was constrained by an interest in politics. In 1903, Cockran returned to Ireland and was made a freeman of the borough of Sligo, at this time he was a vigorous supporter of Home Rule. Cockran protested against the execution of the leaders of the 1916 Rising, and also condemned the introduction of martial law in Ireland in 1919. In December 1919, while working on the Dail Eireann Bond Certificates and Bond Drive he called for formal American recognition of the Irish Republican Government.  
In this letter, Walsh was sending 500 printed copies of deValera&#39;s instructions regarding the bond drive to Cockran. This material was to be distributed to city chairmen, treasurer and other officers as well as campaign workers. These manuals were to be used for both reference and guidance in the selling of bond certificates.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>William Bourke Cockran Papers, Box 13, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6706</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0925">Frank P. Walsh</persName>
              <date>1919-12-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1646">New York</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Bourke Cockran</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1646">New York</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6706_img_None_1"  url="phpen999N.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6706_img_0_1"/>
             American Commission on Irish Independence<lb/>Frank P. Walsh Chairman   411 Fifth Avenue<lb/>New York    December Eighteenth<lb/>Nineteen Nineteen    Hon. W. Bourke Cockran,<lb/>100 Broadway<lb/>New York, N.Y.    Dear Mr. Cockran:-   I am sending you 500 printed copies of<lb/>President De Valera's Manual of Instructions for the use of<lb/>your City Chairmen, Treasurer, and other officers and, where<lb/>desired, campaign workers. It is probable that each campaign<lb/>worker who is interested would feel complimented by having one<lb/>of these manuals for his own reference and guidance.  I hardly need add that the sooner these documents<lb/>are in the hands of those, for whose use they are intended, the<lb/>better, especially in view of the shortness of the campaign.  Wishing you a Merry Xmas and a Happy New Year, I am   Yours very truly,    Frank P Walsh<lb/>Chairman  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>