<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5481">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert Henry Asquith, 2 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert Henry Asquith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter was written by Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), then Liberal Prime Minister of Great Britain. The letter is a response to an appeal for clemency for Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) who was under a sentence of death. He writes that the British Cabinet had decided that they could not offer a reprieve. Casement had been imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. A campaign was launched featuring many prominent figures such as W.B. Yeats and George Bernard Shaw to secure a reprieve for Casement but he was hanged on 3 August 1916, the day after this letter was written.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,078 /7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5481</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0737">10 Downing Street, Whitehall, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1928</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5481_img_514_1"  type="Letter"  url="7bb99f8184f571e6c24e03745dca8ec0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5481_img_514_2"  type="Letter"  url="78d60322f560f706a585e7ec9c4bc85e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5481_img_514_1"/>
             10, Downing Street, <lb/>Whitehall S.W.   <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   2 Aug 1916   Dear Madam,   It is with <lb/>sincere pain (&amp; only <lb/>in compliance with your <lb/> request) that I inform <lb/>you that, after my <lb/>full consideration, the <lb/>Cabinet today came
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5481_img_514_2"/>
            to the conclusion that <lb/>there were no sufficient <lb/>grounds for a reprieve.   I need not assure you <lb/>that I wish it had <lb/>been possible for them <lb/>to arrive at a different <lb/>decision.   Yours very faithfully   H.H.Asquith   This is a <hi rend="underline">secret</hi> communication.   I am returning the <lb/> documents. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>