<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4150">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 8 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/49</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4150</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4150_img_3524_1"  type="Letter"  url="39d678210555174f28c716a52e135438.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4150_img_3524_2"  type="Letter"  url="37e6eed928b75b1707ed50b73b803f41.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4150_img_3524_1"/>
             Nov. 8.   My   Just a buff slip today <lb/>to thank you for your last daily <lb/>letter an extra nice one, &amp; <lb/>to give the pink pares something <lb/>to find in the bran pie enclosure.   Yesterday was quite interesting <lb/>&amp; if the Goc now wishes me <lb/>to go I shall be surprised, as <lb/>he must have seen by the <lb/>way the others treated me <lb/>that he has not got a yonny <lb/>cub of a captain.    I too find a pr r is just <lb/>as bothering as ever &amp; that <lb/>I miss her evidently more <lb/>than Miss L Dean misses <lb/>her b w sometimes!   The GOC has ordered me to <lb/>return to the House of Lords via
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4150_img_3524_2"/>
            the Duke of Luynes who has   <lb/>as have also all the other Liaison <lb/>officers — not the interpreters of course — <lb/>because so on dit they talked too <lb/>much. <seg type="del">I showed that</seg> I was <lb/>not too willing to come back <lb/>as the family party in the <lb/>Commons with <seg type="unclear">Borjian</seg> Smith <lb/>is certainly a cheerier crew, &amp; <lb/>I let them know that I didn't <lb/>wish to be a kind of gormers <lb/>to dim in to make up the party.   My chilblained right <lb/>hand is itching so that I <lb/>can't go on writing. I am <lb/>glad I left off rings. Are you <lb/>wearing mine? Did you write <lb/>to the Dean &amp; if so what was his <lb/>answer? A poor snubbed p r ?    I believe you are staying at Rugby <lb/>but dare not risk it &amp; any how you <lb/>will be more definite next time.   Your   BW 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>