<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0488">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Home Office to Joseph Devlin, 26 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>The Home Office</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from the Home Office to Joseph Devlin (1871-1934), Irish Parliamentary Party MP for Belfast West, acknowledging Devlin&#39;s 22 July letter to the Herbert Samuel (1870-1963), British Home Secretary, where Devlin makes representations on behalf of a constituent who was appointed petty sessions clerk on condition that he pass a qualifying examination. The constituent failed the examination and was removed from the post. Devlin&#39;s dissatisfaction with the conduct of the examination is evident in the letter and also suggests the constituent being of military age may have also contributed to the decision. Devlin asks Samuel to look into the matter with a view to having the man reinstated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13049/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/488</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1033">The Home Office</persName>
              <date>1916-07-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1832">Home Office, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0915">Joseph Devlin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0077">House of Commons, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0488_img_1851_1"  type="Letter"  url="1f416cc119b091104547e813cc612dd8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0488_img_1851_2"  type="Letter"  url="b4292ab8c3214ceda60f6f6139714e7b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0488_img_1851_3"  type="Letter"  url="7bd3aabb11f2d8ae166591fd48d1d069.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0488_img_1851_1"/>
              PPS for report E.OF 29.7.16    26thJuly 1916   Dear Sir   I am desired by the <lb/> Home Secretary to acknowledge the <lb/> receipt of your letter of the <lb/> 22nd instant, and to say that it <lb/> shall receive consideration  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully   Joseph Devlin Esq., M.P.  </seg> Bring up 3 August 29/7 16  A.U.S. <lb/> In favour of <lb/>report A.P.M. 28/7   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0488_img_1851_2"/>
             <seg type="head"><hi rend="underline">PRIVATE</hi></seg>   22nd. July, 1916   My dear Mr Samuel,   I have been asked to write you on behalf of <lb/> Mr Michael McConville, son of Mr Patrick McConvillem J. P. <lb/> of Crossmaglen, who was appointed Petty Sessions Clerk <lb/> for the Crossmaglen Petty Sessions District on the 16th <lb/> January last. The appointment was subject to his <lb/> passing a qualifying examination. The examination <lb/> was held in Dublin Castle under O'Connell Caddle <lb/> Registrar of Petty Sessions Clerks, on the 21st. June <lb/> last. Sixty-seven questions were given: Mr McConville <lb/> states that he answered fifty. The examination closed <lb/> at 1.40 p.m. and at 2 p.m. the result was communicated <lb/> to him;he was told that he had failed for lack of <lb/> knowledge; and fault was found with the way he had kept <lb/> the books of the Court during his tenure of the office. <lb/> Mr McConville and his friends fail to see how the papers <lb/> could have been properly examined in twenty minutes. <lb/> He believes he was rejected largely on the ground that <lb/> he is of military age. The order prohibiting the <lb/> appointment to public offices of candidates of military  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0488_img_1851_3"/>
              age was only issued at Easter last, whereas Mr McConville <lb/> was appointed last January. He is a young man of the <lb/> highest respectability and was educated at St. Patick's <lb/> College, Armagh, and St. Mary's College, Dundalk, and <lb/> passed the Preliminary Examination of the Pharmaceutical <lb/> Society. There is the best reason to believe that the <lb/> Court books were very satisfactorily kept.   I would take it as a special favour if you would <lb/> have enquiries made into this case with a view to having <lb/> his appointment confirmed. I feel sure you will give <lb/> the case youe sympathetic consideration.   Thanking you in anticipation <seg type="closer"> I remain <lb/> Yours sincerely   <lb/> The Rt. Hon. Herbert Samuel M.P. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>