<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2258">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to William Coote, 27 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to William Coote. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
William Coote (1853-1924) was a politician and in 1916 he was representing South Tyrone as a Unionist MP and continued to do so until 1922.
The letter talks about the choices that Edward Carson will have to make for the good of the Unionist movement. Montgomery also writes to Coote to enclose various letters that are not included with this copy.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2258</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Coote</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2258_img_1701_1"  type="Letter"  url="750094dff122f41fb796ceca5190f8d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2258_img_1701_2"  type="Letter"  url="259d2ff2aadd6a856a06a04edc171f73.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2258_img_1701_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Private</hi> <lb/>Copy  27th May, 1916.   Dear Mr. Coote,   I enclose a copy of the draft of a letter I intended <lb/>sending to the "Times", but which I have now entrusted to <lb/>a safe hand in London to use or not as he thinks wise.   Knowing what very good information and advice <lb/>Mr. Asquith got from many people of influence and ability <lb/>over here, I am disappointed at the character of his statement .<lb/>The position is very difficult. Sir Edward Carson woud be <lb/>serving our interests badly by putting himself too violently <lb/>in conflict with any strong current of public opinion in <lb/>England in favour of some sort of a "settlement." I am <lb/>sure he will not give away our position here <hi rend="underline">in substance,</hi> <lb/>but he may have to take up a position which, to some of <lb/>our more stiff-necked friends here, will look like some <lb/>sort of surrender; and it will be necessary, above all <lb/>things, to prevent our people losing confidence in him, <lb/>as, if they do, we are lost. We have no other friend of <lb/>sufficiently commanding ability and position in the <lb/>political world to steer us safely through the very difficult <lb/>water ahead.   I am rather pleased to find how nearly the wording <lb/>of the second resolution I send you corresponds with what <lb/>Sir Edward Carson said in response to Mr. Asquith's statement.   Yours very truly, 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2258_img_1701_2"/>
             P.S. I enclose a typed copy of the resolutions I drafted <lb/> at your suggestion, and I add a copy of a further resolution <lb/> which I think we might very well pass. I think it would be <lb/> better that these resolutions should not be proposed and <lb/> seconded by me , but by some of the rank and file of the <lb/> Delegates.    I enclose a copy of a letter I am sending to each of <lb/> the members of the conference on Tuesday in hopes that it <lb/> will save time at the meeting. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>