<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0761">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 12 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender expresses discontent that a few of his letters have been published in the press without his consent. He gives an account of his own situation, describing the surrounding countryside, the family who live in the chateau, and his strained relationship with a colleague. He describes a lacklustre 12 July, noting the exhaustion of the men. He asks Lillian to thank his mother for her donation to the Ulster Fund, congratulates Lillian herself on her continuing hard work, and hopes that that work might do something to bridge the class divide in Ulster.Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/342</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/761</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0761_img_2293_1"  type="Letter"  url="aef85c4fe4dfc652c0810d0e5be29abe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0761_img_2293_2"  type="Letter"  url="504c9ce107710f8ba5a08a1f1e376997.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0761_img_2293_3"  type="Letter"  url="b9312327256fd1946bf7e1648c89e3e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0761_img_2293_4"  type="Letter"  url="22e4875355708790c82e866f964b32ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0761_img_2293_5"  type="Letter"  url="5b4cadfe9d170df3934203161b635671.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0761_img_2293_1"/>
                12 July   My p r   I'm afraid letters are rather ragged just <lb/>now, but when one is on the move things <lb/>are always a little more difficult &amp; I am <lb/>away from the ordinary post till tomorrow.  I thought you were at <seg type="unclear">Sir Edwards</seg><lb/>last week-end but find it is to be this one <lb/>so will chance sending a letter there.  I hope he is well &amp; feeling well but <lb/>wish he could have seen his way to <lb/>have taken a more active part in <lb/><seg type="unclear">(or agin)</seg> the Government of the country.  I am getting a little restive at the <lb/>way my letters get into the papers! My <lb/>one to you was all right tho' only <lb/>intended for Mr G's private perusal, but I <lb/>wrote a personal one to Col Crawford &amp; <lb/><seg type="del">an</seg> a letter of condolence ( with some <lb/>religious remarks) to Mr Davidson &amp; <lb/>it never occurred to me that these  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0761_img_2293_2"/>
              would be published. I suppose one ought not <lb/>to mind but it seems lacking in delicacy <lb/>&amp; I should certainly have written very <lb/>differently had I known. I hope Craig <lb/>will not publish anything more â I have <lb/>sent him 2 letters â as one might get <lb/>into trouble &amp; I hate to feel that I am <lb/>advertising the division.  Luckily in some ways Sir G also <lb/>published the General's letter &amp; his orders. <lb/>He is rather <seg type="unclear">livid</seg> about it. I also wrote <lb/>to Gen Powell &amp; Sir G I do hope the <lb/>latter won't take mine to the Press! It is <lb/>private on the face of it.  I enclose a letter from Sir Ralph <lb/>Really it is <seg type="unclear">nice</seg> of him to have written &amp; <lb/>I appreciate it but I shall take him at <lb/>his word for the present &amp; not answer  We are now in country like Norfolk <lb/>which is very much nicer than I <lb/>had expected but we move another 15 <lb/>miles tomorrow when I expect the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0761_img_2293_3"/>
              country will be still flatter &amp; more <lb/>full of dykes &amp; perhaps less healthy  We expect to be left alone for some <lb/>weeks getting out drafts and training the men <lb/>-rather sad work in some ways as you <lb/>can understand especially as they will <lb/>not be our men.  The Lady of our chateau has 6 <lb/>little daughters all stepping up 1 year <lb/>apart from 2 to 9. Rather like a <seg type="del">p r</seg><lb/>family tho' I don't quite fix yet <lb/>which is to be the p r of the bunch!!  The mother is teaching them music <lb/>and plays accompaniments to their scales <lb/>on the fiddle &amp; simple exercises â vey <lb/>much like one's early school days.  P &amp; I have got along much better lately <lb/><seg type="del">yesterday</seg> but I am afraid he overheard <lb/>yesterday a rather unguarded remark <lb/>I made to S which he probably resents <lb/>&amp; will pay back.  Everyone here talks so well of the <lb/>division that one feels that one's <lb/>pride in belonging to it is not all <lb/>swank.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0761_img_2293_4"/>
              A sorry 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July but our men <lb/>are wearing their lilies tho whether <lb/>bought or stolen or presented I don't <lb/>know. Most of them have had <lb/>long marches so I don't expect they <lb/>will do much drumming.  Saunderson aged 55(?) is to succeed <lb/>Farnham as ADC! He is said to have a <lb/>very rude manner &amp; a bad temper but <lb/>this may pay with the G O C &amp; Farnham <lb/>who has done splendid work has I <lb/>hope taught Harry his job.  I must write to Mater for her <lb/>most kind cheque some of which will <lb/>go to the Ulster Fund. Please tell her so <lb/>so that she may not feel bound to do <lb/>anything more for it. She really is a <lb/>wonder with her reduced income but <lb/>I don't think she ought or will be able <lb/>to continue these munificent presents.  My room is at the top of the <seg type="foreign">Chateau</seg><lb/>so nice &amp; airy. I wish I could take  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0761_img_2293_5"/>
              <lb/>it or my hut with me  Please convey to Lady C how very <lb/>greatly I appreciate their kindness to you <lb/>&amp; how much easier it makes things for <lb/>me to know that you have such kind <lb/>friends to look after you &amp; to prevent <lb/>your work from becoming over burdensome.  Yes I am indeed glad you took up this <lb/>work &amp; not the other now &amp; I think you <lb/>are probably doing more for the future of <lb/>Ulster than either of us quite <seg type="unclear">could</seg> of. <lb/>any <seg type="unclear">neglect</seg> now would certainly spread &amp; <lb/>make a gulf between the classes which the <lb/>UVF days have closed for a time.  Quite a good letter considering <lb/>which deserves a good mark but I see no <lb/>chance of getting i for a long time yet. <seg type="closer"> Your  b w <lb/>W B Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>