<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3030">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Henry Augustus Robinson to Thomas Nally, 2 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Augustus Robinson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Henry Robinson writes to Thomas Nally stating that he has read his play, the Spancel of Death, remarking that it is &#39;powerful&#39; and &#39;held me spell bound&#39;. He points out an historical inaccuracy in the play but concludes that the play will be a great success if staged.

The Spancel of Death was due to open on easter Tuesday at the Abbey theater. It was postponed due to the Easter Rising.

Sir Henry Augustus Robinson (1857–1927) was an Irish public servant. He was primarily responsible for the drafting and implementation of the local government act of 1898, and shortly before the bill became law was appointed vice-president of the Local Government Board.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Thomas Nally Papers; MS 36,213/4-6a-c</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3030</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1153">Henry Augustus Robinson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0210">Lisnacarrig, Foxrock, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1110">Thomas Nally</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3030_img_243_1"  type="Letter"  url="04419454717edd77bd7c09338f7eb8cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3030_img_243_2"  type="Letter"  url="3612672d64153bd482b56a14f7e584c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3030_img_243_3"  type="Letter"  url="a77c5867e24ef9f9d19c99779137e3fe.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3030_img_243_1"/>
             TELEPHONE 13 FOXROCK   LISNACARRIG, <lb/>FOXROCK, <lb/>Co.DUBLIN.   2. Apr 1916   My dear Sir   I have read your <lb/>play &amp; think it is <lb/>the most powerful &amp; <lb/>romantic thing I <lb/>have ever read. It <lb/>held me spell bound.   I wonder if the <lb/>Abbey people have <lb/>any woman in their <lb/>company capable of <lb/>doing justice to the <lb/>role of Sibly Cottle— <lb/>It would need <lb/>a Maire O'Neill.   My wife
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3030_img_243_2"/>
            <lb/>remembers Biddy <lb/>Holian the last of <lb/>the witches race, &amp; <lb/>she had a bad <lb/>name — an inheritance <lb/>I suppose from Judy.   Old Sir Harry <lb/>Lynch Blosses evil <lb/>reputation <seg type="del">was</seg> <lb/>is a tradition in <lb/>the family even <lb/>now and my <lb/>wife tells me that <lb/>when her fathers <lb/>generation suffered <lb/>from gout or other <lb/>ailment or misfortune &amp; <lb/>they always regarded it <lb/>as a visitation for <lb/>the sins of Sir Harry.   There is one little <lb/>mistake you made <lb/>which is a pity in <lb/>a story which is <lb/>otherwise historically <lb/> accurate.   You made <seg type="del">th</seg> <lb/>Lord Oranmore the <lb/>person who is arranging <lb/>the marriage with <lb/>Altamounts daughter.   Now the Oranmore <lb/>peerage was only <lb/>created in 1836
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3030_img_243_3"/>
            <lb/>and Sir Harry's <lb/>period was nearly <lb/>100 years earlier.   The play will <lb/>create a great <lb/>sensation if <lb/>properly staged. The <lb/>dialogues are so <lb/>natural that I can <lb/>almost hear the people <lb/>speaking.   Wishing you <lb/>every luck with it <lb/>&amp; with many thanks <lb/>for your courtesy in <lb/>letting me see it.   I remain <lb/>Yours truly   <hi rend="underline">H A Robinson</hi>   I omitted to mention that <lb/>my wife doesn't see any <lb/>reason why any of her <lb/>family <sic>shd</sic> object to the <lb/>play.   I will register it &amp; <lb/>send it back tomorrow 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>