<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0322">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edith Francis Maxwell to Lady Clonbrock, 22 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edith Francis Maxwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edith Francis Maxwell (b.1874) to Lady Clonbrock (1840-1928). Maxwell writes to Lady Clonbrock asking if a Private Matthew James is on the list of prisoners receiving aid from the Irish Women&#39;s Association. Maxwell explains that the Private&#39;s family are not in the position to send out parcels and she and her sister can no longer afford to send aid to James as they already send parcels to two other men and do not want to forget about them as they are very grateful.Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne. Edith Francis Maxwell née Battersby, the eldest of seven children, had a number of brothers serving in the Great War. Her brother Augustus Wolfe Battersby was gazetted to the 4th battalion of the Connaught Rangers. Battersby was killed in action during a combined Anglo-French campaign against the German colony of Cameroon in the summer of 1915.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54, Ms. 35,796/10/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/322</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0042">Edith Francis Maxwell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0153">Corduff House, Lusk, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0322_img_1546_1"  type="Letter"  url="b9f49d3901cc9d7b22381677d09c540b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0322_img_1546_2"  type="Letter"  url="1d5effa194be6688b81afff4ce28ea23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0322_img_1546_3"  type="Letter"  url="a5155973619bfba40e663bacc353e305.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0322_img_1546_1"/>
                Corduff House  Lusk  Co. Dublin    June 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>   Dear Madam   I would be so grate- <lb/>ful if you find out for <lb/> me if a P<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> Matthew James <lb/>2.<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Connaught  8056  Rangers <lb/>Cellilager ZX <lb/>Hanover <lb/>is on the list of prisoners <lb/>helped by the County <lb/> Fund. We know his <lb/>people are not in a <lb/> position to help him <lb/> his father &amp; mother are  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0322_img_1546_2"/>
              drunkards in the slums <lb/> of Dublin, another brother <lb/> was wounded &amp; the two <lb/> younger ones who <lb/> were working here in <lb/> the summer with my <lb/> brother enlisted in the <lb/> Dublin Fusiliers since. <lb/>My sister &amp; I send him <lb/>occasional parcels but <lb/> are not able to do more <lb/> than that, as we had <lb/> 2 other Connaught Rangers <lb/> prisoners before we heard <lb/> he was a prisoner &amp; <lb/> don't like to give up the <lb/> other men, Bdm, Hurt   &amp; C<hi rend="superscript">pl</hi> Leach though they <lb/> are Englishmen as they <lb/> are so grateful for what <lb/> we send. Poor men <lb/> they are terribly to be <lb/>pitied. <seg type="closer"> Yrs truly  (Miss) h. Maxwell. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0322_img_1546_3"/>
               1916 Miss Maxwell <lb/>June 26 <lb/>re M James, 8056, <lb/> C.R. <lb/>not in Galway <lb/>but on I.W.A. list <lb/>a Lady in Eng. sends <lb/>to him through them  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>