<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1299">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter From E. Blackwell to George Gavan Duffy, 2 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>E. Blackwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from E. Blackwell, under secretary of state for the Home Office to George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951) and refers to the execution of Sir Roger Casement, who had been tried for treason having been arrested on the eve of the Easter Rising. Blackwell is responding to Gavan Duffy&#39;s request that Casement&#39;s body be bured outside of prison walls, the desire of Casement&#39;s family, and that he be allowed to be present at the execution, noting that the Secretary of State for the Home Office (Herbert Samuel) could not accede to the request.George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List no. A15, Ms. 13,088 /12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1299</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1476">E. Blackwell</persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1712">Home Office, Whitehall, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0654">4 Raymond Buildings, Gray's Inn W.C., London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1299_img_518_1"  type="Letter"  url="4a9c2eed8848c8c8ba17bdcfef6119f6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1299_img_518_1"/>
                Home Office,  Whitehall. S.W.     2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> August 1916.   311643.  Sir:-   I am directed by the Secretary of State to say that <lb/> he is unable to comply with the request made by you on behalf of <lb/> certain relatives of the prisoner Roger David Casement that his body <lb/> may be buried outside the prison as the law requires that it shall be <lb/> buried within the walls.  I am to inform you also that the Secretary of State is <lb/> unable to accede to your request that you may be present at <lb/> the execution. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant,  E. BLACKWELL.   G. Gavan Duffy, Esq.,  4 Raymond Buildings,  Gray's Inn. W.C  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>