<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0477">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Town Clerk, Blackrock, County Dublin, to Lord Wimborne, 20 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Town Clerk</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from the Town Clerk&#39;s Office, Blackrock, informing the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Lord Wimborne (1873 -1939), of the Resolution passed by Blackrock Urban District Council at their bi-monthly meeting. The Resolution is regarding the appointment of Mr. J. H. Campbell as Attorney General for Ireland over Mr. James O&#39;Connor (1872-1931), Solicitor General.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918. J.H. Campbell would hold the office of Attorney General for Ireland from 1916 to 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7307/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/477</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1452">Town Clerk</persName>
              <date>1916-04-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1791">Town Clerk&#39;s Office, Town Hall, Blackrock, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1787">Vice Regal Lodge, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0477_img_1831_1"  type="Letter"  url="d0f216f314b52b1b4489ed825245beb9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0477_img_1831_2"  type="Letter"  url="9378d4b0cc9f18bf973ce00c3eb4e113.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0477_img_1831_1"/>
                Urban District Blackrock  Town Clerk's Office,  Town Hall Blackrock Co Dublin.    20th April 1916.   Sir,   I am directed to forward you herewith copy of Resolution <lb/> passed at the Bi-Monthly Meeting of the Blackrock Urban <lb/> District Council, last night.  <seg type="closer"> I am Sir, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,   <seg type="unclear">Robert Finlay</seg>  Town Clerk.   The Rt. Hon. Lord Wimborne,  Lord Lieutenant of Ireland,  Vice Regal Lodge,  D U B L I N  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0477_img_1831_2"/>
              MOVED by Councillor J.P., McCabe J.P. ( Chairman ) <lb/> SECONDED by Councillor Frank Foy. <lb/> and carried:-   ' THAT we regard the <lb/> appointment of Mr J.H. Campbell as Attorney General for <lb/> Ireland over the head of Mr James O'Connor, Solicitor General, <lb/> to whom the office should revert in accordance with the usual <lb/> practice' as perpetuating the worst days of Tory ascendancy <lb/> and calculated to bring the administration of the law into <lb/> disrepute. The appointment of the Law Adviser of the Covenantors <lb/> whose declared intention it was to defy the law of the <lb/> Land, to a position in which he would be responsible for <lb/> instituting criminal prosecutions, is in our opinion highly <lb/> dangerous at this particular period and may lead to unpleasant <lb/> consequences. Further we are strongly of opinion that the <lb/> filling of a Judicial vacancy at this time, after the public <lb/> convenience had been sacrificed by the refusal to appoint a <lb/> Police Magistrate for Dublin because the vacancy should have <lb/> been filled by a Catholic, and the refusal to fill other <lb/> appointments which by their nature should have fallen to <lb/> Catholics, is a clear indication that a effort is <lb/> being made by the bigoted ascendancy party to fully resume <lb/> their intolerant domination in this country. We consider this <lb/> attempt must be met by native organisation on the part of <lb/> Nationalists, however loath they may be to follow such a course <lb/> at this period, and would respectfully earnestly urge the <lb/> Irish Party, in whose ability to safeguard the interests of <lb/> Ireland we have absolute confidence, to consider the present <lb/> situation in the light of these new developments'.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>