<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0789">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Gourlay to Charles Arthur Munro, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Gourlay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Gourlay, foreman of works at Mountjoy Prison, to the prison Governor, Charles Arthur Munro (1869 - 1952) concerning a collapsed wall. This letter is part of a series of correspondence regarding the collapse of a shared wall between the neighbouring laundry and prison. According to the foreman the clay used to construct the wall was of poor quality and the prison&#39;s ivy had little to do with it&#39;s collapse.Charles Arthur Munro was the governor of Mountjoy prison in Dublin. He is also the brother of the noted author H.H. Munro, better known through his literary pseudonym, Saki.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/2892/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/789</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0541">Robert Gourlay</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0487">Charles Arthur Munro</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0789_img_2330_1"  type="Letter"  url="16c8fc3596ee2c20dedb201935eed452.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0789_img_2330_2"  type="Letter"  url="e01c0047afaaa9bb9824bfef7ee4f782.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0789_img_2330_1"/>
                Mountjoy Prison    22.11.15    With reference to a <lb/>communication dated 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. <lb/>received from the N.C. Laundry <lb/>re wall blown down <lb/>I beg to report that I made <lb/>a thorough examination <lb/>of the site and noticed a <lb/>considerable quantity of <lb/>clay and rubbish on the <lb/>Laundry side where it had <lb/>evidently been dumped <lb/>and lain there for a long <lb/>time. I particularly <lb/>noticed that the mortar <lb/>used for building the wall <lb/>was of a very poor quality <lb/>and that there was no <lb/>thorough bond, the wall <lb/>is 2 feet thick and was <lb/>built one stone each side <lb/>and filled in the centre <lb/>with small stone chippings <lb/>and mortar. I pointed <lb/>all this out to the Laundry <lb/>Manager. That portion of <lb/>the wall which fell was <lb/>the most exposed, the remainder <lb/>being sheltered by the Laundry <lb/>Buildings. A part of the <lb/>wall is still standing against <lb/>which the greater bulk of <lb/>the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0789_img_2330_2"/>
              (2) <lb/>the ivy is growing a fact <lb/>which tends to show that <lb/>the ivy was not responsible for <lb/>the fall of the wall taking <lb/>all these conditions into <lb/>account I am strongly <lb/>of opinion that the exceptionally <lb/>heavy rains of late falling <lb/>on the bank of earth against <lb/>the wall which fell all of a <lb/>piece at that spot and the <lb/>terrific storm on the night <lb/>of the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst following as it <lb/>did in repeated gusts from the <lb/>Laundry side was too much <lb/>for a badly built old wall <lb/>to stand against. <seg type="closer"> R. Gourlay <lb/>Foreman of Works</seg> The Governor  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>