<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1953">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell to James Lawler, 30 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926) to James Lawler the clerk for the Navan Urban District Council. O&#39;Farrell was the assistant under-Secretary to the Viceroy of Ireland Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne. The lord lieutenant or viceroy was the monarch’s representative in Ireland. In the letter O&#39;Farrell is replying to Lawler denying the request he wrote on behalf of the Council for permission to end the appointment of the Office of Shop Inspector, which he says costs the Council an unnecessary £10 a year.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8988/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1953</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0139">James Lawler</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0040">Navan</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1953_img_1402_1"  type="Letter"  url="e8a0bd185f7e93e2da1bf9273960d136.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1953_img_1402_1"/>
             30th May, 1916.  <lb/>8988.  Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 26th instant <lb/>I am directed by the Lords justices to acquaint <lb/>you for the information of the Navan Urban District <lb/>Council, that Section 13 (1) of the Shops Act re- <lb/>quires that an Inspector shall be appointed to en- <lb/>force the provisions of the Act    I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your Obedient Servant,   EO'F   The Clerk, <lb/>Navan Urban District Council, <lb/>Navan. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>