<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5946">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Gus to Eamonn O'Modhráin, 13 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Gus</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin (Edward Moran) (1881-1954) from a friend, Gus. O&#39;Modhráin had been arrested and imprisoned after the Easter Rising and spent time in Wakefield Prison and Frongach Internment Camp. This letter was sent while O&#39;Modhráin was in Wakefield. The author refers to a conversation with a prisoner recently released from Wakefield, friends held in other prisons and friends and family at home, including O&#39;Modhráin&#39;s brother Lewis, who had been released from Wakefield.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O&#39;Modhráin Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5946</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0006">Gus</persName>
              <date>1916-06-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0843">41 Windsor Avenue, Fairview, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1527">Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1424">Wakefield Prison, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5946_img_1576_1"  type="Letter"  url="5090f51ba230e322bacfe7aa7fdcfca0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5946_img_1576_2"  type="Letter"  url="30b36d2bef5f0651f5a9b797dc617688.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5946_img_1576_3"  type="Letter"  url="afe002878f08ba269ae542228535c545.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5946_img_1576_1"/>
                41 Windsor Ave,  Fairview,    13/6/16   My Dear Ned,   I was very<lb/> glad to hear that you<lb/> continue well. The girls<lb/> were in Ballysax on<lb/> Sunday and I believe <lb/> everything is going on<lb/> well there. I was<lb/> speaking to a chap  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5946_img_1576_2"/>
              named Macken who has<lb/> lately returned from<lb/> your 'college'. He gave <lb/> me a good account<lb/> of all the Rules and<lb/> Regulations of your present<lb/> abode. I am expecting <lb/> to see you back here any<lb/> day but in case you<lb/> don't arrive before <lb/> next week I intend<lb/> going over to see you  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5946_img_1576_3"/>
              I will probably leave Dublin<lb/> Monday or Tuesday night 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> or 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Inst. In the meantime <lb/> if you want anything particularly<lb/> write home to Ballysax as I<lb/> will be there on Sunday (D.V.)<lb/> and I can bring whatever you<lb/> require. It is pleasant to know <lb/> that a good number of the<lb/> restrictions placed on you at first<lb/> have since been released. <seg type="del">Ben</seg><lb/> Eoghan O'Brien is in Stafford and<lb/> his brother Peadar is in Knutsford.<lb/> Their mother died last week (RIP)<lb/> and they never knew a word about<lb/> it. We are all well here. Lewis<lb/> is coming to himself again. Best<lb/> wishes hoping to see you soon <seg type="closer"> Yours  Gus </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>