<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0072">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Counterfoil addressed to William Pearse, April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is the counterfoil from a mobilisation order (which has also survived) sent by William Pearse (1881-1916) to Seán Thomas O&#39;Kelly (1882-1966) on 21 April 1916.William Pearse was a sculptor and brother of Patrick Pearse, one of the leaders of the Easter Rising. William held the rank of captain on the headquarters staff of the Dublin Brigade of the Irish Volunteers. O&#39;Kelly was a politician and later president of Ireland. In 1916 he was also a member of the Irish Volunteers and Irish Republican Brotherhood and served as aide-de-camp to Patrick Pearse during the Rising. The order was a personal order for O&#39;Kelly, signed by &#39;Acting Chief of Staff&#39; Willie Pearse, and was for the planned manoeuvres on Easter Sunday, 23 April. Unbeknownst to the rank and file, these manouevres were to be used as a cover for the beginning of the Easter Rising but were countermanded by Eoin MacNeill, chief of staff of the Irish Volunteers, when he became aware of the plans. The Rising then went ahead on 24 April with significantly reduced numbers. The counterfoil was to be signed and returned to William Pearse but never was.William Pearse was executed for his part in the Rising on 4 April. O&#39;Kelly was arrested and imprisoned until December 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Document, Seán T. O&#39;Kelly Collection, BMH CD/95/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/72</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0853">William Pearse</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0713">St. Enda's College, Rathfarnham, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0072_img_1141_1"  type="Letter"  url="3453fa49ec7a28791ccf2932f600dfef.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0072_img_1141_1"/>
                To:-  Capt. Wm. Pearse,  St. Enda's College,  Rathfarnham    Staff No  Address .............<lb/> ........................<lb/> ...........April, 1916  Sent at......m.  I acknowledge receipt of your order to report to you at <lb/> temporary Headquarters............<lb/> at the hour of......... m. on ......<lb/> next..... inst., and to hold myself in readiness to act on<lb/> the Staff of Commandant P. H. Pearse, during the Easter Manoeuvres.  (Signed)......<lb/> (Rank)........  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>