<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0866">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from S. A. Arthur to Sir Robert Chalmers, the Under-Secretary for Ireland, 13 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>S. A. Arthur</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from S. A. Arthur to the under secretary of Ireland referring to financial management of Miss Quin and Miss Flanagan who are residing in a lunatic asylum in Caen. Enclosed is a letter from the Foreign Office to the same effect.At the time this letter was written Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was serving as the Under-Secretary for Ireland. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as a replacement for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5618/12070/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/866</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0434">S. A. Arthur</persName>
              <date>1916-07-13T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0856">Home Office, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0866_img_2428_1"  type="Letter"  url="ba8f5aef3e22ab724e3e6aaef6dd3656.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0866_img_2428_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="448cff2f2f5d3a593ad87005b25eae3f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0866_img_2428_1"/>
                HOME OFFICE,  WHITEHALL.    13th July, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Secretary of State to send, <lb/>herewith, to be dealt with by the Irish Government, a letter <lb/>and enclosures which he has received from the Foreign Office <lb/>regarding the money owing for the keep of two ladies, Miss <lb/>Flanagan and Miss Quin, in a Lunatic Asylum at Caen. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  S.A. Arthur   The Under Secretary,  DUBLIN CASTLE  </seg> <seg type="unclear">I.G.</seg> For report as to <lb/>the relative of the two ladies. <seg type="unclear">PCuF</seg><lb/><hi rend="underline">24—VII—16</hi>  Under Secretary, <lb/>Reports regarding the two cases <lb/>are attached.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0866_img_2428_2"/>
              Reference to previous correspondence: —  Letter to <seg type="del">from</seg> Foreign Office:  The Under—Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents <lb/>his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for the <lb/>Home Department and is directed by the Secretary of <lb/>State for Foreign Affairs to transmit the accompanying copy of <lb/>two despatches which have been received from Hill <lb/> Consul General at Havre concerning <lb/>owing for the keep of Mrs Quin <lb/>and Mrs Flanagan now at <seg type="foreign">L'Aside d'Alienes <lb/>du Bondaureut de Caen.</seg>  The Secretary of State would be glad to be advised <lb/>what answer should be returned to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Churchill. <seg type="closer">  Foreign Office    26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June, 1916.  </seg> <seg type="del">(Similar letter sent to</seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>