<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0664">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mary M to James Ryan, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mary M</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Mary M. to James Ryan (1891-1970). She says that she&#39;s sorry he&#39;s being moved to Frongoch prison, but that her father is there and that he should look him up. She tells him about the exam results that have come out, and says that she heard he has had a chance to use his medical skills in prison.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>James Ryan Papers, P88/25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/664</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1140">Mary M</persName>
              <date>1916-07-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0090">Church Street, Tipperary</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0664_img_215_1"  type="Letter"  url="b98ed7803781af23752e6442c21d6865.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0664_img_215_2"  type="Letter"  url="af43c53403eaaacdc8183d0f8c2fb151.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0664_img_215_3"  type="Letter"  url="f8036ee219d2c92142fa82ddbb6df658.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0664_img_215_4"  type="Letter"  url="d66c9b84be5d2111d1c1c2784c191ba1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0664_img_215_5"  type="Letter"  url="b98ed7803781af23752e6442c21d6865.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0664_img_215_1"/>
                1/7/16    Church St  Tipperary   Dear Jim,   I have just got your P.C.<lb/> I am awfully sorry you are <lb/> going to Wales, because in that<lb/> case I'll never hear from <lb/> you again. You will be with <lb/> my Dad. You ought look <lb/> him up if possible. I do not <lb/> know how to describe him as <lb/> I am sure he has changed <lb/> altogether, with beard and<lb/> other hirsute attachments, but<lb/> his number is 306. Tell him <lb/> to let me know if you get <lb/> my letter, 'cos its no good writâ<lb/> ing if they don't get there.  Well the old exams are Next section is written sideways across top of page   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0664_img_215_2"/>
              over and luckily I passed.<lb/> Indeed Miss very unkindly <lb/> remarked that it was the<lb/> triumph of idleness. I believe <lb/> she saw you all âlooking very <lb/> pretty with lovely flowing <lb/><sic>moustachios</sic>, you must look <lb/> sweet. You no longer <lb/> resemble me in that case<lb/> âI don't mean in the latter <lb/> case.  I stayed in town for a week <lb/> after the results, and only<lb/> arrived home last night, and <lb/> of course this corner of the <lb/> world is about the dullest <lb/> part of it in which to be <lb/> at large. I think its terrible <lb/> for us to be bored, while we <lb/> have our freedom. We should <lb/> give it up altogether âbut I <lb/> am afraid it is not easy.   I was looking at the results <lb/> of the final and I am afraid <lb/> that the only one I remember  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0664_img_215_3"/>
              is Dolittle âthe name took <lb/> my fancy so completely, but <lb/> I don't think there were more <lb/> than 8 names up. A girl <lb/> got first place as usual. Wait <lb/> till you see me with the <lb/> Birmingham gold medal for <lb/> anatomy next year. I'll take <lb/> you all to dinner in Jammets <lb/> to celebrate the occasion. If <lb/> you prefer anywhere else you <lb/> can let me know before then<lb/> and I'll make sure that it <lb/> will be arranged as you wish.  I believe there is a terrible<lb/> crowd of you now in Frongoch. <lb/> If you heard all the attempts <lb/> to pronounce that name! I spent <lb/> about 10 minutes getting lessons<lb/> in it from Father Paul, and <lb/> in the end I had to think very<lb/> hard even before second venture <lb/> on saying it. Mary <seg type="unclear">Mouyey</seg><lb/> had a letter from Desmond  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0664_img_215_4"/>
              Ryan the other day. Of course <lb/> I read it although I had never <lb/> seen the youth in question. He <lb/> sent a great collection of extracts <lb/> from 'Barrack room Ballads' <lb/> so to speak. I hope you will <lb/> be all out next year. I am <lb/> dying to see all the people whose<lb/> names I know so well now. <lb/> I was going to ask you a list<lb/> of questions but of course it <lb/> is no use as they are destined <lb/> to remain unanswered, even <lb/> before they are formulated.  I believe there are occasional <lb/> calls on your medical skill,<lb/> and I heard you also had <lb/> athletic possibilities. I always <lb/> thought you were too good a stud<lb/> ent to do anything but culti<lb/> vate your mind. I have the<lb/><sic>refree</sic> whistle I took from you <lb/> at your dance yet. I must get  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0664_img_215_5"/>
              it mounted and<lb/> enshrined when<lb/> I refind it.<lb/> I'll write<lb/> again some<lb/> time soon. Love to all the<lb/> people I know<lb/> and even to those<lb/> I don't know<lb/>. I don't mind<lb/> 'picking up you'<lb/> people. Its not<lb/> like the ordinary<lb/> thing. <seg type="closer"> Love from   Mary M </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>