<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1461">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mabel FitzGerald to John Redmond, 27 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mabel FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947, to John Redmond (1856-1918), leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party from 1900 to 1918. In this, and in other letters, Mrs. FitzGerald is seeking help in relation to her husband&#39;s incarceration and insists that her husband was non-combatant. She asks that, in the event of an amnesty for people who received comparatively short sentences, the severity and injustice of her husband&#39;s sentence be taken into account, particularly as she feels he is being punished for previous transgressions, for which he has already paid. Mabel Fitzgerald was the wife of Irish Volunteer Desmond Fitzgerald. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week. John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Desmond FitzGerald Papers, P80/1589/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1461</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1757">2 Loretto Villa, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0077">House of Commons, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1461_img_911_1"  type="Letter"  url="8ed083e8fa08a210143592d4eb2d472c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1461_img_911_1"/>
                2 Loretto Villas,  Bray,    27 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916    Dear Sir,   I must thank you for your reply, per Mr.J.J. Hanna, <lb/> to my letter of 23 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> inst., re my husband's case. My husband, <lb/> Mr Desmond Fitzgerald, was a non-combatant and was sentenced to <lb/> 20 years penal servitude, ten of which were remitted.   I quite realise that it is not a case of getting release <lb/> but amnesty ; I do not desire that Mr Fitzgerald's case should be <lb/> pressed with a view to release, but I hope that a remittance of <lb/> the sentenced <sic>amy</sic> be obtained so that if the Amnesty be a graded <lb/> one only freeing those persons whose sentences are comparatively <lb/> short, he may be able to profit by it as he would have been able <lb/> to, had his sentence been in accordance with the evidence.   His case is a peculiar one, and I do not think I am asking <lb/> for special favour to be shown him when I suggest that a portion <lb/> of his sentence ought to be remitted till it <seg type="del">u</seg>is one based on the <lb/> evidence against him and not on extraneous matters use  d  to prejudice <lb/> his case, matters for which he has already paid the penalty in <lb/>deportation <sic>and imprisonment.</sic>  Cases of such obvious injustice would, I think, do a <lb/> great deal if exposed, to strengthen the demand for Amnesty.   I am glad to know that I can rely on your doing every- <lb/>thing in your power for my husband when you feel <sic>theproper</sic> time <lb/> has come to obtain a reconsideration of sentences.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Yours faithfully   Mabel W Fitzgerald   John Redmond, Esq, M.P.  House of Commons,  London.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>