<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5454">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Fitzgerald to Michael Gorman, 12 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Michael Gorman was one a large Catholic family living at a farm in Ballinalug, County Laois (then Queen’s County). Susan Fitzgerald (d. 1980) was one a Church of Ireland family living in Raheenahone House near Stradbally, County Laois, also in the Slieve Bloom mountains. At the time the letter was written they were involved in a courtship but owing to the religious difference the love affair had to be kept secret. Eventually both were in Dublin: he in the Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin (where he eventually became Professor of Agricultural Botany and Biochemistry and she as a volunteer nurse in the Royal Hospital in Baggot Street. They eventually went to London to marry.
In the letter, Susan refers to time spent with a mutual friend and her new uniform for the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.), a voluntary organisation providing nursing to wounded British army soldiers, which she had just joined. She also mentions that she would like to meet in Maryborough (now Portlaoise) and tells Michael not to feel too down about the recent death of his mother after a long illness.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Michael Gorman</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5454</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1259">Susan Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-01-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1800">Raheenahone House, Stradbally, County Laois</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Michael Gorman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1251">Albert Agricultural College, Glasnevin, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1980</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5454_img_486_1"  type="NULL"  url="a17f9524e67468c9486c3d8ec3c4e8ef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5454_img_486_2"  type="NULL"  url="5eea8618b9e3a1c285e8f43aaac55400.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5454_img_486_3"  type="NULL"  url="67f75723024e760e92ce257a1c5c7568.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5454_img_486_4"  type="NULL"  url="04d928f3c166c1dea3198286c27e7c3f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5454_img_486_1"/>
             RAHEENAHONE HOUSE<lb/>STRADBALLY<lb/>QUEENS CO.   <hi rend="underline">January 12.</hi>    My dear Mickie   I was very glad<lb/>to hear from you and<lb/>I meant to reply <seg type="unclear">on<seg type="unclear"><lb/>yesterday. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Auley<lb/>came over and spent<lb/>the evening with us.<lb/>he was in great form</seg></seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5454_img_486_2"/>
             &amp; seems to be having<lb/>a very good time. He<lb/>was to go to Grange Con<lb/>today &amp; he told us that<lb/>Kearns was to come There<lb/>tomorrow. I'm sorry you<lb/>weren't here, as mother<lb/>was away for the day &amp;<lb/>night &amp; of course Molly<lb/>&amp; I were here alone.<lb/>I only got a card from<lb/>Mac that morning, saying<lb/>he intended calling in  <lb/>the afternoon. We had<lb/>Austin McKenna here this<lb/>afternoon. He has a very<lb/>nice new motor. He told<lb/>me he knew you, he also<lb/>knows   Eva Kavanagh<lb/>I've got my dresses,<lb/>caps, aprons &amp; mother<lb/>&amp; Molly think I look<lb/>very young in the<lb/>uniform, but I rather like<lb/>that I hope I'll be<lb/>called to Hospital soon.<lb/>I may be included in<lb/>the February classes, if  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5454_img_486_3"/>
             not I'll go up to town for a<lb/>week-end or so. When are you<lb/>coming down to the Queen's Co again<lb/>will you come over? I love<lb/>to meet you at Maryboro<lb/>if the weather was anyway<lb/>decent I expect to go down<lb/>to Roscommon soon for a<lb/>short time. I can't write<lb/>with this pen, so I'll say<lb/>goodbye &amp; <hi rend="underline">don't</hi> be downhearted<lb/>over your mother. It is far<lb/>better for her to be gone &amp;<lb/>to be relieved from such<lb/>suffering.  With love<lb/>Ever Yrs/salute<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Sue.</hi>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5454_img_486_4"/>
             M. J. Gorman Esq., <lb/>Albert College, <lb/>Glasnevin <lb/><hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>