<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0505">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegram from Power, Irish Office, London, to the Under Secretary, 4 May, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Power</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Power in the Irish Office, London to the under secretary for Ireland, Sir Robert Chalmers. Power relayed a question in Parliament put forward by William Doris inquiring whether there were plans to reduce the number of Irish prisoners, and if so, which prisons were to close.Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was the under-secretary for Ireland. Chalmers became under-secretary for a brief period following the resignation of Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) following the 1916 Rising. Doris (1860-1926), was an Irish Member of Parliament, belonging to the Irish Parliamentary Party) representing West Mayo.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13335</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/505</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1157">Power</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1483">Irish Office, Old Queen St., London SW, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0505_img_1875_1"  type="Letter"  url="2004dc771280f5ef197263012cb7d460.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0505_img_1875_1"/>
              Service Instructions: Alt OHms  Handed in at: Irish Office London at 10.24a.m. Received here at:10.34a.m.  To: Undersecretary Dublin  Question for today May 4th<lb/> no 3 mr Doris to <lb/> ask the Chief <sic>secy</sic> whether<lb/> a further reduction in the<lb/> number or status of Irish<lb/> prisons is Contemplated and if<lb/> so whether he can state<lb/> what prisons are to be <lb/> closed or reduced. <seg type="closer"> Power </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>