<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2732">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his father, Harford Hugh Montgomery, 13 December, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>William Montgomery Papers, D27941/1/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2732</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1915-12-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0348">Monacherra, Malone Road, Belfasr, Northern Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_1"  type="Letter"  url="9df4e03493ef50f85203f62908f515dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_2"  type="Letter"  url="03f1c16efcfd8b43d026cfb1b4bc64bb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_3"  type="Letter"  url="dc1fde857f8c82b0ff15c0436f8b1d38.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_4"  type="Letter"  url="00c0b405f14b23686f75313b40d424c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_5"  type="Letter"  url="c66f170b83665e974bf59422ea2efaa4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_6"  type="Letter"  url="7167f04c162f8b995eabe7ff95e783e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_7"  type="Letter"  url="469f7062cee1d5246060dc1cff0066d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_8"  type="Letter"  url="673799e0b355b682ef6e9b5905fbcdf8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_9"  type="Letter"  url="103ad4c4de56bd0bf6548bc18860c885.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_10"  type="Letter"  url="b85e4acfd9c7c4693ed42e0fca6c8e23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2732_img_2152_11"  type="Envelope"  url="e98a7a713d75c6a3eda69aa2f3240ba7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_1"/>
             In the Field   13.12.15   My Dear Father   I have yours<lb/> of 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> with enclosures<lb/> for which I thank you.<lb/> The second revolver holster<lb/> was for Maynard Sinclair<lb/> who will probably pay me<lb/> for it sometime when we<lb/> have a square up. I wont<lb/> bother about Acetylene<lb/> Lamps just at present<lb/> thanks. Carbide is the<lb/> difficulty &amp; we are now<lb/> being issuedwith paraffin<lb/> for lamps. We have got quite<lb/> good cheap oil lamps, which<lb/> we carry about with us.   I havent spent your £1 yet
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_2"/>
            as we got quite a lot of<lb/> candles both from Belfast<lb/> &amp; from Govt. issue. The<lb/> fuel question is also adjusting itself. I got<lb/> your very welcome parcel<lb/> yesterday, containing<lb/> 3 paper holders  with  <seg type="del">at</seg> which<lb/> my Coy. Sergt. Major &amp;<lb/> Coy. Q. Master Sergt were<lb/> delighted. They will come<lb/> in most useful. I am<lb/> I am writing this with the<lb/> fountain pen which is<lb/> a much appreciated Godsend.  The handkerchiefs were<lb/> also most useful. I hunted<lb/> the whole parcel for a<lb/> note from you but came<lb/> to the conclusion that
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_3"/>
            that you must have forgotten to put it<lb/> in. I am in splendid health &amp;<lb/> spirits. In fact I think I have put on <lb/> a little weight. We also appreciate<lb/> the <seg type="del">galore</seg> copies of Punch which arrive<lb/> quite safely. I hope you read the<lb/> "At the Front" articles. They are<lb/> undoubtedly written by someone who<lb/> has been through it. They are quite <lb/> true as regards atmosphere and<lb/> detail. We scream over them. It<lb/> is the first thing we turn to. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_4"/>
             Courtney Shillington had a <lb/> lucky escape. Men &amp; Officers<lb/> have been lost since he was,<lb/> going to the same place on<lb/> patrol duty. <seg type="unclear">Gaffihin's</seg><lb/> Coy lost 3 men there<lb/> last time we were uo &amp;<lb/> the 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> lost Stanley Hunter<lb/> there &amp; all the patrol<lb/> except one Corporal, who<lb/> crawled back wounded.   The Germans put the<lb/> notice about Courtney<lb/> Shillington's safety (nicely<lb/> framed) in a place<lb/> "tween lines" known as<lb/> the "Near Willows" at the<lb/> very certain risk of their<lb/> lives. The notice was found<lb/> attached to a willow tree
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_5"/>
            not more than 20 yards<lb/> from our WIRE.   Plucky of them <sic>wasnt</sic> it?<lb/> This is the first fine day<lb/> we have had for weeks.<lb/> You <sic>dont</sic> quite realise what<lb/> that means to us. It means<lb/> that by working men until<lb/> they collapse, are <seg type="unclear">tinkered</seg><lb/> up again, &amp; worked more<lb/> that we <hi rend="underline">may</hi> get a little<lb/> ahead of the mud &amp; water<lb/> in the trenches &amp; make<lb/> <seg type="del">g</seg> dugouts a little more<lb/> weatherproof &amp; then when<lb/> you ahve done quite well<lb/> at it, you get shelled<lb/> the whole contraption<lb/> smashed up &amp; start again.   I have had more
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_6"/>
            trouble with drink. I had<lb/> another sergeant broken<lb/> by Field General Court<lb/> Martial and a Rifleman<lb/> sentenced to a lengthy<lb/> spell of Field Punishment<lb/> N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> !. This is not a<lb/> pleasant punishment.<lb/> Part of it is tying up<lb/> by the hands above the<lb/> head as high as they will<lb/> go (without injury to health)<lb/> for an hour in the morning<lb/> and another hour in the<lb/> evening, feet tied as well.   While men are in the<lb/> trenches punishment<lb/> is suspended but begins<lb/> again as soon as we<lb/> come out again. I have
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_7"/>
            to see the men tied up. I have 12 at<lb/> present all for moderately trivial<lb/> offences. They <sic>dont</sic> look pretty on a<lb/> cold morning after they have had<lb/> about 3/4 hour. Incorrigibles<lb/> can be helped towards better ways by<lb/> placing their feet on a brick, tie up<lb/> hands as high as they will go &amp;<lb/> then remove he brick for ten<lb/> minutes or so. One of mine was<lb/> quite cured this way. I can see<lb/> a German Aeroplane being shelled
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_8"/>
            from where I am sitting<lb/> writing this. They are<lb/> hard to hit. I <sic>havent</sic> seen<lb/> one brought down yet.<lb/> I have seen them staggered<lb/> but they always got back<lb/> safely.   Over the drink troubles<lb/> I have taken the drastic<lb/> step of not paying the<lb/> Company. I warned them<lb/> first of course. Then the<seg type="del">y</seg><lb/> two cases occurred &amp; when next<lb/> pay day came neither<lb/> William nor the money<lb/> was there. I understand<lb/> they were stunned with<lb/> horror. They are now<lb/> blacklisting all the<lb/> doubtful boys with a
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_9"/>
            view to taking care of them<lb/> when within a mile of <lb/> drink. They have sent several<lb/> deputations to me with all<lb/> sorts of pathetic tales of<lb/> children at home being<lb/> disappointed at not receiving<lb/> Xmas presents etc. etc. etc.<lb/> But a Coy. Cmdr. in the field<lb/> would not keep his job long<lb/> if he weakened on tales like<lb/> that. They have done some<lb/> good work lately &amp; so next <lb/> time we come out, I shall<lb/> parade the Coy. &amp; rewarn<lb/> them &amp; pay them.   It is requested that none<lb/> of all this 'be communicated<lb/> to either press or public'.   By the way I wonder
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_10"/>
            could you find me two<lb/> Aluminium cases for my<lb/> razors. They are so rusty<lb/> now that they are getting<lb/> positively dangerous to use   Horace is in great form<lb/> He <hi rend="underline">is</hi> father.   I must close now as<lb/> we move again this<lb/> afternoon.   Your affect son   <hi rend="underline">W. Montgomery</hi> 
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_2732_img_2152_11"/>
             Harford H Montgomery<lb/> <seg type="unclear">Monacherra</seg><lb/> Malone Park<lb/> Belfast.   <seg type="unclear">JM Sinclair</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>