<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6397">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Victoria Mary Tyrrell 9, October, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his sister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6397</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-10-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6397_img_None_1"  url="1489a6c56e03a896c26196cef93c46e3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6397_img_None_2"  url="45f5494657412e94a622654041e00602.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6397_img_0_1"/>
              9 October 17    My dear Minnie   I was delighted to get your long<lb/>letters last night. I am glad that<lb/>some of the photographs were good<lb/>anyway.  I am not surprised to hear that<lb/>they had lost trace of Hunter otherwise<lb/>he would have heard before.  I think you may send me out<lb/>another suit if heavy flannels<lb/>as the weather might get cool any<lb/>time now. Of course there is not<lb/>the least hurry.  It rains quite a lot at night now<lb/>but is usually very fine during<lb/>the day.  I am glad Daddy got a couple of<lb/>pheasants.  Yesterday we sent our man who<lb/>buys stuff for us and told him 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6397_img_0_2"/>
             to get some fish sole is possible<lb/>and two dozen eggs - He came<lb/>back in a great way and said they<lb/>had not got 2 dozen sole but<lb/>he could only get six and would<lb/>that be any use. He evidently<lb/>thought we wanted 2 dozen sole<lb/>too. Not bad for 4 people ! He<lb/>evidently does not realise cubic<lb/>capacity.  No news. Everything is very<lb/>very quiet.   With very best love to all<lb/>from<lb/>Your most affec brother<lb/>Willie   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>