<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1185">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr John Fitzgibbon to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 14 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Fitzgibbon </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Fitzgibbon (1882-1918) to the father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Fitzgibbon&#39;s week at the front. Fr John &#39;Jack&#39; Fitzgibbon SJ was ordained a priest on 31st July 1915. His father, John Fitzgibbon, was a successful draper and Member of Parliament from 1910-1918. Fr Fitzgibbon served in the 6th Division of the British Army, having enlisted shortly after the death of his brother at Gallipoli. He was promoted to senior chaplain in 1917, and in the same year he was gassed at Loos on 5th September and awarded the military cross. Fr Fitzgibbon was killed in action by a shell on the 18th September 1918, and is buried at Trefcon, St. Quentin, Picardie.Father Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/4-5, IJA/CHPI/21/4-5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1185</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0333">John Fitzgibbon </persName>
              <date>1916-03-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1193">Paris, France </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1185_img_3864_1"  type="Letter"  url="9cc4992d935bb33e85bd531244733ce5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1185_img_3864_2"  type="Letter"  url="1ede70fde2750c74f58126d25d93e000.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1185_img_3864_1"/>
                23rd Field Ambulance,  B.E.F. France.   My dear Fr Nolan -   I have completed a full week <lb/>at the <hi rend="underline">Front</hi> and although I was twice daily on my <lb/>horse, I have not been able to get to see the R.C's <lb/>in my inspection of the Division. They are scattered in all <lb/>directions in and out of the trenches + some of them <lb/>miles apart. However I was able to hear quite <lb/>a number of confessions on last Thursday, Friday and <lb/>Saturday - under the most extraordinary circumstances <lb/>&amp; in all kinds of places.  My first day in the trenches was decidedly <lb/>interesting but not by any means what one would <lb/>call comfortable, as a certain amount of <lb/>shelling was going on, though none dropped <lb/>nearer to me than about 100 yards away.  One day I was going up when I met two <lb/>poor fellows coming down on stretchers both <lb/>badly wounded; but before we reached the <lb/>'dug outs' one of them - the catholic - had died, as <lb/>I had to go back + get him buried.  The burial service was quite reverential <lb/>ceremonious though many could not <lb/>attend it, because a crowd would invite <lb/>shelling. The poor fellow was buried within <lb/>an hour after he died, and a nice <lb/>cross was being prepared for him as I left <lb/>that evening.  The two places where I had 'service' - 12 Mass <lb/>Sermon, Confessions &amp; Communion - were about <lb/>seven miles apart. In one place I heard Confession <lb/>the day before; while on Sunday I heard them <lb/>in the more distant places, then having preached <lb/>for about 10 minutes on Confession, I got quite a <lb/>number to Confession after Mass, comprising <lb/>mostly men who had accidentally heard of my <lb/>Mass; as it was impossible to get round or even <lb/>to discover where all the different sections are <lb/>burrowed. For instance my labours lie with <lb/><hi rend="underline">four</hi> full regiments, not to mention Flying Corps men <lb/>R.F.A. men of which, there are 200 R.C.'s alone. - Grenade <lb/>comp. Scout + mining comps. R.H.A. Comps. <lb/>R.A.M.C. Corps. - Supply Columns - several odds and ends. <lb/>All of these are spread out over a large area + I have <lb/>been told that if I see <hi rend="underline">all</hi> every <hi rend="underline">two</hi> months  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1185_img_3864_2"/>
              should feel quite happy.  Where I had to say Mass on Sunday had been <lb/>shelled before I arrived &amp; a portion of the roof was <lb/>shattered; but as I could not send word to all <lb/>concerned we held our service &amp; in perfect peace.  A few days ago after returning from the trenches <lb/>I called into a barn where there was another officer <lb/>whom I knew, in order to secure a cup of tea, - <lb/>a little refresher after six hours in the trenches - we <lb/>were about to feel comfortable when a shell <lb/>burst in the garden outside, just fifteen yards <lb/>away. It appear the Germans were finding the <lb/>range of the road but to no effect. Although <lb/>mighty nervous I did not move, but enjoyed my <lb/>tea as best I could &amp; cleared out a few minutes <lb/>later.  As far as men &amp; officers are concerned they could <lb/>not be nicer to me, and most obliging, although <lb/>there are only two Catholic officers, as far as I can <lb/>find out, in all the different sections. But the <lb/>number of different 'Padres' in comparison to <lb/>Priests is simply prodigious, they are to be found <lb/>everywhere &amp; overlapping one another. There are <lb/>two in my Mess &amp; they have about one tenth of the <lb/>number of men to look after.  I must now close, as I am rather tired &amp; I <lb/>want to be up early to try &amp; manage a 'Service' <lb/>of some kind for St Patrick's Day: but I fear it is <lb/>hopeless &amp; I don't want to get on the officers nerves.  In conclusion I may say that I am quite <lb/>happy &amp; in the very best of health. <seg type="closer"> With very best wishes etc. to fathers Brown &amp; Darby <lb/>I remain <lb/>Your obedient child in Xt,  J. FitzGibbon S.J. </seg>  14/3/16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>