<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1318">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cecil Stafford to Sir Henry Grattan Bellew, 17 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cecil Stafford</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Cecil Stafford, Department of Recruiting for Ireland, to Sir Henry Grattan Bellew (1860-1942) about Frederick Kerr, a nephew of Father Flanagan, the parish priest in Stafford&#39;s parish. Kerr is anxious to obtain a commission as an officer in the 4th Connaught Rangers as his parents will not allow him to join the ordinary ranks. Stafford requests that Sir Henry might facilitate the request.Sir Henry Christopher Grattan Bellew was the third baronet of Mount Bellew in County Galway. He held the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel, 4th Battalion Connaught Rangers. His son, sir Charles Christopher (1887-1948) held the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel, King&#39;s Royal Rifle Corps. He was decorated with the award of the Military Cross (M.C.) in 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bellew of Mount Bellew Papers, Collection List No. 33, Ms. 27,290</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1318</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1355">Cecil Stafford</persName>
              <date>1916-01-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0967">Department of Recruiting for Ireland, 32 Nassau Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Henry Grattan Bellew</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1318_img_612_1"  type="Letter"  url="b8ca63745216c4179c70fa0a104396d6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1318_img_612_1"/>
                THE DEPARTMENT OF RECRUITING FOR IRELAND,  32, Nassau Street,  DUBLIN    17th. January, 1916.    Dear Sir Henry,   A man named Fredrick Kerr came to see me <lb/> on Friday last. He is a nephew of Father Flanagan <lb/> our local Parish Priest, and is a son of the agent to <lb/> Captain Pakenham-Mahon of Strokestown.  He is very anxious to obtain a Commission in <lb/> the 4th. Connaught Rangers, but unfortunately he has had <lb/>no previous military experience. My selection board <lb/> cannot, therefore, do anything for him. He seems <lb/> quite a nice man but his parents will not allow him to <lb/> join the ranks.  I wonder if you could possible do anything <lb/> for him. I am sorry to bother you about the matter, <lb/> but I promised his uncle to do anything I could for him. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely,   <hi rend="underline">Cecil Stafford</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>