<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1174">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 30 October 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s request about sending money for buying caskets for the Chaldraw Priests. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/34-35, IJA/CHPI/54/34-35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1174</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-10-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1174_img_3851_1"  type="Letter"  url="af6be0580dbc1fa3400dc6a2a648601e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1174_img_3851_2"  type="Letter"  url="d78caa3735bf415cbfecf39692a41dea.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1174_img_3851_1"/>
                Mesopotamia    30 Oct. 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   I said 20 Masses for <lb/>Fr Farley during October.  .Everything is still going well. The weather is <lb/>quite pleasant. We had rain a few days ago, but <lb/>the regular rains again next month. Things are <lb/>made brighter, too, by the attitude of Austria, <lb/>who, it seems, wants immediate peace at <lb/>any price. The Turk walas also are not <lb/>in a very favourable position for keeping on. <lb/>Let us hope that it will be Right that will <lb/>win after all. (Emphasis on the first 'will')  I told you how D<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Dillon-Kelly had been <lb/>posted to my hospital, and was shifted to my sorrow <lb/>a day or two afterwards. He had hardly gone <lb/>when his brother Cecil took his place. Cecil <lb/>is still with us.  I hope your Reverence will approve of my <lb/>having given Â£10 to buy cassocks for a <lb/>number of Chaldean Priests who are among the <lb/>refugees from the north. They are now clothed <lb/>and supplied with Mass outfits. The protestant <lb/>plague is at work I believe out here. Not <lb/>to make Protestants (the people aren't such fools)  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1174_img_3851_2"/>
              but to hinder re-union of schismatics with <lb/>Rome. I have been told that one of the men <lb/>working in the refugee-camp as an <lb/>Intelligence Officer, was or is secretary, to <lb/>the pseudo-archbishop of Canterbury's foreign <lb/>mission fake. The Syrian Archbishop <lb/>who lives in Baghdad says most of these <lb/>schismatics are really Catholics but owing to <lb/>fitting their own definitions to terms which <lb/>we define differently they seem to be heretics. <lb/>At present the call themselves Gregorian Christians. <lb/>They are Armenians mostly. The Chaldeans are <lb/>Catholics.  In case the wily U-boat has interfered, <lb/>I respect my request for a 1919 Ordo, and <lb/>a new Catalogue. The list of changes reached <lb/>me all night. I was surprised to see that <lb/>F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Albert Power had gone to Australia.  The time passes wonderfully quickly here. <lb/>Sundays seem to come about twice a week, <lb/>and each month to drop seven or eight <lb/>days, so that the Ordo notice '<seg type="foreign">hoc anno <lb/>hebdomada</seg> so-and-so <seg type="foreign">omittitur</seg>' has more <lb/>meanings than would appear on the surface.  I recommend myself to your Reverence's Masses <lb/>and prayers, and to the prayers of all. <seg type="closer"> Yours in Christ,  Francis M Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>