<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0952">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Caddell to the Urban District Council, 1 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Caddell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Henry Caddell, a clerk at Dublin Castle, to the Longford Urban District Council concerning a surplus of money generated from the sale of licenses under the Dog Regulation (Ireland) Act 1865 in Longford for the year 1915.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Longford County Archives Service</repository>
                  <collection>LUDC-1-3-1916-6-6, LUDC-1-3-1916-6-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/952</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0963">Henry Caddell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Nicholas Lamb</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0870">Urban District Council, Longford</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0952_img_2767_1"  type="Letter"  url="10651ffcb5c6924d18d930c6592c5c7b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0952_img_2767_1"/>
                Registrar of Petty Sessions  Clerk's Office  Dublin Castle.    1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi><hi rend="underline">June</hi> 1916   Sir  —   I beg to acquaint you for the information <lb/>of the Urban District Council, that the proposition of <lb/>surplus monies arising from the sale of licences <lb/>under the 'Dogs regulation (Ireland) Act 1865 <lb/>amounts to £10.19.10 for the Urban District of <lb/>Longford for the year 1915 and to state that the <lb/>Lord Lieutenant has directed that this sum <lb/>should be paid over to the Treasurer to the <lb/>Urban District Council <sic>purssuant</sic> to the <lb/>'Dog regulation (Ireland) Act 1865 to be <lb/>applied by him in aid of the Urban District rates <lb/>in such manner as the Council shall direct. <seg type="closer"> I am Sir <lb/>your <sic>obd servt</sic>  H Caddell   The Clerk  Urban D<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> Council  Longford.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>