<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2184">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Brown to Robert Dunlop, 8 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Brown</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Robert Brown, assistant manager at the National Marginal Company in Leith, Scotland, to Robert Dunlop (b. 1869), district inspector for Commissioner of the R.I.C.
Before the war middle class,a  British household tended to put butter on the table, and reserve margarine for cooking purposes. But because the rations for margarine were more generous than for butter, margarine worked its way out of the kitchen and into the dining room. there was a national butter and two types of national margarine.
In the letter Brown is requesting that Dunlop repays him for the expenses he paid to attend an assizes in Belfast.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/1205/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2184</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1431">Robert Brown</persName>
              <date>1916-01-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2044">10 Quality STreet, Leith, Edinburgh</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0211">Robert Dunlop</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1916">Commissioners Office, Royal Irish Constabulary, Belfast</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2184_img_1630_1"  type="Letter"  url="ed635f89ad3877c6d4c5fdd4eb37260e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2184_img_1630_1"/>
             8th Jan 1916   Robert Dunlop Esquire, <lb/>D.I. for Commissioner, <lb/>R.I.C. <lb/>BELFAST.   Dear Sir,   I beg to refer you to my letter of 27th.inst containing <lb/>particulars of my expenses for attending <seg type="del">for</seg> <sic>the assixes</sic> as from <lb/>1st.inst as required by the writ served on me in connection with <lb/>McCambley, receipt of which you have not yet acknowledged.   I shall esteem it a great favour if you will kindly remit <lb/>the sum as soon as possible.   Yours truly,   Rob Brown  <lb/>Assistant Manager
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>