<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0522">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from a soldier in the British Army (J.B.) to Miss. Lyden, 27 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter written on the Thursday of Easter Week from a soldier in Protobello Barracks to a Miss Lyden. In his letter J.B. writes that there are four regiments battalions of the Notts &amp;amp; Derby regiments, in addition to two Sherwood Forrestor battalions. He writes about Sheehy-Skeffington and notes that Alderman Kelly is also being detained. According to the letter soldiers have been confined to barracks and are now on war rations.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Museum of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>HE, EW.1142</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/522</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1217">J.B.</persName>
              <date>1916-04-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0190">Portobello Barracks, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Miss Lyden</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0198">104 Marlborough Rd., Donnybrook, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0522_img_1894_1"  type="Letter"  url="051d836a68b9c8e990387758d3488a0c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0522_img_1894_2"  type="Letter"  url="c8121098735952dda8f8cc2585ed392d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0522_img_1894_3"  type="Letter"  url="d11408ca7bf9b688d2e83dbe43429914.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0522_img_1894_4"  type="Letter"  url="6d15c9031d029564c12031c2670d2df6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0522_img_1894_1"/>
              Found in <lb/> Brooks Thomas Co <lb/> a few days after <lb/> Rebellion by <lb/> GT    Portobello Barracks  Dublin.    Thursday morning   My dear Miss Lyden,   Just a few lines to <lb/> let you know I am going on <lb/> OK. We are kept very busy <lb/> here at present. Do you know <lb/> it all seems like a bad <lb/> nightmare. <seg type="del">I am</seg> Try and <lb/> let me know how things are <lb/> going on up there. Have the <lb/> people gone home yet. I <lb/> tried to get on the phone to <lb/> Kellep. but it is only open <lb/> for military purposes. We <lb/> have 4 Battalions of the Notts <lb/> and Derby Regiment and <lb/> two of the Sherwood Foresters  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0522_img_1894_2"/>
              One of the Sherwood Foresters and <lb/> one of the Veterans Corps were <lb/> brought in here dead, during <lb/> the night. I will never forget <lb/> the shooting of Sheehy Skeffington, <lb/> the Editor of the 'Eye-opener' <lb/> (He wont open his eyes again) <lb/> Also the Editor of the 'Toiler' <lb/> We have Alderman Kelly a <lb/> prisoner here also.    I believe the city is <lb/> in a horrible state. I had <lb/> a decent sleep last night I <lb/> managed to get a bed. that <lb/> was the first time I got one <lb/> and the first time I had my <lb/> clothes off since Sunday <lb/> Have you been able to get  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0522_img_1894_3"/>
              into town at all, and what about 'Peg o' my heart' <lb/> also Lal, You can take a kiss from me. also <lb/> give them one. If the post is going again and <lb/> if my people are gone home, would you please drop <lb/> them a line letting them know I am all right. <lb/> Dear knows when I will be able to see you again <lb/> as we expect to be confined to Barracks for <lb/> weeks. It is jolly awkward for me here as I <lb/> have nothing except what I stood in no razor <lb/> brushes or anything. We are on War Rations <lb/> Bully Beef and Biscuits so it is proper active  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0522_img_1894_4"/>
              Service. Early this morning the <lb/> machine guns were cracking for <lb/> all they were worth. I hear <lb/> Liberty Hall is blown up.    How about Sister Mae, Mrs Mac, <lb/> Mr and Mrs Bolton. I am anxious <lb/> to know how they all are.   I must now close for the <lb/> present. hoping to hear from <lb/> you soon,  <seg type="closer"> I am<lb/> Yours as ever  J. B. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>