<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5645">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Resident Medical Superintendent to James Smith. 4 February 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Resident Medical Superintendent </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The Resident Medical Superintendent asking James Smith Esq. to acknowledge receipt of Mary O&#39;Leary&#39;s letter which is attached. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_3755_3_3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5645</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0317">Resident Medical Superintendent </persName>
              <date>1916-02-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2114">District Asylum, Killarney, Co.Kerry</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Smith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1280">Office of Lunatic Asylum, Dublin Castle, Dublin </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5645_img_737_1"  type="Letter"  url="71560a60a716d30b2a45ddddb3408269.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5645_img_737_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="d2c7df405c383888014dd5bbc74834ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5645_img_737_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="ba721f6e6aa04ffd5270a9b16fe794ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5645_img_737_1"/>
             256   District Asylum, <lb/>Killarney   4 February, 1916   Sir,   I beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.252, <lb/> dated yesterday, enclosing copy of a letter from Miss <lb/> Mary O'Leary to the Inspectors referring to the appoint- <lb/> ment of Dressmaker and Nurse. The matter will be duly <lb/> submitted to the Committee of Management at their next <lb/>meeting on the 24th inst.   I am, Sir, <lb/>your obedient servant   S.W. Duffin  <lb/>Resident Medical Superintendent  James Smith Esq. <lb/>Office of Lunatic Asylums, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5645_img_737_2"/>
             Seartaglin, <lb/>Farranfore, <lb/>Kerry   1/2,/'16   Sir,   May I most respectfully <lb/>call your attention to the appointment <lb/>of "Dressmaker and Nurse " which <lb/>has been carried through at the last <lb/>meeting of "Committee of Management" <lb/>"Killarney District Lunatic Asylum."   The meeting was held on the 27th Inst <lb/>and out of the applicants one was <lb/>only qualified as regards age; Miss <lb/>Cremmin was therefore duly elected <lb/>as seamstress for a month pending <lb/>observations from Matron and R.M.S.   Miss Cremmin had only <lb/>one testimonial accompanying her
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5645_img_737_3"/>
            application, and that one was <lb/> from a local dressmaker certifying <lb/> that Miss Cremmin gave a few <lb/> month's apprenticeship — she produced <lb/> no more credentials — May I point <lb/> out, Sir, that the Advertisement <lb/> issued for this important position <lb/> was — " that the lady elected should <lb/> be able to cut material, sew, for the <lb/> female part of the House, possess a <lb/> knowledge of Nursing &amp; Housewifery <lb/> and to be responsible for same <lb/> when the Matron is absent."   Miss Cremmin, Sir, does not <lb/> show or present any qualifications <lb/> whatsoever (she was in third class <lb/> leaving School, her mother died some <lb/> time ago in the Asylum, at present <lb/> her aunt and cousin are there) and <lb/> many of the members of the Committee <lb/> visibly expressed the opinion that <lb/> Miss Cremmin was literally unqualified <lb/> for the position, and yet she was <lb/> dumped into a job that honestly <lb/> she knows nothing about.   The facts are really valid and I <lb/> was one of the applicants, fully qualified <lb/> but being a fortnight short of the age.   Trusting to hear from you soon   Signed - Mary O'Leary 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>