<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1208">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick F. Quinlan to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 12 October 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>P.F. Quinlan </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from P.F. Quinlan to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan (1867- 1941) regarding a letter that Quinlan received from the War Office about Fr. Fitzgibbon and financial issues. Fr. Thomas Nolan became the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus from 1912 to 1922. Besides that, he was a Distribution Committee member responsible for the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who had found refuge in Ireland on account of the World War I.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/33, IJA/CHPI/21/33</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1208</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0614">P.F. Quinlan </persName>
              <date>1918-10-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1208_img_3891_1"  type="Letter"  url="68ef4271f3c646d314644fc2cefa951e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1208_img_3891_1"/>
                68 Middle Abbey Street,  Dublin    12 Octr 1918.  <lb/>P.F. QUINLAN LL.B., <lb/>solicitor   Very Rev. T.B. Nolan S.J.  Provincial, The Presbytery,  Up. Gardiner St. Dublin   re: Major Rev. J.J. Fitzgibbon. S.J., M.C., C,F.. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Deceased.</hi> Dear Fr Nolan,   I have this morning received a letter <lb/> from the Assistant Financial Secretary to the War <lb/>Office, copy of which, is as follows :—  'War office, <lb/>London. s.W. <lb/>10 Oct 1918. <lb/>'Sir, <lb/>' with reference to your letter of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> inst, I am <lb/>' directed to acquaint you that it is not yet known <lb/>' in this Department what amount, if any, is due to <lb/>' the Estate of the late Major Rev. J.J. Fitzgibbons. M.C. <lb/>' Army Chaplain from Army Funds. <lb/>' The necessary enquiries are being made and <lb/>' communication will be addressed to you, as soon as <lb/>' these are completed' <lb/>I am, sir, <lb/>'You obedient servant <lb/>(Signed) ' C. Harris <lb/>' Assistant Financial Secretary  This letter does not bring the matter any further and I must <lb/>now await hearing from the War office again. <seg type="closer"> Faithfully Yours  P.F. Quinlan A.G.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>