<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1326">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Oscar L. Disney, 22nd Royal Fusiliers, to Father Darlington, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Oscar L. Disney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Private Oscar L. Disney, 22nd Royal Fusiliers, A Company, 3 Platoon, to Father Darlington. Disney was serving with the British Expeditionary Force and the letter gives news about his service. His company is at rest several miles back from the front. Disney writes primarily about his desire to gain a commission as an officer. He seems to have had a setback as his company officer, Captain Clifford, &#39;says it is no use his taking me before the colonel and asking that I be recommended, for he has done it for many and the colonel has absolutely refused to recommend any one, excepting for gallantry.&#39; He hopes that Sir Henry Christopher Grattan Bellew (1860-1942), the third baronet of Mount Bellew in County Galway, might write a letter to his commanding officer recommending him for the commission.This letter is from a collection of miscellaneous letters relating to the Bellew family. Sir Henry Christopher Grattan Bellew was the third baronet of Mount Bellew in County Galway. He held the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel, 4th Battalion Connaught Rangers. His son, sir Charles Christopher (1887-1948) held the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel, King&#39;s Royal Rifle Corps. He was decorated with the award of the Military Cross (M.C.) in 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bellew of Mount Bellew Papers, Collection List No. 33, Ms. 27,290</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1326</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1554">Oscar L. Disney</persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Father Darlington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1326_img_621_1"  type="Letter"  url="81ac8f9989591cfe3e5b156f748b4894.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1326_img_621_2"  type="Letter"  url="fc53fd864e4122b502881be8b0761bf8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1326_img_621_3"  type="Letter"  url="260241b099e3b50e6f5d968ce28f4d74.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1326_img_621_4"  type="Letter"  url="712a46f905d41eb789eda02d19c14998.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1326_img_621_5"  type="Letter"  url="ab8de8482b7e57f1e70dfbc533a1d8d9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1326_img_621_1"/>
              Please <lb/>destroy when <lb/>read. T.D.    June 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1916   My dear Father Darlington   At present we <lb/> are enjoying a short rest, <lb/> a few miles back from the <lb/> trenches. I posted you a <lb/> short letter a day or two <lb/> ago,in reply to yours <lb/> of April 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>, and hope <lb/> very much that you <lb/> have received it <lb/>safely. Well Father I <lb/> find necessity a great <lb/> compelling force and <lb/> I have accomplished tasks <lb/> which in ordinary life I <lb/>should have thought  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1326_img_621_2"/>
              practically physical <lb/> impossibilities. I have <lb/> developed a great <lb/> respect for the chaps <lb/> who have stood the <lb/> riguors of the trenches <lb/> for nearly two years <lb/> now. I have acquired <lb/>quite a comprehensive <lb/> knowledge of the true <lb/> significance of the <lb/>term 'artillery activity.' <lb/> I hope and pray that <lb/> I shall be fortunate <lb/> enough to see this <lb/> horrible war through. <lb/>If I am so favoured, I <lb/> think I shall be able to <lb/> exact a good deal of <lb/>compensation from the <lb/> proper enjoyment and  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1326_img_621_3"/>
              appreciation of the <lb/>advantages of civilization <lb/> and freedom, as we know <lb/> it in our Empire, and <lb/> which previously, I for one <lb/> looked upon as a part <lb/> of our national inheritance <lb/> and never fully realized <lb/> the dangers and <lb/> hardships that have <lb/> been willingly undergone <lb/>in order to obtain them. <lb/> I keep on praying for my <lb/> commission and have <lb/> asked Our Lady of <lb/> Pep. Succour to take my <lb/> cause in hand and <lb/> obtain good success. <lb/> I think I shall ask <lb/> St.Ignatius also for he <lb/> was a soldier once. If  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1326_img_621_4"/>
              I fail I shall be happy <lb/> for I shall be sure it is <lb/> for the best. Well, Father <lb/> I have definite news <lb/>for you today. I had <lb/> an audience with <lb/> my company (A) Officer, <lb/> Captain Clifford, he is <lb/> a Catholic and will <lb/>help me all he can <lb/> in the way of the <lb/>commission. He says it <lb/> is no use his taking <lb/> me before the Colonel, <lb/> and asking that I <lb/>should be recom m ended, <lb/> for he has done it for <lb/> many and the Colonel <lb/> has absolutely refused <lb/> to recommend any one, <lb/> excepting for gallantry  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1326_img_621_5"/>
               please destroy T.D. <lb/>on the field. Well I might <lb/> wait years and not <lb/> get an opportunity <lb/> and if an opportunity <lb/> does turn up, I must <lb/> be noticed. Captain <lb/> Clifford has advised <lb/> me to get another <lb/> c/o to write a note, <seg type="del">to</seg><lb/> (not an official one) to <lb/> my Colonel telling him <lb/> he is interested in me <lb/> and would like me <lb/> for an officer. Well <lb/> Father can you help <lb/> me now? I don't know <lb/> if Sir Henry Bellew <lb/>will be willing to write <lb/> to my c/o in the sense <lb/> suggested. But I am  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>