<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0625">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 24 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to Maria Duffin (1854-1954) regarding her life working at the third general hospital in London. Celia writes that the men in her ward were getting restless as they returned to fitness and describes a pillow fight which took place between two neighbouring wards. Additionally, Celia writes about the difficulties with the new matron in her new day ward. While writing about her daily activities Celia mentions that one of the girls has had to go into a home for a &#39;rest cure&#39; due to a breakdown. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA. Celia was an accomplished poet, publishing, among other volumes, a book of poetry with her sister Ruth.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/A/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/625</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1393">3rd London General Hospital, Wandsworth, London</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0625_img_2066_1"  type="Letter"  url="53c670f6fc1355248a4e3df7bdeadbb7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0625_img_2066_2"  type="Letter"  url="4b7e1fd93d669f0bc79765fe02dfed18.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0625_img_2066_3"  type="Letter"  url="84ef51c44ab7b3d14881b8985eec8f1c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0625_img_2066_1"/>
                3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> London General    24 January   Dearest Mamma   Thank you very much for your <lb/> letters, it is nice to hear all the home news, <lb/>and I have little news to give you in return. <lb/>One good thing, I am on day duty again, as I <lb/> find seven weeks of night work just as <lb/> much as I want. I feel half alive all the <lb/> time and haven't the energy to do anything <lb/>but get into bed at the first opportunity — <lb/> Also the men were getting very hard to keep <lb/>in order, as most of them were feeling <lb/>absolutely fit, being convalescent enteries, but <lb/>not allowed to mix with the other soldiers in <lb/>camps or places yet. They were all consequently <lb/>very bored with life and ready to do anything <lb/>for the sake of some amusement. When I <lb/>came on in the evening, I used to find  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0625_img_2066_2"/>
              them all in the wrong beds, or a carefully <lb/>arranged pillow in one bed and two men <lb/>in the next. I generally managed to get them <lb/>quieted down pretty soon, but the other night, <lb/>just when I thought they were all settled down, <lb/>there was a sudden loud whistle, and all <lb/>the men who were able suddenly jumped <lb/>out of their beds, each armed with a <lb/>pillow and rushed into the next door ward. <lb/>All the men there were soon out of bed too, <lb/>and there was a regular free fight. The <lb/>sister there could do nothing but wait <lb/>till they had finished. I was thankful <lb/>when I got them back to bed again, as <lb/>if any of the authorities had come in, <lb/>the ward and the nurse in charge would <lb/>most likely have been reported to the matron <lb/>and there would have been no end of <lb/>a fuss.   Unfortunately I am <cb/><lb/>back in the ward where I was once before <lb/>under the dragon sister McIntyre, and <lb/>the nice staff nurse is gone, and a <lb/>disagreeable creature in her place. After <lb/>being allowed to do practically what I <lb/>liked in my last day ward and being <lb/>under a nice sister, it is horrid being <lb/>ordered about all the time. She is the <lb/>kind who has all her favourite patients <lb/>in the kitchen to drink tea with her, <lb/>and yet pulls you up if you dare to <lb/>speak to a patient. I have only been with <lb/>her for three days but expect we shall <lb/>fight before long as I don't intend to pay <lb/>her any attention.   Terry seemed very well, I think he is <lb/>lucky to have that job. I didn't like <lb/>his moustache, but I suppose it is 'the thing'.   Surely <hi rend="underline">Aunt Elizabeth</hi> Hincks  will have left <lb/>you some sort of ornaments, it will be most<lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0625_img_2066_3"/>
              disappointing if she <seg type="del">he</seg> hasn't.    I didn't get your letter in time to meet O. <lb/>but anyway don't think I would have had <lb/>time. You seem to be having an unlucky <lb/>time with your cooks, what a nuisance servants <lb/>are. By the time I leave here, I <seg type="del">ch</seg> shall be <lb/>a well—qualified housemaid and think I <lb/>ought to apply for the post at Dunowen.    I went home for breakfast with Miss Gosse <lb/>the other morning when I was doing nightwork, <lb/>and met her people; her sister is much younger <lb/>and a pretty girl. They live not far from <lb/>Miss McNeils' house, who asked me to go to <lb/>see her, and I have never been yet. I was <lb/>speaking to Frank Dalziel down the telephone <lb/>this morning, poor Norma has had to go into <lb/>a home for a rest cure, evidently a break down.  Please thank Dorothy for her letter, I shouldn't <lb/>advise her to start nursing, but wait and see <lb/>if she can't get some of the Post office or clerk <lb/>appointments in a hospital, she'd like it much <lb/>better and lots of VAD's are doing the work — I <lb/>shd apply for that.  <seg type="closer"> Best love, dearest <lb/>from   Celia. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>