<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6731">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Monahan to John Quinn, 21 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Monahan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Michael Monahan (1865–1933) to John Quinn (1870-1924), discussing Quinn’s article in the New York Times (13 August 1916) regarding the execution of Roger Casement. Michael Monahan was the editor and proprietor of the literary magazine The Phoenix, formerly known as The Papyrus, based in Connecticut. John Quinn was a lawyer in New York, the son of Irish immigrants who maintained close ties with Ireland during his life through his patronage of the arts. In this letter, Monahan thanks Quinn for sending him a copy of Quinn’s New York Times article titled &#39;Roger Casement, martyr&#39;. Monahan agrees with Quinn’s sentiment in the article, that Casement’s execution was unjust. Monahan also believes that the executions of the 1916 leaders will negatively impact the Americans relationship with Britain.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>John Quinn Memorial Collection, Box 7, f.4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6731</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0620">Michael Monahan</persName>
              <date>1916-08-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1188">South Norwalk, Connecticut, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1279">John Quinn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0945">31 Nassau Street, New York, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1933</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6731_img_None_1"  url="phpBjZiTT.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6731_img_None_2"  url="php9fxich.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6731_img_0_1"/>
             The Phoenix<lb/>Michael Monahan, Editor &amp; Proprietor<lb/>(Originally founded as The Papyrus, July 1903  Subscription - One Dollar the Year<lb/>To Foreign Countries, One twenty-five  ZN12   Suth Norwalk, Conn    August 21, 1916.   You have put me under a rare obligation by your<lb/>thoughtfulness in sending me the Casement paper which<lb/>I might otherwise have missed (I do not see the Times<lb/>regularly).  It does you everlasting credit and, even more, it<lb/>is a high credit to the Irish name. You must also allow<lb/>me to take pride in it as an exhibition of ability and<lb/>talent such as we are rarely favored with in these dull<lb/>times. It is at once a splendid statement of the Irish<lb/>question, a poetical justification of Casement and his<lb/>fellows, a terrific scorching up of the Ulster Patriots<lb/>and their English backers and accomplices and a com-<lb/>plete exposure of the value of German friendship for<lb/>Ireland. You have cleaned up the subject - there is<lb/>nothing more to be said!  Finally, as a piece of English this paper is not less<lb/>remarkable; there are things in it that recall the<lb/>Grattans and the Currans, the noblest traditions of Irish<lb/>patriotism and its canonized utterances. I tried to<lb/>read it aloud to a friend, and had to stop more than once - 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6731_img_0_2"/>
             The Phoenix<lb/>Michael Monahan, Editor &amp; Proprietor<lb/>(Originally founded as The Papyrus, July 1903  Subscription - One Dollar the Year<lb/>To Foreign Countries, One twenty-five  ZN12   Suth Norwalk, Conn   #2<lb/>perhaps because I am Irish, but I guess even an alien<lb/>would feel the pull. That terrible  picture of the  doing to death of<lb/>Casement and his felon's grave will cost the English some-<lb/>thing in American friendship and sympathy. Doesn't<lb/>it beat the Devil how they can't help blundering in<lb/>regarding to us? - it is the heritage of centuries.   Faithfully yours,<lb/>Michael Monahan  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>