<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0858">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his family, 21 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to &#39;his folks&#39;, i.e. his family. The letter is to be forwarded to four different family members, and eventually back to Lady Lillian. This is Spender&#39;s self-described &#39;Xmas mail&#39; to his family. He sends them his &#39;dear love&#39; and Christmas wishes, and assures them that his mother&#39;s present is more than enough, that he doesn&#39;t wish to receive any more gifts, and that &#39;really one has to think of every ounce of kit&#39; that one will have to cart around while on the front. He suggests that he and his fellow staff officers arguably &#39;overdo our creature comforts&#39; at the present time. He recounts a recent visit to the trenches, writes about &#39;5 chaps who had just been gassed&#39;, and curses &#39;the brutes&#39; who began that style of warfare. Spender praises the cheeriness and hard work of the Ulster soldiers, and gives details of life in the trenches, noting that many trenches are cut off from communications during the day, and the men can be &#39;isolated in the mud&#39; for up to 24 hours. Spender discusses the problem of fuel, the men&#39;s attitude to him, and their relationship with soldiers of the Irish regiments. He promises to return home soon on leave, and sends love to a number of named individuals.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#39;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/116</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/858</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Spender family</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0858_img_2418_1"  type="Letter"  url="0469d8f4512019c027bdf0bcdd6da828.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0858_img_2418_2"  type="Letter"  url="d914c170096ff47660c93be6ca0a7162.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0858_img_2418_3"  type="Letter"  url="a031bc6cd3a7e60a7743fa1d88b33114.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0858_img_2418_4"  type="Letter"  url="79549bc82de1ea1c5810ed2bd40cdd52.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0858_img_2418_1"/>
              <seg type="del">Mater &amp; Prat</seg><lb/>Lily <lb/><seg type="del">El</seg><lb/><seg type="del">Rex</seg>    21 Dec 1915   My dearest Mater &amp; all dear Folks,   This I suppose, is my Xmas<lb/> mail &amp; it carries my very dear love to you all, &amp; as<lb/> I know your thoughts will include the 3 soldier brothers,<lb/> so will mine think of my dear folks at home &amp; you <lb/> all on Xmas morn.   I am hoping not to receive ay Xmas gifts this <lb/> year having already had from Mater a more than substantial<lb/> one which I shall hope to use in helping the Country <lb/> now, &amp; ourselves in the future. Really one has to think<lb/> of every ounce of Kit, which I am afraid is too often <lb/> forgotten by Staff officers with their extra comforts. I shall<lb/> not hesitate to ask for anything really useful later.   In food &amp; even luxuries we <hi rend="underline">at present</hi> have no lack,<lb/> in fact in my opinion we a little overdo our creature comforts, <lb/> but that may be altered anytime.  Yesterday I paid a visit to our men in the trenches, <lb/> arriving 20 minutes after a rather heavy artillery bombardment<lb/> by the enemy but having a very quiet time. I got right up  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0858_img_2418_2"/>
              to the front when our men<lb/> were mining, &amp; saw 5 poor<lb/> chaps who had just been gassed, but who I hope will recover.  Really one finds it hard to forgive the brutes who started that <lb/> form of warfare, &amp; I should have been glad to bring up some<lb/> of our German sentimentalists from home!   Our own Ulstermen win for the cheeriest of the <lb/> men I saw, &amp; were working with a will at improving the<lb/> lines. The other battalions who had of course been longer<lb/> in the trenches than ours looked war weary &amp; worn &amp;<lb/> I felt glad we had so many men still out of those conditions<lb/> till  a little of  the winter weather  has  passed, but I suppose their turn will<lb/> come before very long.   Some of the trenches were so bad that they could not<lb/> be used, &amp; consequently parts of our line were entirely cut <lb/> off from all communication by day, but every night<lb/> under cover of darkness the men are relieved from their<lb/> 24 hours isolation in the mud.  One of the burning questions was fuel , &amp; the French<lb/> Railway authorities do not seem to me to have done all that<lb/> was possible in this matter.   Our men seem to have done very well, &amp; also<lb/> appeared genuinely pleased to see me, &amp; also glad at the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0858_img_2418_3"/>
              hopes which I was able to hold out that they might<lb/> come back to the Division.   I had different accounts of how they got on with<lb/> the Dublin's &amp; other Regiments, the officers said excellently,<lb/> but the men told me quite another story. I fancy it is <lb/> as well that they are likely to be separated before Xmas; tho'<lb/> our men will be in the trenches till Xmas night.    One wandered about on one's own- with Douglas who<lb/> was glad to have a view at the front - &amp; it was <lb/> very difficult as one walked down a track by the side of<lb/> a bank to realise that if one walked by a short cut<lb/> leading a little to the left ( &amp; used at night ) one's<lb/> chances of reaching the trench line would be very small.<lb/> One of our own officers was wounded at this spot, &amp;<lb/> a bullet whistled just past my head as I went along as if<lb/> they knew one was passing, or had seen my cap.   I had on my top boots which was as well<lb/> for the mud was half way up them in places.  I took a long view through a periscope from<lb/> one of our advanced sentry posts &amp; thought I saw a <lb/> movement in a trench 40 yards off. It may have been a  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0858_img_2418_4"/>
              hat, or else it may have been a  bit of the  head of the first German<lb/> I have seen out here!  There was a good deal of musketry &amp; 2 heavy <lb/> shells boomed not very far off but I did not see where<lb/> so it was probably quite 400 yards away.  I mustn't let my pen wander on, especially<lb/> as I hope to see you all if the fates are propitious<lb/> as there is a chance of my getting home for 6 days<lb/> on the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>of the month or 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of the New Year!   Till then at any rate my <seg type="del">dear</seg> love to<lb/> all including the stalwart Hubert Lassie Reggie <lb/> for whom a good nickname would be podge, the Walters<lb/> twain &amp; the wonderful Mabs who without a cook <lb/> can still find room at her Xmas party for Granny .   <seg type="del">B</seg> <seg type="closer"> Your loving son frater &amp; Uncle  Wilfred B Spender  </seg> <seg type="del">Mabs</seg><lb/><seg type="del">Edwin</seg><lb/>Bert  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>