<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5965">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alfred Woods to John Ritchie's secretary, 12 May 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alfred Woods</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by an Irish soldier who experienced racial harassment while serving in the British army. Alfred Woods states that &#34;Orangemen&#34; in his battalion offended him. Interestingly, this letter is part of a collection of government correspondence relating to the Liverpool Race Riots (termed &#34;colour riots&#34; by contemporaries) of 1919. After the end of the First World War, many former soldiers from all regions of the British Empire were struggling to adjust to civilian life. As they often sought employment in vain or waited to be repatriated, conflicts escalated between &#34;foreign&#34; ex-servicemen and the local population. People of colour or those who housed them were attacked. Buildings were set on fire. The documents kept by the Liverpool Record Office reflect the concerns of the demobilised soldiers as well as the authorities&#39; efforts to restore peace.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Liverpool Record Office</repository>
                  <collection>From Great War to Race Riots Archive, 352/MAY/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5965</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0780">Alfred Woods</persName>
              <date>1919-05-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0768">17 Heytesbury Street, South Circular Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Secretary to the Lord Mayor of Liverpool</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1699">Liverpool, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5965_img_None_1"  url="phpSOol8o.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5965_img_None_2"  url="php8X2cua.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5965_img_0_1"/>
              war    17 Heytesbury Street,<lb/>South Circular Road,<lb/>Dublin,<lb/>Ireland,    12/5/'19.    The Secretary,   The Rt. Hon. The Lord Mayor.,<lb/>City of Liverpool.   Sir,   I would be much obliged if you<lb/>would draw his Lordship's attention<lb/>to the fact that I was connected with<lb/>the 15<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Battalion of the King's Liverpool<lb/>Regiment in England and the 1/5th<lb/>Battalion of the Regiment from March<lb/>1916 to December 1917, and during that<lb/>time received many insults and unwarrant-<lb/>able treatment from some of the low<lb/>classes of Liverpool people in the Regiment    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5965_img_0_2"/>
             352 MAY/1/1  just because I was Irish. They seemingly<lb/>possessed orange leanings and the<lb/>antipathy and bigotry they showed<lb/>towards Irishmen made it most unbearable<lb/>for me whilst in his Majesty's Forces.<lb/>I believe myself the more responsible<lb/>citizens of your great city would not up-<lb/>hold the conduct of such people against<lb/>Irishmen who happened to live and fight<lb/>with them.  Let it be hoped that people<lb/>totally different to a strange community<lb/>in religion, race and political sentiments<lb/>will in future be safeguarded against<lb/>coming in contact with its rabble element.  Liverpool can really initiate a<lb/>move in this direction, because speaking<lb/>on my own account I regret to state<lb/>that I suffered from the abuses of the<lb/>class of Orange Liverpool citizen whom<lb/>I have already described.   Yours most truly,<lb/>Alfred Woods   (Journalist &amp; younger son of the late Mr. James Woods, <seg type="unclear">Freeman's Journal, Dublin</seg>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>