<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1612">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her brother Tommy Martin, 26 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her brother Tommy Martin (1891-?) who served in the Connaught Rangers. Marie Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM). In this letter from the theatre of war, Marie writes to her brother to thank him for his letter. She is updating him on the news form Malta and wishes him the best and to keep safe.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF114</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1612</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1915-11-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Tommy Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0143">Connaught Rangers, Bere Island, Co. Cork, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1612_img_1076_1"  type="Letter"  url="c60eb43aa41c0703b67fa5e13898c442.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1612_img_1076_2"  type="Letter"  url="560453c814666e113cab65b27a509ce3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1612_img_1076_3"  type="Letter"  url="f4a97b05ae4674fd2aa144b883458c55.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1612_img_1076_4"  type="Envelope"  url="a56a81f46c18becb7a4cc42ad98f4046.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1612_img_1076_1"/>
             Dearest Tommy,   A thousand thanks for your <lb/> very nice long letter I was delighted <lb/> to hear from you &amp; glad to <lb/>hear you have quite recovered <lb/> from your wound but hope <lb/> it will be some time before <lb/> you have to go on Active <lb/>Service again, I shall of course <lb/> be delighted to see you if
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1612_img_1076_2"/>
            you are sent out this way <lb/> again but don't be in a hurry <lb/> as I do not think these seas <lb/>are <sic>two</sic> safe just now— <lb/> I believe they have caught a <lb/> good number of extra large <lb/>size salmon around here these <lb/> last few weeks, we are very <lb/> worried as we are told we <lb/>shall not get <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> mails for <lb/> another 3 of 4 weeks. I have not <lb/> heard from home since the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Feb</seg> but know of course it is <lb/> the fault of Mails. Is there any <lb/> signs of this war ending <lb/>it is getting more terrible every <lb/> day &amp; if it is true about Greece <lb/> I cannot think what will happen. <lb/>We are frightfully busy here <lb/> in fact just now we are really
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1612_img_1076_3"/>
            over worked &amp; very <sic>understaff</sic> but <lb/> am glad to be able to say <lb/> I feel A.1. of course very tired <lb/>when I come off duty. yesterday <lb/> a new convoy came in so I <lb/> was on all day from 7-30 <lb/>to 8.15. I tell you what we <lb/> did work hard. As I had no <lb/> time to finish this yesterday <lb/>I am making up this very short <lb/> &amp; uninteresting note— <lb/>With every good wish &amp; the best <lb/> of Luck - God bless you &amp; <lb/> take care of you—  Your most loving <lb/> sister—   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1612_img_1076_4"/>
             Leuit. T.S. Martin, <lb/>5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Batt. Connaught Rangers <lb/>Bere Island <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>