<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4043">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from 12 named individuals to 'the Public', undated</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Appeal to the Public for funds on behalf of the Widow Shanahan and her seven orphan children to enable her to rebuild her premises and restart her business.  The appeal was made by 12 individuals (three Priests, six Justices of the Peace, and three others including  a solicitor).
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers 1916, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-5526b</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4043</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1886">Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4043_img_3425_1"  type="Letter"  url="36f7e5c1f0a69698987f510f86e0e817.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4043_img_3425_1"/>
            <seg type="head">APPEAL FOR ASSISTANCE ON BEHALF OF THE <lb/>WIDOW SHANAHAN AND HER SEVEN HELPLESS <lb/><hi rend="underline">CHILDREN</hi></seg>  The undersigned hereby appeal to the Charitable <lb/>Public on behalf of the Widow Shanahan of PORTMAGEE, and Her <lb/>SEVEN Helpless Children, whose Premises were <sic>accidently</sic> <lb/>burned down on the 6th of November last, for Help to enable <lb/>her to rebuild her premises and restart her business.   Her Premises and Stock thereon, which were not <lb/>insured were totally destroyed thereby reducing her from <lb/>comparative Comfort to dire distress.   In this her extreme need we trust that our Call <lb/> will not be in vain and a generous Response will be given <lb/>to tide her over her present difficulties.    Father O'Brien P. P. Father Costelloe C. C. <lb/>Father Keane P. P.    Edward Fitzgerald J. P. John Nannix J. P. <lb/>William J. Leslie J. P. Timothy Galvin J. P. <lb/>Timothy O'Driscoll J. P. James Trant J. P.   C. G. O'Connell., M.J. O'Sullivan Solicitor <lb/>J. Butler.   C.C. SHANAHAN <lb/>T. HURLEY <lb/>(Hon. Secretaries)   SUBSCRIPTIONS WILL BE RECEIVED BY EITHER <lb/> OF <hi rend="underline">THE HON. SECRETARIES.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>