<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5565">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 7 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

May made pancakes for Shrove Tuesday.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5565</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-03-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5565_img_661_1"  type="Letter"  url="e28acc207fd4abf87b75ce13cd09e1fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5565_img_661_2"  type="Letter"  url="373f2fd8909e6e7c65598d1b9604d06b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5565_img_661_1"/>
            <!-- Extra part of the letter written at the top left-hand corner sideways --> I am childish enough<lb/>to be <sic>quiet</sic> looking forward<lb/>to getting watch, <hi rend="superscript">not</hi> the watch<lb/>so much as the token of<lb/>love it must be, at least<lb/>that it is in my eyes.  Love from   May<lb/>   <lb/>X X X X X  <!-- Beginning of letter --> Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar    7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1916    My dearest James   You were indeed very <sic>thoughtfull</sic> to manage a<lb/>moment to send me a line, I must say you are a very good dear<lb/>man. I was very glad to have your letter this morn and very early<lb/>I had it too, but I could not find energy to get through my few jobs<lb/>having nothing to hurry for better than dinner, for the first time<lb/>I felt a want in country life but I was not so silly as I call it as to let<lb/>that be seen but I hurried to write this letter to you &amp; then set to <seg type="del">o</seg><lb/>&amp; make <hi rend="underline">pancakes</hi> for the tea on account of Shrove Tuesday, it is<lb/>a big job for so many but I wish there was one more. I fancy you<lb/>would not care for them- I will eat them tho’ I know well I will wish<lb/>I did not –Johnnie C. did not hear anything today<lb/>Christy is not feeling well he is staying inside all day &amp;<lb/>complains of pains in his side he got a bottle of pills &amp; ointment. I hope they<lb/>will have the desired effect -nothing wrong with his appetite yet- he was<lb/>anxious to know if the eggs were dropping out on you. I did not tell<lb/>Mrs S, I was afraid she would say I had <seg type="del">a</seg> right to mind them, she<lb/>was up as usual last night, gave me “down the banks” for not telling<lb/>her anything. I told her to ask me some suitable questions &amp; I’d<lb/>see if I could answer. She said I was too clever altogether for 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5565_img_661_2"/>
             her taste I don’t know why she thinks<lb/>me like that but she has hinted that way<lb/>very often of late what harm I’m sure you<lb/>would like to have a clever girl for your <hi rend="underline">wife</hi>,<lb/>here is no news at all going around<lb/>that is worth writing. Joe Nolan was here<lb/>yesterday evening but I know you<lb/>are old sick of his sayings &amp; etc. Jennie<lb/>wrote to Mrs S today. She seems to be<lb/>getting on grand I got back in the two<lb/>train I had not one minute to spare.<lb/>I hope you were not lonely last night<lb/>when you went home I was very lonely<lb/>sitting at the fire not but Mrs S<lb/>said I did not even say if they were or not<lb/>when I went to bed it was relieved<lb/>by tears &amp; then away with me<lb/>to dreamland no such luck as<lb/>happy dreams even.  I have not another word now but<lb/>Very very best love from your own  big girl   May    <seg type="unclear"></seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>