<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0194">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B. N. Mahaul, 28 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>B. N. Mahaul</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from B. N. Mahaul. Mahaul is writing in the hope that the letter will be brought to the attention of the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939). Mahaul was writing to complain about the newspaper &#39;The Eye-Opener&#39;. The paper caused some controversy due to an article it published with the heading &#39;Black Peril&#39; which attacked Indian students. The paper claims that &#39;coloured people&#39; were savage and that any white person seen in their company was a disgrace. Mahaul asks the lord lieutenant to act against the offensive paper.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5575/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/194</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0022">B. N. Mahaul</persName>
              <date>1916-03-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0138">King&#39;s Inn, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0194_img_1334_1"  type="Letter"  url="9b24f3c70f4b52f557793d4e40108b38.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0194_img_1334_2"  type="Letter"  url="3aeeac60a7dc2526233f50ee4ae6bfdb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0194_img_1334_3"  type="Letter"  url="70e9dba2030f82052b2a4c911f35989f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0194_img_1334_4"  type="Letter"  url="9828f98e497dbd2b261bbc797b45b5d0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0194_img_1334_1"/>
                28th March,1916   Dear Sir,   May I ask you to oblige <lb/> me by bringing the following <lb/> to the notice of His Excellency <lb/> the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.   The editor of the paper <lb/> eye-opener is doing a great <lb/> mischief in inciting race <lb/> against race by his articles <lb/> 'Black Devil'. He has been <lb/> writing against very many <lb/> people here. But his allowance <lb/> to Condemn a race under the <lb/> British rule are surely doing <lb/> more harm than is visible <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0194_img_1334_2"/>
              at present.   Individuals whom he <lb/> has been libeling might not <lb/> have thought fit to bring <lb/> an action against him. <lb/> But maker becomes <seg type="unclear">ruinous</seg><lb/> when he attacks a class <lb/> of His Majesty' subjects.   During the war such a <lb/> wretched publication can <lb/> easily be stopped under <lb/> the Defence of the Realm <lb/> Act for inciting race <lb/> hatred and disturbing <lb/> peace.   I may add that my <lb/> information is that the Editor <lb/> is not a responsible person <lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0194_img_1334_3"/>
              and has been in jail <lb/> before. The doings of— <lb/> such a man should <lb/> surely be met with <lb/> strong measures. <lb/> By so doing His Excellency <lb/> will be placing a sector <lb/> of the loyal subjects of His <lb/> Majesty under a deep <lb/> debt of gratitude.   Hoping my request <lb/> shall move His Excellency <lb/> who is known to be so sympathetic <lb/> and popular over here   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0194_img_1334_4"/>
              <seg type="closer"> Yours most obedient servant.  B. N. Mahaul. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>