<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1519">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nancy Campbell to Mrs. O'Rahilly, 17 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nancy Campbell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter of condolence from Nancy Campbell to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). The writer expresses sympathy with Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly family on the death of her &#39;heroic&#39; husband, mentioning the children and &#39;the child yet to be born&#39;. Campbell also writes about the honour of having known The O&#39;Rahilly and the other men who &#39;died for Ireland.&#39;Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1519</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1336">Nancy Campbell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1874">Kilmolin House, Enniskerry, Co. Wicklow, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1519_img_979_1"  type="Letter"  url="4937973c1fb21eb038c5f749413158ae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1519_img_979_2"  type="Letter"  url="76c497f18af6bbd5664da1f9d65aba8a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1519_img_979_1"/>
                Kilmolin House,  Enniskerry,  Co. Wicklow    May 17th 1916.   Dear Mrs. O'Rahilly   I would have written before <lb/> but I heard you were ill - <lb/>both Joseph &amp; I would like <lb/> to send our deepest sympathy, <lb/> &amp; also to tell you how <lb/>greatly we admire the <lb/> O'Rahillys behaviour - if <lb/> anything could comfort you <lb/> it must be the thought <lb/> of his heroism - even the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1519_img_979_2"/>
              newspapers are full of his praise, <lb/>I see. The little boys will have <lb/> a wonderful memory to live up <lb/> to - &amp; perhaps the new baby <lb/> (there is to be one, isn't there) will <lb/>be a comfort to you too - it <lb/>must be all so terrible for you. <lb/>I feel so proud of having <lb/>known the O'Rahilly &amp; some <lb/> of the other brave men who <lb/>died for Ireland with him. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Nancy Campbell</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>