<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5668">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Administrative Area Office, Royal Hospital Kilmainham, to the Chief Crown Solicitor, 26 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A colonel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the Administrative Area Office of the Royal Hospital Kilmainham to the Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland, Malachy Kelly (1850-1916). The letter concerns the injury of Patrick Sheehan (1879-?), a labourer from Cork, who injured himself while working. The letter states the wages of Mr Sheehan at the time of injury, also stating he has no written contract with the employer.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3785</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5668</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1352">A colonel</persName>
              <date>1916-02-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0027">Royal Hospital, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1023">Malachy J. Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5668_img_761_1"  type="Letter"  url="5f2d05ec26cb9cce0d0f6b0076742187.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5668_img_761_1"/>
             Adminis<hi rend="underline">trative Are</hi>a Officer <lb/>Please see Solicitor Generals queries opposite <lb/>and let me know full <seg type="unclear">testimonials</seg> <lb/>M. Kelly <lb/>9.3.16   Ref.No.155/58<seg type="del">3</seg> 2 2. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Subject. Injury to <sic>Patk.</sic> Sheehan.</hi>   A.A.O., Ireland, <lb/>Royal Hospital, <lb/>Dublin.   26th February, 1916.   The Chief Crown Solicitor, <lb/> Dublin Castle,   Sir,   In reply to your minute of 25/2/16, <lb/>this man is a casual labourer employed at 6d per <lb/>hour as and when required. There is no written <lb/>contract as to the terms of his employment.   Yours faithfully,      Colonel, <lb/>Administrative Area Officer. <lb/>M.R.  2 <lb/>I require to know a great deal <lb/>more about this mans employment <lb/>to be able to say if he was "employed <lb/><seg type="unclear">with course</seg> than for the purposes of <lb/>the employment trade or harriers' <lb/>what was he carrying the sacks <lb/>for? Etc. Etc. <lb/>EOF.   Solicitor General <lb/>Please advise. <lb/>M. Kelly. <lb/>29.2/16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>