<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0188">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Sheehan to Lord Wimborne, 26 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Sheehan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Sheehan (b.1877), clerk of the Fermoy Urban District, to Ivor Guest, the Lord Wimborne, (1873-1939), lord lieutenant of Ireland. The letter concerns a malicious injury claim made by Sarah J. Rowe (b.1868) due to the death of her husband William N. Rowe (1867-1916), RIC constable who was shot in an attempt to arrest members of the Kent family in connection with Sinn Fein activity in County Cork. Thomas Kent (1865-1916) was later executed for the murder of Constable Rowe. The letter also has a copy of a resolution made regarding the case, calling on the authorities to pay Mrs Rowe some form of compensation. It goes on to state that the application for the fund to be levied off the rate payers should be withdrawn, so not to disturb the peace.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9090</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/188</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1314">William Sheehan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1217">Fermoy, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0188_img_1324_1"  type="Letter"  url="f0ee537774dcf76e822e9849757057e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0188_img_1324_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0ee537774dcf76e822e9849757057e4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0188_img_1324_1"/>
                Council Chamber, Fermoy,    26th May 1916  <lb/> To.   His Excellency Baron Wimborne  Lord Lieutenant of Ireland. Dublin Castle.   May it please Your Excellency:   I am directed by the Fermoy Urban <lb/>Council to transmit to you the undermentioned Resolution in <lb/>reference to the Malicious Injury Claim lodged by Mrs Rowe for <lb/>£2500 compensation for the death of her husband the late Head Const <lb/>Rowe, which occurred on the 2nd inst. <seg type="closer"> I remain, <lb/>Your Excellency's, <lb/>Most Obedient Servant  Wm Sheehan <lb/>Town Clerk. </seg> I ack <lb/> II  <lb/> Please say what pension <lb/> may be paid to Mrs Rowe under <lb/> the R.I.C. Acts. 29-5-16  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0188_img_1324_2"/>
             <seg type="head">Copy Resolution</seg> 'That solely with a view to the continuance of the <lb/>'good, peaceable, and law abiding character of this District, and to <lb/>'obviate any cause of friction or ill feeling, We most earnestly urge <lb/>'on the Authorities to provide out of some fund at their disposal such <lb/>'compensation to the Family of the late Head Constable Rowe R.I.C, <lb/>'Fermoy, as they may justly be considered <sic>entutled</sic> to for his loss which <lb/>'we all regret, and that the pending application of his Widow for <lb/>'compensation to be levied off the Ratepayers should be withdrawn. <lb/>'We do not desire to express any opinion as to the merits or otherwise <lb/>'of the application, but we consider that the levying of such a Decree <lb/>'for compensation off the Ratepayers would inevitably provoke a <lb/>'disturbance of the peace of the District and lead to a repetition of <lb/>'the unfortunate occurrences with which this Barony of Condons and <lb/>Clongibbons was visited in the Eighties'.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>