<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5442">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. Ua Sabháil to Piarás Beaslaí, 9 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. Ua Sabháil</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from M. Ua Sabháil of Mungret College, Limerick, to Piaras or Pierce Béaslaí, born Percy Beazley (1881-1965). The letter refers to Béaslaís play &#39;An Fear na Millúin Punt&#39;. Mungret College was a secondary school founded by the Society of Jesus, of the Jesuits. Ua Sabhháil requests a copy of the play for the college so they can stage it in the future and describes those plans.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Piaras Béaslaí Papers, Collection List No 44; Ms. 33,933 (3)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5442</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">Irish</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0941">M. Ua Sabháil</persName>
              <date>1916-01-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1608">Mungret College, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5442_img_474_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa5ed11818aec5be6a95855b044f3955.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5442_img_474_2"  type="Letter"  url="f1012c72147b027c3aa3446c9c8e01de.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5442_img_474_3"  type="Letter"  url="2166e21f0d1cd79ee69710323a267de0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5442_img_474_1"/>
             Copy Sent   <seg type="foreign">Eanair</seg> 9<hi rend="superscript">ad</hi> 1916    Eanair 9<hi rend="superscript">adh</hi>, 1916.   <seg type="foreign">A duine uasal</seg>,   <seg type="foreign">Chonnaic mé an lá <lb/> eile trachtas ar do dhrama .i. "Fear <lb/> na milliún bpunt", agus ó's fíor <lb/> gur mór do moladh é, ní fulair <lb/> nó gur breagh an drama é.   Ar an adhmhar san, ba mhaith liom <lb/> cóip d'fhaghail le feiscint an feidir <lb/> linne sa gColáiste é cur ar an <lb/> ardán.   Tá an t-airgead na chomhair le faghail <lb/> sa litir seo, agus ba geal liom ar <lb/> fad é bheith again chomh luath &amp; is feidir é.</seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5442_img_474_2"/>
            <lb/><seg type="foreign">Táimid ag déanamh ár ndithchillín <lb/> annso le cúis na teangadh chur ar <lb/> aghaidh. Bidheann rannganna <lb/> comhráidh againn sa siamsa d'éis <lb/> an tsuipéir i gcomhnuidhe agus <lb/> tigeann sluagh mhaith chughainn. <lb/> Tá sprid mhór i measc na mbuachaill, <lb/> agus is breagh thar barr a <lb/> ndúil sa nGaedhilg.   Bidheann spaisteoireacht againn ar <lb/> fud na tíre mor-timchioll ag <lb/> labhairt na Gaedhilge, agus tá cuid aca <lb/> ag tosnamh i labhairt go blasta.   Mar san, "guala le ghualainn", agus beidh <lb/> sí fé meas arís.   Mise le meas mór <lb/>M. Ua Sabháil, C.I.</seg>  <!-- begin translation -->  January 9th, 1916. <lb/>  Dear Sir, <lb/>  I recently saw an exposition on your play, ‘The Man of the Million Pounds’, and it must be a fine play as it was highly praised.   For that reason, I would like to obtain a copy to see if we in the College could stage it.   Payment for it is enclosed in this letter, and I would dearly love to have it as soon as possible.   We are doing our best here to progress the cause of the language. We hold language classes in the gathering after supper always and a good crowd attends. There is a great spirit among the boys and their interest in Irish is truly wonderful.   We hold walks in the surrounding countryside through Irish, and some of them are beginning to speak fluently.   So, “shoulder to shoulder”, and it will be held in high esteem again.   Yours respectfully ,<lb/>  M. Ua Sabháil, S.J.  <!-- end translation -->
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5442_img_474_3"/>
             9½ 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>