<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3877">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 10 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to his father, Hugh Doyle, regarding his activities before being sent to the front. Fr Doyle describes his surroundings in Witley Camp for his father and laments over the constant trouble with mud in the camp. Doyle informs his father of the officer&#39;s rich diet at the camp, causing the officers to look forward to their dispatch to the real front so they can stop gaining weight. Doyle notes that he has a good number attending daily Holy Communion and also hosts confession and the rosary. Before signing off Doyle writes about his future movements and their expected dispatch to France.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3877</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1915-12-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0728">Witley Camp, Surrey, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2113">Melrose, Dalkey, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_1"  type="Letter"  url="7773a4ef5ae063105e0c42f8a8e5f42e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_2"  type="Letter"  url="1f6384305cccec8e64d3af1d618e0f14.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_3"  type="Letter"  url="c730c909aa107a6195ebfbef540c0527.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_4"  type="Letter"  url="b075662a474bac8d24cbc523fcc5bf4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_5"  type="Letter"  url="118c2e40953e2aa8e505aec8f1cd34c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_6"  type="Letter"  url="3fc811016fc4643f2b0c69a5fcc5b65a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_7"  type="Letter"  url="eb35e1a6245c7b96002c5b7212503bd9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3877_img_3257_8"  type="Letter"  url="eefed6a07271b6cfdcb97c655a42501d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_1"/>
             J2183 (6)<lb/> Many thanks for<lb/>the notes. <lb/> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> R. I. Fusiliers,<lb/>Witley Camp,<lb/>Surrey.    10/12/'15.    My dear Father,   Your welcome<lb/>letter came like a ray<lb/>of sunshine reminding<lb/>me of old times at<lb/><seg type="unclear">Ratcliffe</seg> when the arrival<lb/>of home news was a<lb/>regular read letter day.<lb/>The fact is I had almost<lb/>come to the conclusion<lb/>that I was living in<lb/>Canada or Norway! Our 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_2"/>
             2  <lb/>camp is built in the<lb/>middle of a vast pine<lb/>forest, in the centre of<lb/>which a clearing has<lb/>been made for the<lb/>huts, parade ground <seg type="unclear">etc</seg>.  We are surrounded by<lb/>trees on every side; a<lb/>real case of Pines, pines<lb/>everywhere and never a<lb/>drop to drink. (I fear I<lb/>am getting mixed<lb/>somewhat). A few main<lb/>roads connect the different<lb/>sections of the camp<lb/>which extends for miles<lb/>through the forest, but  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_3"/>
             3  <lb/>the rest is clay or sand,<lb/>which under the gentle<lb/>influence of steady,<lb/>almost unceasing rain<lb/>for the past fortnight<lb/>has reached a state of<lb/><seg type="unclear">mudpilism</seg> which baffles<lb/>description. I know now<lb/>the exact meaning of<lb/>stuck in the mud, a<lb/>lamentable state of<lb/>things which happens<lb/>to one at least a<lb/>score of times each day.  For all that we are a<lb/>jolly, good humoured set<lb/>of officers, and I am<lb/>daily feeling more and  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_4"/>
             4  <lb/>more at home though<lb/>the work is fearfully<lb/>hard. To begin with,<lb/>breakfast is a serious<lb/>undertaking consisting of<lb/>porridge, fish, bacon &amp;<lb/>eggs, toast and jam,<lb/>with tea &amp; coffee to <seg type="unclear">Faugh</seg><lb/>a Ballagh. Lunch at<lb/>one means hot meat<lb/>or cold joint and potatoes<lb/>with a choice of <seg type="unclear">sweets</seg>.  By a tremendous effort<lb/>we are able to keep<lb/>body &amp; soul together till<lb/>tea and cake at four,<lb/>and a seven o' clock<lb/>dinner, consisting of<lb/>soup, fish, meat, sweets,<lb/>fruit and coffee brings  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_5"/>
             5  J2/83 (7)<lb/><lb/>an arduous day's work<lb/>to a close. We all wear<lb/>a Sam Brown belt (usually<lb/>known as Buster Brown) —<lb/>the addition of the <seg type="unclear">adjective</seg><lb/>is obvious, no wonder we<lb/>are all praying to get<lb/>to the real Front soon<lb/>to avoid catastrophy, as<lb/>another front is daily<lb/>becoming more visible.  It is not very easy for<lb/>me to get at the men<lb/>but I have Mass each<lb/>morning at seven, a<lb/>good number attending<lb/>with a varying number<lb/>for Holy Communion daily. 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_6"/>
             6  Between four and dinner<lb/>time I hear confessions,<lb/>winding up with the<lb/>rosary which the men<lb/>like, judging by the<lb/>crowds who come.  One of the soldiers who<lb/>serves at Mass is a <seg type="unclear">Dalkey</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">man</seg> living at St. Patrick's<lb/>cottages, named Duff; he<lb/>knows you very well, &amp;<lb/>I suppose on that account<lb/>takes good care that<lb/>I have all I want at<lb/>table.  We are to remain here<lb/>till the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> when we<lb/>move to Bordon Camp,  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_7"/>
             7  <lb/>Hants, to join the<lb/>other three battalions of<lb/>the 49<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Brigade. In one<lb/>way it is no harm to<lb/>spend the most part of<lb/>the winter at home,<lb/>for we shall certainly<lb/>get as much roughing<lb/>as we wish next Jan;<lb/>The 47<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 48<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Brigade,<lb/>both part of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div,<lb/>are sailing for France<lb/>on the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> so it is possible<lb/>we may get orders sooner<lb/>than we expect.  On the whole I must<lb/>say my present life  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3877_img_3257_8"/>
             8  <lb/>in a most acceptable<lb/>charge &amp; rest from<lb/>the busy time of the<lb/>past few years. I am<lb/>feeling all the better<lb/>for it but somewhat<lb/>anxious about the<lb/>Buster Brown Belt.  You might send on<lb/>any letters to the Rev<lb/>Charles for I find that<lb/> escaped my <sic>correspondants</sic>.   With much love<lb/>from <!-- Ever? -->your affectionate son<lb/>Willie.  The address on the letter<lb/>was quite correct 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>