<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2059">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell to the Recorder of Galway, 19 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell (c.1857-1926), the assistant under-secretary to Lord Lieutenant Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939), to the recorder of Galway. In the letter O&#39;Farrell states he has been directed by Wimborne to transmit files to the recorder relating to the application on the part of Michael Connolly for permission to sell liquor.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5611/8458/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2059</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Recorder or Galway</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1895">11 Upper Fitzwilliam Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2059_img_1506_1"  type="Letter"  url="040e687f9e6f22cb8081db1d1bb7390e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2059_img_1506_1"/>
             Dublin Castle   19th May, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Lord Lieutenant to transmit to you <lb/>the accompanying file of papers relative to the application of <lb/><hi rend="underline">Mr. Michael Connolly, Roundstone, Co. Galway,</hi> <lb/>for permission to sell Excisable Liquors until the next Quarter Sessions, <lb/>and to request that you will favour me with your opinion thereon for His <lb/>Excellency's information.   I am also to request that the file of papers may be returned.   I have the honour to be <lb/>Sir <lb/>Your obedient Servant   E O'Farrell   His Honour <lb/>The Recorder of Galway, <lb/>11 Upper Fitzwilliam St., <lb/>Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>