<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3240">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to Alice Katherine Wynne, 31 March 1916	</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from Charles Wyndham Wynne (1895-1917) to his mother, Alice Wynne (d. 1928). Charles was an officer in the British army and writes from Lenan Head Fort in Donegal, where he was stationed. He described the monotony of garrison life and his desire to see his family at home but notes that he won&#39;t get leave for quite a while.
Enclosed is a &#39;form&#39; created by his mother with a list of questions, which he answered and sent back with his letter.
Charles was killed in action in June 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin	</repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/796</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3240</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1215">Lenan Head Fort, Clonmany, Co. Donegal</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1818">Avoca, Co. Wicklow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_1"  type="Letter"  url="f7f6c8935152e26e3c8095d9701565b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_2"  type="Letter"  url="fe5328e23358423b8d7f4e366f811876.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_3"  type="Letter"  url="72b67f25978acd2cf86947c437d2de6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_4"  type="Letter"  url="0a95b0ee45282ffce1827a5939b8e4cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_5"  type="Letter"  url="24e57b1d1c1dc1ab444d8d22eaed86c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="29853e2013382e31f1921679029620b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_7"  type="Envelope"  url="36ae427944d9e22802c16d46305ddbb3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3240_img_266_8"  type="Envelope"  url="62d5fe5ac2d1600d893de0e5d63f0926.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_1"/>
             10247/1/796   Lenan Head Fort<lb/>Clonmany,<lb/>Co Donegal<lb/> 31/3/16 <lb/> Dear Mother,      I couldn't help smiling<lb/>at the form you sent<lb/>it reminds me of an<lb/>Orderly Officer report. I<lb/>will fill it up as well<lb/>as I can. I don't know<lb/>how it was I forgot to<lb/>mention the analgesics<lb/>stuff — I suppose I slipped my<lb/>mind. Thank you very<lb/>much for <seg type="del">sending</seg> ordering  it  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_2"/>
             I asked for the book in<lb/>Dublin but it wasn't out<lb/>in a cheap edition — I have<lb/>quite forgotten what it was<lb/>about. I have been<lb/>very well lately which I<lb/>think it rather remarkable<lb/>considering the demoralising<lb/>sort of life I've been living<lb/>lounging in front of the<lb/>fire all day — but I never<lb/>have a trace of headache<lb/>eat collosally and feel  <lb/>grand  on it : I can't say that my<lb/>memory is good but at<lb/>any rate I think its quite up to normal. Since<lb/>coming back from Tigrouey<lb/>I have had two short walks<lb/>on one of which occasions I got it<lb/>in the neck for leaving the<lb/>fort: that's what I don't<lb/>like here you never can<lb/>leave the fort and if one<lb/>could there's such awfully<lb/>nice country around — if<lb/>only I could get the least bit<lb/>of esercise I shouldn't mind.<lb/>I wonder whether I shall<lb/>be able to get any bathing  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_3"/>
             this year.  O'Brien the officer that I'm<lb/>taking the place of has got a<lb/>couple of day leave so I<lb/>don't go back to <seg type="unclear">Dunrce</seg> till<lb/>Wednesday; by which time<lb/>Major Fitzgerald will be on<lb/>leave and when he comes back<lb/>the Colonel will be going on<lb/>leave so that Fitzgerald will<lb/>come here so I'll be released<lb/>of his company for quite a<lb/>long time.  Today here though stormy<lb/>is nice and warm so I so<lb/>hope that the spring should be<lb/>in just in time to see Father<lb/>about again. Its grand  he's<lb/>doing so well.  Lenan Head Fort,<lb/>Clonmany,<lb/>C<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">o</hi></hi>.Donegal.  It is simply splendid Veronica<lb/>having got a decent place at<lb/>last. I have been grousing a lot<lb/>about loneliness etc here, but<lb/>I'm afraid Veronica must have<lb/>had a much worst time it<lb/>must have been frightfully<lb/>dismal coming back of an<lb/>evening. However you bet she's<lb/>all right now.  Eiu must have had a<lb/>pretty rotten time coming<lb/>back: I saw the Irish Times 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_4"/>
             said the blizzard kept clear<lb/>of Ireland well I  just  wish that<lb/>man had been at Lenan or<lb/>(I espect) better still at Dunree<lb/>and perhaps that would have<lb/>taught him something — I have<lb/>met a few blizzards in my<lb/>time at Dunree — but not many<lb/>worse that that — and in spite<lb/>of all the snow, we had some<lb/>dazzlingly roid lightining in the<lb/>evening though the roar of the<lb/>wind completely drowned the<lb/>thunder. I had large fire in my <lb/>   room — all windows shut and<lb/>about five thickness of blanket<lb/>on my bed!  I hope it wasn't so bad<lb/>with you. I wish I was<lb/>back for a bit while Father<lb/><seg type="del">was</seg> is  getting all right but I'm<lb/>afraid it will be a pretty<lb/>good long time before I get<lb/>leave now. I wonder when<lb/>it will work round to Jack's<lb/>turn for leave : He's still<lb/>in the forest isn't he. May<lb/>was awfully decent and sent<lb/>me a beautiful cake which<lb/>was much appreciated as<lb/>we get such beastly old cakes    
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_5"/>
             at Dunree.  Well now I'll stop this<lb/>long yarn about nothing<lb/>by the way I been reading<lb/>comparatively quite a lot for<lb/>me! Have you ever read a little<lb/>play called an Irishman's House<lb/>by Redmond's nephew and Carson's son.<lb/>I'm afraid you'd probably think<lb/>it rubbish but I thought there<lb/>were quite some points in it.  I don't think Aunt Sophey would like it!!  Your very loving    <hi rend="underline">Charles</hi>   I think I also owe 1/1/— for<lb/>Mr O'Duffy which I am enclosing 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_6"/>
             10247/1/796a  Did you ever get a small tube of<lb/>Benquis analgaesic I ordered for you?  <lb/> Yes   Did you get the Ordeal by battle?  <lb/> No (see later)   How has y. head been as to headache  <lb/> Grand.   also memory? —  <lb/> Ditto   Have you taken up your memory<lb/>course?  <lb/> Not yet (too beastly lazy).   Did you get leggings &amp; apples<lb/>that Winifred sent you?  Yes. Please thank Win very much — it I hope<lb/>it wasn't much trouble it was awfully good of her<lb/>putting in the apples.  <lb/>Please fill up form and return 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_7"/>
             Mrs A. A. Wynne <lb/>Tigrouey <lb/>Audree <lb/>Co. <hi rend="underline">Wicklow</hi> 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3240_img_266_8"/>
             UBIQUE 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>