<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0382">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Christopher Cox to the Chief Secretary of Ireland, 4 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Christopher Cox</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Christopher Cox (b.1886) to the Chief Secretary of Ireland. The letter concerns Cox&#39;s claim for damages to his shop following the 1916 Rising. He states that on 27 April the military broke into his shop and that there were soldiers billeted there until Monday morning. Cox claims that when he returned to the shop the best of his stock was gone and £3 pounds was missing. Enclosed with the letter is statement of the monetary value of the damages that were incurred to Cox&#39;s business.At this time there is no official Chief Secretary following the resignation of Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) on 3 May 1916. Birrell&#39;s resignation was a consequence of the 1916 Rising, for which he accepted responsibility. His successor, Henry Edward Duke (1855-1939), was not officially appointed until 31 July 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9774/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/382</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1556">Christopher Cox</persName>
              <date>1916-06-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1386">13 Summer Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Chief Secretary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0382_img_1640_1"  type="Letter"  url="5a70be765385a8a9d51d2e59b4501cbd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0382_img_1640_2"  type="Letter"  url="2be7fd8bef0d8600fd2f4feb85cae108.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0382_img_1640_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="d1ad8f6bbe480a271da209907dce7663.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0382_img_1640_1"/>
              ack. and say that the claim <lb/> appear to be one which should be<lb/> addressed to the <seg type="del">military authorities</seg> Major General VC of administration <lb/> Irish Command Parkgate<cb/>    13 Nth Summer St   Dear Sir    Attached please find<lb/> Claim for Damages done by<lb/> Military to shop at 158 N <lb/> King St from April 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> On 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April the <seg type="unclear">infantry</seg><lb/> broke into shop not allowing<lb/> time for doors to be opened.<lb/> I was then in the upstairs of<lb/> the house for safety. I was<lb/> delayed on the upper portion<lb/><seg type="del">of</seg><seg type="unclear">while</seg><seg type="unclear">persons</seg>in it<lb/> were fully searched &amp; when <seg type="unclear">I</seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0382_img_1640_2"/>
              was allowed to go down again<lb/> to shop. I found it was full<lb/> of soldiers also the room at<lb/> back of same; these soldiers<lb/> were billeted there until<lb/> Monday morning 29th April.<lb/> On examining my shop I found<lb/> the   best portion of stock<lb/> Tobacco. Cigarette. Sweets Groceries<lb/> etc was gone &amp; later I<lb/> discovered. that money of<lb/> Â£3 (three pounds) was taken<lb/> from a small cabinet in<lb/> my room.  As my business was a small<cb/> one &amp; under these conditions I<lb/> had to give up &amp;<lb/> friends at the above address<lb/> therefore losing my way of living<lb/> On May 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I sent a<lb/> similar claim to Police<lb/> at New Brudenell  The Â£10 represents money &amp; Stock<lb/> Â£6 Loss of Business <seg type="closer"> I am<lb/> Yours Respectfully  Christopher Cox <lb/> ToChief Secretary </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0382_img_1640_3"/>
                13 N<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Summer Street    June 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    To amt. Goods &amp; money<lb/> Â£10<lb/> Loss of Business = <hi rend="underline">6</hi><lb/> Total Â£16<lb/> Christopher Cox<lb/> At Premises<lb/> 158 N<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> King St  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>