<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3895">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 17 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-44</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3895</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-03-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1671">8th Royal Irish Fusiliers, B.E. Force, G.P.O., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2113">Melrose, Dalkey, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3895_img_3273_1"  type="Letter"  url="1cb0518ad96374db3982f892b23f86d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3895_img_3273_2"  type="Letter"  url="86d5c66640cfe8f51d4ce7e54c9ce6ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3895_img_3273_3"  type="Letter"  url="a761022260cbf0bb52aeb74f2a0c931f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3895_img_3273_4"  type="Letter"  url="a3a217a50d241557bdc7e0b57465b33e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3895_img_3273_1"/>
             J2/83 (44)   8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Royal Irish Fusiliers,<lb/>B. <seg type="unclear">A.</seg> Force.<lb/>G. P. O. London.   17/3/'16.    My dear Father,   As an old friend of mine, who had<lb/>a wonderful way of mixing things up, used to<lb/>say: It is an ill wind that blows no where! The<lb/>returning your envelope for the full address<lb/>gave me the advantage of getting two letters<lb/>from you instead of one. Nearly all my<lb/>letter have gone astray for a time, or have been<lb/><sic>delay</sic> because 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> R. I. Fusiliers may mean Royal<lb/>Inniskillings as well as Royal Irish. It was my<lb/>mistake originally. The above is the full and<lb/>correct address#: no Division or Brigade should be<lb/>put on the envelope.  I have very little news to give you this time. As<lb/>things are at present I find it is quite impossible<lb/>to do my work as I should wish, simply because<lb/>I cannot be in four places at the same time!<lb/>I have charge of a half Brigade (two regiments)<lb/>which are billeted about five miles apart; that<lb/>would not matter so much but one half of each<lb/>regiment remains in the village while the other is<lb/>up at the firing line, if I go to the dressing station 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3895_img_3273_2"/>
             to look after the wounded, the men at the base<lb/>cannot get to Confession, and vice versa. I can<lb/>only do what I can; later on things will be<lb/>better when the whole Brigade comes together, for<lb/>at present they are holding the trenches with other<lb/>troops to train them to their work.  One day is very much like another, and yet<lb/>each one is full of interest and stirring events —<lb/>it is quite delightful never to know what may<lb/>happen next. Aeroplane <sic>fights</sic> are a daily<lb/>occurrence. I believe we have got new fast<lb/>machines but the German <seg type="foreign">Fokers</seg> that I have<lb/>seen simply walk away from our men and<lb/>seem able to do what they please.  Yesterday I was watching the bombardment of an<lb/>old mill &amp; some houses, about half a mile away,<lb/>by the Germans. Their guns were so far away I<lb/>could not even hear the report, but they kept<lb/>dropping shell after shell with <sic>marvellous</sic><lb/>precision on the little mound, believing, I understand,<lb/>that we had some heavy guns there, which was<lb/>quite true but they had been removed. With<lb/>Lena's glass I could follow the whole thing<lb/>as distinctly as if I had been standing near;<lb/>I can say with all truth I was jolly glad<lb/>I was not. But now comes my part of the<lb/>story. This morning I thought I would stroll<lb/>over to the mill and take a look at<lb/>the damage done. Not much was left, as you 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3895_img_3273_3"/>
             J2/83 (45)<lb/>may imagine, while the ground all round was<lb/>ploughed up by huge shell holes, though within a<lb/>narrow radius, showing the accuracy of the enemy's<lb/>fire. I marched round for some time, when it<lb/>flashed across my mind that if the Germans thought<lb/>it worth while to bombard that spot yesterday, they<lb/>might think the same today. I thought also of<lb/>several useful maxims: A living ass is better than<lb/>something else and He who runs away will have<lb/>a chance of second innings — I turned round &amp;<lb/>started down the hill. Just as I did so I heard<lb/>the scream — the diabolical scream — of a shell coming<lb/>straight from where I was. ;This time it seemed like<lb/>Abraham's Bosom, but to my relief the beastly<lb/>thing went on and burst close to the road a<lb/>couple of hundred yards away; fortunately for me<lb/>the Germans had changed their target for the moment,<lb/>as an hour later they started shelling the mill again.  <hi rend="underline">Moral</hi>: Leave mills alone unless they have a good deep well<lb/>into which you can drop in case of necessity.<lb/>These little things give a zest to life and prevent things<lb/>becoming too monotonous, but they also turn one's<lb/>thoughts with gratitude to the good God and make<lb/>one trust still more in His loving protection.  I thought my days of French speaking were a<lb/>thing of the past but the little knowledge i have 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3895_img_3273_4"/>
             has proved of immense service to me. Very<lb/>few of the officers can make any show at all,<lb/>except by gestures, so I have to act as interpreter<lb/>and get them out of difficulties. The foreign<lb/>tongue does not bother the Tommies a bit, for<lb/>they talk away and make love to the girls as<lb/>if they had been born in France, but what<lb/>they say the Lord alone knows.  The weather has taken a turn for the better and is<lb/>now fine and warm, in fact almost too hot for<lb/>winter clothes.  I have had to write this in bits and scraps as<lb/>but I could. If I do not post it now you<lb/>may not get it for some time. <seg type="foreign">Au revoir</seg><lb/>much love to everyone.  Ever your loving son,<lb/>Willie.  I shall not forget the dear anniversary on<lb/>Sunday, though I doubt she needs our<lb/>prayers. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>