<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1785">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Moore to William Howell Davies 3 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Moore</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Sir William Howell Davies (1851-1932) a British politician. Davis held a seat in Westminster for the South Bristol district. The letter is written in the context of the death of the Chief Crown Solicitor Malachy Kelly (1850-1916). The letter begins by asking Davies for his influence to help the author&#39;s friend, who is applying for the vacant position of chief crown solicitor. The letter names the man as William Horner (b. 1878), a solicitor in London-Derry who is supported by the Attorney General John Gordon (1849-1922), the Unionist Party and would be acceptable to Nationalists also. The letter ends with the request to pass on the matter to Augustine Birrell (1850-1833), the chief secretary of Ireland, stating that Birrell would learn the status of Mr Horner through the attorney general.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/6463/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1785</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0056">Moore</persName>
              <date>1916-04-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Howell Davies </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0864">3 White Hall Court, London S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1785_img_1240_1"  type="Letter"  url="908ba40eba88b53ebf680c00b0772774.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1785_img_1240_1"/>
            <seg type="unclear">Bristol</seg>  April <hi rend="underline">3/16</hi>  <lb/>Sir W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi>. Howell Davies M.P.  3 Whitehall Court, <lb/>London SW.,    Dear Sir William   I am writing to ask you to give your kind influence <lb/>to a friend of mine who is applying for the Office of <lb/>Chief Crown Solicitor of Ireland.    My friends name is M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi>. Horner, a solicitor in <lb/> <lb/>Londonderry, and I understand he would have the <lb/>support of the Attorney General of Ireland, and the <lb/>Unionist party, and would also be acceptable to <lb/>the Nationalist party.   Would you be so good as to mention the matter to <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Birrell, who no doubt, if you asked him, would, <lb/>enquire from the Attorney General M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Horner's status, <lb/>in the profession etc.   Yours Very Faithfully   <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> Moore 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>