<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0668">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David Leighton to Millicent Tate, 27 September, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David Leighton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from David Leighton to Millicent Tate regarding the death of a mutual friend, Jim Roche. Leighton writes of issues surrounding the wills of Roche and others, including who was due funds from various estates. Leighton wishes good health for Millicent&#39;s husband, Alec, and her baby and concludes that he and Millicent are unlikely to meet due to distance. Alec C Tate served with British army in India before he married Millicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William, continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. James spent the majority of the war in India during which time the Indian Expeditionary Force was dispatched to Mesopotamia.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Tate Papers, D2859/3A/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/668</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1137">David Leighton</persName>
              <date>1916-09-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0825">Ravenswood, Co Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Millicent Tate</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1964">Glenluce, Ballycastle, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0668_img_2160_1"  type="Letter"  url="6621208e0b129c777febda9b198f697d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0668_img_2160_2"  type="Letter"  url="21949bbb5ea6ea12ac1cd15cea43ab4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0668_img_2160_3"  type="Letter"  url="b36522894c43e54877c41aaf85247df7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0668_img_2160_4"  type="Letter"  url="e9d5e17e1dc2822ef3aa5943d8f6ba5f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0668_img_2160_5"  type="Envelope"  url="f27a4905806c1305b9cc38461fe53be2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0668_img_2160_6"  type="Envelope"  url="720008a39707149e673ab0e6f283215a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0668_img_2160_1"/>
                27th.Sept.'16.   Dear Mr. Tate,   Thanks for your kind <lb/>letter of 24th.  I wish I had been at the <lb/>funeral, if only to show my <lb/>regard and respect for the brave and kind <lb/>old man. It was however almost <lb/>impossible for me to make the <lb/>journey.  As regards his affairs, I have <lb/>no status whatever, and I have no <lb/>knowledge. The only time that he <lb/> ever took me into his confidence was  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0668_img_2160_2"/>
              <lb/>at my last visit to him in August '06. <lb/>All he said was that <sic>Scottie</sic> would, at <lb/> his death, come on the <sic>S.M.T.</sic> fund <lb/> for £200 a year, and that he had, on <lb/> Jim Roche's death, fixed her allowance <lb/> at that figure, but that she had always <lb/> exceeded it. That did not surprise <lb/> me because I had some experiences of <sic>Scottie</sic> in India.  I went on to Cork, and was so <lb/> much dissatisfied with what I saw <lb/> there, that I wrote to him, rather <lb/> forcibly, about the children <seg type="unclear">8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></seg>. In <lb/>his reply he gave me some figures of <lb/><sic>Scottie's</sic> expenditure, which did as <lb/>tonish me. Naturally I surmise, <lb/>from your reference to <sic>Scottie's</sic> debts,  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0668_img_2160_3"/>
              <lb/>that the <seg type="unclear">sublime</seg> in (?) 1913, was due <lb/> to further calls upon him. With what <lb/> her second husband left, with the children's <lb/> allowance from the Queen's fund, and <lb/> with the £200 from the <sic>S.M.B.</sic> fund, <lb/> we may feel confident that <sic>Scottie</sic> is <lb/> well provided for, and that she will go <lb/> on piling up debts for the rest of her <lb/>life.  I'm sorry I cannot help you in <lb/>regard to the name of W. Robertson's <lb/>mother. <seg type="unclear">Louie</seg> told me the little I know <lb/> about her family. The <seg type="unclear">paucity</seg> of her <lb/> relations was due, I believe, to the fact <lb/> that her father, and his father were only <lb/> children, and her mother one of two. <lb/> She would be pleased that the Johnston <lb/> family get so little.  You may be quite sure that the <lb/> will will not be disputed. It was just <lb/> to leave most to Mabel.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0668_img_2160_4"/>
              I cannot clearly recollect <sic>Ballycastle</sic><lb/> I sincerely hope that the change has done <lb/> your baby good, and that she will soon <lb/> be quite well. Also that Alec will soon <lb/> be fit again. She and I have reached an <lb/> age. My trouble is <sic>stomachic.</sic>  I cannot sufficiently praise you <lb/> for sacrificing yourself as you have done, <lb/> and returning to Abbotsleigh, to help <lb/> Mabel. Now, I conclude, the executors <lb/> will attend to every matter.  Yes, I fear that we are too far <lb/> apart geographically, to be likely to meet. <lb/> If- as seems possible, my interest in Rubber <lb/> and coconuts turns out well, we would let <lb/> our house for a while - but our <seg type="unclear">sojourn</seg> would <lb/> be in Italy. Nevertheless we shall continue <lb/> to hope for a visit from you &amp; the girls. <seg type="closer"> With very kind regards, <lb/>Yours sincerely,  David Leighton. </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0668_img_2160_5"/>
                Mr Tate  Glenluce  Ballycastle  Co Antrim  Ireland.    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0668_img_2160_6"/>
               
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>