<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0483">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hubert Davis to the Secretary, Dublin Castle, 16 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hubert Davis</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Hubert Davis, writing from the Carlton Cinema, Upper Sackville Street (now O&#39;Connell Street) to Augustine Birrell (1850–1933), Chief Secretary for Ireland from January 1907 until May 1916, asking for a permit to be granted to carry a camera and take photographs in Phoenix Park, for the production of miniature postcards. Davis describes the camera in question as one manufactured by the Chicago ferrotype Co New York. According to the manufacturers, the style of the camera does not apply as a plate camera. Davis seeks permission based on advice from a solicitor in Dublin. As Ireland was under the Defense of the Realm Act (DORA), at this point in time, photography in public spaces was restricted.Birrell (1850-1933) served as the chief secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish education system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares and, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred leading to his resignation on 1 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7311/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/483</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0157">Hubert Davis</persName>
              <date>1916-04-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1170">Carlton Cinema, Upper Sackville Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Chief Secretary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0350">Chief Secretary's Office, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0483_img_1846_1"  type="Letter"  url="a4e614cfbd57c9c9bcbd197a3f696f25.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0483_img_1846_2"  type="Letter"  url="5c74f04839f15743e5233ad404d71519.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0483_img_1846_3"  type="Letter"  url="ec4854f12e2d1f6835b22651ade6646b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0483_img_1846_1"/>
              <seg type="unclear">Insp</seg> Purcell <lb/> for report <lb/> 19 April     Carlton Cinema  Upper Sackville St  Dublin    April 16 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>16     The Secretary  <hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi><hi rend="underline">Castle</hi>   Dear Sir   I am writing to <lb/> know if you will <lb/> give me a permit <lb/> to carry a oneâ <lb/><seg type="unclear">minute</seg> camera <lb/> which to take photos <lb/> while you wait <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0483_img_1846_2"/>
              at 3 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi> each same <lb/> as used at sea <lb/> side towns. <lb/> no plates are used <lb/> only miniature <lb/> postcards. I want <lb/> the permit to <lb/> use same in the <lb/> Phoenix Park. The <lb/> camera is the <lb/> manufacture of <lb/> the Chicago ferrotype <lb/> Co New York &amp; sold <cb/> through their English <lb/><seg type="unclear">house</seg> in Liverpool <lb/> They say this style <lb/> camera does not <lb/> apply as a plate <lb/> camera. I enclose <lb/> their letter you <lb/> see what they say <lb/> I have seen <lb/> a solicitor here <lb/> on the matter <lb/> and he advised me <lb/> to write you <lb/> and that you  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0483_img_1846_3"/>
              would give me a <lb/> permit. It is quick <lb/> work as you will <lb/> see by the enclosed. <lb/> the style of camera   Thanking you <lb/> in anticipation  <seg type="closer"> Yours Faithfully  Hubert Davis </seg> 1 ack <lb/> 1 Chief  <lb/> <lb/> 17/4 16 <lb/>  1 done 18/4 <lb/> 1  18/4    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>