<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6730">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard W. Hale to John Quinn, 18 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard W. Hale</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Richard W. Hale (1872-1943) to John Quinn (1870–1924), discussing Quinn’s article in the New York Times on the 13 August 1916. Hale was a lawyer and author from Boston and was partner in the Hale &amp; Grinnell law firm. John Quinn was a lawyer in New York, the son of Irish immigrants who maintained close ties with Ireland during his life through his patronage of the arts. In the letter, Hale criticises Quinn’s article that describes the unjust nature of Sir Roger Casement’s execution. Hale argues that Quinn is not viewing the situation with an impartial eye.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>John Quinn Memorial Collection, Box 7, f.4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6730</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0996">Richard W. Hale</persName>
              <date>1916-08-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1514">16 Central Street, Boston, Massachusetts, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1279">John Quinn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0945">31 Nassau Street, New York, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6730_img_None_1"  url="php0Nbur8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6730_img_None_2"  url="php7mlmt4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6730_img_0_1"/>
             Richard W. Hale<lb/>Frank W Grinnell<lb/>Roger D.Swaim  John M. Maguire<lb/>Harvey H. Bundy   Hale &amp; Grinnell,<lb/>Attorneys and Counsellors at Law,<lb/>16 Central Street, Boston, Mass   Long Distance Telephone<lb/>Fort Hill 510  Cable Address Hafis, Boston   August 18, 1916   H/jl   John Quinn, Esq<lb/>31 Nassau St.<lb/>New York City    My dear Quinn,   I have your letter of August 17th. My object in<lb/>writing about your Casement article was double. First, and<lb/>principally, to praise it. Second, to comment on it in the<lb/>direction of saying that I thought you had understood the<lb/>case against Casement looked at from the point of view of<lb/>deterrent punishment. From your letter, I feel still more<lb/>strongly that you do not see that case with an impartial eye.<lb/>The story about the diary suggests nothing but sympathy for<lb/>Casement. But how could Casement have the knowledge or the<lb/>authority to deny either of the two following statements?  That the average Irish soldier prisoner would<lb/>expect a selfish profit from doing what Casement urged<lb/>him to do.  That the German Government would look less kindly<lb/>on those who refused the appeal than on those who accepted<lb/>it.  -1- 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6730_img_0_2"/>
             J. Quinn Esq. #2  H/j l c   8-18-16   In other words, I think you see the punitive<lb/>and not the deterrent side of the British case against<lb/>Casement and that if you could grasp and take a really<lb/>tolerant point of view of the deterrent value of such<lb/>punishment, you cold make as strong a case.  I suppose your answer is that such a punishment<lb/>induces more crime than it deters. That may be true in<lb/>Ireland, let us say in the south of Ireland. But I feel<lb/>pretty sure that if the English had inflicted drastic and<lb/>deterrent punishment in Ulster, it would have deterred<lb/>both Ulster and Dublin   Yours cordially<lb/>Richard W Hale   -2- 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>