<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1159">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 24 November 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s recent conversation with Dr Murphy and Dr Dowdall. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/17-18, IJA/CHPI/54/17-18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1159</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1917-11-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0786">Bombay, India </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1159_img_3836_1"  type="Letter"  url="6ececfaae1023adf4bf5d82954f5648d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1159_img_3836_2"  type="Letter"  url="fd92f8a8d26b0dd69ef23261baa497cb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1159_img_3836_1"/>
                24 Nov. 1917.   My dear Father Provincial, P.C.   I hope to be in Capetown tomorrow, not, <lb/>unfortunately, on the way home. I shall be quite an <lb/>expert at 'doubling the Cape.' I had an interview on the <lb/>way with D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Murphy, who was consecrated in Dublin <lb/>about a year ago: at least I think it was in Dublin. <lb/>He was very interested in my Irish news I had to give <lb/>him; and in return presented me with two sermons in <lb/>French which he had preached in his cathedral.I had <lb/>about twenty of his flock on board. I met a sister of <lb/>Father Pat Barrett also in one of the convents âSister <lb/>Frances, a Loreto nun. She was under the impression that <lb/>it was Father Pat who had assis<seg type="del">s</seg>ed F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Willie Doyle at <lb/>the end. I did not undeceive her. D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Murphy is very <lb/>well liked. I was told the poor and the children are <lb/>his special care. 'The stormy winds do blow,' at present <lb/>but one expects that in these latitudes. Our ship is <lb/>steady enough as the wind is head on. I am able to <lb/>say Mass on board without any difficulty. On this <lb/>voyage I have had about seventy in Catholics among  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1159_img_3836_2"/>
              the patients. One of them named O'Keeffe was a servant <lb/>at C.W.C during 1908â9. He says he would like to be back <lb/>there again. I have given well over fifty Holy <lb/>Communions since we left port. One of our Doctors is <lb/>D<hi rend="superscript">r </hi> Dowdall â his father is or was Chairman of the <lb/>Westmeath Co. Council. He is a good fellow. When we <lb/>left, F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> OMahony was still at anchor, but I'm sure he <lb/>has had an expedition or two since then â he will be <lb/>in calmer waters too. I saw that a Father <lb/>Fitsgibbon had been wounded. I suppose it is F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> John. <lb/>It is a wonder he escaped so long. F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> MacSheahan <lb/>will have his work cut out. One of the 'patient â <lb/>officers' on board started off with a little attack on <lb/>Ireland a day or two ago â I administered two full <lb/>hours of information to him on various subjects, as a <lb/>consequence â small nationalities, scraps of paper, the <lb/>Pope, the 'Priest in politics', the Empire, <seg type="unclear">etc.</seg> all came <lb/>under review in course of the discussion.  I shall be able to write again in a week, so I <lb/>can then send my Mass list.  I recommend myself to your Reverence, and <lb/>everybodys prayers <seg type="closer"> Your Reverence's servant in Christ. <lb/>Write to Archbishop's House.<seg type="unclear">Warehouse</seg> R<hi rend="superscript">d</hi><lb/>as usual   FrancesMShaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>