<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5939">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nellie May Preston to Albert G. Woodman, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nellie May Preston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Nellie May Preston (b.1890) to her fiancé Albert G. Woodman (1891-1969) describing the impact of the Rising on the daily life of the family. The letter appears to be in two parts. The first five pages are clearly written by Nellie. It is the first letter she writes to Albert since the Rising. She details the disruption to daily life the destruction of businesses in Dublin, the curfew imposed on Dublin residents, and her fear of snipers in the city.Also enclosed with the letter is a detailed daily account of her family life during and after the Rising, from 26 April through 2 May.Albert and his four brothers fought for the British Army during the Great War. Albert served in France with the &#39;L&#39; Signal Company, part of the Royal Corps of Engineers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Joyce Timms</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5939</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0760">Nellie May Preston</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0030">Ivanhoe, 15 Lyndsay Road, Glasnevin, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arthur G. Woodman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1094">'L' Signal Company, Army Post Office S. I., British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5939_img_1892_1"  type="Letter"  url="03767ee60f82ab47b2e167cdae3f85d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5939_img_1892_2"  type="Letter"  url="e66f71a3c918a1379caf1b63418f450e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5939_img_1892_3"  type="Letter"  url="79a59565919daf2dd086cc2619de7ff3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5939_img_1892_4"  type="Letter"  url="94ae30c1464a6a4b1c3e99878496c650.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5939_img_1892_5"  type="Letter"  url="ac14da68cdbeb7af65235c4cac21227c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5939_img_1892_6"  type="Envelope"  url="10f367c3e75ff146eae8c559babb44ad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5939_img_1892_1"/>
                Ivanhoe  <hi rend="underline">Lindsay Road.</hi>     Thursday 4th    My darling Bert    Well my dear once again I can sit <lb/> down &amp; write you a letter. Thank God we are all <lb/> still alive &amp; well, although I need hardly tell you we've <lb/> been through an awful time. Oh no Bert I never want <lb/> to hear guns again. we've had quite sufficient since Easter <lb/> Monday. We are all very well up in sniping &amp; machine <lb/> Guns etc. etc. On Easter Monday Kit and I were going off <lb/> to Howth by the 10 to 3 &amp; your Father, Mother, Uncle Joe <lb/> Auntie Mag &amp; Arthur were going down by the same train <lb/> just as we were going up Liindsay Road a Priest stopped <lb/> us and said for goodness sake not to go down town as there <lb/> was terrible work going on down there and that the Sinn Feiners <lb/> had taken the Post Office. Needless to say we didn't attempt <lb/> to go down to Howth but just went up the canal for a <lb/> walk. About 1 o'clock in the morning we were wakened by <lb/> the most awful banging &amp; this went on off and on for the week. <lb/> I suppose Bert if I say too much this letter won't be <lb/> let through so like the soldiers in France we'll have to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5939_img_1892_2"/>
              Sing dumb. Suffice it to say that Sackville St from <lb/> Taaffes down to O'Connell Bridge is in ruins our old <lb/> show half of it is standing all right but the rest is in <lb/> a hopeless state &amp; we've got to start work again on Monday, <lb/> in the good half, all the staff are quite all right thank <lb/> goodness. You know my dear I came up to Ivanhoe for <lb/> three days and I'm here still and it's just a fortnight now. <lb/> Louise and her Mother only came back from Cork yesterday <lb/> They had ten days there instead of one, but as I told <lb/> Louise she was well out of it. I'm sure you were in <lb/> an awful state Bert when you didn't get any letters.<lb/> &amp; were wondering what on earth had happened. I was pitying you <lb/> &amp; wishing I could let you have a word to say we were <lb/> all right. Poor Uncle Joe's place is down and out, wouldn't <lb/> you feel awfully sorry for him after all his years work gone <lb/> for nothing. So Auntie May says if you have any have any stray halfpennies <lb/> knocking around you can send them on, she also said she <lb/> would write when things settle down a bit. Oh by the <lb/> way Kiddums has the sore throat. I hope you have quite <lb/> got rid of it by this. I do hope we'll get some letters <lb/> very soon to let us know how you are Of course <lb/> Chris hasn't turned up yet. I suppose they wouldn't <lb/> let him cross, but it's very well that he didn't come for <lb/> Easter. Well Bert dear when we all get together again <lb/> you boys won't be the only ones that can tell tales <lb/> about the war. The funny side of the business was  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5939_img_1892_3"/>
              to see all the men going for the grub and carrying <lb/> sacks of flour, bundles of rhubarb &amp; cauliflower <lb/> We were nearly sick of the sight of rhubarb, I'm <lb/> sure the men never did so much shopping in their lives <lb/> Your Mother introduced me to Howard one day, so <lb/> we had a long chat with him. I also was speaking <lb/> to his wife &amp; saw the baby. Well Bert there <lb/> was a delivery of letters to day &amp; I got your one <lb/> written on Good Friday &amp; I was very glad to hear <lb/> that the throat was better, you certainly must have <lb/> had it pretty bad. but you showed your good sense <lb/> in not smoking as it would have irritated it terribly <lb/> It was grand getting a letter again after not having <lb/> had one for just a fortnight. Oh no my dear I wouldn't <lb/> like to have to go through a week like we've just had <lb/> not for all I'd get. What absolutely got on my nerves <lb/> were the snipers as you didn't know where on earth <lb/> they were firing from you can imagine that when Kit <lb/> and I were sitting out in the garden we heard a bang <lb/> &amp; a whiz over our heads you should have seen <lb/> me doing a gallop into the house. Another evening <lb/> we were down in Uncle Joe's &amp; were sitting out in <lb/> the garden when a few whizzed by, we had the <lb/> military up as far as the top of Lindsay Road <lb/> Doyle's Corner &amp; Cabra was a pretty hot place. A <lb/> bullet came in the window of our little room off <lb/> the kitchen at home. but there was nobody in the <lb/> room at the time lucky enough. Oh I could tell <lb/> you any amount only I can't think of everything  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5939_img_1892_4"/>
              I will send you on the papers &amp; then you can judge <lb/> for yourself all that's happened You would honestly <lb/> feel inclined to cry if you saw the town &amp; especially <lb/> the G.P.O. which had been done up so beautifully. <lb/> the four walls and pillars are really all that's standing <lb/> Of course there were terrible fires in town &amp; that's what <lb/> did the most of the damage. On Easter Monday <lb/> night Percy couldn't get home from Howth he had <lb/> to stay in the Royal Hotel &amp; June couldn't get back. <lb/> from the mountains &amp; of course I was up here so <lb/> Mother &amp; the Pater were in a terrible state they weren't <lb/> so anxious about June as they thought she might have <lb/> gone to Dartmouth Villas but they didn't know where <lb/> Percy had got to &amp; of course Mother kept imagining <lb/> the worst. However, I'm thankful to say they both <lb/> turned up on Tuesday, although Percy had to walk <lb/> from Howth along with many another, as they didn't <lb/> run any trams the whole time. Some of the nights <lb/> I didn't get more than a few hours sleep as you know of <lb/> old Bert I'm not a terribly brave person. Oh I <lb/> absolutely can't tell you how thankful I am that <lb/> it's all over. We can breathe freely again now. <lb/> We've all got to be in at 7.30 &amp; as there's no <lb/> trams or noise of any kind the silence is sometimes <lb/> inclined to get on your nerves. My dear when you come <lb/> home we'll have so much to tell you about <hi rend="underline">our war</hi>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5939_img_1892_5"/>
              that we won't have time to listen to your French a/c <lb/> we were getting off too safe altogether we simply had <lb/> to have our share but we've had quite sufficient, I <lb/> can tell you. I went in to  <lb/> to day nearly all the staff were there but of course <lb/> we couldn't do anything, the men folk were trying to <lb/> get the good half into some kind of order, the place was <lb/> simply soaking in water after the Fire Brigade, a lot <lb/> of stuff was looted &amp; of course a lot damaged but <lb/> I was surprised to see such a lot of stuff intact <lb/> considering. From the G.P.O. down to the place beside <lb/> us is completely in ruins. Oh I simply couldn't <lb/> describe the look of the place to you Bert. I only <lb/> stay in my office   back here for <lb/> the rest of the day. I suppose we will have to stay <lb/> all day on Friday though. Did you hear anything about <lb/> this trouble over in France Bert? You might by <lb/> chance have heard it but I suppose the other Boys <lb/> wouldn't hear anything at all. Now dearest I'm not <lb/> going to write any more this time &amp; I hope sincerely <lb/> that this will reach you safely, as I'm sure you <lb/> are anxiously looking out for a letter. Oh yes dear <lb/> we have a great lot to be thankful for.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5939_img_1892_6"/>
                No. 75598.  Sapper A. G. Woodman  'L' Signal Company.  Army Post Office S.I.  British Expeditionary Force  <hi rend="underline">France</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>