<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0750">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 19 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender briefly discusses the bravery of General Powell in volunteering for the Air Force, the infighting among the General Staff, the progress of the fighting on the battlefield, and the work of Lillian&#39;s committee.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/318</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/750</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0750_img_2273_1"  type="NULL"  url="5406697e0b228f63f0a7c33b4c83f026.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0750_img_2273_2"  type="NULL"  url="1c608a2890d1fbae4037a013222ac61f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0750_img_2273_3"  type="NULL"  url="5406697e0b228f63f0a7c33b4c83f026.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0750_img_2273_1"/>
                June 19   My p r   Very short <seg type="unclear">comms</seg><lb/> lately but hope this will<lb/> be some amends. Many thanks<lb/> for your orders for me. I hope<lb/> they may come soon so<lb/> that I can have them in<lb/> my dug out.  What a fine old boy<lb/> Gen Powell really is in<lb/> volunteering for the Air<lb/> Service. When you write tell<lb/> him how splendid I think<lb/> it of him.  P &amp; I have been getting <lb/> on a little better lately, but<lb/> he had had beg rows with<lb/> the others which have been<lb/> hushed up partly for my <lb/> sake when I said I held myself<lb/> partly responsible. I do hope<lb/> this will be the last of such  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0750_img_2273_2"/>
              trouble now.  It is hard to understand<lb/> the Germans. Last night within<lb/> 600 yards of their lines in<lb/> the open there were hundreds<lb/> of men <sic>waggons</sic> lorries<lb/> horses &amp; mules â a terrible<lb/> but necessary risk &amp; their<lb/> guns were silent. The <lb/> noise was like Piccadilly<lb/> at 11 p m If only we<lb/> can get through tonight<lb/> equally well with only a<lb/> bit of machine gun fire I<lb/> shall be relieved in mind.  Your lists must be mounting<lb/> up &amp; I'm afraid your<lb/> committee will be over working<lb/> themselves soon so keep your<lb/> self fit &amp; look out for helpers<lb/> all round. Do not spare expense<lb/> on your health for the sake of this<lb/> Div &amp; perhaps of yours truly who<lb/> still fails to <seg type="del"> </seg><seg type="unclear">get tired of the funny</seg>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0750_img_2273_3"/>
               on first page   animal<lb/> he picked<lb/> off a<lb/> Canadian<lb/> dairy<lb/> farm <seg type="closer"> W B Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>