<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3377">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kathleen Teebay, Stafford, England to James Ryan, 1 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Teebay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.
Kathleen Teebay had come to know Ryan while he was imprisoned in Stafford detention camp and the letter was written after his release from Frongach and return to Ireland. In the letter she refers Mrs Figgis, wife of Darrell Figgis who was imprisoned in Reading after the Rising. Ryan had thanked her the help she had given to relatives visiting those imprisoned in Stafford after the Rising and response makes it is clear that she had some sympathy with the rebels.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/46</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3377</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1016">Kathleen Teebay</persName>
              <date>1916-08-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1157">41 Wolverhampton Road, Stafford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3377_img_279_1"  type="Letter"  url="f7ad5f882f4e2b00021e0406010ab381.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3377_img_279_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5b3d173f39de948b4794a6de6b2756c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3377_img_279_3"  type="Letter"  url="b017fbe33b86cbc589e62767664ee234.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3377_img_279_4"  type="Letter"  url="6baffecfa9bbc4a0241761f31012ff13.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3377_img_279_1"/>
             41 Wolverhampton Rd <lb/>Stafford   Tuesday. 1.8.16.   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Ryan,   Thanks for your <lb/>letter. I must congratulate you <lb/>on your return to Ireland. <lb/>I saw from the papers a good <lb/>many had been releasesd <lb/>but I was rather surprised <lb/>to hear you were out. You must <lb/> be very glad to be back once more. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3377_img_279_2"/>
             F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Moore had a letter from <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. O'Connell at the weekend about <lb/>the photos - he was in the other day <lb/>and he remarked how strange <lb/>it was he had not mentioned you <lb/>or Mr. Collins. So he was very <lb/>pleased when I told him about you.   M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Figgis is at present in <lb/>London. She is a splendid <lb/>correspondent and keeps us well <lb/>informed of all her doings. She <lb/>certainly must have an affinity for <lb/>railway officials, sergeants etc. as <lb/>she is now having fresh encounters <lb/>with them in London - when she <lb/>goes to see the boys arriving &amp; <lb/>departing. Her husband is having <lb/>a good time at Reading - feather <lb/>beds &amp; bunches of roses! She did
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3377_img_279_3"/>
            did not say who gave the latter. <lb/>She went down to Lewes one day &amp; would <lb/>find out the requirements of the ladies <lb/>there but was not allowed to see <lb/> them.   I am going to Ireland but <lb/>only for rather a short stay. As <lb/>far as I know at present it will <lb/>be somewhere about the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of <lb/>August, I will stay in Dublin <lb/>or near there so I hope you will <lb/>be still up as I am not going <lb/>anywhere in the vicinity of <lb/> Wexford.   Dont thank me for anything <lb/>I did. We tried to do all we could <lb/>for those who came over visiting <lb/>etc. It was the only way <lb/>we could show sympathy &amp; it
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3377_img_279_4"/>
            was so little. Besides it was <lb/>a pleasure to us as Stafford is <lb/>rather a quiet place as perhaps <lb/>you gathered from what you <lb/>saw of it.   Good bye now - hoping you are <lb/>having a thoroughly good <lb/>time now to make up for what <lb/> you have missed.   I remain, <lb/>Yours very sincerely   Kathleen <hi rend="underline">Teebay.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>