<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4281">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 13 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/219</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4281</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-13</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4281_img_3645_1"  type="Letter"  url="88730bebfe3e7f06aa50e738ab5bfceb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4281_img_3645_2"  type="Letter"  url="c77f3c01d5ac8ccbeffb2ce448f4ee9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4281_img_3645_3"  type="Letter"  url="3714adffcf52ea029723b38c62029e22.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4281_img_3645_4"  type="Letter"  url="0a1bff7c12a00552df35b487dc703f06.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4281_img_3645_1"/>
             Ap. 13   My p r   but for 1 big <lb/>compensation I really <lb/>think one could call <lb/>oneself an unlucky number <lb/>Leave has been stopped <lb/>from tomorrow &amp; I had <lb/>just really begun to think <lb/>it was coming off.   One day earlier &amp; at any <lb/>rate I should have seen <lb/>something of you, tho' <lb/>probably to be recalled.   I'm afraid some little <lb/>pink pink pearls may <lb/>be wasted for which the <lb/>German Service are suppose <lb/>responsible; there were <lb/>very nearly some brown
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4281_img_3645_2"/>
            <lb/>mind splashes about too <lb/>last night when I went to <lb/>bed. However both of us <lb/>are out for work, &amp; to <lb/>earn repose later so we <lb/>mustn't grumble.    I am a little afraid of <lb/>Edmund's visit to Sir E. <lb/>The former is sometimes <lb/>a little provincial in his <lb/>vision, as if the West of <lb/>England contained 1/3rd of <lb/>our population &amp; I am <lb/>very nervous lest he may say <lb/>something to Sir E about <lb/>me with the Kindest intentions.   You know exactly how <lb/>I feel about this.  Richardson came back from
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4281_img_3645_3"/>
            <lb/>leave yesterday looking a <lb/>new man. It was real <lb/>joy to see him. He came <lb/>back in the General's car <lb/>from Boudergen as have he <lb/>had come to the dentist <lb/>&amp;apparently talked of <lb/>me. I fear he may <lb/>have led the Gen' to <lb/>think I am a bit <lb/>disappointed about myself.   I was but if Place does <lb/>will for the Dir I shall <lb/>be glad in the end.   I am getting more recon- <lb/>siled to the vision of a <lb/>quiet life later with a <lb/>p r, with a view that <lb/>we have done our part &amp; <lb/>need not bother about
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4281_img_3645_4"/>
            <lb/>relative results &amp; ruvands.    As a matter of fact <lb/>leave might have done us <lb/>both good &amp; our work <lb/>too, but Richardson says <lb/>I am looking much better <lb/>-rather I fear as a result <lb/>of the expectation of <lb/>seeing a p r-.   He said that his <lb/>wife had wanted to see <lb/>you. I think she is <lb/>waiting for an invita- <lb/>tion- <lb/>18 Park Avenue <lb/>Bedford.    Rex's name is not in <lb/>the Gazette yet. I expect <lb/>he too is blocked. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>