<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1504">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Vane of Hutton to John Dillon M.P., 3 October 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane (1861-1934) to John Dillon (1851-1927). Vane was in command of Portobello Barracks during the Rising. He says that he should have obtained an important command on foot of his participation in an attack on the rebels at the South Dublin Union, for which re received a commendation from Colonel Maconchie. Instead, he believes, because he reported the murder of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington and others, he was punished by being thrown out of the army. He feels that in reporting the murders he has done a service to Ireland and England by exposing &#39;villainy in high places&#39; and now he wants the National Party to get him his rights. He encloses a statement of his case.Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane was a British officer in command of Portobello Barracks. When he learned about activities of Captain J.C.Bowen-Colthurst he reported the matter to his superiors but, sensing a cover-up, he went to London and reported to Lord Kitchener and Maurice Bonham Carter, Private Secretary to the Prime Minister. Although Bowen-Colthurst was court-martialed and found guilty, Vane was that he was &#39;retired&#39; from the military for his actions. John Dillon was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs.Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, TCD MS6837/27/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1504</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1025">Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1916-10-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0781">National Liberal Club, Whitehall Place, London S.W., England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2017">2, North Great George St, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1504_img_962_1"  type="Envelope"  url="5bca07a39f2348fbda775917407e0ea8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1504_img_962_2"  type="Letter"  url="c1f77b9f0d5fcafe6044b6883c0998b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1504_img_962_3"  type="Letter"  url="7ad4e6fa3230abf9362f5d25d1af0fa3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1504_img_962_4"  type="Letter"  url="8cef73c860b889d543dbdd49f7535f4c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1504_img_962_5"  type="Letter"  url="f155b784e55bafe0ac1d663654ccc2e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1504_img_962_6"  type="Letter"  url="f5be9fd8c0ab0a66c82e8539ebb7abfd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1504_img_962_1"/>
                TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. C/O 'ENELSEE WHITALL LONDON'  TELEPHONE N <hi rend="superscript">O</hi>  3700 VICTORIA  4 LINES  NATIONAL LIBERAL CLUB  WHITEHALL PLACE S.W.    5 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October 1916    My Dear Mr Dillon   You know my case now and there never <lb/> was in the world a more clear one. <lb/>On the report of the Brigadier for my action <lb/> on the 27 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April, I am prepared to show that <lb/> any officer would have obtained an important <lb/>Command. But I reported the Skeffington <lb/> murders, and so I was punished by being <lb/> thrown out. I did good service to Ireland and <lb/>England but exposed villainy in high places <lb/>and was dismissed. I was in fact dismissed <lb/>because I saved some innocent Irish lives. <lb/>I send you my reply to the W.O. letter of the 3 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi><lb/> and I consider that it is really up to the <lb/>Nationalist Party to get me my rights. <lb/> I think that as I have suffered in the cause  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1504_img_962_2"/>
              the righting of one should be embodied <lb/>in your Party Programme <sic>for for</sic> good or <lb/>evil my action is connected with the whole <lb/>National case.   I enclose also a copy of my case, as before <lb/> sent to you. <seg type="del">in</seg> <seg type="closer"> I remain <lb/>Yours very truly   Francis Vane of Hutton </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1504_img_962_3"/>
              <hi rend="underline">A CASE FOR INQUIRY </hi><lb/>ADMITTED FACTS AND DOCUMENTS <lb/><hi rend="underline">IN CASE OF MAJOR SIR FRANCIS VANE, Bt.</hi>  I was training men of Royal Munster Fusiliers from October <lb/>1914, (when the Battalion was raised) to October 1915, the eve of <lb/> the departure of the battalion for the front.   March 1915. (six months after I joined) General Parsons <lb/>reported officially <hi rend="underline">Major Sir Francis Vane is an energetic officer <lb/> with a happy knack in dealing with and training recruits </hi>. (This is on record and the copy can be seen.)   30th April 1915. Lieutenant Colonel H.F.Williams wrote me a <lb/>Letter to show at War Office <hi rend="underline">Major Sir F. Vane has been training <lb/> with this battalion for seven months and has worked most zealously <lb/>never sparing himself in very trying weather </hi>. (this letter can <lb/> be seen.)   End of March 1915. I made a recruiting speech in which I <lb/>declared myself a nationalist obtaining 50 recruits. For this I <lb/> was severely reprimanded by General Parsons by letter in violent <lb/> terms. He saying that <hi rend="underline">on account of this speech I was unfit to <lb/>command men. </hi> I strongly protested that against this reprimand and <lb/>demanded a court martial. This was refused.   In October 1915. General Parsons wrote an unfavourable <lb/>report on me in which such irrelevant terms as <hi rend="underline">very conceited, a <lb/>crank </hi>, etc., occurred.   On this the Army Council called upon me to resign which I <lb/> refused to do demanding a court of inquiry and I had a question <lb/> put in the house by Mr. Charles Duncan.   <hi rend="underline">Between November, 1915 and January 1916, the three officers <lb/> who had reported against me, General Parsons, Brigadier General <lb/> Buchanan and Colonel H.F.Williams, were removed from their command. </hi>  <hi rend="underline">January 15th, 1916. Without my consent I was gazetted out <lb/>of the army. </hi>  21st March, 1916. The officer commanding the men whom I had  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1504_img_962_4"/>
              <lb/>trained who had been three months at the front reported to <lb/> me in these terms.   <hi rend="underline">The men are absolutely indifferent to shell fire, there is <lb/>no crime of crumbling. I know that I am right in saying that <lb/> this is entirely due to the early training and the spirit <lb/> of discipline and espirit de corps which you always were at such <lb/>PAINS IN INSPIRITING INTO THEM </hi>  31st, March 1916. Through exertions of Rt.Hon.H.J. <lb/> Tennant I was regazetted as recruiting officer in Ireland. 24th April, 1916. I volunteered and was gazetted for the rebellion.   27th April, 1916. I took a party of men to the relief of <lb/>the munition convoy <hi rend="underline">and commanded seven officer and 92 men <lb/>in the successful attack on the South Dublin Union. </hi>  8th May, 1916. I took a party of men to the relief of the munition convoy <hi rend="underline">and commanded seven officers and 92 men in the successful attack on the South Dublin Union.</hi> 8th May, 1916. Colonel Maconchie, C.B. C.I.E. D.S.O., <lb/> commanding the 178th Brigade who witnessed the engagement, <lb/> reported to General Maxwell <hi rend="underline">Major Sir Francis Vane rendered <lb/>valuable assistance and his dispositions were excellent. I <lb/>recommend him for mention in despatches &amp; that he be sent back <lb/> to his regiment. </hi> 15th May, 1916. General L.B.Friend wrote <lb/> to me, ' <hi rend="underline">I hasten to inform you that your conduct on the 27th <lb/> April, as reported by Colonel Maconchie, will be brought before <lb/> General Sir John Maxwell now commanding the forces in Ireland, <lb/> together with other recommendations of a similar kind. </hi>'   3rd May, 1916. I reported personally to Lord Kitchener the <lb/> murders of <hi rend="underline">Messrs Skeffington, Dickson &amp; McIntyre</hi> by Captain <lb/> Colthurst and was commended for reporting.   26th May, 1916. I received orders to leave Ireland and <lb/> report in London for General Maxwell.   30th June, 1916. I received from W.O. the following communi- <lb/>cation :- <hi rend="underline">In view of the report of the general officer command- <lb/>ing in chief of the forces in Ireland, you will be relegated <lb/> to unemployment &amp; to request that you will report the last day <lb/> you performed duty. </hi>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1504_img_962_5"/>
                John Dillon Esqe M.P.   2 North Great George Street   Dublin Ireland.     
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1504_img_962_6"/>
                blank back of envelope   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>