<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1514">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alice Schmutz, 28 October 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alice Schmutz</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter was written by Alice Schmutz and enclosed with Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington’s letter of the same date to John Dillon MP. Mrs. Schmutz gives her version of the visits to her house by detectives between 9 and 19 October 1916 and says that she cannot understand why Sgt. Megahey denies all of this. This note was enclosed in a letter dated 28 October 1916 from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington to John Dillon MP. This letter also survives.Alice Schmutz was the landlady of Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, a suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916) was on the streets trying to muster a civilian force to prevent looting during the Rising. On 25 April 1916, Skeffington, and two others, pro-British journalists, Thomas Dixon and Patrick McIntyre, were arrested by Captain J.C. Bowen-Colthurst (1880-1966), an Anglo-Irish officer of the Royal Irish Regiment. On 26 April all three were summarily executed by firing squad at Portobello Barracks.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, Ms. 6837/32/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1514</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0738">Alice Schmutz</persName>
              <date>1916-10-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1322">43 Moyne Road, Ranelagh, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1514_img_972_1"  type="Letter"  url="c2e631605e84f48c0ae10e48836037c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1514_img_972_2"  type="Letter"  url="c392367e8f08160d0694a6a24978ee0c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1514_img_972_1"/>
                43 Moyne Road,  Ranelagh  Co. Dublin    Oct. 28.16   Dear Sir/    With reference to a letter Mrs Skeffington <lb/><seg type="del">which</seg> gave me to read  (Mr Dukes safely -Parliament)  I fear you have <lb/> been misinformed about the real facts of the case.   <hi rend="underline">On Oct 11th</hi> Constable Devine came to my house and asked <lb/> me if I was aware of the regulations with regard to <lb/> registering lodgers, I told him I was , he produced a <lb/>book of rules and regulations and showed me a paragraph <lb/> in it; he then said he would like to see the forms <lb/> I showed him two, one for M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington &amp; one for her <lb/>little boy; when he read them he asked me why <lb/><hi rend="underline">No's 10. 11 and 12</hi> were not filled in, and I told him <lb/> none of my lodgers ever filled in those numbers as I <lb/>thought - they referred to aliens he told me I made a <lb/> great mistake 'as I would be responsible for her <lb/>address, I referred him to M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffingtons Father <lb/>Darill Sheehy Esq. he then asked who received <lb/> her letters and then asked for M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffingtons <lb/>sister's name and address which I gave him and <lb/> he took <hi rend="underline">down notes in his note book</hi>  On the same evening I went to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1514_img_972_2"/>
              the Rathmines Police Station and saw Sergt Megahey <lb/> and told him what happened; he told me if I <lb/>ever heard about M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington or heard where she <lb/> was I could keep the address, he also told me that <lb/><hi rend="underline">'if a question did arise <hi rend="underline">as to her whereabouts'</hi></hi> I would be held responsible.   <hi rend="underline">On Oct 16th</hi> Sergt Megahey came to my house himself and <lb/>asked me if I had heard anything further and I told <lb/>him I had not. He asked me if there was any furniture of hers in my house.   <hi rend="underline">On Oct 19th</hi> Mrs Skeffington returned home unexpectedly <seg type="del">arrived at my home</seg><lb/>through family trouble. I then sent <seg type="del">for</seg> to Sergt Megahey and <lb/>told him M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington was with me, thinking it was <lb/> necessary on account of their recent enquiries. When Sergt Megahey called in person &amp; made further enquiries. <lb/>Why Sergt Megahey denies all this I cannot understand, and <lb/>a Sergt Hearon also called <seg type="del">also</seg>  (between Oct11th and Oct 16th)   and said he wanted to see <lb/> M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington privately and also asked for her address.   <hi rend="underline">On Oct 9th</hi> Constable Devine called with reference to my <lb/> permit - I would also like to state that my Father is a <lb/>retired member of the R I Constabulary,I have also (2) two <lb/>brothers in France since the beginning of the war, and <lb/>what would be my object to bring myself under the <lb/>notice of the Police if I had not been annoyed by <lb/>them?   Hoping you will give my statement your careful <lb/> investigation.  <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/>Faithfully Yours    Alice. <hi rend="underline">Schmutz</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>