<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5307">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Earls to the Staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast 1 March, 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Earls</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Enclosed is a letter from Captain Francis C. Forth to the staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast. The letter was written a fortnight before his death and expresses, &#34;earnest hope that you may each and all be blessed with abundant health and every prosperity&#34;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5307</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0494">John Earls</persName>
              <date>1919-03-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">the Staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5307_img_None_1"  url="1819b8f2358db3e2ee5a335ad407a9df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5307_img_None_2"  url="7d62fe39d2d29d17fec84fe0a5abb868.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5307_img_None_3"  url="8556a4cda47a3913940565ae5d72a734.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5307_img_0_1"/>
             Telephone No. 1168  Principal   <seg type="unclear">FRA. C. FORTH. FRCScI</seg>   Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast.    1st March, 1919.    Dear Sir, (or Madam)   About a fortnight before his death, when his illness  had taken a marked turn for the worse, the late Principal wrote  a letter setting out his feelings towards his colleagues on the  Staff of the Municipal Technical Institute and requested me to  have a copy forwarded, after his death, to every member of the  Staff.  In handing the letter to me he asked me to say that  he realised that it was a very imperfect expression of the  kindly feelings which he entertained towards the members of the  Institute Staff and hoped that you would accept it and supple-  ment it accordingly.   Yours faithfully,    J.Earls.    Vice-Principal.   Enclo: 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5307_img_0_2"/>
              Ravenswood, B E L F A S T.      February, 1919.    To    My dear Colleagues and friends of all and     every grade on the Staff of the     Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast.   On looking back over a fairly long connection (now over  eighteen years duration) with the Scheme of Technical Instruction  in Belfast, nothing I think impresses one more than the quite  remarkable developments that have taken place i technical instruc-  tion in the city.  The vigour of the movement generally, the strenuous  efforts of the students, often exerted under great difficulties  due to business and home conditions, the devotion of the Staff to  their duties whatever those were, have all been outstanding  features of our Institute and its operations.  It is to testify to those apects of our Institute and  to the cordial co-operation with the management which all these  imply that I am writing you this brief note of farewell.  It is a great satisfaction to me to be permitted to tell  one and all how thoroughly I have appreciated the part you have  taken in building up our great organisation.  There have, of course, been times of stress and strain  in the Institute as there must inevitably b wherever change,  development and advancement are taking plcace, but I have always  hoped, and indeed believe, that such stress and strain passed away  with the conditions that gave rise to them, and that our work  proceeded on improved lines better, certainly not worse,  for the testing.  To 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5307_img_0_3"/>
             To you my dear Colleagues I send my most cordial  good wishe with the expression of the earnest hope that you  may each and all be blessed with abundant health and every  prosperity. May your association with the Municipal  Technical Institute be ever a happy one, and may the Institute  maintain in your hands that position which we have all for years  striven to secure for it, namely that of the front rank in the  Technical Institutes of the United Kingdom.   With renewed expressions of my good will and regard,    I sign myself,    sincerely and affectionately Yours,    F. C. FORTH.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>