<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5290">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to Elizabeth Tyrrell, 22 August 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

Summary of the present letter:

Letter from Willie to his mother. William requests new underwear as his are full of holes.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5290</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-08-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5290_img_None_1"  url="c5b4221cf69c22d09345572b545af4f2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5290_img_None_2"  url="67d8e0850931dff95a3b906401a1714f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5290_img_0_1"/>
              22<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> </hi>August 1917    My dearest Mamy   When I write to you so often you<lb/>cannot expect long letters + what is<lb/>more if you did expect them you<lb/>would not get them as there is absolutely<lb/>not a word of news.  I discovered today much to my distress<lb/>that all my cotton drawers are almost<lb/>non-existent + I am not sufficient<lb/>of a tailor to make them return to their<lb/>former state so if there are any old<lb/>ones <seg type="del">b</seg> about that are not all in <seg type="unclear">holes</seg><lb/>please send them on to me. That is<lb/>really the only exciting news. I had<lb/>a long letter yesterday from Mr. B<lb/>+ also one from Daddy which I was<lb/>delighted to get. I am very sorry you<lb/>are getting flooded out now. It is just<lb/>what we got the first week of August. Out<lb/>here the weather has quite reformed and 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5290_img_0_2"/>
             is much too hot now.  No news but will write<lb/>again tomorrow probably.  With love from   Your most <seg type="unclear">eff</seg> Son,<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>