<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0298">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Ahern, 29 July 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Ahern</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent along with a petition for the reprieve of Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). William Ahern, an Irish father, farmer, and stone cutter of County Meath, is upset over England&#39;s recent executions of his fellow Irish countrymen. He claims he had two of his nine sons in the army, but others refused to join, due to England&#39;s recent actions. He warns England will incite a full rebellion in Ireland and also that England will not get any more of his sons.Sir Roger Casement was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. Casement believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany. He spent eighteen months in Germany, arriving first as an envoy of Irish-American leaders, attempting to encourage Germany to support Irish separatist aspirations by providing arms. Casement succeeded in securing limited German support but his attempt to form a brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps to fight against Britain was largely unsuccessful. When it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15, Ms. 13,088/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/298</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1296">William Ahern</persName>
              <date>1916-07-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1489">Ross Mountnugent, County Meath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Madam</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0298_img_1516_1"  type="Letter"  url="06bd65fa7bfd8ea1c2fc344f7a3abb47.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0298_img_1516_2"  type="Letter"  url="2f0baac2da60c48b8adb555aa0b83814.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0298_img_1516_3"  type="Letter"  url="60c97bc56cd752be5c818eb147c981de.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0298_img_1516_1"/>
                Ross, Mountnugent  Co. Meath  Ireland    July 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   Dear Madam,    forwarding <lb/> enclosed petition — <lb/> I beg to state that <lb/> I have a son a 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/> Lieut. in the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Leinsters. <lb/> 2 <seg type="unclear">nine</seg> of my sons <lb/> refused to join the <lb/>army owing to the <lb/> wholesale executions &amp; <lb/> murders of my poor <lb/> misguided fellow Country men <lb/> in Dublin. To my <lb/>mind and I know my  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0298_img_1516_2"/>
              Country men well — <lb/> better than any Englishman <lb/>does. The government <lb/> want to drive the <lb/>Irish into open revolt <lb/> - and damp the ardour <lb/>of our brave sons at <lb/> the front . If Roger <lb/> Casement is hanged, <lb/><hi rend="underline">England will get no more <lb/> of my sons</hi> — and I have <lb/> 9 — and I will be heartily <lb/> sorry that a son of mine <lb/> should fight &amp; die for <lb/> vindictive England  I may say that I am in favour of the Allies <lb/> &amp; have spoken in several <lb/> recruiting platforms <hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">tick</seg></hi> <seg type="closer"> Yours respectfully  William Ahern J.P. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0298_img_1516_3"/>
              My son 2 cousins and <lb/>4 nephews — 17 of my <lb/> workmen are in the <lb/>army— all joined since <lb/>the war began — and <lb/>all because they believed <lb/>it was in Ireland's best <lb/>interests —I may say <lb/> that there is not a drop <lb/>of blood in my veins <lb/>but Fenian blood and <lb/>my wife is the daughter <lb/>of a Fenian — we have <lb/> 14 children —what does <lb/>England want? Does <lb/>she want us to rear a <lb/>new generation of rebels? <lb/>She lies in her own hands <lb/>W.A.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>