<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0119">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to Mary Martin, 21 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Marie Martin (1892–1975) to her mother Mary Martin. In the letter Mary describes a letter she had received from a Mrs. Gartlan, going on to discuss a new job Gerald has received. She goes on to write she has written to her uncle Frank Martin (b. 1870) and that she is writing to A. Maysie on this day. Marie had been in touch with a doctor from London who has given her advice about Frank Martin&#39;s complaint i.e. illness, which Marie describes. The letter goes on to acknowledge a letter written by Gerald, whom she notes though the world of her brother Charles (1895-1915), who died the previous December in the Great War.Marie was born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the outbreak of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Medical Missionaries of Mary, B/F/1/64/1916/09/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/119</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-09-21</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1575">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0119_img_1203_1"  type="Letter"  url="c11122359f1d9e842179f1abcd75660b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0119_img_1203_2"  type="Letter"  url="a5928aa9434c1aeb38a744052f0e1800.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0119_img_1203_3"  type="Letter"  url="6dd8585e21397b94abdbcbc6cb6b2d87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0119_img_1203_4"  type="Letter"  url="27842dc6b5f92ef0e5e724e71b16a50c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0119_img_1203_1"/>
              B/F/1/64    21.9.16   My very dearest Mother   <sic>Ihad</sic> the <sic>rippiest</sic><lb/> post yesterday, 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi> of all your <lb/> very nice letter with all the home <lb/> news &amp; the inclosure from Mrs <lb/><sic>Garttan</sic> &amp; then <sic>Ihad</sic> a very <lb/> nice long letter from Gerald <lb/> telling me his news, I am just <lb/> delighted and <sic>things</sic> he deserves <lb/> everything, it is splendid for <lb/> Mrs Garttan to know he is <lb/> fairly safe for some time. <lb/> He seems very hard worked <lb/> but <sic>Ithink</sic> likes the job, I <lb/> wonder if he minded having the old Batt.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0119_img_1203_2"/>
              I wrote to Uncle Frank yesterday <lb/> but intend writing to A. Maysie <lb/> to-day &amp; enclosing <sic>a</sic> address <lb/> of a Dr in London which was <lb/> given to me by my M. O. <lb/> who is extremely <sic>cleaver</sic> &amp; <lb/> has made a great study <lb/> of Uncle F. <sic>complain</sic>, he <lb/> says it <sic>arrises</sic> from some <lb/> septic <sic>absortion</sic> which is the <lb/> first thing that must be <lb/> treated &amp; <sic>remove</sic>. Then <sic>ofcourse</sic><lb/> he says dieting &amp; injections <lb/> are all very good but when <lb/> it has got to U. F stage <lb/> each joint must be treated <lb/> for it self &amp; that is what <lb/> this man is so good at <lb/> as well as <sic>an</sic> good <sic>allround</sic>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0119_img_1203_3"/>
              man. He has done wonderful <lb/> things for some of his patients <lb/> Captain <seg type="unclear">Hunt</seg> is consulting Phy: <lb/> at Guys London so must be <lb/> fairly good, certainly he <lb/><sic>seem</sic> marvelous the way he <lb/> has worked over these Gas Case &amp; the results.  <sic>Iam</sic> glad to hear Tommy <lb/> is keeping very well. <lb/><sic>it</sic> is too bad about <lb/> Dicko.  Is it true Charlie has been <lb/> awarded the D S. O. Distinquished Service Order awarded to officers Gerald <lb/> saw it in the Downside <lb/> record, do let me know <lb/> also send me a paper if  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0119_img_1203_4"/>
              you have one of where he is <lb/> mentioned in dispatchesâ <lb/> Gerald did write such a nice <lb/> letter about poor Charlie he <lb/> thought <sic>a</sic> world of him. <lb/> Now <sic>Imust</sic> close as I <lb/>am writing this on duty. <seg type="closer"> With fondest love <lb/>Your ever loving  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>