<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5464">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Fitzgerald to Michael Gorman, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Michael Gorman was one a large Catholic family living at a farm in Ballinalug, County Laois (then Queen’s County). Susan Fitzgerald (d. 1980) was one a Church of Ireland family living in Raheenahone House near Stradbally, County Laois, also in the Slieve Bloom mountains. At the time the letter was written they were involved in a courtship but owing to the religious difference the love affair had to be kept secret. Eventually both were in Dublin: he in the Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin (where he eventually became Professor of Agricultural Botany and Biochemistry) and she as a volunteer nurse in the Royal Hospital in Baggot Street. They eventually went to London to marry.
The letter was written after Susan had arrived in Dublin as part of the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a voluntary group established to provide nursing to wounded British army soldiers. She refers to Michael as a &#39;horrid cod&#39; for not coming to see her and asks that he visit tomorrow.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Michael Gorman</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5464</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1259">Susan Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0451">27 Lower Mount Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Michael Gorman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1251">Albert Agricultural College, Glasnevin, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1980</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5464_img_496_1"  type="Letter"  url="7c5668924ebbe0383bcba9f9301ed62a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5464_img_496_2"  type="Envelope"  url="442c52531137557069ef2ec5c2414738.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5464_img_496_3"  type="Letter"  url="71be81b1476e30ed8e2dcb4c13870357.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5464_img_496_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">27 Lr. Mount Street</hi>   Dearest Mickie   You are a horrid <lb/>cod not to have come <lb/>down on Thursday &amp; <lb/>I intended going on <lb/>Friday &amp; spend the <lb/>day looking out <lb/>for you   <lb/>come down tomorrow <lb/>no matter how wet <lb/>Im drenched at <lb/>present   Love   Sue  <lb/>Come to Mount Street
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5464_img_496_2"/>
             M.J. Gorman Esq <lb/>Albert College <lb/>Glasnevin <lb/>Dublin 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5464_img_496_3"/>
             IF USED FOR TRANSMISSION TO ANY PLACE ABROAD TO WHICH THE 1d. RATE <lb/>OF LETTER POSTAGE DOES NOT APPLY, THE ADDITIONAL POSTAGE REQUIRED <lb/>SHOULD BE PREPAID BY MEANS OF ADHESIVE POSTAGE STAMPS. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>