<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5763">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 19 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancee Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June and the letters were written between them during that period. He lived in Dublin, she lived in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. He tells how he &#34;had his eye on her&#34; for a long time but waited until she was old enough. Throughout the series of letters you can see how their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters and how her confidence grows.
The series is not complete; it is interrupted by visits to each other’s homes and by obviously missing letters. They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child, my father. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him: this explains their survival. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats, so that she ended up quite comfortable off!
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him, trying to demand he be carried in to meetings. 
Neither May nor James were politically active though, like many in the Civil Service, James was obviously somewhat activated, learning Irish, probably Gaelic League, and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in it. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
A very short letter, apologise for delay, looking forward to his visit</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5763</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2073">Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5763_img_863_1"  type="Letter"  url="9431baa5927e32b3c21e64e3d0c9c34f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5763_img_863_2"  type="Letter"  url="fedd8db6a562e6f4695751f89281eb0e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5763_img_863_1"/>
              My dear James. <lb/>I am awfully sorry you were disappointed this morn<lb/>but as you will see It was not my<lb/>fault I wrote yesterday &amp; got no<lb/>chance to post. I am going to Mullingar<lb/>now &amp; I will post my self- I don’t<lb/>mean I’ll put myself in the<lb/>box but I’ll put the letter I have  no  <lb/>extra news except how delighted<lb/>Louis is with himself says he is<lb/>just as happy as James Finn ever was<lb/>Johnnie C. is getting very very low<lb/>in himself the first bad signs he has<lb/>ever shown so that he is taking a lot of<lb/>the pleasure out of Louis’s engagement<lb/>for Mrs S I am going to see about<lb/>that costume piece perhaps I might see<lb/>something I would like better. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5763_img_863_2"/>
             I suppose we can expect you by the<lb/>late train Thursday no chance of your<lb/>mother coming with you I suppose<lb/>I have no news at all so good-bye<lb/>I hope you will excuse me for disappointing<lb/>you &amp; excuse this scribble too<lb/><lb/> Very best &amp; warmest love<lb/>From your loving<lb/>May<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>