<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0564">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. Welby to Sir Robert Chalmers, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Alfred Cholmeley Earle Welby</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Alfred Cholmeley Earle Welby (1849 – 1937) to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 – 1938), the under-secretary for Ireland. Welby writes in acknowledgement of a former correspondence informing the Royal Patriotic Fund Corporation that letters patent have passed the Great Seal of Ireland appointing the Right Hon. Viscount Massereene and Ferrard, Algernon Skeffington (1873 - 1952), to be His Majesty&#39;s Lieutenant for the County of Antrim.In 1916, Welby was serving as secretary of the Royal Patriotic Fund Corporation. The Royal Patriotic Fund Corporation, also known as the Royal Pat, was a charitable body set up by royal warrant in the United Kingdom during the Crimean War (1853 – 1856). It provided assistance to the widows, orphans and other dependents of members of the armed forces. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13142, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13142</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/564</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1546">Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Alfred Cholmeley Earle Welby</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1900">17 Waterloo Place, London, England </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0564_img_1953_1"  type="Letter"  url="7dbb1b5b17ffc7c7a07b4e793fd238a3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0564_img_1953_1"/>
                17 Waterloo Place,  London S.W.    31st July, 1916   Sir   I beg to acknowledge receipt of your letter of <lb/>the 29th instant, No. 12711, informing the Royal Patriotic <lb/>Fund Corporation that Letters Patent, bearing date 9th June <lb/>1916, have passed the Great Seal of Ireland appointing the <lb/>Right Hon. Viscount Massereene and Ferrard to be His Majesty's <lb/>Lieutenant for the County of Antrim  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   A. Welby  Lt. âColonel. <lb/>Secretary.   The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>