<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0687">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 11 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary. Davidson writes to his mother that he would prefer to be in the trenches than their current location as the accommodation was better. He mentions that he was ill from what he thought was bad food. He reminds her that parcels from home are very welcome.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/687</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0687_img_2179_1"  type="Letter"  url="70343a173172bd7fd90fd3f56d0e80cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0687_img_2179_2"  type="Letter"  url="b0039e37645efb7f997bba3ca8214c99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0687_img_2179_3"  type="Envelope"  url="36b0ee2abc2e78880ad00240c88639d6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0687_img_2179_1"/>
                11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Jan. 1916   My dearest mother —   we are now back in <lb/> our old quarters &amp; what a dreary spot it is <lb/> compared with the place we left. We arrived <lb/> on Saturday &amp; were told we should find that <lb/> the previous Division had carried out all <lb/> kinds of improvements but of course as we <lb/> quite expected, practically nothing had been done <lb/> in this direction.   There is a very big scheme <lb/> now on foot to improve all the billeting areas <lb/> so as to make them more comfortable for the <lb/> men — for instance repairing buildings, constructing <lb/> wash houses, drying rooms, incinerators, etc etc. <lb/> The regiments are therefore being largely employed <lb/> on this work &amp; if it is not exactly soldiering it <lb/> is a welcome change to the continual training. <lb/> Machine Gunmen &amp; Grenadiers however have <lb/> to continue at their own special work — I rather <lb/> wish it was otherwise as it would be a pleasant <lb/> change to be turned on to something new.   You <lb/> have no idea how deadly dull it is here. <lb/> Imagine what it would be like to be in a <lb/> little village about the size of Portaferry, with <lb/> no railway near at hand &amp; away from the <lb/> sea.   When we came here for the first time  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0687_img_2179_2"/>
              <lb/>it did not seem so bad but to return here <lb/> after being in a good area is very disagreeable — <lb/> we should all have much <sic>prefered</sic> going back to <lb/> the trenches.    The parcel from Thompsons — I <lb/>mean Malcolmsons — arrived all right &amp; also one <lb/> from Pattersons &amp; I have just been told there is <lb/> a small wood box for me in the Bde. office which <lb/> is probably the one with apples from home. Thanks <lb/> ever so much for all.    Was so glad to hear from your last <lb/> letter that Kathleen is getting along all right though I <lb/> am sure it must be very tedious for her that the <lb/> progress is so slow.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0687_img_2179_3"/>
               On Active Service<lb/> Rcd 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January/16<lb/>  Mrs. S. C Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  Ireland   JS Davidson   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>