<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4398">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to her aunt, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers; D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4398</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0181">3rd London General Hospital, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4398_img_3751_1"  type="Letter"  url="aaae9035671599710fd708416a0cb8a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4398_img_3751_2"  type="Letter"  url="3fac90c1d19eac75701d731d4f7737f9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4398_img_3751_3"  type="Letter"  url="388b12919d727254978a39e0c3f7405a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4398_img_3751_1"/>
             3rd London General Hospital <lb/>SW.   1915   Dear Auntie B   Thanks awfully for sending the <lb/>plants, I have planted them in the hut <lb/>garden, and I do hope they will do <lb/>well, so far they look quite perky. <lb/>One of the patients takes a great interest <lb/>in my gardening, he can't help much <lb/> as he can only use one hand, by he <lb/>thinks his advice very valuable and <lb/>tells me exactly what I should do. <lb/>Even on the wettest days, he solemnly <lb/>fills the watering pot and insists on <lb/>my coming out to water the plants - <lb/>when I tell him the ground is wet
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4398_img_3751_2"/>
            <lb/>enough, he shrugs his <seg type="del">soldiers</seg>shoulders and <lb/>gets quite sulky. He presented me with <lb/>3 large clumps of dahlia roots the other <lb/>day , which I suspect he must have stolen <lb/>from some place else, and told me they <lb/>had flowers as big as two plates.    We have a few patients at present <lb/>that the war office has told the <lb/>colonel to close down some of the huts <lb/>and dismiss some of the staff, so <lb/>perhaps I may get a holiday. I <lb/>would rather like to come home now, <lb/>and go out to France with Emma <lb/>a little later.   Nise is a nice Lutton girl here, a <lb/>cousin of the Wicksteeds. I had a letter <lb/>from M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Wicksteed last week, and she <lb/>says Justine is to be married quite soon.    Thanks for the cuttings of the poems, <lb/>I like Katherine Tynan's very much. It <lb/>is a pity <seg type="unclear">maunsel</seg> has failed, I am <lb/>sorry for poor M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Roberts as I think <lb/>he is a real book lover, and brought all <lb/>his <seg type="del">books</seg> books out so well -    It is nice having Dorothy here, though <lb/>I am afraid I won't see much of <lb/>her; I went to her lodgings the other <lb/>day and thought them very nice. Then <lb/>we went on the top of the bus to <lb/>Hampstead Heath as neither of us had <lb/>been there before, and sat there in <lb/>the sun for a little -   The King's surgeon comes to our Ward
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4398_img_3751_3"/>
            <lb/>and operates on nearly all our bad <lb/>cases, he is a very solemn person and <lb/>stalks round with great state -    Please give Aunt Ellen my love, <lb/>I am sorry she has been having such <lb/>a bad time, I hope she'll soon be <lb/>all right again.   Some of our patients went to <lb/>Buckingham palace to a tea party <lb/>given by the King. They came back <lb/>full of excitement as the King came <lb/>and chatted to them all, and <lb/>Princess Mary poured out their tea.   Best love and many thanks <lb/>From your loving    <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>