<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0006">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Moynihan to Michael Moynihan, 9 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Moynihan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from John Moynihan (d. 1946) of Tralee, County Kerry, to his brother Michael Moynihan (d. 1918) where John discusses literature, specifically French literature, and books that Michael has read or requested. In the letter He also refers to the political situation in Ireland, commenting disparagingly on Irish Parliamentary Party and nationalist leader John Redmond, and the Easter Rising. In response to a comment by Michael, he writes that in some circumstances physical force is &#39;not only justifiable but necessary&#39;.Maurice Moynihan had joined the Civil Service Rifles, a unit of the British Territorial Army, before the outbreak of the Great War. In June 1916 he volunteered for foreign service and was sent to France as a private in the London Regiment. In 1917 he received a commission in the 8th (Irish) Battalion of the King&#39;s Liverpool Regiment and was killed in action in June 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Michael Moynihan Papers, P57/196(1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1368">John Moynihan</persName>
              <date>1916-08-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0871">Ballyard, Tralee, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1459">Michael Moynihan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0006_img_1027_1"  type="Letter"  url="7680a0cd223e7ca4c775115e9eb05152.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0006_img_1027_2"  type="Letter"  url="278a75896b3cc787199d509eb7f58d13.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0006_img_1027_3"  type="Letter"  url="22700bc412f9d9a138c509b42408915e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0006_img_1027_4"  type="Letter"  url="a6905b31b1308116b32a1e017a642bfe.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0006_img_1027_1"/>
                Postmarked Listowel, 10/8/16  addressed to Pte. M. J. Moynihan  Attached to the 178 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> (or 179 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>?)   Irish Brigade Headquarters  60 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division   British Expeditionary Force      Ballyard,  Tralee,  Ireland    9 Aug. 1916   My dear Michael   I am glad you admire Pascal, though <lb/> he was identified with the Port Royal <seg type="foreign">diet — <lb/> istas </seg>. Have you found the taint of Ivesy in <lb/> him? I believe his <seg type="foreign">'Lettres Provinciales'</seg> are <lb/> a crushing attack on the Jesuits; if I re <lb/> member rightly, Nelson does not recommend <lb/> them.   I have heard of Jos. de Meistre, too. I <lb/> rather envy your access to books like his, <lb/> though my <seg type="del">kno</seg> ignorance of French would <lb/> make it useless to me. By the way, if you <lb/> can get at Montalembert's 'Monks of the <lb/> West', read it. I believe it is a magnificent <lb/> book.   It is a pity Dent's hadn't 'Faust' in <lb/> stock. I have just found that it is also <lb/> included in Bolin''s Pop. Lib. I shall have <lb/> it sent to you. With regard to the other <lb/> book you asked for — Brunetière's 'Balzac' —  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0006_img_1027_2"/>
              Nelson's don't appear to give their address <lb/> on any of their books so, I got Eason's <lb/> man to order it on getting your first letter. <lb/> About a week later he <seg type="del">tol</seg> asked for fur <lb/> ther particulars as the book could not be <lb/> traced. I told him all I knew, but, again, <lb/> the result was the same. I shall write <lb/> now to Nelson's with 'London' for address, <lb/> for a catalogue and, if I can make <lb/> out the book, I shall send it. By the <lb/> way, I do not like Balzac. He seems to <lb/> be a man without vision; is it not <lb/> enough that, when he  had  settled to pros <lb/> perity after a long struggle, it was said <lb/> to him, as to the man in the Parable, <lb/> 'Fool this night — '? However you <lb/> shall see for yourself. To help your judg — <lb/>ment will I send two volumes of him; <lb/> one in French, containing <seg type="foreign">'La peau de <lb/> Chagrin' </seg>, <seg type="foreign">'Le cure´ de tours'</seg>, and 'Colonel <lb/> Chabert'; the other a translation of <lb/> 'Eugenie Grandet'.    Wouldn't it be a good plan, if I <lb/> sent a deposit to Dent's or Bells' so  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0006_img_1027_3"/>
              that you could order books according to <lb/> your requirement?   The political outlook in Ireland is, <lb/> indeed, uncertain, but not wholly gloomy. <lb/> At least one gleam of light pierces the <lb/> darkness — John Redmond can never stand <lb/> on his feet again. He has been so batter <lb/> ed and knocked about and kicked while <lb/> on the ground by the press, the Cabinet and <lb/> the Bishops that he is a hopelessly bruis <lb/> ed and broken man. We doubt the <lb/> chivalry of some of those who have turned <lb/> on him — most Rev. Dr. Walsh's letter, which <lb/> you will have seen in the 'Weekly Freeman', <lb/> should have been the most potent possible <lb/> stimulant for Redmondism — but we can <lb/> not doubt the net result. The love of <lb/> Redmondism  open by the Rising  must, indeed, remain open <lb/> for the present. It is best so, for all <lb/> the poison that has threatened the <lb/> life of Ireland will pour through it.   I suppose I agree with your re <lb/> marks about use of force by idealists <lb/> though, there are circumstances in which it  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0006_img_1027_4"/>
              is not only justifiable, but necessary, <lb/> And what more potent <seg type="del">voice</seg> expression <lb/> can the voice of the spirit receive in this <lb/> world, than that which is given it by <lb/> the mute victim of materialism dying <lb/> on the scaffold or in the barrack yard? <lb/> The political and religious history of the <lb/> world will answer.  <seg type="closer"> Yours,  J.M. </seg><seg type="postscript"> PS. May I send you,  occasionally , a paper called 'Irish <lb/> Opinion'? It publishes rather freely the <lb/> opinions of its readers and, therefore, <lb/> (this is my reason for asking permission <lb/> before sending it) sometimes contains <lb/> articles which, though not seditious or in <lb/> flammatory, we may bust Maxwell <lb/> and Lord Decies? for that — are perhaps <lb/> disloyal.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>