<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5778">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Joseph Devlin, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter from an unknown sender is sent to Joseph Devlin MP (1871-1974). Devlin was a key organiser for the Irish Parliamentary Party, an influential constitutional nationalist and had been an MP since 1902. In the aftermath of the Easter Rising, Devlin supported the temporary partition of Ireland but the scheme collapsed. In this letter Devlin is asked to use his influence to remove the negative marks from Constable Nicholas Rainsford&#39;s record. Rainsford was to be transferred following being charged after allegations from Protestant civilians that the writer claims were made up. The author calls for quick action to &#34;let those Orangemen see we are yet possessed of some influence.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/4087/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5778</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-03-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0915">Joseph Devlin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5778_img_877_1"  type="Letter"  url="229d698555048b473b27c845583a178f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5778_img_877_2"  type="Letter"  url="711946f6e4fc24ecd52554fd7f52e912.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5778_img_877_1"/>
             J.G. <lb/> For report please <lb/>M.N. 2/3   Dear Mr.Devlin,   With feelings of regret I am compelled to <lb/>write you in connection with a matter that occurred here <lb/>recently— where Constable Nicholas <sic>Rainsford</sic> of Leopold Street <lb/>Barracks was charged with:- (1) Entering the house of Miss Flos- <lb/>sie Gillian, Geoffrey St, on the night of the 29th December <lb/>last, at 8.30p.m., shook hands with her and said, I came to <lb/>arrest you. She was supposed to resent his action and said <lb/>her uncle was coming and that the Const. then left. (2) That <lb/>he called back the next night at 11 30p m, and knocked at the <lb/>door. That she tapped the wall of the house next door which is <lb/>occupied by an ex-soldier named Donnelly. Donnelly was <lb/>supposed to have come out to the Const. and charged him with <lb/>being knocking at Miss Gillan's door at the same time &amp; the <lb/>latter came on the scene and fainted. The Const. was reported, <lb/>a sworn inquiry held. Miss Gillan &amp; Donnelly swore what I <lb/>have above stated &amp; which is absolutely false. On the first <lb/>night he had six of the most respectable men on the Crumlin <lb/>Road to prove that he had been in their company from 7 15 p m, <lb/>to 10 p m. Also Father Ignatius was speaking to him on the <lb/>night in question in Ardoyne Hall and Const. McDonagh out of <lb/>the same Barracks was with him the whole time; consequently, <lb/>you can see for yourself that the charges were false and ground- <lb/>less beyond dispute. When he had such good evidence to sup- <lb/>port his innocence he was acquitted of the first night's <lb/>proceedings, but having no evidence to prove his innocence <lb/>on the second occasion, as he was on night duty, on this street, <lb/>he was found guilt of the second charge, (on the evidence of <lb/>the two who had previously sworn falsely against him) — got an <lb/>unfavourable record and transferred to Co. Kildare at his own <lb/>expense. He is to be leaving here on the 24th instant.   Well Dear Mr. Devlin, I must now tell you that this <lb/>business was solely concocted against Rainsford by the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5778_img_877_2"/>
            Protestant R.I.C. men of Leopold Street for the simple reason <lb/> that they know he devotes the greater part of his time to the <lb/> several meetings and committees held at Ardoyne. They have <lb/> boasted on several occasions that he would get the kick out <lb/> of Belfast, and now they have done it... I shall be forever <lb/> grateful if you will assert your influence - get the unfavour- <lb/> able record wiped out and the transfer cancelled. Try if <lb/> possible to get the transfer cancelled, and let those Orangemen <lb/> see that we are yet possessed of some influence.    Immediate action is necessary as he is going on the 24th <lb/> instant. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>