<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0657">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Roger Casement to Margaret Gavan Duffy, 2 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Roger Casement</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) to Margaret Gavan Duffy on the eve of his execution. He thanks various friends, and asks that God forgive his mistakes made in the cause of Irish freedom. He signs the letter with the Irish variant of his name, ;Ruair铆.The note is written on the reverse of the prayer-poem &#39;Fac me cruce inebriari&#39; by Father Thomas Gavin Duffy, published in the Dublin Review, a Catholic journal, in 1911. Thomas Gavan Duffy (1888-1942) was the brother of Margaret&#39;s husband, George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951), who unsuccessfully defended Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising. Casement was a humanitarian and Irish Nationalist. He believed that an Irish insurrection would be crushed unless it received substantial assistance from Germany, and when it became clear that adequate help would not be forthcoming he travelled to Ireland by submarine. Casement landed and was arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on Good Friday 1916. He was tried in the Old Bailey for treason and subsequently executed by hanging at Pentonville Prison on 3 August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>George Gavan Duffy Papers, P152/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/657</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1220">Pentonville Prison, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Margaret Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Last letters before death</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0657_img_214_1"  type="Letter"  url="b23f1e21b36ca5b7efc2c70cb9902d5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0657_img_214_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="1950bf5f4f1d42b36b3398dbf397fd17.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0657_img_214_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="b2e2a06582fb32507cce544dff6264c1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0657_img_214_1"/>
               To dear Margaret Gavan<lb/> Duffy -   From <hi rend="underline">Ruari.</hi> in my last<lb/> cell 芒聙聰 <hi rend="underline">2 Augt 1916</hi><lb/> 9 p.m.  Thank you dear friend<lb/> and Moya &amp;and Dana and<lb/> Eva and all the fond<lb/> ones.  Tomorrow St Stephen's Day<lb/> I die the death I sought<lb/> and may God forgive the<lb/> mistakes and receive the<lb/> intent 芒聙聰 Ireland's<lb/> freedom. <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">Ruari</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0657_img_214_2"/>
              <seg type="foreign">Fac Me Cruce Inebriari</seg>  Make merry, soul of mine, say: 'More!' say<lb/> 'More!' Art thus o'ercome the feast before?<lb/> Thy chalice sparkles...Or<lb/> Wouldst be milk芒聙聰nurtured till the sod has gaped?<lb/> Not so! Drink of the wine Heaven-graped<lb/> None ever yet escaped;<lb/> A myriad sainted hearts love芒聙聰pressed in pain,<lb/> Have spurted blood of Christ; 'twere vain<lb/> Another hope to feign.<lb/> Come, come, drink deep, my soul, inebriate!<lb/> Stagger a most unworldly gait!<lb/> Be inarticulate<lb/> Thy love to state!   The world's prim ears in thine unlovely key<lb/> Startle, while God brings out in thee<lb/> His heavenly symphony.<lb/> Roll in the dust 芒聙聰 is that a fall for us?芒聙聰<lb/>; Be wounded. Let the dead discuss<lb/> Why thou art Lowered thus.<lb/> Exult that Evil, seemingly at peace,  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0657_img_214_3"/>
              Triumphant prides in thy decrease芒聙聰<lb/> Thy pain, not his, will cease...<lb/> Will cease? Is not! For some commingling<lb/> sweet<lb/> Decrees thy pain a counterfeit,<lb/> Nor leisure leaves to greet<lb/> Sorrow so fleet.  There is a master芒聙聰vision haunts thy dreams,<lb/> Whose face a mist of spittle seems,<lb/> A fog of blood, where beams<lb/> No more the sun of beauty! Ah! 'tis he<lb/> Hath overset thus utterly<lb/> Thine heart's identity!<lb/> See how he creeps to conquest amid jeers:<lb/> Falls, rises, totters...meekly bears,<lb/> A thousand shames! His tears<lb/> Speak agonies to thy love.芒聙聰Come, soul of mine,<lb/> To where at last thy Worm Divine<lb/> Must on His Cross resign<lb/> His life for thine <lb/> Ah! Cross of Christ! my own, my own thou art!<lb/> Hug closer, lest thy counterpart<lb/> Steal off my fickle heart.<lb/> Let me not love the staid and sober road.<cb/> But ever, with unfaltering goad,<lb/> Drive me where bleeds thy Load<lb/> May not I be the mystic Body's side<lb/> Spear-thrust, one of the wounds nail-plied<lb/>? These shall be glorified..<lb/> Cross! Vine of vines, bearing death-trampled<lb/> Fruit!<lb/> The quest of all our mad pursuit<lb/> Hangs there, the world's dispute芒聙聰<lb/> Joy undilute. <lb/> Soul, soul of mine, be not unworthy found<lb/> Her slavery, whom Calvary crowned<lb/> A queen compassioned芒聙聰throned;<lb/> Be moulded Jesus-shape in her embrace;<lb/> Be crucified; and on thy face<lb/> The Passion hall芒聙聰mark's trace<lb/> Be cut and hammered for eternity,<lb/> Thou Temple芒聙聰stone. Gold, minted be<lb/> For next world currency.<lb/> Mary! the magic metamorphosis<lb/> Of such an earth-clung soul as this<lb/> To any form of His<lb/> Thy secret is.  T G D  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>