<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0356">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Irish Prisoners, Frongoch to Laurence J. Ginnell, Esq., MP, 9 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by a group of Irish prisoners in Frongoch to Laurence Ginnell. The representatives want Ginnell to raise questions in parliament regarding the administration of a scheme in the camp whereby prisoners are entitled to a rebate of a percentage of what they have spent in the canteen. Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; because of the revolutionary nature of the inmates.Laurence Ginnell (1852 – 1923) was an Irish nationalist politician, lawyer, and member of parliament. He initially ran as a member of the Irish Parliamentary Party, but, from 1910 onward he ran as an Independent Nationalist. Among the signatories to this letter are Michael Staines, Thomas Sinnott and Richard Mulcahy.Staines (1885 - 1955) was a member of the Irish Republican Brotherhood and served as Quartermaster in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was elected Head Leader by his peers.Sinnott (1893 - 1965) was the Officer Commanding Wexford Brigade, 1916. After the rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was a Room Leader.Richard Mulcahy (1886 - 1971) fought with Thomas Ashe in Ashbourne during the Easter Rising. After the Rising, he was detained in Frongoch where he was also a Room Leader</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD 45/4/8/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/356</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0137">Frongoch Internment Camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1462">Laurence J. Ginnell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0356_img_1594_1"  type="Letter"  url="e7ea7888e6539c6c2cc2d342a1255585.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0356_img_1594_2"  type="Letter"  url="a3f001aeb3612e2c90a433a036ba44b7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0356_img_1594_1"/>
             <seg type="head"><hi rend="underline">9/10/16 Q.F.B. 10/10/16</hi><lb/></seg>   Irish Prisoners,  Internment Camp,  Frongoch,    9th October 1916.   To Laurence J. Ginnell, Esq., B.A. B.L., M.P.  Sir,   We the undersigned being the duly elected leaders of the<lb/> above Camp would feel very much indebted to you if you could see<lb/> your way clear to having the following questions asked in<lb/> Parliament, at the earliest convenience :â  (1) What is the percentage of the rebate allowed to the<lb/> Irish Prisoners in Frongoch on their purchases in the Camp Canteen?<lb/> Is the percentage of the rebate allowed supposed to be fixed at 10%?<lb/> And if so, are the Camp Leaders or Prisoners' Auditor allowed to<lb/> see the Canteen A/C each month. If not, why not, considering that<lb/> it is solely the Prisoners' money that is being dealt with? (3) How are the Prisoners to know that they are receiving a rebate<lb/> of 10% other than the system of merely letting the Leaders know<lb/> that they can draw on the Canteen Fund up to Â£10 per month (4) Is<lb/> it a fact that when there were 1,800 prisoners in the Camp in July<lb/> they were only allowed Â£4:10:0 while an average of 900 men<lb/> in August they received Â£10 and with 545 men in Sept. they also<lb/> received Â£10 (5) Why are not the Camp Leaders allowed to<lb/> purchase such goods as they think most suitable for the prisoners<lb/> in the way of food, tobacco, cigarettes, etc., considering that it is<lb/> solely the Prisoners' money? <seg type="postscript"> P.S. We would be glad if you would make inquiries<lb/> into the alleged connection of the Adjutant of the Camp â Lieut.<lb/> J.T. Burns (who has charged of the Canteen Fund) with the officer of<lb/> that name connected with the Lipton scandal some few years ago. </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0356_img_1594_2"/>
              There are strong rumours concerning this; and certainly the<lb/> Adjutant is obviously an officer of much service and experience<lb/> for a mere Lieutenant. If this alleged connection is correct<lb/> it may have a pertinent bearing on the above questions.<lb/> Signed (5) <seg type="closer">  12/10/16  <lb/> To A. Byrne Esq.<lb/></seg><seg type="postscript"> We have been informed by the Adjutant on yesterday,<lb/> 11th inst. that we may draw on the Canteen a/c up to Â£25 for<lb/> this month, but we are not allowed to check accounts. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>