<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4177">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin, 8 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Dorothy Duffin (b. 1881) to her mother Maria Duffin (1854-1954). 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4177</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0947">No 16 General Hospital, Le Tréport, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4177_img_3550_1"  type="Letter"  url="800be1bc0f7f9ea4d7a4ad0e0686d007.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4177_img_3550_2"  type="Letter"  url="97e829fb2b0e1ea21ee2b275966a251d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4177_img_3550_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">On Active Service</hi> <lb/>WITH THE BRITISH <hi rend="underline">EXPEDITIONARY FORCE</hi>  THE BRITISH EXPEDITIONARY FORCE, <lb/>c/o General Post Office, <lb/>LONDON. B<!--This address is top left -->  16 <seg type="unclear">Gen:</seg> Hospital  <!-- address top right of page -->  Nov 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915  My Dear Mamma.   I hope to hear from you <lb/>to-morrow. I am awfully happy &amp; have been <lb/>having a splendid time &amp; I am very free now <lb/>owing to Mrs <seg type="unclear">Bell</seg> being here. You see my <lb/>choice with the cross on him but I hope to <lb/>send you a better one soon. <!-- a photograph? --> The Colonel <lb/>is delighted with us and says we are <lb/>made for each other - he called to see me and I <lb/>returned it Saturday. Everyone is pleased <lb/>about it as <seg type="unclear">Lester</seg> is awfully popular here <lb/>with everyone, of course it is hopeless to keep <lb/>it a secret here as I go about with him <lb/>everywhere. We had a busy day in Dieppe <lb/>as Capt. <seg type="unclear">Worthian</seg> was motoring over and took us with <lb/>him &amp; yesterday we had another <lb/>long day in the town as the Colonel gave <lb/>us his car for the day. Work here <lb/>has been so slack that we have been seeing <lb/>each other a very great deal but an away is
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4177_img_3550_2"/>
            expected tomorrow which will probably make a <lb/>difference. There is no use making plans about <lb/>coming home then til I hear from you. He <lb/>expects to get leave time soon &amp; if so will <lb/>come back with me.   I must stop &amp; get to work now. Much love <lb/>to all Dear. Do hope you'll like what you can <lb/>see of his ugly, old face. He is Dutch, <lb/>English &amp; Spanish. He is so demented with <lb/>me I don't know how he'll ever let me go!   Your loving   <hi rend="underline">Dorothy</hi>   Colonel Thomson is the most charming man, he has been awfully kind to us and says he <lb/>feels responsible for the whole thing but he <lb/><seg type="unclear">properly</seg> certain we've done the right thing. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>