<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1218">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Note from the Chief Crown Solicitor to Sir Matthew Nathan, 16 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Malachy Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Note from the Chief Crown Solicitor, Malachy Kelly (1851-1916), to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). The case involves Mrs Maggie Kiernan who is accused of falsely applying for a separation allowance. The War Office wishes to have the results of the case and if the case is successful to have any reports that appear in local newspapers.Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. Sir Malachy Kelly was the Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland. He was appointed Crown Solicitor for Mayo in 1884 and was involved in a number of high profile cases. In 1905, he was appointed Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland and moved to Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI/CSO RP/1916/6810/3/2b, NAI/CSO RP/1916/6810/3/2b</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1218</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0509">Malachy Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-02-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1380">Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0890">Dublin Castle</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1218_img_398_1"  type="Letter"  url="aeda0c66b39c65e464198414ffabcfe9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1218_img_398_1"/>
              Chief Secretary's Office, Ireland. <lb/>Chief Crown Solicitor's Department <lb/>Subject. <lb/>War Department <lb/>re <lb/>Separation Claim <lb/>Mrs. Maggie Kiernan, <lb/> Edgeworthstown, <lb/>Co.Longford <lb/>Minute  Mr Delaney, Crown Solr. <lb/>For necessary action <lb/>at an early date &amp; <lb/>for attention to the <lb/>Solr.General's directions <lb/>EOF <lb/>28/2/16   Under Secretary,   I beg to submit papers re- <lb/>ceived from the War Office herein with the <lb/>Solicitor General's directions and request <lb/>that they be sent to the Local Crown <lb/>Solicitor Mr.Delaney to take <lb/>charge and prosecute.  The prosecution should be brought under <lb/>47 &amp; 48 Vic. c. 55 s. 3 and the case dealt <lb/>with summarily.  War Office requests that I should <lb/>report the result of the proceedings in <lb/>due course and at the same time return the <lb/>documents in connection with the case.  In the event of the prosecution being <lb/>successful War Office wishes to have any <lb/> reports which may appear in the Local Press <lb/> in regard to the case or else a short <lb/> summary of the proceedings and I request that <lb/> the local Crown Solicitor be asked to obtain <lb/> a few papers containing the reports or supply <lb/> a short summary of the proceedings to enable <lb/> me comply with said request. <seg type="closer"> M. Kelly </seg> <lb/>Chief Crown Solicitor <lb/>26. 2. 1916  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>