<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2645">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maria Duffin to Celia Duffin,  6 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

This letter was written by Maria Duffin (1854 – 1954), to her daughter Celia (b. 1888). In this letter Maria recounts the family’s news for Celia, including the execution of the estate of ‘Aunt E’, who is recently deceased. Maria also mentions that she has heard a rumour that the Germans are pouring on the Western front, which has her worried.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2645</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1392">Dunowen Belfast</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2645_img_2070_1"  type="Letter"  url="d6a05fb86cf05c384e20603707ebeec5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2645_img_2070_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0668e68b5ca60f7d39d7241ea436c8d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2645_img_2070_3"  type="Letter"  url="b99f1c2c9380c5550ff974bb05071a65.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2645_img_2070_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/B   Dunowen,<lb/>Belfast    Feb. 6 1916    My dearest Celia   I am glad you<lb/>had a quiet night and<lb/>arrived safely. We missed<lb/>you very much. I wonder<lb/>will you see Olive, who<lb/>has gone to London to meet<lb/>Marjorie. You may see them<lb/>both possibly. No more<lb/>mumps so you are quite<lb/>safe.  A letter from Aunt E's executors<lb/>this morning. I am left<lb/>£500 &amp; a silver cream ewer &amp;<lb/>sugar bowl; £450 is left to<lb/>my children in equal shares. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2645_img_2070_2"/>
            So I suppose you may count<lb/>on about £45 as<lb/>yours. When it will<lb/>come I don't know.<lb/>Bernard <seg type="unclear">Squire</seg> gets the<lb/>portrait and £1000 &amp; is <seg type="unclear">sending<lb/>legalie</seg>, which <hi rend="underline">may</hi> amount<lb/>to £2000 more, so he comes off<lb/>rather the best. Aunt E's<lb/>three nieces get £800 each<lb/>&amp; someone else £300. Then there<lb/>are some specific bequests<lb/>of furniture etc. The rest<lb/>is all to be sold on the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<lb/>I am rather <seg type="unclear">pleased</seg> as<lb/>I had <seg type="unclear">never</seg> to expect any<lb/>thing and am glad you<lb/>all get a little bit for yourselves. Nothing here has happened<lb/>since you left.  I had tea with <seg type="unclear">Butts</seg> on<lb/>Thursday &amp; she was here<lb/>yesterday. I saw poor Mrs<lb/>O'Brien again and she told<lb/>me she has got an annunity<lb/>of £83 from the Local Government<lb/>Board. Which is a help,<lb/>poor thing! She looked<lb/>ill and her feet are dreadfully swollen.  Dorothy &amp; your father are <seg type="unclear">gurt</seg><lb/>off to the Garrett Campbells.<lb/>We have had much lightning<lb/>&amp; thunder today and it is<lb/>very cold.  I wonder how you feel in<lb/><seg type="unclear">Hicoola </seg> Terrace. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2645_img_2070_3"/>
             Peter comes tomorrow and I<lb/>hope won't hurry the arrival<lb/>of the kittens!  There is absolutely no other<lb/>news, so goodbye darling.<lb/>It was nice to see you<lb/>and hard to let you go.<lb/>I wonder where we shall<lb/>meet next?<lb/>   I see a rumour that the<lb/>Germans are pouring on<lb/>the Western Front, which<lb/><seg type="unclear">mahis</seg> me terrible.  Much Love, darling<lb/>Your ever loving<lb/>Mother  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>