<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0734">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jennie Johnson to George Hackney, 4 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jennie Johnson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Jeannie Johnson to George Hackney (1889-1977). Jennie expresses the hope that George is well and that he manages to hold on to his good luck. She writes that an imprisoned friend, &#39;Willie&#39;, has recently died of his wounds. Jeannie describes that she has recently returned home from a trip away, and gives some details of that trip, and of recent weather.This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney, a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;. In 1916 he was injured and spent some time a Hospital in Calais, France, and in Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/734</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1344">Jennie Johnson</persName>
              <date>1916-09-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1468">4 Wynnefield Road, Rathmines, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0391">19 Ward, 35 General Hospital, Calais, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0734_img_2244_1"  type="Letter"  url="3efaa90e18a27c6268849ab2d9bad1b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0734_img_2244_2"  type="Letter"  url="62150367120df91939a97736624b01b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0734_img_2244_3"  type="Letter"  url="96c53ec382f5ec0cb9d0073994d7b451.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0734_img_2244_4"  type="Envelope"  url="2e6437a3b859d8af70fc203ea379950a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0734_img_2244_5"  type="Envelope"  url="f07288c81fabf8b27f59a64e5c5d519c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0734_img_2244_1"/>
                7 <seg type="unclear">Wynnefield</seg> Road    4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi rend="underline">Sept 1916</hi>   Dear Mr Hackney,   Many thanks for letter which I was glad <lb/> to get. I am so sorry that you have <lb/> been ill. I do hope that you are feeling <lb/> nearly yourself again. Indeed I dont <lb/> wonder that you broke down after all <lb/> was over. You must have come through <lb/> a terrible time. I hope that your <lb/> good luck will stick to you all.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0734_img_2244_2"/>
              through, &amp; that you will come safely home. <lb/> You will have heard that poor <lb/> Willlie died of wounds on July 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> He was a prisoner poor boy. <lb/> We had so hoped for good news <lb/> of him. It is just a short time <lb/> since we heard.  I have got back home again <lb/>from the Country, I had a very <lb/> nice time. I was quite sorry <lb/>to come back to town life. <cb/>though it is nice to get settled down <lb/> at home once again. I seemed to be <lb/>away such a lot this summer. <lb/> I had very good weather all the <lb/>time I was away. I did quite <lb/>a lot of walking &amp; also some <lb/>cycling, but not a lot as it is <lb/>nearly 7 or 8 years since I was <lb/> on a bike, it did seem very strange <lb/> being on one again. I much prefer <lb/> walking. The roads were in fine  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0734_img_2244_3"/>
              order. I hope to go to blackberrying <lb/>some day very soon. The weather has <lb/> been rather cold &amp; wet for the <lb/> last week or so. I see it is <lb/> almost post time so I must close <lb/> wishing you all good luck.  With kindest regards &amp; good <lb/>wishes <seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Jennie Johnson</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0734_img_2244_4"/>
                Lce. Cpl. G. Hackney  19 Ward  35 General Hospital  <hi rend="superscript"><seg type="del">8th Platoon 'B' Coy.</seg></hi>  <hi rend="underline">14th Batt. R.I.R.Y.L.V</hi>  <hi rend="underline"><seg type="del">B.E.F.</seg></hi>    
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0734_img_2244_5"/>
                7 Wynnefield Road  Rathmines  Dublin.  —Ireland    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>