<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3146">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 3 November 1915.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother Maria (1854-1954) informing her about her daily activities in London. At the beginning of her letter Celia mentions her desire to join her sister Emma (1883-1979), who was posted to Alexandria, and an offer she received to work on a hospital ship.

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin PApers D2109/9/4/B/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3146</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3146_img_2564_1"  type="Letter"  url="d376b4e0a79e5252d6ed66396b9ce93d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3146_img_2564_2"  type="Letter"  url="fe0575902a56e1a777b08e8a9d37fc26.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3146_img_2564_3"  type="Letter"  url="eb2b498d441b5d29b8888426765f76a7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3146_img_2564_4"  type="Letter"  url="752b6770db0ecb3e34fd69fec6c9fe39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3146_img_2564_5"  type="Letter"  url="5d046046c756d7c74c1b36e345cffdbb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3146_img_2564_6"  type="Letter"  url="995f2e665acdc82cd608153063ba4b30.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3146_img_2564_1"/>
             Nov. 3<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> <lb/> <hi rend="underline">1915</hi>    Dearest Mamma   I enclose a lot of letters that were <lb/>forwarded to me thank you so much for <lb/>sending them, it was nice seeing them <lb/>all. Olive’s poem and Molly Carson’s <lb/>letter <seg type="del">was</seg>  were  picked up by one of the orderlies <lb/>just outside the hospital, and she returned <lb/>them to me. It must have dropped out of <lb/>my pocket just as I left. I am glad <lb/>it turned up. I liked the poem. Emma <lb/>seems to be having a queer life at <lb/>Alexandria. I want to try to join her <lb/>when my 6 months here are finished <lb/>and will write to the St. John's Headquarters <lb/>about it, if you approve. The War <lb/>Office wrote and asked some of us
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3146_img_2564_2"/>
            who had been here longest to volunteer for <lb/>a hospital ship. I didn’t as I am such <lb/> a bad sailor and I think they got <lb/>enough quite easily.   I got my travelling voucher all right <lb/>when I left home, but I spent 10/ on inci- <lb/>dental expenses, cabs etc, which the War <lb/>Office has just paid to me now. After <lb/>this we get extra pay, £1 -13/4<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> for <lb/>sure every month, and about £2 <lb/>more I expect <hi rend="underline">over</hi> from our govern- <lb/>ment allowance; this however depends <lb/>on how much is spent on food, <lb/>lighting, housing etc. So far it has <lb/>all been used up, but now that <lb/>the furnishing etc is paid for, we are <lb/>to get all the extra money, so I think <lb/>we are well treated. We have nothing <lb/>to pay out of this except our washing, so <lb/>I hope soon to be able to repay you <lb/>the money you advanced for my uni- <lb/>form.   I went and saw Miss John one evening, <lb/>so I have got that off my chest. She <lb/>seemed very happy and delighted in <lb/>her work. She says the War Office of- <lb/>fered her a good post, but she wouldn’t <lb/>leave her present job! She was all <lb/>over me and <hi rend="underline">kissed</hi> me when I went <lb/>away. Such a funny little room <lb/>she has, and attended by a dear little <lb/>French nun in a wide starched cap <lb/>who doesn’t know a word of English. <lb/>Eva Andrews wants to join her there, <lb/>but at present there is no room. <lb/>I had supper with all the other boarders,
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3146_img_2564_3"/>
            an odd collection of females, some old <lb/>ladies, two young Belgian girls, and <lb/>one or two of the hard-working strenuous <lb/>English type. The Mother Superior apolo- <lb/>gised for "<seg type="foreign">pas de viande</seg>" as it was a <lb/>fast day, so we supped on eggs and <lb/>vegetables and suet pudding.   Miss Monaghan and I went out to Ealing <lb/>on a pouring wet day, and I had <lb/>tea and dinner with her family. <lb/>The mother seemed a rather uninterest- <lb/>ing person and the other sister was <lb/>fair and pretty with features exactly <lb/>like Olive's; she reminded me of her <lb/>all the time. They live in a <lb/>flat overlooking the <seg type="unclear">golf links</seg> and have <lb/>dreadful pictures on their walls. They <lb/>were very kind and begged me to
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3146_img_2564_4"/>
            go back; they all seemed to be in love <lb/>with Terry, especially the mother. Miss <lb/>Monaghan gets £1-10/ a week as cook <lb/>at the orderlies' hostel, but of course, <lb/>she was well-trained in London. I am <lb/>sure she is a capable person, very bright, <lb/> and a great talker.   I was rather tired last half day, so <lb/>I went to  see  Mrs. MacLeod again and <lb/>curled up in a big chair by her <lb/>fire while she read and recited to <lb/>me. Then we went out together <lb/>and looked at frocks at her dress- <lb/>makers. Such a pretty little mannikin <lb/>showed them off - and then we <lb/>went and chose her a new black <lb/>hat trimmed with fur. I stayed
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3146_img_2564_5"/>
            on for dinner as "Bill" was away <lb/>shooting, and was introduced to <hi rend="underline">Hindy</hi>. <lb/> Mrs. MacLeod's Ladies <sic>Made</sic>  <lb/>The house is so pretty, it makes one <lb/>quite sad to see it all, everything so <lb/>beautifully planned by a young bride. <lb/>Her husband has gone to the front <lb/>and she has gone home. I hope he <lb/>will come safely back to his pretty <lb/>house. I wonder if Helen would <lb/>lend me Rupert Brooke's poems, Mrs. <lb/>MacLeod read me some, and I would <lb/>like to see the others. I'll send them <lb/>safe back to her.   Many thanks for all the squares, <lb/>I wrote a note to Miss Bruce, but please <lb/>thank her too the next time you see her. <lb/>Mrs. MacLeod was going to have tea with <lb/>Mrs. Harper, and was surprised when I <lb/>told her I had just been there.   The rug hasn't turned up yet, but I <lb/>expect it will come all right.   It was nice getting all that money <lb/>for Emma's men, the ones here have a <lb/>good many people to visit them, so they <lb/>don't need things so much.   It is sad about Dr. O'Brien, I suppose <lb/>she will be left dreadfully badly off. <lb/>Colonel Bruce-Porter has gone to a <lb/>hospital in France and we have a new <lb/>head. I think the late Colonel is <lb/>coming back to take some of the staff <lb/>out with him, and some of the V.A.D's <lb/>hope to go too.   I think I am getting my November day
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3146_img_2564_6"/>
            next week, and if so will go to the <lb/>Tillings; it is a nice easy place to get <lb/>at from here.   If you are sending me a cake, I <lb/>should like one of our nice chocolate <lb/>ones best. I make myself funny <lb/>suppers of force and buns or bread <lb/>and milk and biscuits. We have a <lb/>big stodgy midday dinner, large helps of <lb/>meat and vegetables and pudding. <lb/>It is very dark getting up these mor- <lb/>nings. Please thank Molly for her letter, <lb/>I shall write to her soon.   Ever your loving   <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>