<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0620">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Carson to Ivor Guest, 22 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Carson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Carson to Lord Wimborne (Ivor Guest) (1873-1938). Mr. Carson is concerned about the development of the resources and wealth of the country but he has found the Irish people hopeless to deal with. He is offering his services to the Crown to provide ‘proper and honest management in development of the resources’, thereby providing honest employment for the people to the benefit of the Country. A comment, added by the CSO, indicates that this letter ‘calls for no notice’.Included in the upload are two enclosures :1. A newspaper cutting showing a letter (to the Editor) written by Mr. Carson outlining his proposal to harness Lough Neagh and the consequent savings.2. A Preliminary Circular which would form the basis of a Memorandum and Articles of Association for a company called Industrial Development and Trading Company Limited, set up by Mr. Carson, with broad-ranging objectives of industrial development. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7288</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/620</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0928">Robert Carson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-22T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0109">7 Waring Street, Belfast, County Down, Northern Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ivor Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0620_img_2038_1"  type="Letter"  url="513c54b86031b4ebe06ee7e7019fc617.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0620_img_2038_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="b08273072521d0f9f03148baee3a2019.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0620_img_2038_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="71c43f1c6a488191ad3a4301747efbb5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0620_img_2038_1"/>
                7 Waring Street  Belfast    April 22 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1916     Lord Wimborne  Vice Regal Lodge, Dublin   My Lord   I see from the newspapers you want to arrange for <lb/>the extension of industries in Ireland after the war.   I have spent years trying to get the Irish people to <lb/>develop the resources and the wealth of the country but <lb/>I have found them hopeless to deal with.   Ireland under proper and honest management in <lb/>developing the resources of the country can provide fully <lb/>Â£20,000,000 a year for next 100 years without increasing <lb/>the taxation on the people.   I know Ireland well for many years and where the <lb/>material is for making the sum named and I offer my <lb/>services to the crown. I can take charge of the undertaking <lb/>and get it started on business lines and provide some <lb/>honest employment for the people to the benefit of the country.  <seg type="closer"> Waiting for your reply, I am my Lord. <lb/>yours faithfully   Robert Carson </seg> Asst. Under Secretary <lb/>This letter calls I think for no notice <lb/>WML 4/5   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0620_img_2038_2"/>
              HARNESSING LOUGH NEAGH. <lb/>(To the Editor.)   Belfast has long been looked upon as the <lb/>most goâahead and enterprising city in Ireâ <lb/>land. But why not take advantage of the <lb/>power that Nature has provided, and which <lb/>has been running waste for generations, undâ <lb/>eveloped, and which, when harnessed, would <lb/>provide a revenue for the city of over <lb/>Â£1,00,000 a year. The tramway loss, and the <lb/>sliding gardens muddle are a small item comâ <lb/>pared with the stupendous waste going on day <lb/>by day. Count it up for the past 100 years â <lb/>Â£100,000,000 lost to Belfast. There are no engineering <lb/>difficulties in the way. Lough <lb/>Neagh, the largest lake in the United Kingâ <lb/>dom, is 18 miles distant from Belfast, is fully <lb/>50 feet above sea level at low water mark, and <lb/>has an area of 340 square miles. Taking the <lb/>high water level of the lake at 54 feet, the <lb/>area would be about 500 square miles. Ten <lb/>rivers flow into it, and there is only one outâ âlet âthe Lower Bann. This vast water power <lb/>has been passing to the sea for thousands of <lb/>years as waste. It has been estimated that <lb/>Belfast could have 100,000 horse power six <lb/>months of the year, 50,000 three months, and <lb/> 30,000 h.p. the other three months (a dry sumâ <lb/>mer). Take the present cost of horse power <lb/>at Â£15 per h.p. per year. This would produce <lb/>Â£1,050,000 a year. Set aside Â£100,000 for inâ <lb/>terest on capital and cost of plant, and <lb/>Â£100,000 for sinking fund, that would leave a <lb/>balance of Â£850,000 a year to credit of the <lb/>city income. After twenty years the entire <lb/>cost of plant and undertaking would be paid <lb/>off by sinking fund, when the entire income of <lb/>over Â£1,000,000 a year would go to credit <lb/>of city revenue. The vast water power would <lb/>be conveyed part of the way by open <lb/>canal, and part of the way by pipes <lb/> from Lough Neagh to the power station. <lb/>situate on the Lagan, where turbines, <lb/>dynamos, and storage batteries would be erecâ <lb/>ted and electricity generated to be distributed <lb/>to tramways, shipyards, mills, factories, and <lb/>for town lighting. Manufacturers and millâ <lb/>owners who now provide their own motive <lb/>power by steam and pay a high price for coal <lb/>and upkeep of their steam plant would unâ <lb/>doubtedly use electric power, for by so doing <lb/>they would get three times the power for the <lb/>same cost. The smoke nuisance would be <lb/>abated and the health conditions of the city <lb/>improved. The water, after leaving the power <lb/>station, would scour out the Lagan, the harâ <lb/>bour, and the straight channel to the deep <lb/>sea, carrying all sewerage with it, and make <lb/>the constant dredging operations now carried <lb/>on by the harbour authorities unnecessary. <lb/>This undertaking would also relieve the large <lb/>area of lands round Lough Neagh shores and <lb/>the lowâlying lands along the Lower Bann <lb/>from periodical flooding. Many thousands of <lb/>acres now of little value would become valuable, <lb/>as the water-level of Lough Neagh could <lb/>be kept at a certain height winter and summer. <lb/>Large sums of money have been spent from <lb/>time to time by the Board of Works cutting <lb/>canals here and there, with the result that <lb/>much land became flooded which had been free <lb/>from flooding formerly. An Act of Parliaâ <lb/>ment will be required, but it is worth all the <lb/>expense. It is now up to the City Council, <lb/>Harbour Commissioners, propertyâowners, and <lb/>the ratepayers of the city to secure this great <lb/>income without delay, and make Belfast a <lb/>city free of rates and taxes. â  <seg type="closer"> Yours, &amp;c.,  ROBERT CARSON.   7 Waring Street, Belfast.    Sept 10 â 1915   <lb/>Evg Tele </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0620_img_2038_3"/>
              <hi rend="underline">1907</hi> ROBERT CARSON, C.E.   7 WARING STREET,   BELFAST.    <hi rend="underline">Preliminary Circular</hi><lb/>INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT AND TRADING COMPANY, LIMITED <lb/>(Incorporated under the Joint Stock Companies Acts, 1862 to 1908).   CAPITAL â Â£500,000. <lb/>DIVIDED INTO <lb/>100,000 Ordinary Shares of 1/â each <lb/>250,000 Guaranteed and fully secured 5% 'A' Cumulative <lb/>Preference SHares of Â£1 each. <lb/>245,000 'B' 6% Cumulative Preerence Shares of Â£1 each. The 'A' Preference Shares will be fully secured as to Capital and dividends, and <lb/>will rank in priority to the 'B' Preference Shares.   PRESENT ISSUE OF <lb/>250,000 Guaranteed and fully secured 5 p.c. 'A' Cumulative Preference Shares of Â£1 each. <lb/>245,000 6 per cet. Cumulative Preference Shares of Â£1 each   PAYABLE AS FOLLOWS : â <lb/>2/6 per Share on application. <lb/>2/6 per Share on allotment. <lb/><lb/>5/â per Share Two Months after allotment. <lb/>And the Balance in calls not exceeding 5/- per Share at intervals of not less than two months.   Subscribers may pay up in full on allotment. <lb/>The Ordinary Shares will be taken up by Mr. Carson and his friends.   The objects for which the Company is formed are :â To revive old and start new industries <lb/>in districts where experience considers there is a reasonable prospect of success. To develop the <lb/>resources in the country, to take up Estates, waste lands, mountains, bogs, woods, waterpowers, <lb/>rivers, lakes, minerals, mining, clay earths, quarries, lands, etc.; to take up and develop all classes <lb/>of manufactures, to promote companies for like purposes, to finance or assist in working or developâ <lb/>ing same ; to underwrite, guarantee contracts and undertakings, to take up Patents, work and <lb/>develop same ; or promote companies to do so ; to buy or sell Patents either for cah or shares ; to <lb/>manufacture all classes of material. Engineers, ship, boat, barge owners and builders. Hotels, <lb/>recreation and sports of various kinds. Stock and share delers, brokers and agents. Railways, <lb/>tramways ; traction engones and trains. Electric, steam, oil, gas, power and lighting, etc. To act <lb/>as carriers, warehousemen ; to discount bills, to borrow and lend money, to erect or pull down <lb/>buildings, to make contacts for all classes of work and carry through or sublet the same or any <lb/>portion thereof ; to make canals, work, sublet or sell them, acquire by purchase or otherwise ; <lb/>reclaim lands, labour, sublet, work or sell the same for any purpose and on any terms. Merchants, <lb/>manufacturers, traders in all kinds of produce and material. Importers, exporters of all or any class <lb/>or kinds of materials and other articles of commerce. To provide employment for many thousands <lb/>of the people of the country, and help put a stop to emigration by providing plenty of employâ <lb/>ment for the people at home. To encourage agriculture in every way, providing markets for the <lb/>purchase of farmers' produce, to buy and sell the same ; to lend money to farmers and others, <lb/>to lend money on securities or otherwise, etc.   The foregoing are a few of the powers I take in the Memorandum and Artices of Association. <lb/>Your assistance and support is respectfully invited. The investment is one of the soundest and <lb/>safest ever put on the market. Real Estate assets to double the amount of entire subscribed <lb/>capital will be vested in 'Trustees', with full power and control to safeguard the A and B Preference <lb/>Shareholders' interests. It is expected that these shares will go up in prce to 40/â within three <lb/>months after allotment. Some o the industries to be stated will make a very large profit, fully <lb/>25% on their capitals required to work the different lines of businesses. Large orders are already in <lb/>hand waiting the starting of 'Plants' and machinery.   I will be able to supply any further information to gentlemen who wish to take an active <lb/>part in this undertaking, either as Directors or Subscribers. A large amount of capital is already <lb/> promised ; the Board of Directors will shortly be seected. Gentlemen who wish to join the Board <lb/>will kindly send in their names to the undersigned, and much oblige,  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  ROBERT CARSON </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>