<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0396">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Ireton to Robert Chalmers, 30 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Ireton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Ireton (1866-1930), city treasurer and town clerk for Cork, to Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), the under-secretary to Ireland. Ireton requests the payment of seventy four pounds, ten shillings and nine pence owed to Cork for the expenses of witnesses and prosecutors at the assizes and sessions. Robert Chalmers assumed the role in 1916 for a brief period following the resignation of Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), after accepting political failure during the 1916 Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5613/9248</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/396</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1076">Thomas Ireton</persName>
              <date>1916-05-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0961">City Hall, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0396_img_1659_1"  type="Letter"  url="3d7c004d02c117c03b810b0955f0d3ef.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0396_img_1659_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">CITY HALL.</hi>  CORK    30th May, 1916.   SIR,   I beg to apply for payment of Seventy Four pounds, Ten <lb/> shillings and Nine Pence due to the Corporation of Cork, being <lb/> the amount paid for Expenses of Witnesses and Prosecutors at <lb/> Assizes and Sessions during the Half-year ended 31st. March, <lb/> 1916, as per Account and Vouchers herewith.  The Crown Solicitor's Certificates are also enclosed. <seg type="closer"> Your obedient servant,  Thomas Ireton.   The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle.  </seg> I Ack. <lb/>II Chief Crown Solicitor, <lb/>Please attach the relevant <lb/>copy. <hi rend="underline">1-6-'16.</hi>  II Mr. Gibbs <lb/>Returns Herewith <lb/>JW Hugo <lb/>parcel <lb/>3.6.16. <lb/><hi rend="underline">EOF</hi>  Secretary. <lb/>Local Government Board <lb/><hi rend="underline">5-6-'16.</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>