<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3853">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to Sir Arthur Stanley, 4 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) to Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) regarding the establishment of a college of nursing. Kirkpatrick informs Stanley that, according to a new resolution adapted by the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI), the college cannot recommend Irish nurses to support the College of Nursing Ltd. unless one fifth of the supreme governing body of the nursing college consists of Irish representatives. Enclosed with the letters are draft copies of this resolution. 

From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

Sir Arthur Stanley was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-3-15-18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3853</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1916-04-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arthur Stanley </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3853_img_3233_1"  type="Letter"  url="4da0f47cc864653a4f112273482f2499.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3853_img_3233_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="d3cea1639a39939b031511b816d91b65.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3853_img_3233_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="a0423ba0af4289dcc23b0e9096a4b274.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3853_img_3233_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="424228f821f29546bcca1eb011311adb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3853_img_3233_1"/>
              The Royal College of Physicians &amp; Surgeons, <lb/>6, Kildare Street, Dublin.   4th APRIL, 1915.   The Hon.Arthur Stanley, M.V.C., M.P., <lb/>83 Pall Mall, London, S.W.   Dear Sir,    A Committee representing the Royal Colleges of <lb/>Physicians and Surgeons of Ireland to-;day met a number of <lb/>ladies representing the Irish Nurses Training Schools. The <lb/>proposed College of Nursing was very fully discussed and I <lb/>was directed to forward to you the following resolution <lb/>which was unanimously adopted :—   Resolved : that this Committee representing the Royal Colleges of <lb/>Physicians and Surgeons of Ireland inform Mr. Stanley that it cannot <lb/>recommend Irish Nurses to support the College of Nurses Ltd., <lb/>unless at least one fifth of the supreme governing body of that <lb/>College consists of Irish Representatives.   I sincerely trust that you will be able to grant to Ireland <lb/>this representation on the Council of the College as, if so, <lb/>I feel that we shall be able to get an almost unanimous <lb/>acceptance of the College by Irish Nurses.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully, </seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3853_img_3233_2"/>
             That this Committee representing <lb/>the <seg type="del">two</seg> Royal Colleges of Physicians <lb/>&amp; Surgeons of Ireland inform <lb/>Mr. Stanley that it cannot <lb/>recommend Irish Nurses <lb/>to support the College of Nursing <lb/>Ltd. unless at least one fifth <lb/>of the Supreme Governing body <lb/>of that College consists of <lb/>Irish Representatives 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3853_img_3233_3"/>
             Dear Sir,   I am directed by the Committee of the Royal Colleges of <lb/>Physicians and Surgeons of Ireland to write to tell you <lb/>that in the opinion of the Members of that Committee <lb/><seg type="del">that</seg>it is most desirable, in order to preserve the <lb/>unanimity <seg type="del">that</seg> at present exist ing  among Irish Nurses, <lb/>&amp; if  it furthers the interests of the College of Nursing, that the <lb/>question of the Irish Representation on the Council of the <lb/>College should be filled at as early a date as possible.   The Committee is anxious to call together a meeting <lb/>of Irish Nurses &amp; I shall be glad if you can inform me <lb/>of the date on which I may expect to have a definite <lb/>answer on the subject.   I remain Dear Sir <lb/> Yours etc   TMK 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3853_img_3233_4"/>
             That Mr Colls be <seg type="unclear">see<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></seg> to be app me Comitee <lb/>to consider &amp; <seg type="unclear">sept</seg> as to how far it is <lb/>poss &amp; desir<seg type="del">e</seg>  of  to  &amp; to institute a cert of comp in nursing to  constitute <seg type="del">an</seg> a <lb/>board to supervise me <seg type="del">and</seg> educ' <lb/>&amp; conduct me exam of such Irish <lb/>nurses at <seg type="unclear">seek</seg> <seg type="del">me</seg>  <seg type="del">a such</seg> <seg type="unclear">mal</seg>   Certif <seg type="del">of me but <lb/>Colls competence in nursing to be <lb/><seg type="unclear">named</seg> by the Roy Colls</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>