<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0993">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Deborah Webb to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Deborah Webb</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Deborah Webb writes to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington regarding the latest Irish Women&#39;s Franchise League meeting and the location of the key to the meeting room. She also writes about another member, Mrs Connery, who expressed strong sentiments to one of the issues raised. In the post script Webb says she came to the meeting to see Skeffington and also inquire as to the health of Maggie. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47;, MS 33,604/15-11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/993</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0173">Deborah Webb</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0586">Irish Women&#39;s Franchise League, Antient Concert Buildings, 42e, Great Brunswick Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0993_img_2840_1"  type="Letter"  url="c46eac37c9ebaaf5dff3c1704fb6a8be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0993_img_2840_2"  type="Letter"  url="38c0a9717769864fa1559c3afcb35680.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0993_img_2840_1"/>
                IRISH WOMEN'S FRANCHISE LEAGUE,  ANTIENT CONCERT BUILDINGS  42e, GT. BRUNSWICK ST., DUBLIN.   Dear Mrs. Skeffington   Key  of press  is behind clock <lb/> &amp; others are in press. I met <lb/>Miss Blake &amp; she told me one <lb/>of the Teachers took away key <lb/>to hold meeting tonight here. <lb/>I think there might to be some <lb/>misunderstanding with those <lb/>people — they seem to be <lb/>holding meetings always.   I am surprised at Miss Connery's <lb/>statement and can attribute <lb/>it to nothing but temper <lb/>which she exhibited to <lb/>a marked degree on last <lb/>Committee night. The matter  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0993_img_2840_2"/>
              re: food supplies for dance <lb/>was settled by the <hi rend="underline">majority</hi><lb/>of the Committee when it was <lb/>decided that the dance if it <lb/>has to be held at all was to <lb/>be run on strict business <lb/>lines and Miss Maxwell was <lb/>deputed to write &amp; ask some <lb/>members if they were willing <lb/>to assist in organizing it <lb/>under these conditions.  The matter can come <lb/>up again at next meeting &amp; <lb/> you are perfectly at liberty <lb/>to read this at next Committee <lb/>meeting — in the presence <lb/>of Miss Connery. <seg type="closer"> Miss. D.W. </seg><seg type="postscript"> I came in this evening hoping to see <lb/>you as I am anxious to know how Maggie is. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>