<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4146">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Terence Duffin to his sister, Dorothy Duffin, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terence Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Terence (Terry) Duffin (b. 1886) to his sister, Dorothy Duffin (b. 1881). 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4146</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0305">Terence Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0699">Headquarters 107th Brigade, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4146_img_3520_1"  type="Letter"  url="e0c449bbebdbad1cc0f303632c14a11e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4146_img_3520_2"  type="Letter"  url="c6116d2edbd7c76c592e4ff9ab0ed9fc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4146_img_3520_3"  type="Letter"  url="74949958b190d8c9877399f1ffdd111c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4146_img_3520_4"  type="Letter"  url="f056c16eeb00353587104ed497902901.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4146_img_3520_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">Hd</seg>Ors 107 Bde <lb/> B.E.F. <lb/> France   My dear Dorothy   I have just heard the <lb/> good news through Edmund <lb/>and am most <hi rend="underline">awfully </hi> glad <lb/> — best of luck to both of <lb/> you — Write and tell me <lb/> all about it if you have time, <lb/> which I suppose you haven't.   Any how the War has done <lb/> you a good turn. I am <lb/> sure all at home will be pleased <lb/> about it.   We are up in the fighting <lb/> line again — All getting <lb/> on first rate though it has <lb/> poured with rain and blown <lb/> hard continuously for 3 days <lb/> — the trenches are in a terrible <lb/> state. I was up today
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4146_img_3520_2"/>
            and waded through water <lb/> and liquid mud up to my <lb/> knees — Most of the dug- <lb/>outs have fallen in and <lb/> likewise portions of the trenches <lb/> which means endless work <lb/> getting them repaired and <lb/> horrible discomfiture — Still <lb/> the men keep cheery through <lb/> it all and even prefer it to <lb/> their rest-billets when they <lb/>are doing fatigue work all <lb/>day — Any how the "<seg type="unclear">Beach</seg>" <lb/> suffers as much from the <lb/>weather as we do —    It seems funny when <lb/> You gaze out of a loop-hole <lb/> <seg type="del">and</seg>of a trench and see the <lb/> German lines only a few <lb/>hundred yards away — in <lb/> fact in some places the trenches <lb/> are only 70 yards apart ! 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4146_img_3520_3"/>
             The Brigade Hd. Ors are in <lb/> two houses side by side, in a <lb/> small village about a mile <lb/> from the trenches — Most of <lb/> the village has been fairly <lb/> well smashed up from time <lb/> to time by shell fire — the room <lb/> next to mine is a <seg type="unclear"><sic>comlete</sic></seg>"gonner" <lb/> A shell went clean through it <lb/> some weeks ago and no one <lb/> has thought it worth while <lb/> to square it up since — We <lb/> have a large cellar to retire <lb/> into if the occasion should <lb/> arise but so far we have <lb/> been left in peace.   Apparently there is nothing <lb/> fresh doing at home. — I <lb/> am glad to hear Edmund <lb/> keeps very much better <lb/> and that there is still
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4146_img_3520_4"/>
            a fair amount of work <lb/> going through the Office.   I don't know if you <lb/>have seen Major Smith <lb/> lately if so, you will know <lb/> what our latest Divisional <lb/> changes are which I cannot <lb/> mention — I haven't seen <lb/> him for a long time.   Well I must off to bed <lb/> now, I scarcely ever clear <lb/> the office work before 10 P.M <lb/> and it is now 11.30 P.M.and <lb/> <sic>a another</sic>days work before me <lb/> tomorrow.    Write soon if you can   Ever your loving    <hi rend="underline">Terry</hi>   12/11/15. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>