<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1321">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from O/C A Squad to the Adjutant, 2/1st Lothians and Border Horse, 13 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Smith Warling</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to the Adjutant of the 2/1st Lothian and Border Horse from Captain Arthur Smith Warling concerning Private Robert Atwell&#39;s desire for a commission and a course of training in the officer training corps. The letter recommends Atwell for the Commission as he is a good soldier with the exception of his horsemanship. This letter was part of the papers of Sir Henry Christopher Grattan Bellew (1860-1942), the third baronet of Mount Bellew in County Galway. He held the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel, 4th Battalion Connaught Rangers. His son, sir Charles Christopher (1887-1948) held the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel, King&#39;s Royal Rifle Corps. He was decorated with the award of the Military Cross (M.C.) in 1918</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bellew of Mount Bellew Papers, Collection List No. 33, Ms. 27,290</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1321</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0071">Arthur Smith Warling</persName>
              <date>1916-03-13</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Adjutant of 2/1st Lothian and Border horse</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1321_img_615_1"  type="Letter"  url="c70511e4e3996a35f551ef44e5be3acd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1321_img_615_1"/>
             <seg type="head">From <seg type="del">Reserve Regiment</seg> O/C A Squadron <lb/>2/1st Lothians and Border Horse <lb/>To The Adjutant <lb/>2/1st L&amp;B Horse.</seg>   7 Wemyss Place,  Edinburgh,    13 March 1916.     Re: Pte.Atwell has spoken <lb/> to me regarding his application <lb/> for a recommendation for a course <lb/> of training in an Officers <lb/> Training Corps.  Pte.Atwell is a <lb/>most hard working &amp; willing <lb/>man &amp; I would now, if I had <lb/>not done so before, <seg type="del">ask</seg>recommend <lb/>him for promotion except for the <lb/>fact that he is not a good <lb/>horseman.  Would the Commanding <lb/>Officer seeing Pte. <lb/>Atwell himself so that he <lb/>may form his own impression <lb/>of him personally!  Pte.Atwell informs <lb/> me that he joined the Regiment <lb/> because he wished to serve <lb/> in the <seg type="unclear">trenches</seg> but that he has <lb/> all along aimed for getting a <lb/> Commission in an Infantry Regt. <seg type="closer"> Arthur Smith Warling  capt</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>