<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1469">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from R.C. Barton to Mabel FitzGerald, 1 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>R.C. Barton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Robert Childers Barton (1881-1975), officer in charge of prisoners&#39; effects, Richmond Barracks, to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). The subject of this letter is Desmond FitzGerald&#39;s overcoat. FitzGerald had a number of transfers between prisons in Ireland before he arrived in Dartmoor Prison. The confusion about the coat arose when the officer in Richmond Barracks found a coat with a label showing the name FitzGerald and forwarded it to Mrs. Fitzgerald. It transpires that this coat belonged to another prisoner and that Mr FitzGerald was already in possession of his overcoat in Dartmoor.R.C. Barton joined the Irish Volunteers in 1913, acting as secretary to Colonel Maurice Moore (1854-1939). At the outbreak of the Great War, Barton accepted a commission in the British Army, serving in the Royal Dublin Fusiliers. In April 1916, he was dispatched to Dublin, where he could observe at first hand the treatment meted out to the rebels. Barton served for a period as officer in charge of prisoners effects at Richmond Barracks. He soon resigned his commission and joined the revolutionary movement. Mabel Fitzgerald was the wife of Irish Volunteer Desmond Fitzgerald. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1597/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1469</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0562">R.C. Barton</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1418">Richmond Barracks, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1437">2 Loretto Villa, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1469_img_919_1"  type="Letter"  url="c57bb298f6c70c616f805c64614d80cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1469_img_919_2"  type="Letter"  url="d778859fff6152972afd2dd29176c5c3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1469_img_919_1"/>
                To Mrs.Fitzgerald 2 Loretto Villas  Bray Co.Wicklow  From O i/c Prisoners Effects,  Richmond Bks Dublin    1/6/16   Madam;   I have received your letter of <lb/>31/5/16. Your letter informing me that your <lb/>husband's overcoat had already been sent to <lb/>Kilmainham reached me too late to enable <lb/>me to stop delivery of the one which I had here <lb/>which had a label bearing the name <lb/>Fitzgerald attached but as it had already <lb/>been forwarded to Headquarters for delivery <lb/>to you at the time I received your letter. <lb/>On receipt of your letter I immediately <lb/>enquired from the Com. <seg type="del">Command</seg>H.M.Prison <lb/><seg type="del">Kilmainham</seg> Mountjoy  who informed me that <lb/>Mr. Fitzgerald had his overcoat with <lb/>him at the time of his removal to <lb/>H.M.Prison Dartmoor.   Previous to the receipt of your letter <lb/> about the overcoat I had forwarded <lb/>to the Governor H.M.Prison   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1469_img_919_2"/>
              Mountjoy, the sum of Â£1-0-0 <lb/>for Thomas Desmond Fitzgerald <lb/>and I hold the Governor's receipt for this amount.   I note that you are returning <lb/>the overcoat which I sent to you &amp; <lb/>this will be delivered to <lb/>the rightful owner as soon as he <lb/>claims it.   I regret having caused you any <lb/>unnecessary trouble.   The sum of Â£1 was sent to the Gov <lb/>Mountjoy at Mr. Fitzgerald's desire <lb/>in letter addressed to me.  <seg type="closer">  RC Barton 2nd Lieut  O i/c Prisoners Effects  Richmond Bks    1/6/16.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>