<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4229">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 21 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter fromSir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/68</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4229</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1215">Wilfrid Spender </persName>
              <date>1915-11-21</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4229_img_3599_1"  type="Letter"  url="49a6f6cd8ea1207312b2607a7e37148f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4229_img_3599_2"  type="Letter"  url="5ba6cd157eeeb65ecd591899f599cddd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4229_img_3599_1"/>
             P.S. <lb/> Look up in <lb/> Castlefield report <lb/> sent you yesterday <lb/> please <lb/> a) N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> of Acres <lb/> planted <lb/> b) N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> to be planted <lb/> c) Total. <lb/> I forget figures. Please <lb/> send along report of <lb/> the <lb/> meetings <lb/> of Rubber Co<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> <lb/> so that I <lb/> may watch them.   21 Nov.   My p r .   2 such encouraging jolly letters must get some kind of acknowledge <lb/> ment even though it is little more than a growl.    It is astonishing how all the wild animals seem to take <lb/> to the p r . Evidently she is not yet domesticated ! Perhaps having been <lb/> 2 years with a very wildl animal has prevented the house <lb/> life from rubbing off the wildness.   I am rather glad you are at home just now as Mater may <lb/> have rather a trying time. Will Bennett has been made a Major &amp; it <lb/> may lead to a certain amount of disappointment &amp; a feeling of failure.   You can try &amp; explain the anomalous situation which I find to be: <lb/> a) Owing to my special qualifications I cannot be spared for Reg' duty. <lb/> b) If I had not got these special qualifications I should certainly have been <lb/> a Reg' Major &amp; <seg type="del">possibly</seg> probably a Lt Col by now <lb/> c) My appointment is much better regarded in respect of status, pay <lb/> &amp; prestige. It is seldom held by a Captain but <hi rend="underline">can</hi> be held by an <lb/> officer of Lt Col Maj or Capt's rank , &amp; consequently they decline to put <lb/> me up. This does not effect my pay which is 50% more than a Major's.   I give you the above details to try &amp; comfort the Mater who may be <lb/> upset about it.   Yes I wish we could have a scamper together old thing, I would <lb/> rather like to have a pup at my loving little p r strange to say.   When I feel inclined to wonder whether I would have taken the line <lb/> I did <seg type="del">when</seg> 2 1/2 years ago had I known what was in store for me I say to myself
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4229_img_3599_2"/>
            that if I hadn't I should not <lb/> probably be bothered with having a pink little beastie to look after, which <lb/> of course quite decides me. Which way?    I hope that what I sent on Friday may be of a little use to you. <lb/> I am sure you will be well advised to keep in touch with the Ulster <lb/> people, so if you do not go over there you can at any rate keep in letter <lb/> communication with them &amp; possibly the lists which I sent you may be <lb/> of use.  to them.  Russel and Richardson have gone to Kirk. I hope to get there tonight <lb/> but are rather glad of this quiet half hour.    Rubber is still bouncing &amp; at the present rates should bring our <lb/> income for the time being somewhere near the figure which successfully <lb/> baited a little wild animal 2 1/2 years ago ! The Germans must be trying <lb/> their hardest to get a substitute &amp; I shall watch the Intelligence reports <seg type="del">after</seg> <lb/> with the keenest interest to see if they succeed. The prices of shares have <lb/> gone up very little showing that this is only looked upon as a tempor <lb/> ary rise  in price  but whilst the p r holds the reins she will be able to show <lb/> that she at any rate was a good manager almost a financial magnate.   The more you tell me of your  Ulster CC  meetings the more necessary <lb/> does it appear for you to be independent, &amp; really I begin to wonder whether <lb/> you could not make my old study your office for ordinary days, but <lb/> it is not worth while starting that if you will be moving out soon.   It appears that you won't have a great deal to do if you only take <lb/> on the ASC RE  &amp; HQ here &amp; I expect you will feel inclined to prance away <lb/> if things don't improve, but you can carry on &amp; wait &amp; see how <lb/> things develop. I don't think my scheme would be bad if you can <lb/> get wholesale prices &amp; show the men how well you can do for them.   I am sure you will do no harm cnsulting Mr Cunningham.   Always your B W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>