<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6666">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Harkin to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 5 February 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Harkin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, Michael Harkin discusses with Joseph Cyrillus Walsh several organizational aspects. Among these are a meeting with a Miss MacSwiney and a request to Walsh to send Harkin some literature on the Association.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph Cyrillus Walsh Papers. Letters: Harkin, Michael 1920-1921 (2)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6666</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0181">Michael Harkin</persName>
              <date>1920-02-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1462">Denver, Colorado, 1929 Champa Street</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6666_img_None_1"  url="php9QR8yx.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6666_img_None_2"  url="phpP9Zy3X.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6666_img_0_1"/>
              1930 CURTIS STREET    PHONE MAIN 5413   DENVER CATHOLIC REGISTER  OFFICIAL ORGAN OF THE CHURCH IN COLORADO   DENVER, COLORADO    1929 Champa Street    Feb. 5 1920.    Dear Mr. Walsh:   I have just been thinking that it was you I met last<lb/>Spring at 411 Fifth Ave. New York. Weren't you in charge of the Bond<lb/>Drive then?  Thanks for your letter. Yes, 1929 Champa can be used as<lb/>headquarters here until things are got going. We were obliged to<lb/>vacate Curtis street, and the present office is not as desirable a<lb/>place as one could wish. However, for meeting purposes we can always<lb/>borrow the use of a hotel room.  I hope to have a wire the moment it is definitely known on<lb/>what date Miss MacSwiney will be here. Wednesday is the least desirable<lb/>evening of the week. Perhaps it will be possible to arrange for any<lb/>evening other than this one? I am thinking that we could give the new<lb/>Association a big send-off with Miss MacSwiney's coming. The Relief<lb/>people may also be anxious to avail of this occasion to launch their<lb/>campaign. However we can arrange about that. The first committee meeting<lb/>of this latter body will take place Tuesday night. I am hoping that I<lb/>shall then succeed in persuading the wealthy men taking part in that<lb/>organization to come in and accept office in ours.  I take it that state secretaryship is an entirely different<lb/>office from that of the local secretary? I have been suggesting an early meet-<lb/>ing of the F.O.I.F. to make arrangements to (-) shut up shop and get<lb/>into the A.A.R.I.I. I think it will be possible to get a good man to act<lb/>in Morgan's place. (<seg type="del">---------------------------------------------------)<lb/>(------------------------------------------------------------------------</seg>).<lb/>The only difficulty of making the transfer I was informed today was this<lb/>one. Morgan's office is considerably in debt, and that has got to be wiped<lb/>out before anything can be done. Few people want to give either the F.O.I.F.<lb/>or their secretary any money, which means that a hustle is out of the ques-<lb/>tion. Of course the debt has to be met and paid if the Association is to<lb/>have any credit.  I shall ask the bishop the boost the Recognition movement. The<lb/>clergy are enthusiastic, I have found out, and John McGauran, U.S. Sur-<lb/>veyor-General, has promised to go out to Pueblo and Colorado Springs to<lb/>speak at the opening meetings. He is a very fine orator, a spell-binder<lb/>in fact, and is a very popular figure throughout the state. He has promised<lb/>every co-operation.  Of course the beginning must be made in Denver. Now that Lent<lb/>is upon us I suppose it will not be possible to do as much as might be<lb/>accomplished at another time. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6666_img_0_2"/>
             We turn out an Easter number here, a publication that will keep me<lb/>busy for( some ) some time, by the way, and if you have any literature in<lb/>regard to the Association, one or two column articles, I would be glad<lb/>to have some to run in this number.  The Register at all times has been  a  strong supporter of the Irish<lb/>movement and the Manager assures me that it can always be counted on,<lb/>other demands notwithstanding, to give us space. Although I had a freee hand<lb/>there were things, I had to learn, that the office was interested in, and<lb/>other things it wasn't.  Through the state correspondents and some of the cleargy and<lb/>laymen I know, I shall be able later on to get a move made outside this<lb/>City. I shall keep you informed on events.  Very sincerely yours,  Michael Harkin   P.S. Do you think would it be possible<lb/>to have (?) come here<lb/>later on? His help at the (?)<lb/>would be invaluable.    M.H.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>