<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0723">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Anne Lambton to Lady Londonderry, 18 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Anne Lambton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence belonging to Lady Londonderry, a large proportion of which concerns Sir Edward Carson and opposition to the Third Home Rule Bill. Lady Londonderry was a prominent figure in politics and high ­society from 1890 until 1919. Her correspondence includes many important figures in literature, the arts, the military, law and the church.The author of this letter is Lady Anne Lambton (1870-1922), a friend of Lady Londonderry.This letter thanks Lady Londonderry for her recent visit, and expresses the hope that &#39;Celia&#39; is well and that the weather is not too cold.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>PRONI-D2846-2-21-50 [The Theresa, Lady Londonderry Papers]</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/723</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1062">Anne Lambton</persName>
              <date>1915-11-18T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0957">Lambton Castle, County Durham, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Theresa Talbot</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0723_img_2228_1"  type="Letter"  url="0afdde8bba7ff34915865ef20dbad4cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0723_img_2228_2"  type="Letter"  url="601633b0bf27ecb7254da3a7d5ea4008.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0723_img_2228_1"/>
                LAMBTON CASTLE  FENCE HOUSES.    18 Nov. 1915   My dear Lady Londonderry,   I am sending <lb/>back a letter of yours which <lb/>had slipped under the sofa.   It was very nice seeing <lb/>you again and &amp; very kind of <lb/>you to face such a climate. <lb/> I hope you found Celia <lb/> in a cheerful mood &amp;  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0723_img_2228_2"/>
              that you were not <lb/> perished with cold by <lb/>the time you got home.  <seg type="closer"> Yrs aff.  Anne Lambton. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>