<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0468">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dermot MacDermot to Edward O'Farrell, 21 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dermot MacDermot</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Dermot MacDermot to Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926), Assistant Under-Secretary, Dublin Castle, indicating they have met in person as MacDermot believes he inadvertently took O&#39;Farrell&#39;s spectacles case. Returning to the question of the post of Clerk of Crown and Peace for County Westmeath, MacDermot states that he would be suited to the post because of his court experience and clients in Westmeath and he spends much of his free time there.There are three testimonials enclosed, including one from the Clerk of Crown and Peace in Roscommon supporting MacDermot&#39;s candidature.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/10367/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/468</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1397">Dermot MacDermot</persName>
              <date>1916-06-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2072">Boyle, County Roscommon, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0468_img_1815_1"  type="Letter"  url="ae7e220d9d78ca2e5db4c53012e15e5e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0468_img_1815_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="a6ebd1f846fdecbc5051e2d9ca2332cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0468_img_1815_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="2d7dcc27c9a187fa6fcfd3d16fea0908.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0468_img_1815_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="1ef9dc35dca9655d0585f84f27f91e70.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0468_img_1815_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="030553046445c55c129bab0a95c414f9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0468_img_1815_1"/>
                Boyle,  Co. Roscommon.    June 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>   Dear Sir Edward O'Farrell   I found two spectacle cases in my pocket &amp; think <lb/>I must have taken yours  as I can't think of where else I could have got a second one.  Referring to Clerkship of <lb/>Peace might I mention one or two points. One of the <lb/>best posts in Co Roscommon is held by a Westmeath <lb/>Solicitor W. P. Kelly of Athlone, a solicitor to Land <lb/>Commission for Co Roscommon. All his other practice <lb/>is in Westmeath. 2) Clerkship of <sic>Cr</sic> &amp; Peace  held  by <lb/>a northern solicitor ( W Leahy). I have done some court <lb/>works  in Westmeath  and office works for Westmeath clients, &amp; nearly <lb/>all my spare time is spent in the county where <lb/>I have many friends, so I am not a stranger there.  Don't trouble to acknowledge <seg type="closer"> Yours  Dermot MacDermot </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0468_img_1815_2"/>
              Copy    Ballyburly,  Edenderry,   King's County.    Mr. Dermott McDermott of Boyle, in the County <lb/>Roscommon, has practised before me for the past eleven years as a <lb/>Solicitor in the County Courts of Counties Rossommon and Sligo and <lb/>I have much pleasure in stating that, in my opinion, he would make <lb/>an excellent Clerk of the Crown and Peace. He does his work very <lb/>well and knows the practice of the County Courts and of Quarter <lb/>Sessions thoroughly. He always makes up his cases really well and <lb/>attends to his business and works hard at it. I should like to add <lb/>that I have always found him a straightforward and honourable <lb/>gentleman in everything which he has done in my Courts and during the <lb/>many years that I have known him. <seg type="closer"> (Signed). John Wakely, <lb/>County Court Judge of Counties Roscommon and Sligo   October 27th. 1915.  </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0468_img_1815_3"/>
               Copy/    Essex Lawn,  Roscommon.    I have known Mr. Dermot MacDermot, Solicitor, Boyle, <lb/>since I became a Clerk of Crown and Peace for this County.  He is amongst the ablest Solicitors and enjoys one of <lb/>the most extensive practices in the County. He conducts his cases <lb/>with marked ability and in the equity side of the County Court, <lb/>where I come into close association with him, he displays a knowledge <lb/>and grasp of this work which I have seldom seen equalled.  I have much pleasure in stating my opinion that <lb/>Mr. Dermot MacDermot will filly any office to which he may be appointed <lb/>with dignity and honour. <seg type="closer"> (Signed.) William Early <lb/>Clerk of Crown and Peace <lb/>County Roscommon.   Roscommon    17th. June, 1916.  </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0468_img_1815_4"/>
              I can strongly re- <lb/>commend Mr Dermot MacDermot <lb/>for the office of <lb/>Clerk of the Crown &amp; Peace for the County <lb/>of Westmeath. He <lb/>is a well educated Lawyer and has a <lb/>good <seg type="unclear">career</seg> in  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0468_img_1815_5"/>
              Dublin University. <lb/>He has had very good <lb/>experience in the <lb/>practice of his <lb/>profession and is <lb/>universally esteemed <lb/>as a highly honour- <lb/>able gentleman. <seg type="closer"> Char. A O'Connor <lb/>Master of the <lb/>Rolls (Ireland)   June 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>