<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6648">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Joyce </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Joyce</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>Joyce, J. Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6648</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0393">James Joyce</persName>
              <date>1923</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName >None</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6648_img_None_1"  url="php2mpr5f.png"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6648_img_None_2"  url="phpqz8X6o.png"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6648_img_0_1"/>
             the prestige of the Italian primo   tenor   assoluto to be<lb/>shattered on the first hearing of Sullivan's voice in<lb/>London, New York and Chicago, which they , not without<lb/>reason, regard as provincial cities not very critical<lb/>but very lucrative for them. I have seen the Italian<lb/>notices of Sullivan in Italy. No tenor, Italian or<lb/>otherwise, has ever had such a press. It is monstrous<lb/>that the Italian ring in London and America and the<lb/>Irish ring there too should have been able to keep<lb/>him for fifteen years out of the theatres where his<lb/>fellow-countrymen could hear him. He is forty-nine<lb/>and what has to be done for him must be done immediately<lb/>and by somebody who puts up the money for these<lb/>theatres; nobody else can do anything against the<lb/>camorra.<lb/>Sullivan does not need to be told that he is the<lb/>greatest dramatic tenor at present alive and that there<lb/>have not been heard on the operatic stage for an<lb/>entire generation such ease of emission, splendour of<lb/>diction and magnificence of tone as he displays <seg type="unclear">xxxx</seg><lb/>every night he sings for 125 dollars.<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6648_img_0_2"/>
             I am giving you most of the facts but use only what y<lb/>you think effective.<lb/>With all my prayers to Saint Cecily for your<lb/>good success , and my warmest thanks,<lb/> sincerely yours   James Joyce       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>