<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0406">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard A. McDowell to Lord Wimborne, Ivor Guest, 18 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard A. McDowell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Richard A. McDowell, a Methodist accountant living in New Jersey, to Lord Wimborne (1873-1939), the lord lieutenant Sir Ivor Churchill Guest. McDowell writes concerning a meeting of a Methodist Episcopal Church in New Jersey and address made by Rev. Wilbert Westcott. In the speech Westcott discussed thousands of Irish men who fought in the trenches for &#39;England and civilization&#39;. The letter goes on to state that the speech was received well and requests a letter from Wimborne for regarding his speech. McDowell also states that he received a number of publications from Gilbert Parker (1862-1932), novelist and propagandist. The letter also discusses McDowells brother who was injured at Ypres, and an event in which McDowell saw Wimborne two years previous. He writes a visit to Clonmel made by the lord lieutenant, comparing it to the visit of his predecessor, however McDowell mistakenly states his predecessor was Earl Spence, when it was in fact John Campbell Hamilton Gordon (1847-1934).Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5613/8581</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/406</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1262">Richard A. McDowell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2065">Perth Amboy, New Jersey, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ivor Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0071">Phoenix Park, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0406_img_1668_1"  type="Letter"  url="f86b82d2892bcb0971a7851e4e7939ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0406_img_1668_2"  type="Letter"  url="885c93ab3b91d1ffa5224913bd89377d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0406_img_1668_3"  type="Letter"  url="c858d5dffd63e7be371831cfe60e70c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0406_img_1668_4"  type="Letter"  url="ae5c90cd4130884fba2330078e958461.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0406_img_1668_5"  type="Letter"  url="467923d6466cc335c850c9dd6b6c68fa.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0406_img_1668_1"/>
                Box No. 332,  Post Office,  Perth Amboy,  New Jersey,  United States of America    March 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    His Excellency,  Lord Wimborne,  Lord Lieutenant of Ireland,  Viceregal Lodge,  Phoenix Park,  Dublin, Ireland   My Lord   I take the liberty of writing to <lb/> you to mention an Irish entertainment <lb/>which took place in the  Simpson  Methodist <lb/> Episcopal church of Perth Amboy last <lb/>evening (cutting from a local newspaper <lb/>enclosed). The Pastor Rev Wilbert  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0406_img_1668_2"/>
              Westcott delivered a very witty address <lb/> on St Patrick and Ireland and <lb/> in the course of same scored in <lb/> very scathing terms the conduct of <lb/> the Irishmen who assembled in New York <lb/> (on March 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> at the Astor Hotel) <lb/>and lunched on champagne and <lb/> then delivered a tirade against <lb/>England hoping she would be defeated <lb/>&amp; and  when  at the same time there were <lb/>thousands of <seg type="del">Irishmen</seg> their fellow countrymen <lb/> in the trenches fighting for England <lb/> and <sic>civilization</sic>.   I am very pleased indeed to be <lb/> able to assure your Excellency that <lb/>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Westcotts remarks on this point <lb/> were very loudly applauded and created <lb/> a very strong impression on the <lb/> audience which numbered over <lb/>six hundred persons, and they were <lb/> most appropriate as this city has <lb/> a population of 40,000 and its <lb/>chief industry is copper refineries and <lb/>powder factories all of which are <lb/> working at their limit for the Allies.  I would be glad if your Excellency can <lb/> see your way to write me a personal <lb/> letter which I could forward to the <lb/> Rev Wilbert Westcott conveying your  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0406_img_1668_3"/>
              appreciation of his nice remarks <lb/>regarding the Irish race — <lb/>I know if you can do so it will <lb/> be very much appreciated by <lb/>M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Westcott and his congregation <lb/> and it will be a big help in <lb/> still stronger cementing the good will <lb/> which the Americans hold towards <lb/> our Gracious Majesty the King and <lb/> his people.  I may mention that Sir Gilbert Parker <lb/> a short time ago sent me a number <lb/> of publications and they were most <lb/><seg type="del">early</seg> eagerly read by the citizens <lb/> here and the newspapers are continually <lb/>printing extracts from them.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0406_img_1668_4"/>
              <hi rend="underline">PS</hi> If I may suggest <lb/> that in your Excellency's <lb/> letter if you can intimate that <lb/> you will convey to his Majesty <lb/> Mr. Westcott's kind remarks regarding <lb/> the soldiers in the trenches i am also sure <lb/> it will be gratefully received <lb/> R.A. McDowell <lb/><hi rend="underline">2</hi>  Personally I regret that my health <lb/>does not permit me to go onto <lb/> the firing lines but I am pleased <lb/> to say that the only brother I have <lb/> joined the First Canadian Contingent <lb/> and was unfortunately wounded in <lb/> the battle of Ypres on April 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/> 1915 and he is now employed <lb/> in the Pay and Record office of <lb/> the Canadian Forces at 7 Milbank <lb/> Street Westminster London.  Two years ago I had the <lb/> privilege of seeing your Lordship  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0406_img_1668_5"/>
              at the Polo grounds in New York <lb/> and I was delighted when I <lb/>received a letter a few weeks <lb/>ago from my native town <lb/> Clonmel to hear that your <lb/> Excellency had received such a <lb/> warm welcome I could not help <lb/> contrasting it with what I believe <lb/> was the last visit of a former <lb/> Viceroy (the late Earl Spencer) I was <lb/> then a schoolboy and he came <lb/> to Clonmel on a visit to the <lb/> Earl of Donoughmore at Knocklofty. <lb/>I was also pleased to see that <lb/>your Lordship was a guest of <lb/> M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Richard Burke whom I <lb/> was acquainted with when I <lb/> lived in Clonmel.  Trusting that your Excellency and <lb/> the Vicereine may have a <lb/>very happy and successful <lb/>administration. <seg type="closer"> I remain, yours sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Richard A: M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">c</hi></hi>Dowell</hi> </seg> P.S. I enclose <sic>you</sic> some cuttings from New York <lb/>papers which may interest you.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>