<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1284">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Fitzgerald to Michael Gorman, 25 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Susan Fitzgerald (d. 1980) to Michael Gorman. The letter refers mainly to a proposed meeting of the pair and Susan writes that she had been dropping hints to her mother to go for a holiday so they could meet in her house. She also briefly refers to events at home and to some mutual friends including &#39;Drew&#39;, James P Drew who went on to become a professor and head of Albert College.Michael Gorman was one a large Catholic family living at a farm in Ballinalug, County Laois (then Queen&#39;s County). Susan Fitzgerald was one a Church of Ireland family living in Raheenahone House near Stradbally, County Laois, also in the Slieve Bloom mountains. At the time the letter was written they were involved in a courtship but owing to the religious difference the love affair had to be kept secret. Eventually both were in Dublin: he in the Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin (where he eventually became Professor of Agricultural Botany and Biochemistry) and she as a volunteer nurse in the Royal Hospital in Baggot Street. They eventually went to London to marry.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Michael Gorman</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1284</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1259">Susan Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-07-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1800">Raheenahone House, Stradbally, County Laois</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Michael Gorman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1251">Albert Agricultural College, Glasnevin, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1284_img_490_1"  type="NULL"  url="93d2762e6f5fc80f6540c9181cd7b318.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1284_img_490_2"  type="NULL"  url="758bf0896d7caffc0f06392a698081c5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1284_img_490_3"  type="NULL"  url="3c57d11e9ffe9a2aa0d1fc0ef91ac36b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1284_img_490_4"  type="NULL"  url="5cc6e7213b32cadcadc682deb6208456.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1284_img_490_1"/>
              Writing at the top left-hand side written sideways  I'm delighted <lb/>with 'smirks sweet' <lb/>&amp;I'll tell you what <lb/>I think of it when <lb/>I see you.  love <lb/>Sue   Beginning of the letter   Raheena House Ho,  Stradbally  Queen's Co  <hi rend="underline">Sunday.</hi> Dearest old Mickie,   I was delighted <lb/>as usual to hear from <lb/>you on yesterday. I've had <lb/>a <hi rend="underline">fairly</hi> busy week <lb/>between tennis &amp; <seg type="unclear">picnic</seg>, <lb/>&amp; a Red Cross fete at <lb/>Mary bow'. The <seg type="unclear">tennis</seg><lb/>was held at a place  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1284_img_490_2"/>
               Note written on the side of the page  Give my best wishes to <seg type="unclear">wow</seg>. Tell him I <lb/>have lots of countrymen now - no need to go down Brumswell <lb/>Street   Continuation of the letter  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1284_img_490_3"/>
               I heard <seg type="unclear">Eddie Wyman</seg> is qualified &amp; expects <lb/>to be in the R.A.M.C. soon   Continuation of the letter have such a nice time <lb/>together, of course <seg type="unclear">we</seg><lb/>could do all this in Sept too <lb/>but August is so much <seg type="unclear">warmer</seg><lb/>&amp; I may not be able to get <lb/>to Dublin for some time. I <lb/>was delighted to hear all <lb/>about Cogley's party. I heard <lb/>Delaney play once in Athy &amp; <lb/>he plays well, I think. How <lb/>long are the <seg type="unclear">Sargent</seg> staying in <lb/>Dalkey. They must have a great <lb/>old time. I was very sorry to <lb/>hear the sad news about Madam <lb/>Brown Is she really bad or what <lb/>is wrong with her? I had a <lb/>letter from Mrs Noble asking <lb/>me up to see Florrie on Saturday. <lb/>She is very ill at present &amp; <lb/>suffering great pain.   I haven't anymore news so I'll finish With very best love <seg type="closer"> Yr  Sue. </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1284_img_490_4"/>
                M.J. Gorman Esq.,  Albert College  Glasnevin  <hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>