<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0935">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Thomas Heath to Sir Robert Chalmers, 10 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Heath</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Little Heath (1861-1940) to Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) concerning the salary of Resident Magistrates who are promoted from the second to the first class while on active service.Sir Thomas Little Heath was a British civil servant. From 1913 to 1919 he occupied the position of permanent secretary to the Treasury. Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5617, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5617</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/935</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1414">Thomas Heath</persName>
              <date>1916-07-10T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1551">Treasury Chambers, Whitehall, London SW, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0935_img_2719_1"  type="Letter"  url="b6388b81e48f38381f6d4066fcb2912c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0935_img_2719_2"  type="Letter"  url="4aacd9787346d56660590e88ded20988.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0935_img_2719_1"/>
              Any reply to this letter should be addressed to- <lb/>THE SECRETARY, <lb/>TREASURY, <lb/>WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W., <lb/>and the following number quoted.  16723 16    10 July 1916   Sir,   The Lord Commissioners of His Majesty's <lb/>Treasury have received from the Treasury Remembrancer copies <lb/>of communications with your Department on the subject of <lb/>the position of Resident Magistrates who are promoted <lb/>from the second to the first class while on active service, <lb/>as regards the balance of civil salary to be paid to them.  I am to request that you will inform the Lords <lb/>Justices that My Lords note that the Attorney General is <lb/>of opinion that in such cases the promoted officer cannot <lb/>legally be deprived of the civil pay attaching to his new <lb/>class, abated by his military pay and allowances.  I am to observe that the effect of this decision would be <lb/>almost the same in substance as if the balance of civil <lb/>pay were not increased, since under the Attorney-General's <lb/>ruling military allowances as well as military pay would be <lb/>deducted, <hi rend="underline">whereas under the Treasury Circulars military pay <lb/>alone is deducted.</hi> The allowances would in most cases <lb/>exceed the difference between the pay of the first and <lb/>second class.  My Lords are nevertheless willing to accept the <lb/>solution which is proposed, namely that the Treasury <lb/>Circular should be applied in the case of any similar <lb/>promotions  The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0935_img_2719_2"/>
              promotions proposed to be made hereafter but should <lb/>not apply to promotions already made. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   J.L. Heath  </seg> The signature is handwritten not typed.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>