<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1311">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to his son Piaras Béaslaí (1881–1965). Patrick Langford Beazley writes about recent family holidays, the condition of family friends, and of a fire in the Irish Journalists Association building which stored some of Piaras&#39; personal effects. He concludes with news of the recent annual meeting of the Irish Speaking League, noting that Piaras was elected president in absentia. Patrick makes further reference to the community of actors and enthusiasts in the Irish acting world that are associated with his works. This letter is part of a collection of letters by Piaras’ parents, mostly during Béaslai’s internment. Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley) was an English born writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, journalist and a member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He wrote twenty plays between 1913 and 1939. Patrick Langford Beazley was born near Killarney, Co. Kerry, son of a tenant who had been evicted from the Lansdowne estate. The Beazleys were an old family in Kerry, of English origin. He was the editor of the Catholic Times from 1884 until his death in the early 1920s.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, NLI33973/5/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1311</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1311_img_58_1"  type="Letter"  url="5150482f07abba400a1a2c40631e1ba2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1311_img_58_2"  type="Letter"  url="170a9cb565d5b7a8a027d15ee1bce401.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1311_img_58_3"  type="Letter"  url="f82817ccd1bc37e1fae4ddfce0b97a30.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1311_img_58_1"/>
              q116<lb/> P. <hi rend="underline">Beazley</hi>    Glengarriff,  Rudgrave Square  Egremont  Cheshire    7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October, 1916.   My dearest Pierce,   I have delayed this letter too<lb/> long, for I know how anxious Mother<lb/> and I were to hear from you and that your anxiety to <lb/>hear from us has been equally great. I need not say what <lb/>a delight it was to get your letter and to find that after <lb/>the long interval your spirits were as bright and cheerful<lb/> as when you wrote previously. Of course we feel that when<lb/> writing in such a happy, contented way you are, to comfort<lb/> us, taking as pleasant a view as possible of a situation<lb/> which, at the best, must be irksome owing to monotony<lb/> and perhaps trying in other respects, but we thank God<lb/> that your health keeps good and that your mind is so free<lb/> from worry and distress. May it be so all the time! Your<lb/> letter dealt with so many matters that I may not be able <lb/> to touch on them all this time, but as I shall have the <lb/> opportunity, please God, of writing again next month I can<lb/>then refer to any points I now pass over. I am very <lb/>glad that you have been mastering Spanish. It is, as you<lb/> know, a language which has great literary stores as well<lb/> as being important to-day for practical purposes. I was<lb/> not less gratified to learn that you are studying Virgil.<lb/> There is scarcely one of the classical authors from whom you <lb/>could derive so much benefit under present circum<lb rend="hyphen"/>stances. His pictures of the old Roman world are not<lb/> only charming, but always reposeful and soothing. The<lb/> Bucolics are more difficult than the Aeneid, but they give<lb/> glimpses of old pastoral romance which repay any trouble,<lb/> though the interest they excite is far inferior to that created<lb/> by the Idyls of Theocritus from which so much of them <lb/>is borrowed. I must pass from the old to the present<lb/> world. My holiday at Bray with Father James was <lb/>very pleasant. The weather could not have been better. <lb/>We spent a great deal of time on the promenade<lb/> and on the walk along Bray Head. There were a  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1311_img_58_2"/>
              good number of visitors, nearly all from different parts<lb/> of Ireland, I was told. We went to Dublin on several <lb/>occasions. I went twice to Gill's to see Mr. O'Kelly about<lb/> your manuscripts, etc., but he was out each time. I was <lb/>told on the second occasion that he was going on his<lb/> holidays. I had no opportunity of seeing any of your <lb/>Dublin friends as Father James regulated all our move<lb rend="hyphen"/>ments. He told me that Sara Scanlon (Mrs O'Connor)<lb/> and her husband happened to be in Dublin during <lb/>the trouble and had some exciting adventures in looking <lb/>for you. He also said that Ben's daughter, Frances, is <lb/>dying in a Paris convent. The only one of the relatives I<lb/> saw during the holiday was John Clancy. I called at<lb/> Sandycove and remained just about ten minutes. People<lb/> told me that I could not look better after the holi<lb rend="hyphen"/>day. I certainly felt very well, as I feel now, thank<lb/> God. Mother, though she has had no holiday, is also<lb/> well, thank God â in fact wonderfully well. But Lang<lb rend="hyphen"/>ford, I am sorry to say, is not in quite such good form. <lb/>He spent the three weeks of his holidays here. When he <lb/>came he seemed to have been suffering from a severe <lb/>cold. He looked rather thin. His voice was somewhat<lb/> hoarse, and he suffered on his feet, being unable to walk<lb/> as briskly as usual. He returned to Dublin a week <lb/>before I came back from Bray. He then walked nearly<lb/> as well as usual and his voice was considerably im<lb rend="hyphen"/>proved, but not quite clear. I wanted him to see a <lb/>doctor, but he very strongly held there was no need to <lb/>do so. Mr. Smyth, of the <hi rend="underline">Fireside</hi>,has been in Dublin<lb/> for his holidays and on his return last Monday I <lb/>asked him how Langford was. From what he said I <lb/>gathered that Langford still suffers from his feet when<lb/> walking and that his voice is still husky. I have, in <lb/>a letter, again impressed on Langford the advisableness <lb/>of seeing a doctor. In his letters he is cheerful and says<lb/> his feet are all right and that his voice is nearly so. Now  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1311_img_58_3"/>
              as to business. We have left your books and manuscripts at Lang<lb rend="hyphen"/>ford's. I understand that Dr. Davitt is the man to apply to for the <lb/>money due for the shorthand note of the Anti-Taxation Society's meet<lb rend="hyphen"/>ing. I shall find out his address and write to him. As to<lb/> what you left in the Irish Journalists' Association's Office, <lb/>the building was partly destroyed by the fire which raged from<lb/> Abbey Street down to the river on the occasion of the insurrec<lb rend="hyphen"/>tion, but Langford says the handbag has been saved and also <lb/>a manuscript in your handwriting. As I stated in my last<lb/> letter, a souvenir of yours was likewise found and pres<lb rend="hyphen"/>erved, but there is no account of a stick. The account will<lb/> be all right. The gold tiepin and Belt Langford will get. He<lb/> has seen Mr. Burke. I have had letters from Messrs.<lb/> O'Kelly, Hegarty, O'Sullivan and R. O'Foghida, all ask<lb rend="hyphen"/>ing to be cordially remembered to you. Mr. Hegarty said<lb/> he would attend to your request in regard to the production<lb/> of your play by the London Gaelic League and the copies of your<lb/> latest play for Gill's. Your play was not produced at the<lb/> Gaelic Festival at Waterford. The Festival was held not in <lb/>Waterford but in Dublin. There were, I am told, no enter<lb rend="hyphen"/>tainments beyond a reception and a concert. The atten<lb rend="hyphen"/>dance was large. The lay vice-president was promoted<lb/> to the presidency and Mr. O'Kelly to the vice-presidency. The Irish<lb rend="hyphen"/>speaking League has prospered by leaps and bounds and <lb/>you were elected president at the annual meeting. The<lb/> Aisteoiridhe are arranging to produce one of your<lb/> plays at the Samhain festival. Langford has seen the<lb/> Merries and explained that they could not communicate<lb/> with you except through me. All your old friends have<lb/> been <sic>enquiring</sic> about you and have asked to be remem<lb rend="hyphen"/>bered to you. Carey was up here for his holidays and<lb/> stayed here a couple of nights. He is as lively and as<lb/> fond of jokes as ever. Mr. Smyth and a large number of<lb/> their friends often talk of you. I have to draw to a close<lb/> now as mother is to fill the other page; so I send you our<lb/> hearts' fondest love â Mother's, Langford's and my own and pray<lb/> that God may always bless you. <seg type="closer"> Ever affectionately,  Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>