<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4384">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to her aunt, Ellie,  12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers; D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4384</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0185">7 Westcliff, Eastbourne, Sussex,  England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4384_img_3739_1"  type="Letter"  url="68b717f05e3e0d3daaec1595d9aa93fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4384_img_3739_2"  type="Letter"  url="10e5507219f6b99555f34b39400c2edf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4384_img_3739_3"  type="Letter"  url="f6f0d5d3f2420e942a3b8e4b56defbad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4384_img_3739_1"/>
             7. West Cliff<lb/>Eastbourne   12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  Nov 1915.  My dear Aunt Ellen,   Thanks so much for your letter I<lb/>put off replying till after I had been to London.<lb/>I went up on Monday last — stayed for 3 days<lb/>with the Miss Bruces, where Hilda <seg type="unclear">Swannir</seg><lb/>was also. I was rather unlucky with poor<lb/>Celia as I only saw her for about 1/2 an hour<lb/>the first <sic>evg</sic>. when she rushed up. It was well<lb/>she did as our arrangements to meet the<lb/>next day were frustrated by her returning to<lb/>bed with a rheumatic chill. At first she<lb/>thought it was mumps &amp; was carried off to<lb/>a quarantine ward &amp; I was much alarmed<lb/>thinking of her that way for months without<lb/>a friend to see her. This morning she wrote<lb/>she is much better &amp; has been out for a walk<lb/>&amp; has a fire in her room, perhaps you will<lb/>telephone this to mamma as I wrote to her<lb/>yesterday.     I went to see Iris &amp; Tom  Tom Sinclair (cousin) badly wounded  who were just leaving<lb/>to return to Woolwich that afternoon.<lb/>Tom looks not very well yet but says he is<lb/>going to be alright now. I think he was pretty 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4384_img_3739_2"/>
            <lb/>bad, but now that he is better it is well for it <lb/>will keep at least 3 months longer at home. <lb/>Iris looked very well &amp; is looking forward with <lb/>much happiness to the arrival.   Her brother was home on 5 days leave &amp; just <lb/>going back that day. He is at Ypres also &amp; <lb/>must be somewhere near Charlie.   London looks very full &amp; very busy &amp; many <lb/>soldiers &amp; foreigners about. It is dark at <lb/>night but not so very dark as Eastbourne <lb/>where one has to grope one's way around after <lb/>sunset. We saw a whole row of German <lb/>guns on view at Whitehall.   There are very few busses &amp; many vans and motor <lb/>vehicles driven by women and women porters <lb/>at the shop doors.  <lb/>Dorothy &amp; my collection for the Hut is getting <lb/>on well. I have about <hi rend="underline">£35.</hi> mamma says <lb/>she has for me a contribution from you <lb/>which is very good of you all 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4384_img_3739_3"/>
             Today it is pouring heavily here &amp; there <lb/>was a storm last night. I am told one of <lb/>the air ships escaped by itself &amp; disappeared <lb/>in the clouds &amp; no news of it.   I hope that Aunty <seg type="unclear">Cha</seg> is better &amp; that you <lb/>are all well &amp; working too hard.    We have 2 guests here at present so Mim <lb/>Roberts is enjoying having them &amp; there is great <lb/>chit chat going on.   Much love to all the Aunties. <lb/>Your affectionate niece   Olive Duffin. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>