<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3011">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Pearse to Mr. O'Danaher, 9 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Pearse</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Patrick Henry Pearse (1879-1916) to Mr. O&#39;Donaher, the father of a pupil of Pearse. In this letter, Pearse tells Mr. O&#39;Danaher that he has enclosed a statement of money owed for the &#34;books and sundries&#34; which Tom, a pupil, has been supplied with since coming to St. Enda&#39;s. Pearse writes that he has allowed credit to Mr. O&#39;Danaher for the half-year of violin lessons which Tom did not receive, and that by the end of the school year, Tom will have received a half-year&#39;s worth of lessons. Pearse reports that Tom &#34;is very well, and is working satisfactorily&#34;.

Pearse was a writer, a teacher, and a revolutionary nationalist. A strong critic of the soulless by-rote approach to learning he termed the &#34;murder machine&#34;, Pearse was the founder in 1908 of St. Enda&#39;s College, a bilingual school for boys with an ethos based around the needs and imaginations of the children themselves. He was a key member of the military council of the Irish Republican Brotherhood, and was one of the signatories of the proclamation of the Irish republic (largely his own writing), which he read outside the GPO after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. As president of the provisional government, it was Pearse who called the surrender. He was executed on 3 May 1916.

The signature on the letter has been cut out and &#34;stolen&#34;, as noted by a second hand on the letter. On the reverse side of the letter, a third hand has made semi-illegible notes, one section of these apparently relating to the &#34;progress&#34; of the O&#39;Danaher children, and another mentioning a &#34;commercial institute&#34; and &#34;bookeeping&#34; [sic.]. This side of the letter contains a fraction of a date: October 1919.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Military Archives of Ireland, Br Allen Collection, Pearse Collection, IE/AL/PC/9?31</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3011</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0387">Patrick Pearse</persName>
              <date>1916-04-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr. O&#39;Danaher</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3011_img_2412_1"  type="Letter"  url="b3f448601c22e97ea74eb404cc0b854e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3011_img_2412_2"  type="Letter"  url="5797308d9e33e3ea105ba0578be81ad3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3011_img_2412_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">IE/AL/PC/9/31</seg>   9-4-16    Dear Mr. O'Danaher   I am enclosing statement of a/c for<lb/>the books and sundries with which Tom<lb/>has been supplied since coming to St.<lb/>Enda's, giving you credit for the half-<lb/>year's <seg type="del">work</seg> violin lessons which he did<lb/>not receive. Between the two teachers<lb/>he will have received a half-year's<lb/>lessons by the end of the school year.  He is very well, and is working<lb/>satisfactorily.   Believe me<lb/>Sincerely yours    Some one stole this<lb/>signature T.D  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3011_img_2412_2"/>
             me well so far with the school books and has been out <lb/> at 6-12-15. I hope she continues to <lb/><seg type="unclear">make this</seg> progress in the future. She is much more <lb/> <seg type="unclear">interested</seg> than her brother Tom. <lb/>1-10-19. <seg type="unclear">slow</seg> with the <sic>voilin</sic> now under <lb/> Mr. <seg type="unclear">Arthur</seg> Chorley Old Road, Bolton.   Commenced Day School, Commercial Institute, <lb/> subjects; short-hand writing, Bookeeping, &amp; <lb/>Office routines 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>