<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1048">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from K.E. Fitzgerald to Clara Davidson, 5 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>K.E. Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter of condolence from K.E. Fitzgerald to Clara Mary Davidson (1852). Fitzgerald was second in command to Clara&#39;s son, James, who died on the first day of the battle of the Somme. Fitzgerald describes James&#39; conduct during the battle, describing him as a great officer. He concludes that only one in ten officers remain in his company. This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>PRONI-D3642-B-8-63, PRONI-D3642-B-8-63</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1048</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1288">K.E. Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1048_img_3138_1"  type="Letter"  url="84ca6a4775da17a7de608c0508e5fd33.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1048_img_3138_2"  type="Letter"  url="a00146dcc78652bfc179c37368d607e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1048_img_3138_3"  type="Letter"  url="32641cc76a4d4b58f48faee066ea590a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1048_img_3138_4"  type="Letter"  url="20a748e21c068232e2554c1c3924892c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1048_img_3138_1"/>
                5' <hi rend="underline">July</hi>1916   Dear <hi rend="underline">Mrs</hi>Davidson,   You will doubtless <lb/>have heard by this time of the death <lb/>of your dear son Capt Jim. I was his <lb/>2<hi rend="underline">nd</hi>in Command &amp; I feel his loss both <lb/>as a personal friend and as my <lb/>Senior Officer. <hi rend="underline">Mr</hi>Ashcroft has <lb/>told you all so I need not repeat <lb/>anything. His untiring spirit and <lb/>heroic conduct whilst wounded in <lb/>the knee, meant the holding of <lb/>hostile bombing <seg type="unclear">party</seg> in check <lb/>for almost a day. He knew no <lb/>fear. I wish I could say that <lb/>of myself. He was the best <lb/>Officer one could desire to be <lb/>led by as he was kind, brave <lb/>and thoroughly conversant <lb/>with all the workings of a <lb/>machine gun Corp. I offer to <lb/>you and his bereaved  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1048_img_3138_2"/>
              father my sincere sympathy <lb/>in your trial and <seg type="unclear">cruel</seg><lb/>loss. He and I knew each <lb/>other from the earliest days <lb/>at Greypoint. We never had <lb/>a row and I always did <lb/>what I could to assist <lb/>him in having a Company <lb/>which any officer might be <lb/>proud of. I will guarantee <lb/>that Capt Davidsons <sic>Coy</sic> Abbreviation for Company <lb/>could compete with any <lb/>Company in the Corps, in <lb/>every respect. What was this <lb/>due to — well it simply was <lb/>this. Capt Davidson was <lb/>a strong officer, capable <lb/>in every respect, most <lb/>thorough and painstaking  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1048_img_3138_3"/>
              I cannot find words to express <lb/>all I thought of him. I <lb/>must not worry you with <lb/>anymore writing. Please <lb/>excuse me if this letter seems <lb/>childish as I feel it is. I cannot <lb/>collect my wits as I am almost <lb/>driven stupid. Four officer out <lb/>of ten is all I have left.  Some parcels came with <lb/>cakes, butter &amp; <seg type="unclear">therein</seg> and <lb/>we decided to consume <lb/>same as the Capt said we <lb/>were to do if anything <lb/>ever happened him. This was <lb/>a mutual arrangement <lb/>all around, as we knew it <lb/>would be a silly thing to <lb/>send them back.  Please excuse me for <lb/>addressing you as I do, but I <lb/>take the liberty in these sad <lb/>circumstances. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely  K.E Fitzgerald </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1048_img_3138_4"/>
                M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi>Davidson  (?) Seabright  Bangor  Co Down.   5/7/16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>