<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1505">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington to John Dillon, c. October 1916. </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington (1877-1946) to John Dillon (1851-1927) . Sheehy-Skeffington wonders if the report of the inquiry will be a &#39;white-washing&#39; exercise but says that either way it is valuable &#39;for its strictures on Martial Law&#39; but the real culprits, the military authorities in Dublin Castle will not be blamed. She reports that none of the property taken in raids on her home has been returned. She also outlines what appears to be harassment of her landlady, Mrs. Schmutz while Mrs. Sheehy-Skeffington was away on holiday. Detectives had called on a number of occasions demanding information as to Mrs. Sheehy-Skeffington&#39;s whereabouts and threatening the landlady with penalties. She also reports an incident with detectives which arose when her mother was being removed by ambulance. She asks Mr.Dillon to make representations on her behalf so that these activities can be curtailed and wants to know if the Government wishes her to report as an &#39;alien&#39; (one of the detectives is based in the Aliens Department).Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged. John Dillon was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs.Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, MS6837/28/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1505</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0722">Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-10-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1322">43 Moyne Road, Ranelagh, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1103">House of Commons, London, England; re-directed to 2 North Gt. Georges Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_1"  type="Envelope"  url="024aa63125d5883df8f3886fb8fbf2ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_2"  type="Envelope"  url="8465d27344a2e7f365ecf4b70746d387.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_3"  type="Letter"  url="2fdd08829ce3fb759c334dbd3c38d6fb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_4"  type="Letter"  url="597b6cc447cd8dfe472c9b611c93cde4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_5"  type="Letter"  url="165bcd405ed97832ca4effa83721d2d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_6"  type="Letter"  url="7cb077621cba129a29152be3d83fd2d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1505_img_963_7"  type="Letter"  url="e2e137e03e45af5f59ec0f48590a735a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_1"/>
              Wrote <lb/>  22 Oct <hi rend="underline">1916</hi>    43 Moyne Rd  Ranelagh   Dear Mr Dillon,   I should be glad to <lb/> know whether the question <lb/> of the inquiry is likely to be the <lb/> subject of comment in the <lb/> House of Commons &amp;, if so, what <lb/> form the debate is likely to <lb/> take? As was to be anticipated <lb/> it seems to me largely a white- <lb/>washing report, still such as <lb/> it is, it is valuable for its <lb/><seg type="unclear">pictures</seg> on martial law. <lb/> It does not however fasten the <lb/> blame on the real culprits, <lb/> the military authorities in <lb/> Dublin Castle.   So far, although we have re<lb rend="hyphen"/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_2"/>
              peatedly inquired no further steps <lb/> have been taken to return to me <lb/> the property raided in my house. <lb/> I had hoped that the inquiry <lb/> would force them to disgorge at <lb/> least my personal belongings <lb/> or attempt to trace their where- <lb/>abouts.   Sir Francis Vane states categorically <lb/> that when he interviewed  <lb/> Price <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the murder to try to <lb/> get Colthurst arrested he replied <lb/><hi rend="underline">'Some of us think anyhow that <lb/> it was a good thing that Sheehy <lb/> Skeffington was put out of the <lb/> way.' </hi> That is significant.   Another significant fact is that <lb/> when I went away recently for <lb/> a brief holiday, on doctor's advice <lb/> leaving no address to have <seg type="unclear">conversations</seg><lb/>forwarded, the detectives  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_3"/>
              besieged my landlady, worrying her <lb/> with all kinds of questions &amp; <lb/> threatening her with serious <lb/> penalties for not knowing my <lb/> address, so that she was afraid <lb/> her house would be raided &amp; <lb/> was timid about receiving me <lb/> back. I should be obliged if <lb/> you could ask a question or <lb/> make some inquiry into the <lb/> matter so that some check <lb/> may be put on the activities <lb/> of these gentlemen at the castle. <lb/>For myself I do not mind how <lb/> much they watch, but I do not <lb/> wish my friends or landlady <lb/> to be annoyed.   Last week my mother was gravely <lb/> ill &amp; was being removed in an <lb/> ambulance when detectives <lb/> appeared &amp; actually peered into  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_4"/>
              her face as she was being removed <lb/> apparently under the impression <lb/> that it was I ! These things <lb/> would be laughable &amp; unbelievable <lb/> in any other country but ours.   The officer who made these <lb/>inquiries is Sergeant McGahey <lb/> who is in charge of the 'aliens' <lb/> department &amp; a constable Devine <lb/> of the 'G' Division <seg type="del">he</seg> also <lb/>distinguished himself.   If the government wishes me <lb/> to report as an 'alien' enemy <lb/> I should prefer to know definitely <lb/> The grievance in this case seems to <lb/> have been that I left no address <lb/> but I have frequently done this <lb/> when I did not wish to be worried <lb/> with correspondence. My landlady <lb/> states that in no other case has <lb/> she had inquiries made when  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_5"/>
              other lodgers went on holiday.   I hope I am not worrying you <lb/> unduly in this matter â trivial <lb/> in themselves, but apparently part of <lb/> a policy. I feel that you will help <lb/> me if anyone can.  <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_6"/>
                John Dillon Esq M.P   2 North Gt. George St. <seg type="del">House of Commons</seg>  Dublin <seg type="del">London</seg>    
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1505_img_963_7"/>
               Blank envelope   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>