<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3744">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Florence Underwood to the Secretary, 29 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Florence Underwood</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Florence Underwood to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1977-1946) inquiring whether Skeffington&#39;s organisation would be interested in collaborating in a meeting with various suffrage organisations. 

Florence Underwood was the secretary to the Women&#39;s Freedom League. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/13-18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3744</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0199">Florence Underwood</persName>
              <date>1915-11-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0163">144 High Holborn, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3744_img_3131_1"  type="Letter"  url="6bf9aee619bad1daab4f5beaa2c9f57a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3744_img_3131_1"/>
             Votes for Women. Women's Freedom League.  Weekly Paper: THE VOTE.  President: Mrs. DESPARD.<lb/>Hon. Treasurer: Dr. ELIZABETH KNIGHT.<lb/>Hon. Organisinig. Sec.: Miss EUNICE MURRAY.<lb/>Head of Political &amp; Militant Dept.: Miss. C. NINA BOYLE.<lb/>Secretary: Miss F. A. UNDERWOOD.  Telephone: Museum 1429.<lb/>Telegrams: Despaard, Museum 1429, London.:<lb/>Colourrs: Green, Gold &amp; White.   Offices: 114 High Holborn<lb/>W.C.    29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> November, 1915    Dear Madam,   We feel that now is the time for an important<lb/>rally of suffragists of all suffragist societies to make an<lb/>uncompromising demand for Votes for Women. Would your<lb/>Society be willing to take part with us in such a meeting?<lb/>We think that Sunday afternoon, December 12th or December 19th<lb/>would be the best dates, and we find that we can get the<lb/>large Portman Rooms on both these days. We in no way wish<lb/>this to interfere with the Albert Hall meeting which it has<lb/>already been proposed to run in February, but we are con—<lb/>vinced that an earlier meeting is necessary at the present<lb/>crisis  Will you kindly let me know, tomorrow by telephone,<lb/>if possible, so that we can get a notice into the various<lb/>suffrage papers this week:<lb/><lb/>(a) if your society would join in this meeting.<lb/>(b) which date you consider most suitable, the 12th ot<lb/>19th pr ox.<lb/>(c) if you will send a representative to a meeting at<lb/>this office Saturday morning, December 4th at<lb/>11 o'clock, to confer with us as to how the<lb/>expenses of this meeting, and any of its profits<lb/>should be shared amongst the Societies taking part<lb/>in it, how best to make the meeting known amongst<lb/>all suffragists, and who are to be the speakers.<lb/>We also should agree on a resolution to be put to<lb/>the meeting.   Awaiting the favour of your reply,<lb/>I am,<lb/>Yours faithfully, <lb/>Florence A. Underwood. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>