<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5276">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 10, November, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell expresses gratitude for a parcel received. Politics and family matters are discussed. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5276</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-11-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5276_img_None_1"  url="1fca3be0e04750c4034a6eac7805a673.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5276_img_None_2"  url="2a36a0f0a225566105f4db7f345ec402.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5276_img_None_3"  url="64c356e9e001179238e7eae1f93d1b5a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5276_img_0_1"/>
              Saturday night    10/11/17    My dear mamy   Two splendid parcels came today, one<lb/>containing fruit and clothes.  The fruit<lb/>is in perfect order and delicious.  The<lb/>other parcel was a real treat.  It was<lb/>dated 1 Nov and containing honey<lb/>which arrived in perfect condition<lb/>Not a single cell broken.  Also<lb/>the chocolate and sweets were<lb/>delicious.  It was not a bit<lb/>spoiled by being so long on the way.  I did not post a letter to you <lb/>today as I had no time to write one.  We are now billeted for a day or<lb/>two in the large town and are<lb/>very comfortable again.  This was<lb/>a wretched wet day and I hope the<lb/>weather is not going to continue so.<lb/>I don't care really so long as we<lb/>are in billets like this but in the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5276_img_0_2"/>
             trenches it is no <seg type="unclear">bon</seg>  I am writing Bobby a good<lb/>birthday letter tomorrow. It<lb/>ought to reach him about the<lb/>right date.  You all seem to be expecting<lb/>a rebellion any day. I have seen<lb/>a lot about it in the paper as<lb/>well as what you tell me but<lb/>I hope things will keep quiet.<lb/>The Italian &amp; Russian situation<lb/>could not be worse but to the<lb/>devil with them all, will beat<lb/>the boshe ourselves.  We are all to be entertained<lb/>at a theatre, the divisional<lb/>poirot troupe are giving us a<lb/>special show previous to our<lb/>departure. All the generals in    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5276_img_0_3"/>
             France are coming to bid us a goodbye<lb/>or how d'ye do during the next<lb/><seg type="del">Im </seg> few days.  I had a long letter from Mrs Howe<lb/>yesterday.   I am sending you her<lb/>letter.  Minnie sent me Bobby's letter<lb/>long ago telling about walking<lb/>the others into the ground.  He<lb/>seems to be getting on quite well<lb/>&amp; his writing &amp; spelling is immensely<lb/>improved.  No more news but I wont<lb/>close my letter till tomorrow in<lb/>case there is anything to add.  Sunday morning<lb/>There is nothing more to add to<lb/>my letter.  This is a nice fine day<lb/>so far. Very best love to all from<lb/> Your most afec Son<lb/>Willie          
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>