<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5555">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 23 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5555</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-02-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2121">Togherstown, Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5555_img_651_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc52f00f6809dad7e28796969771d9bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5555_img_651_2"  type="Letter"  url="0d49c81ec34d22b5a7e492c3e169d19d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5555_img_651_3"  type="Letter"  url="b721368af3bf7a71f91c2fd7926f3f50.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5555_img_651_1"/>
            <!-- End of letter written at the top left hand side sideways --> comes to meet you. I have no more news so<lb/>I will say bye-bye to my<lb/>own little man (rather<lb/>soon to be holding such<lb/>a grip on you) very<lb/>very best love to my<lb/>dear James  from his<lb/>loving   <hi rend="underline">May   </hi>  <!-- Beginning of letter --> Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar <lb/> 23 Feb. 1916. <lb/> My dearest James,   I know a am horrid<lb/>not to have written to you yesterday<lb/>you are so good to write and you<lb/>so very busy always but I intended<lb/>writing only I had a bad head 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5555_img_651_2"/>
             ache &amp; went to bed with it I<lb/>slept until I missed a chance<lb/>of posting you can know it<lb/>is not always easy to post here<lb/>messengers sometimes are<lb/>very scarce. But it’s not what you<lb/>would call cute of me to tell I<lb/>would go to bed with only a head<lb/>ache but I’m not one to be fond of<lb/>lying up with anything whatever<lb/>gives me that bad head ache I don’t<lb/>know it was not the winter gardens<lb/>this time However I must thank<lb/>God they are few and far between.<lb/>I feel quite fresh after it today   and always do I never was as much<lb/>ashamed as I was to have to go to bed<lb/>that night in your house. I had to do it<lb/>or I would never have gone. I’m sure your<lb/>mother thought it very –well pettish if<lb/>you like, what matter now if she never<lb/>thinks worse of me than that I’m very<lb/>safe.  Joe Finn has come from the<lb/>fair he got not what he expected but<lb/>beat us by 5/- that was a consolation<lb/>to him Christy got £5.10 each for 5 five pigs<lb/>but gave most of it back again<lb/>for a fat pig, there were great prices<lb/>got but I don’t think people were<lb/>satisfied.  Mattee Keanan the black smith    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5555_img_651_3"/>
             was going round with his love letters<lb/>Sunday I was not at home but he was<lb/>asking Mrs S. about “us” he said<lb/>he thought you’d be a priest long<lb/>ago, he used to be serving mass with<lb/>you long ago, he gave you great praise<lb/>says it’s a <hi rend="underline">“prince”</hi> you ought to be<lb/>married so now.-  Tim is getting on grand he wrote<lb/>to us &amp; to Mrs Seery. Jennie’s little boy<lb/>got jealous when he saw Tim &amp; left.<lb/>She will get it very hard to get another.  I will be in Mullingar Sat so will<lb/>my Mother but she will go home<lb/>in the <seg type="unclear">sim</seg>. I expect &amp; I will wait for<lb/>somebody to bring me home I<lb/>suppose I’ll get a seat from whoever    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>