<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3766">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Clara Davidson, 9 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Captain James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother Clara Mary Davidson informing her how he has spent the last few days of his leave. Davidson notes that the leave has done him a lot of good and hopes it will only be about three months before he is granted leave again. 

This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers, D3642-B-8-42</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3766</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1518">Jermyn Court Hotel, Piccadily Circus, Jermyn Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3766_img_3152_1"  type="Letter"  url="e0cd17ec098c2b023006d2738be07ada.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3766_img_3152_2"  type="Letter"  url="5993ec2543e13c5f2d60a398fb5cefca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3766_img_3152_3"  type="Letter"  url="7bc88cc4d83dfa99038aaf71a6322956.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3766_img_3152_4"  type="Envelope"  url="f7b2e7053ffdf295772cf8f0c2cecd09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3766_img_3152_5"  type="Envelope"  url="1b4cb0a2ee240fafb779af6421630d7a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3766_img_3152_1"/>
             JERMYN COURT HOTEL <lb/>PICCADILLY CIRCUS. <lb/>Main Entrance:- Jermyn Street, S.W.    9<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> April   My dearest Mother   This is another <lb/>lovely day &amp; am going <lb/>motoring with a man <lb/>I know out Richmond <lb/>way. Leave is up <lb/>tomorrow. It has all
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3766_img_3152_2"/>
            gone past so quickly <lb/>but it has been a delightful <lb/>little change &amp; done me <lb/>a lot of good. Perhaps <lb/>the next leave will come <lb/>round sooner — it should <lb/>be in 3 months.   Mrs Ducat dined with <lb/>me last night &amp; we <lb/>went to see Romance. <lb/>It was one of the best <lb/>things I have seen for
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3766_img_3152_3"/>
            a long time. The train <lb/>was awfully late arriving <lb/>on Sat. &amp; I only had time <lb/>to go &amp; order a pair of boots <lb/>at Faulkners &amp; get one <lb/>or two other odds &amp; ends <lb/>but will finish my shopping <lb/>tomorrow. The boots <lb/>will be sent to Seacourt &amp; <lb/>then I will let you know <lb/>when to send them to me. <lb/>Will post a pair of shoes <lb/>home tomorrow before <lb/>leaving. With my fondest <lb/>love &amp; hoping dear Mother <lb/>you will keep well while <lb/>I am away   Your loving son   Jim 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3766_img_3152_4"/>
             Mrs. S.C. Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor <lb/>Co Down <lb/>Ireland   8-10 April 16 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3766_img_3152_5"/>
             JERMYN COURT HOTEL <lb/>Piccadilly Circus. <lb/>Main Entrance:Jermyn Street,S.W 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>