<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5199">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Daly to Liam Daly, 6 April 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Daly </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/7/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5199</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0946">May Daly </persName>
              <date>1923-04-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1113">KnockaneCoolteen, Ballyfinane, Firies, Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0375">Liam Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1982</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5199_img_None_1"  url="3adb2952952f2735b7a9bccb6897761b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5199_img_None_2"  url="6917ed6710ffbaeb795d03f1f8c27892.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5199_img_0_1"/>
              P41/7/16    Monday night.    Líam a Cara Dílis   Received your letter on Thursday last. <seg type="unclear">begora</seg> we were<lb/>beginning to think did you forget the home address. <seg type="unclear">two</seg> to the Bungalow and<lb/>none here. But as you say it could not be helped. So we will forgive you<lb/>this time. I think I have good idea what the nature of Mollie's <seg type="unclear">proposal</seg><lb/>that should receive such consideration was like, although Mollie hasn't<lb/>enlightened me<seg type="unclear"> any.</seg> What if it twere K.M.? Well. well. how will I ever thank<lb/>you enough for the beautiful article. how thoughtful of you to make it so<lb/>perfect. - you Hun - what were you up to <seg type="del">all</seg> at all. Twas well I didn't<lb/>go over myself. I sent Bertie over and Ned Mahony said <seg type="unclear">no</seg> he hadn't any<lb/>message for me. Can it be possible he is making a mistake. What harm but i was<lb/>delighted with visions of <hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">my parcel</seg></hi> . Such guessing as to what it would be.<hi rend="underline"> <hi rend="underline">Some</hi> </hi><hi rend="underline"><lb/><hi rend="underline">people</hi></hi> went so far as to say twas some <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">musical instrument</hi> </hi>on a minature<lb/>scale. Oh what a land I got last night when Bertie returned. Didn't the rest<lb/>laugh though. We had news of Tom ay last so far he is alright.<lb/>buidceas le Día. Neilie Curtain is released too. Kate Breen and some<lb/>Tralee girls came home too. J. Barretts sister amongst them. So far <seg type="unclear">Aggy</seg><lb/>S. or Dorothy. H havent come. Jimmy. Cronin and <seg type="unclear">Timony</seg> Murphy were<lb/>taken last Sunday week. Tom Connor and some more went to America<lb/>Long ago the D<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> ordered Tom to Australia for his health.  How is Duffer. Jim Connor &amp; Co about this week twelve months<lb/>they were taken. Would Duffer take holidays now? Does he know Liz<lb/>went to America. Indeed his adventures are often discussed in J Js.<lb/><seg type="del">or</seg> circle. They often wonder if Jim still worries ye with talk. I saw<lb/>some  rings  made by Jimmy Barrett and they are very nice. His sister came<lb/>to see us. as she had met all those Northern girls who were friends of Charlie.<lb/>She had many little stories of him. Joe M<hi rend="superscript">ac</hi> is still on parole when he<lb/>went in last time the Brig gave him an extention. He is putting<lb/>down a great time <seg type="unclear">they</seg> did not return till last Wed. I think Pat M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>M<lb/>is home for good. I had a from May <seg type="unclear">Scollard</seg> from<lb/>Swinford last week all her enquiries were for you. I haven't heard<lb/>from Uncle Will since although he wrote home some time ago and said<lb/>he had a surprise for me. Susie is finished at  <seg type="unclear">nohoval</seg>  today.<lb/>she got £15 for 5 weeks. Not a bad old job at all.    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5199_img_0_2"/>
             2  Momma is going to town on Thursday and you shall get the<lb/>stamps and tobacco. We have Patie Fitz at the potatoes<lb/>half are dug. I was down at Crowes yesterday.May is<lb/>away in Tipp but is very well. Old Crowe is very feeble<lb/>now his right hand is parlized. Josie writes often her letters<lb/>are great, ah, you should see her attempts at French. We<lb/>have not seen Dave since the elections, still sure we <hi rend="underline">hear<lb/>from</hi> <hi rend="underline">him.</hi> Julianne Neagle (Georges sister) was released too<lb/>Did anyone tell you that Nellie Connor Mrs G. Kileen<lb/>died Mike Murphy is dying too of cancer in the hand.<lb/>I think Bill Burke is expected home too. Bessie<lb/>is in great form. she was to come across last<lb/>week but she had visitors. Liz Loughlin is doing<lb/>a lot of entertaining too lately. You never asked for<lb/>Judy + Bill in you last letter then you know I had<lb/>to tell a lie. You see the fact of you + Tomas<lb/>asking for them is their greatest consolation now<lb/>they are <seg type="del">we</seg> very well. <seg type="foreign"></seg><lb/>All the household send you their best wishes.  Le Grath go leor<lb/>May  p.s. No we dont expect you till we<lb/>see you. Daddy is busy as ever.<lb/>Tadg O Baun is a corporal now.       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>