<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4278">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 10 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/215</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4278</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-10</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4278_img_3642_1"  type="Letter"  url="d0825e479167cbcd189d8ea1be05f340.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4278_img_3642_2"  type="Letter"  url="d321abdf4dd710811c40cd90b7782a40.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4278_img_3642_3"  type="Letter"  url="9c32e659c5ad00371e8018c1a725cc90.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4278_img_3642_4"  type="Letter"  url="66e212a410ed9a4f6c1152867fddc49e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4278_img_3642_1"/>
             10 April   My p r    I am putting forward an <lb/> ultimatum about leave in order <lb/> to get some kind of settlement one <lb/> way or the other, &amp; so hope <lb/> to let you know definitely in <lb/> a day or 2. It is not hope-<lb/>less but not very hopeful.   Thanks for 2 very nice <lb/> letters , which I suppose means <lb/> none tomorrow, &amp; also for <lb/> the books.   Douglas told me about the <lb/> strong feeling in Belfast about <lb/> G.   He is delighted because he <lb/> says 12 of the 13 batt<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi> have <lb/> chosen your committee &amp; not <lb/> the Belfast one — This he looks <lb/> on as a snub for the latter <lb/> but you must prevent this being
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4278_img_3642_2"/>
            <lb/>so if it is the case.   Farnham came out yesterday with <lb/> all the account of the Irish flags <lb/> which you were so good about.   I do hope Sir E is a little less <lb/> indiscrete than he used to be.   Douglas told me that the flat <lb/> would not do for you in summer, <lb/> so I rounded on him as a <lb/> conspirator but he said that <lb/> you had said nothing to him, but <lb/> that the flat was quite stuffy <lb/> already.   You are quite right about <lb/> the song piece from Heaven. <lb/> Another he sang which was <lb/> very pleasing to me was " The <lb/> Long long trail" do you know <lb/> this? If so get it for our <lb/> next meeting. It is I suppose <lb/> sentimental but has the <lb/> semi religious Irish lilt <lb/> which appeals to my old <lb/> fashioned temperament. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4278_img_3642_3"/>
             I do not think Mrs Stewart <lb/> will be one with whom Sarah's friends would stop <lb/> very long. She has no method, <lb/> is kind but inconsiderate.    Went with the Gen' <lb/> to Amiens today on <lb/> business but had no <lb/> time to stop &amp; see <lb/> anything else. Rather a <lb/> nice motor drive   Very glad about your <lb/> eyes.   Perhaps Lady C could <lb/> someday visit some of <lb/> the wounded with you
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4278_img_3642_4"/>
            <lb/>or the Duchess    Postman waiting   Best love <lb/> from your b w 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>