<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1762">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles P. O'Neill to Sir Matthew Nathan, 3 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles P. O&#39;Neill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Charles P. O&#39;Neill (b. 1867) an Irish solicitor and member of the Irish Parliamentary Party, to the under-secretary for Ireland Sir Mathew Nathan (1862–1939). Nathan had become under-secretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell (1850–1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned due to his misjudgment and failure to stop the Rising.
The letter is written regarding the vacant position of chief crown solicitor due to the death of the former solicitor Malachy Kelly (1850-1916). There are two enclosures attached. The first recounts a meeting with O&#39;Neill, noting his political activity on Pembroke Urban District Council, also recommendations made my men such as Patrick Joseph Brady (1868–1943) an Irish solicitor and politician on O&#39;Neill&#39;s behalf. The second enclosure is an introductory note by O&#39;Neill.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5729/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1762</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0246">Charles P. O&#39;Neill</persName>
              <date>1916-04-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0774">36, Dawson Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1762_img_1218_1"  type="Letter"  url="87c60696848a83542578770b0abb04cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1762_img_1218_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="6059728e0af15f0cd8e1aa904789dffa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1762_img_1218_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="06d19884603ea42e2eb86e38540894b1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1762_img_1218_1"/>
             Chambers, 36 Dawson Street, <lb/>Dublin   3 April 1916   Sir   Referring to the interview I had the honour of <lb/>having with you on Wednesday last with regard to the <lb/>position of Chief Crown Solicitor when you suggested <lb/>to me to send you a formal letter of application, <lb/>I beg to say that on Thursday last I sent by hand <lb/>such a letter addressed to you. Not knowing <lb/>whether it reached you, I venture to ask whether <lb/>you received it?   Your obedient servant   <hi rend="underline">Charles P. O'Neill</hi>   The Right Honourable <lb/>Sir Matthew Nathan <lb/>Dublin Castle   U.S. <lb/>I have spoken to Mr. O'Neill on the telephone <lb/>&amp; he says he has now received the acknowledgment <lb/>sent yesterday <lb/>J.B. 4/4 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1762_img_1218_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Memorandum of Interview</hi>  Mr. CHARLES O'NEILL, a Solicitor, came to see <lb/>me this morning with a note of introduction from the <lb/>Solicitor General to make a personal application for <lb/>the vacant Chief Crown Solicitorship. He set forth <lb/>his political services; how he had given continuous <lb/>support to the Nationalist Party, and quoting Messrs. <lb/>T. P. O'Connor and Brady, M's P. as favouring his <lb/>candidature. He referred to his having retired from <lb/>an election contest in order to make room for Mr. <lb/>Abraham. As regards his professional qualifications, <lb/>he had been Solicitor for a number of local Bodies. <lb/>He also referred to his having been Chairman of the <lb/>Pembroke Urban District Council, which in various ways <lb/>was a model that the Dublin Corporation might well <lb/>follow.   Mr. O'Neill had heard that there might be a re- <lb/>construction involving no new appointment, but if one <lb/>was made he hoped his claims for it would be fully con- <lb/>sidered.   I asked Mr. O'Neill to make formal application <lb/>for the appointment referring in it to the professional <lb/>work on which he had been engaged.   DUBLIN CASTLE,   29th March, 1916. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1762_img_1218_3"/>
             This is to introduce Mr. <lb/>Charles P. O'Neill, solicitor, <lb/>who, as chairman of the <lb/>Pembroke U.D.C., has guided <lb/>the fortunes of that body <lb/>with success for the last <lb/>six years   <seg type="unclear">James Connor</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>