<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5155">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell, 26 July 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell expresses gratitude for a parcel and requests to be sent some Horlick&#39;s Malted Milk.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5155</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-07-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5155_img_None_1"  url="f8299acdee2714135b32365bc2b2e7d4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5155_img_None_2"  url="1ba1e819e7bae307416778a48b2898ef.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5155_img_0_1"/>
              26 July 1917.    My dearest Mamy   Thank you very much<lb/>indeed for the lovely parcel which came<lb/>yesterday and also your grand<lb/>letter. The parcel was A 1. the<lb/>cake was splendid and quite fresh.<lb/>Also the potted meat and toffee is<lb/>lovely. The toffee called triple<lb/>cream is particularly nice and I<lb/>am very fond of cafe au lait.  Also that chicken you sent once<lb/>or twice was lovely and I think<lb/>might be acceptable in the future.  I would also like to try just once some<lb/>Horlicks malted milk as people talk<lb/>a lot of it out here. Just send<lb/>it once or twice until I tell you<lb/>what it is like.  I am now writing on the pad you<lb/>sent and it is just what I wanted. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5155_img_0_2"/>
             It fits easily into my haversack.  There are a lot of cyclists<lb/>round here but no trace of any<lb/>Canadian ones.  The weather is very <seg type="unclear"><seg type="del">kind</seg></seg> fine<lb/>again now for which thank<lb/>goodness.  With very best love to all<lb/>from<lb/> your most affec Son<lb/><hi rend="underline">Willie</hi> <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>