<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0956">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Slevin to the Longford Urban District Council, [July 1916]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Slevin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Joseph Slevin to the Longford Urban District Council in July 1916, concerning the drainage and sanitary arrangements for some houses in Longford. Joseph Slevin (b.1856) was the Town Surveyor for Longford. The Longford Urban District Council was the towns local authority and was renamed the Longford Town Council in 2002.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Longford County Archives Service</repository>
                  <collection>Longford Urban District Council, LUDC-1-3-1916-8-8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/956</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0938">Joseph Slevin</persName>
              <date>1916-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0047">Co. Longford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2059">Longford Urban District Council, Co. Longford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0956_img_2775_1"  type="Letter"  url="69450e7bfd0a76b600e5f2b1217a59e6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0956_img_2775_1"/>
               Mr. Chairman &amp; Gentlemen   I inspected the drainage and sanitary <lb/>arrangements at the back of houses on <lb/>St. Joseph's Road, Mr. Farthy's house etc. <lb/>I found (a) the drain pipe not self- <lb/>cleaning (b) joints not pointed in cement. <lb/>(c) that the pipe has been broken in several <lb/>places and not sealed up afterwards (d) <lb/>where the pipes pass through the dwelling house <lb/>the floor has been broken and not properly <lb/>repaired. There seems to be no disconnecting trap <lb/>or proper ventilating shaft. The paving of yard <lb/>and channel is very open and bad, the closets <lb/>and pit are very near back doors. Fowl are <lb/>kept in boxes quite near each back door <lb/>and the place seems very congested <seg type="closer"> Your obdt. servant  Joseph Slevin </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>