<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4323">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Somerset Francis Saunderson to Edward Carson, 15 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Somerset Francis Saunderson </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Somerset Francis Saunderson (1868-1927) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Saunderson was the first born son of Edward James Saunderson, leader of the Irish Unionist Party for much of its existence. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4323</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0834">Somerset Francis Saunderson </persName>
              <date>1916-06-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1279">5 Wilton Place, S.W., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4323_img_3683_1"  type="Letter"  url="e026c844ea15fed713d9192cc4fd33dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4323_img_3683_2"  type="Letter"  url="481c1562930b1a1f8f9b751ef2b11ed7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4323_img_3683_3"  type="Letter"  url="987d3ec1442c60723c91768ac8085cb4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4323_img_3683_4"  type="Letter"  url="ec62c7e30f14a3318302acd889239260.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4323_img_3683_5"  type="Letter"  url="1fb3444cddfec2b6ffe5bab654b0356b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4323_img_3683_1"/>
             from <lb/>E. Saunderson   June 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.16.   PAGE 1 OF 3   5,WILTON PLACE, <lb/>S.W.   My dear Carson,   The proceedings on Monday <lb/>left me among many others with <lb/>the impression that we had been <lb/>Sold &amp; betrayed by our Leaders in <lb/>the Coalition by reopening the Home <lb/>Rule Question during the continuance <lb/>of the war &amp; by putting it to us on <lb/>the grounds that an immediate settlement <lb/>was necessary for the successful <lb/>conduct of the war, a reason which <lb/>in my humble opinion from the <lb/>moment I heard it was in plain <lb/>language "bunk'um".   One of those Leaders is an old <lb/>friend of mine &amp; a man who
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4323_img_3683_2"/>
            <lb/>in my opinion has always been <lb/>a straight &amp; honest gentleman. I <lb/>could not believe in his being a <lb/>party to a betrayal of those whom <lb/>he once led in the fight against <lb/>Home Rule. Walter Long is of course <lb/>the man. I went to see him <lb/>this morning &amp; I now learn that <lb/>Lloyd Georges proposals were never <lb/>&amp; have never been before the Cabinet. <lb/>Walter Long himself &amp; he is not alone <lb/>in his opinion cannot see any <lb/>reason connected with the conduct <lb/>of the war for experimenting with <lb/>a Home Rule Parliament <lb/>in the present condition of Ireland. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4323_img_3683_3"/>
             PAGE 2 Of 3   Nor was Lloyd George authorised <lb/>to make proposals entailing such <lb/>an experiment. The idea was <lb/>that he should try &amp; get <lb/>all parties in Ireland to agree <lb/>to the provisions of the amending <lb/>act so that the Home Rule <lb/>Bill could come into operation at <lb/>the <hi rend="underline">end of the war</hi> in such a shape <lb/>as to avoid strife &amp; bloodshed <lb/>in Ireland.   After seeing Walter today I <lb/>called at your house &amp; was told <lb/>you will be back on Saturday. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4323_img_3683_4"/>
             Could you spare me a few <lb/>moments on Sunday morning. <lb/>I think it is important that I should <lb/>see you. Arthur Farnham went <lb/>back to France today &amp; I represent <lb/>his views also &amp; I have received <lb/>Walter Long's permission to tell you <lb/>a good deal in confidence that <lb/>I cannot write.   Please leave a message with your <lb/>servant what will be a convenient <lb/>time for you to see me &amp; I will <lb/>call at your house for it on <lb/>Saturday   Yours <lb/>Sincerely   SomersetSaunderson. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4323_img_3683_5"/>
             PAGE 3 OF 3   With regard to the question of Walter <lb/>Long resigning. I am quite sure <lb/>that he will do so unless it is <lb/>made clear that he was not a <lb/>party to forcing us to accept <lb/>Home Rule now, &amp; I surmise <lb/>that Lloyd George  will  have to make <lb/>the admission that his proposals <lb/>had never been before the Cabinet. <lb/>as he led us to understand.   Unless I hear to the contrary <lb/>I will call at your house on Tues.12 12 o'c.   Yours ever   <hi rend="underline">SomersetSaunderson</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>