<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1346">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Mabel FitzGerald, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is an unsigned and undated letter sent to to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond Fitzgerald (1888-1947). The letter seems to have been written while Desmond was still in prison and thanks Mabel for her advice and requesting that she asks the author&#39;s daughter to come home if possible. The author also refers to some Irish Volunteers activities in Kerry.Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1545/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1346</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1346_img_685_1"  type="Letter"  url="e129b10f3d27c532744ad20867c56117.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1346_img_685_2"  type="Letter"  url="a5e8d6b38ca90e95842c5c1a86d3806a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1346_img_685_1"/>
               Well Mrs it is time <lb/> for me to write to you and <lb/> I am very thankful to you <lb/> on <sic>acount</sic> of your <sic>advicing</sic><lb/> me and <sic>advicing</sic> my little <lb/> Girl and if you can at <lb/> all tell her to come home <lb/> if you can at all how is <lb/> Mr Fitzgerald is out <sic>off</sic><lb/> prison yet We are all <lb/> Germans here and any <lb/> amount of <sic>Voulintears</sic>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1346_img_685_2"/>
              <lb/>in Dingle yesterday <lb/><sic>their</sic> did a Band came <lb/> from Dingle <seg type="del">agin</seg>against <lb/> Ballyferriter <seg type="unclear">Voullintears</seg><lb/>Well no more to say <lb/> But I am very thankful <lb/> to you send me Nellion <lb/><sic>adress</sic> if you can  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>