<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1384">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Sheehan, 22 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Sheehan </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>One of a series of letters between the Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Dublin and the Chief Crown Solicitor, Dublin Castle concerning an injury sustained by Patrick Sheehan while he was working as a casual laborer employed by the Forage Department to handle hay, oats and straw. The series of letters concerns possible compensation as this was an injury sustained at work. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_3785_10, NAI_CSO_RP_1916_3785_10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1384</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1441">Patrick Sheehan </persName>
              <date>1916-02-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0374">14 Desmond Square, off Barrack St. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1384_img_752_1"  type="Letter"  url="9ad2ea5932c6f1d62e44b409c2a06f9b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1384_img_752_2"  type="Letter"  url="cd4689b2153cd2e7b37af10315d55131.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1384_img_752_1"/>
                22/2/1916    I the under <lb/>signed was accidentally <lb/>hurt on the 28 day <lb/>of January 1916 at the <lb/>Lee Mills. Sheairs Street <lb/>whilst bringing down <lb/>stairs one bundle of <lb/>empty sacks. In doing <lb/>so I <sic>sipped</sic> and recei- <lb/>-ved a dislocated <lb/>ankle which renders <lb/>me incapable of <lb/>Working. I was detained <lb/>at the South Infirmary <lb/>for 16 days under <lb/>the care of Dr Horace <lb/>Townsend whose  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1384_img_752_2"/>
              <sic>Certificat</sic> if required <lb/>will bear out that <lb/>I am at present <lb/>physically unfit to <lb/>carry on my ordinary <lb/>work  <seg type="closer"> Patrick Sheehan   14 Desmond Square  off Barrack Street  Cork  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>