<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1023">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert Samuel to Lord Wimbourne, the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, 15 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Home Office</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Home Office, London to Lord Wimbourne, the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, 15 February 1916, regarding the Colonel Proby&#39;s application for the arms of Ireland to be allowed to be used on a memorial to Field Marshall Earl Roberts in Wellington Barracks. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP/1916/3600/3, NAI CSO RP/1916/3600/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1023</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0034">Home Office</persName>
              <date>1916-02-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Wimbourne, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1023_img_293_1"  type="Letter"  url="716c4675e5dac36ec2b70c8a410ba0d8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1023_img_293_1"/>
                HOME OFFICE  WHITEHALL. S.W.    15th February, 1916.   My Lord,   In reply to your letter (1848) of the 3rd instant, <lb/>I have the honour to inform you that I have submitted <lb/>to The King Colonel Proby's application for permission <lb/>to place the Arms of Ireland on a Memorial to the late <lb/>Field Marshal Earl Roberts in the Guards' Chapel at <lb/>Wellington Barracks, and that His Majesty has been <lb/>graciously pleased to approve thereof.  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/>My Lord, <lb/>With great truth and regard, <lb/>Your Excellency's obedient Servant,   Herbert Samuel   His Excellency  The Lord Lieutenant  of Ireland.  </seg> Inform Col. Proby with reference <lb/>to his letter of the 26 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Jan. <lb/>EoF <lb/><hi rend="underline">21-II-16</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>