<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0459">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Local Government Board to Emily J. Slocock, 11 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Local Government Board</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written Local Government Board to Emily Julia Slocock (1874-), His Majesty&#39;s senior lady inspector of factories and workshops. The author of the letter was writing to ask advice regarding the condition of spinning and weaving mills in Belfast as the workers may become distressed and she wishes to know what needs to be done to prevent this.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7443/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/459</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0699">Local Government Board</persName>
              <date>1916-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1380">Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Emily Julia Slocock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0120">Belfast</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0459_img_1804_1"  type="Letter"  url="29cb007f29dd0ef66066864987323882.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0459_img_1804_1"/>
                Local Government Board,  Dublin.    11th March, 1916.  <hi rend="underline">Private.</hi> Dear Miss Slocock,   I hope you will forgive me for asking you to give me <lb/> the benefit of your special information as to the conditions <lb/> and prospects of spinning and weaving mills in the city <lb/> of Belfast.   I hear that in addition to the 'short time' which the <lb/> Belfast Mills have been compelled to adopt owing to shortage <lb/> of raw material that there is danger of a further reduction <lb/> in working hours owing to the difficulty of obtaining coal <lb/> supplies. If this is so it may involve something in the <lb/> nature of serious distress among the mill workers which it <lb/> may be necessary for my Board to anticipate.   I also gather that there is a good deal of discontent <lb/> chiefly among the women on 'short time' in the mills upon <lb/> the question of munition employment. Is it true that a <lb/> number of manufacturers engaged upon munition work are <lb/> employing amateur ladies upon their work to the exclusion <lb/> of girls who are more or less in distress owing to the 'short <lb/> time' in the mills?   Any advice or help that you can give me in advising <lb/> my Board on the matter will of course be regarded as quite <lb/> confidential.  <seg type="closer"> With kind regards, <lb/> Yours truly,    Miss Slocock,  H. H. Inspector of Factories,  Belfast.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>