<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0891">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to his wife, Lillian Spender, 9 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender née Dean, (1880-1968). He writes about their earlier arrangement and describes life with the Battalion. Spender also mentions the visit of British Field Marshal Douglas Haig, who was appointed to command of the British Expeditionary Force in late 1915 following the resignation of Sir John French (1852-1925). Haig&#39;s role in planning the costly Somme offensive in July 1916 earned him the moniker of &#39;the Butcher of the Somme.&#39; This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>PRONI/D1633/1/1/126, PRONI/D1633/1/1/126</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/891</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-01-09T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0891_img_2465_1"  type="Letter"  url="bd5acb76704e7354a3160d710ef80410.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0891_img_2465_2"  type="Letter"  url="f676b9c49217bd9eeefb1004f19b7a42.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0891_img_2465_1"/>
                Sunday Jan 9   Dear Pr.   I have just as much work as I can do <lb/>now for the next 3 days , so in accordance with our agreement <lb/>shall cut down letters.  C in C Sir D Haig arrives on Tuesday for <lb/>inspection.   Genl very disinclined to do much just yet, &amp; <lb/>inclined to let the A branch run the show. I expect <lb/>there will be a fracas this next week in consequence.  <seg type="unclear">Mil sir</seg> from A.H.Qs called today with <lb/><seg type="unclear">Dalmerry.</seg> The latter I do not take too â quite a snake  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0891_img_2465_2"/>
              as regards this Division, I expect but one may <lb/>be wrong.   A beautiful day â it would be in this New <lb/>Forest.   Douglas not at all well . I have sent <lb/>him to bed.  <seg type="closer"> Best Love <lb/>When do I write to new address  Your  BW </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>