<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4880">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Boraston to Richard Dawson Bates, 15 February 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Boraston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Ulster Unionist Council</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4880</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0425">John Boraston</persName>
              <date>1919-02-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0702">Unionist Central Office, 1 Sanctuary Buildings, Great Smith Street, S.W.1., London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1358">Richard Dawson Bates</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4880_img_None_1"  url="67773827c007ddf6b694bb97e5fde16a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4880_img_None_2"  url="28813e35f0c5ffdd974faf94f7415e86.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4880_img_0_1"/>
             Telegrams: Telephone: 'Contitute, Phone, London' Victoria 9740 (11 lines)<hi rend="underline"></hi>  <hi rend="underline">The National Unionist Association </hi><lb/><hi rend="subscript">Of Conservative and Liberal Unionist Organizations</hi>  <hi rend="subscript">Joint Principal Agents</hi>  Sir John Boraston  } Honorary Secretaries  <lb/>William Jenkins  Thomas Cox, Secretary   Private    Unionist Central Office,<lb/>1.Sanctuary Buildings,<lb/>Great Smith Street, S.W.1   <hi rend="superscript">  February 15th, 1919. </hi>   Dear Mr. Dawson Bates,   The Press Department of this Office has been<lb/>communicating with you with reference to obtaining informa-<lb/>tion on newspapers in Ireland, and you were good enough in<lb/>your letter of February 10th to send a list of the Irish<lb/>Unionist Agents. Captain Malcolm Fraser has not, however,<lb/>been demobilised yet, and pending his return, I wonder<lb/>whether, if I explained matters, you would be kind enough<lb/>to assist.  We are obtaining from the Agents in the English and<lb/>Scottish Constituencies detailed information as to the Local<lb/>Press. Forms similar to the enclosed have been sent to each<lb/>Agent and when all the forms have been returned, they will be<lb/>classified and we shall then have a complete survey of the<lb/>politics, etc., of the Press of the country. We took similar<lb/>action in 1912 and on the result we were able to base a series<lb/>of Press services which we sent out weekly to the various local 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4880_img_0_2"/>
             and other papers, and by this means we were able to supply,<lb/>chiefly the smaller Press, with Leaders, Articles and House<lb/>of Commons Sketches, each of which did not overlap the neigh-<lb/>bouring paper's territory. In this way we were enabled to<lb/>obtain excellent and widespread propaganda of the right kind.<lb/>In order efficiently to do this, you will, I know, realise<lb/>how necessary it is to have the detailed information for<lb/>which the form asks from each constituency. Can you advise<lb/>me how this can beat be done so far as Ireland is concerned?<lb/>Would it perhaps be wiser to supply you with the blank forms<lb/>and encroach on your courtesy by asking you to forward them<lb/>to the Agents to obtain the necessary details and then return<lb/>them out to us here?  I am sorry to trouble you in this manner but I think<lb/>that the importance and urgency of the matter will prove<lb/>sufficent excuse.   Yours sincerely,    John Boraston.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>