<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3872">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 25 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to Father Provincial Thomas V. Nolan SJ (1867-1941) regarding Jack Colter&#39;s application to join the Jesuit order. After recommending Colter to Nolan Doyle informs him that they have not yet been dispatched to the front and that it could be a while before they depart. 

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.

Fr. Thomas V Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War. During the Rising Nolan was based at St Francis Xavier’s, Upper Gardiner Street and, alongside Rector Fr John Fahy SJ, risked his life in aiding the wounded and supplying local areas with food and milk.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-CHP1-14-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3872</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-01-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2035">Guadaloupe Barracks, Bordon, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V. Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3872_img_3252_1"  type="Letter"  url="f3a46ea06882ee906116558e6989040a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3872_img_3252_2"  type="Letter"  url="81826856d2a1fdbde0ab071ff2c073b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3872_img_3252_3"  type="Letter"  url="62807ab0f0a2656c6849c54d37aba1d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3872_img_3252_4"  type="Letter"  url="d0588a13bffc55250b2cd0a52206fc6e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3872_img_3252_1"/>
             CHPI/14(3)   Bordon Camp<lb/>Hampshire    25 /1/'16    My dear Fr Provincial,<lb/>P.C.   I understand<lb/>that my friend Mr<lb/>Jack Carter has written<lb/>asking to be admitted<lb/>into the Society. From<lb/>what I know of him<lb/>I think he would    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3872_img_3252_2"/>
            <lb/>suit in every way <lb/>He is smart, clever <lb/>young man of 30, <lb/>in business at present <lb/>with a firm of <lb/>chartered accountants <lb/>in London, and has <lb/>given this proposed <lb/>step a good deal of <lb/>serious thought. I have <lb/>been able to see him <lb/>several times and we <lb/>have talked the whole
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3872_img_3252_3"/>
             <lb/>matter over. Should<lb/>your Reverance be in<lb/>London he would be<lb/>glad to see you as<lb/>he will not be able<lb/>to go to Ireland till<lb/>Easter.  We were to have left<lb/>for the Front on the<lb/>31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> but sickness has<lb/>broken out in camp &amp;<lb/>we may have to wait<lb/>some time  <lb/> Believe me, dear Fr Provincial<lb/>Your obediently in Xto<lb/>W. Doyle. C.F.     
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3872_img_3252_4"/>
             P.S. Fr Vaughan very kindly<lb/>came down at my request &amp;<lb/>gave the officers &amp; men a lecture<lb/>last Sunday. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>