<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5161">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 1, September, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Refers to enclosed sports day program. William Upton Tyrrell was responsible for his unit winning a race. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5161</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-09-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5161_img_None_1"  url="a68fd623090c4003a0e747fc68dbbffb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5161_img_None_2"  url="74537106fe734c18d75f0f7009abbc4d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5161_img_0_1"/>
              1 September 1917    My dear Mamy.   The reports went off A1 yesterday<lb/>and we all spent the most<lb/>enjoyable afternoon we have had<lb/>for a long time. I enclose the<lb/>progamme and the detail of the<lb/>Representative  race. Each coy <lb/>and head quarters were represented.<lb/>Of course C coy <seg type="del">or</seg> won thought<lb/>not too easily so I had the honour<lb/>of delivering the winning message<lb/>to the C.O which I did by more or<lb/>less spitting it at him. Moore<lb/>was the Platoon commander who<lb/>brought it to me and I just<lb/>stuck it in my mouth, while<lb/>saddling up and when I got to the<lb/>C.O of course could not stop<lb/>so I just spit it out passing.<lb/>I do not know if that is 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5161_img_0_2"/>
             treating the Commaning Officer<lb/>with proper respect. However my<lb/>company won - The horse race<lb/>also caused much excitement.  Please keep these enclosures<lb/>for me as they are very interesting  The weather has improved<lb/>considerably the last day or<lb/>two.  It is a shame for the Canon if he<lb/>comes home. I suppose there<lb/>must have been talk of him<lb/> coming out &amp; so he have<lb/>old Lindsay a few extra drinks<lb/>to clear out.  No news but with best love   Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>