<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3575">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M.K.C. to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 11 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M.K.C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from M.K.C. to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946, M.K.C. writes to Hanna that they went into town to see her but were not able to get in touch. They write regarding the Connollys, saying that Mrs. Connolly was able to see her imprisoned husband James Connolly, though he is executed on the 12th of May, the day after the letter is written. M.K.C. writes that they have been to Mr. Sheehy Skeffington&#39;s grave at Glasnevin, and expresses their grief regarding his death, imploring Hanna to ask of them anything she might need.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3575</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0874">M.K.C.</persName>
              <date>1916-05-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0881">Portmarnock, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3575_img_2977_1"  type="Letter"  url="a8330c77c7d0b481bce94fe0545a92b9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3575_img_2977_1"/>
             Ganyowen<lb/>Portmainock<lb/>Co Dublin   11. May. 16 <lb/> Dear Mrs Skeffington,   I went into town on<lb/>Wednesday to see how you were, but failed<lb/>to find you. I was twice at the Office morning<lb/>and afternoon. While I was there Mrs Connelly<lb/>&amp; Norah Connelly called asking for you. Mrs C<lb/>had been allowed to see her husband in the Castle<lb/>and was to see him again that evg. Mr Wiggell<lb/>also called to inquire for you. He was very<lb/>sympathetic. I told them both about your message<lb/>of being home after 6oc. I was glad that Con<lb/>met you, he told me about the funeral. I had to<lb/>go in to town yesterday and I went to <seg type="unclear">Haxeven</seg><lb/>and saw the Skeffington's grave. My thoughts were<lb/>black and bitter thoughts — if only thoughts could<lb/>wither tyrants up! It was too late to go out to see<lb/>you afterwards. Please send me a line, tell me<lb/>how you are, &amp; if there is anything I can do for you<lb/>in any possible way? I wish you would come out<lb/>here for a while. It would be a change at least; &amp; I feel<lb/>cut off completely here by myself. I have got a letter<lb/>from Mrs Cousins, &amp; have sent her papers with the notice<lb/>of Mr S.S &amp; the last Citizen. She will be so sorry for this<lb/>desolation.   With much love. Yours MKC  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>