<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4249">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 1 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/86</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4249</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4249_img_3616_1"  type="Letter"  url="878a8e5270efd81d509bf8e57c3f324f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4249_img_3616_2"  type="Letter"  url="9b951aafbe5b05ade189e4f0f9c76ef7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4249_img_3616_1"/>
             1 Dec 15   My p r    We are I suppose settling in, but I am rather restive, partly <lb/> lack of uesful work, &amp; a feeling of staleness which pervades the whole <lb/> division &amp; for which one has to make allowances in other people.    <seg type="unclear">Preston</seg> is getting trying sometimes &amp; when mistakes are pointed <lb/> out takes them as personal reflections on him as a senior officer. He <lb/> is another of Gen P's mistakes, &amp; he has made a good many.   <sic>Im</sic> afraid we shall lose Richardson for good, &amp; shall miss <lb/> him very much. A course for budding GSO 2s is to start <lb/> on the 15th to which I have strongly advised him to go, &amp; <lb/> I don't think he will come back after it. He is too good a chap..   It shows what I had begun to suspect that GSO 2s <lb/> are getting rather cheap now, tho' he will be one of the best. <lb/> I don't know who we shall get in his place. Farnham would <lb/> do but I don't suppose for a moment he will be allowed to <lb/> take it &amp; I certainly do not see another Major Domo in his <lb/> place with our GOC.   Our chateau has parts of it very old including a ghost, <lb/> but the part we live in mainly is I think 250 years old. <lb/> There are signs of stone bullet marks on the towers.    Certainly the French have no idea of home &amp; yet this <lb/> could be made so nice. However I had better reserve this for a <lb/> general letter.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4249_img_3616_2"/>
             I am not sure on thinking it over whether my suggestion for your <lb/> War loan scheme is not too difficult, &amp; it might not take on with <lb/> these independent people, tho' it would be the truest form of charity to <lb/> make them learn thrift for themselves. The Government could have much <lb/> on offer of warloan in part payment of Navel &amp; Military pay which would <lb/>have been attractive if well organised, but I'm afraid they have tied their <lb/> hands by saying that all <seg type="del">future</seg> past  loans will get the same  terms &amp; interest as all <lb/> future loans that may be required.    Before we subscribe I ought to see our pass book, but so much depends <lb/> on <seg type="unclear">Carnsmerry</seg> calls to think we shall soon owe £210. Perhaps the best <lb/> thing would be to put this amount on deposit in case it is made &amp; <lb/> to see what else one can do. I have not received any report of the <lb/> Castlefull <hi rend="underline">meeting</hi> but perhaps it has not been circulated yet, or may <lb/>have been sent in newspaper form as they sometimes do.   The  rubber  shares are giving a return of per cent on their present prices, so <lb/> apparently the Stock exchange does not expect them to continue these <lb/>kind of dividends after the war. At the same time it does not pay us <lb/> to sell out so the only way to look upon the dividends is as being <lb/>temporarily much above their future average.   I wish I wasn't such a dull dog today tho' I'm sitting <lb/> by an open window, with rather a shabby look out it is true, but <lb/> an open window in December is a blessing to be thankful for if <lb/> it does not mean a cold.    I find the best way of going to sleep is to hold an imaginery <lb/> conversation with you, &amp; I do this now every night. Tho it has good <lb/> results it is rather an empty kind of pleasure. Letters are again getting <lb/> blocked due to a railway breakdown I believe. At Xmas one will be <lb/>lucky to see them at all.   Best love from a rather dull bw, but still yours   WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>