<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5211">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Donoghue to Cornelius Daly, 18 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Donoghue</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/8/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5211</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1193">Thomas Donoghue</persName>
              <date>1923-03-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Cornelius Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5211_img_None_1"  url="f7de4be5d063806382f1996c0bf3eb3a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5211_img_None_2"  url="c3ca523732c47881f8a012639fe84cbd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5211_img_None_3"  url="c6b171886c6a0acab9c812366f147491.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5211_img_None_4"  url="5bad19c54a78d03af50ea87588282b7c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5211_img_None_5"  url="29a6141fe75f70f748b6570fc7786a15.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5211_img_0_1"/>
              Mr. Cornelius W. Daly<lb/>Knockaneacolteen<lb/>Ballyfinane<lb/>Firies (P.O)  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5211_img_0_2"/>
             P41/8/13   Clonmellane    Sunday<lb/>Mar 18th 1923    My Dear Con,   It is with<lb/>feelings of the most profound<lb/>regret that I pen you<lb/>these few lines to express<lb/>my heartfelt sympathy<lb/>to you &amp; your family in<lb/>your very sad bereavement.<lb/>Certainly sad to see your<lb/>darling boy cut down in<lb/>the prime of life with 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5211_img_0_3"/>
             apparently a prosperous and<lb/>brilliant career before him,<lb/>but a glorious death when<lb/>you come to think of what<lb/>he died for. What he died for,<lb/>is, what he strove for the<lb/>last 4 or 5 years to establish<lb/>in our land, Liberty, Truth<lb/>and Justice. Any man dying<lb/>in the sincere attempt to<lb/>establish those, I say his<lb/>death is certainly grand,<lb/>and his resurrection will<lb/>certainly be glorious. Suffice 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5211_img_0_4"/>
             (3)  it to say that with this<lb/>hurried note I sincerely wish<lb/>to again convey my very deep<lb/>sympathy to you and your family<lb/>in this your hour of trial. It<lb/>certainly is an hour of trial,<lb/>but if you stand that trial<lb/>with patience and resignation<lb/>to Gods will your reward will<lb/>certainly be great. Think of<lb/>the words which God himself<lb/>spoke when he said 'Gold and<lb/>Silver are tried in the fire<lb/>but the just man is tried in 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5211_img_0_5"/>
             the fire of humiliation' You<lb/>certainly are tried in that<lb/>fire now, but look to the<lb/>future with that undying<lb/>hope that we shall all meet<lb/>one day where sorrow shall<lb/>be no more and suffering<lb/>shall be at an end. In<lb/>conclusion I hope and pray<lb/>that God may give you grace &amp;<lb/>patience to bear this your trial,<lb/>and that his soul may find<lb/>everlasting rest<lb/>Yours faithfully<lb/> Thos Donoghue <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>