<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3100">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 16 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Peter Mooney (b.1886) to his sister, Katie (b.1884). Peter thanks Katie for the various items she sent to him, concluding that she is minding him very well. Peter writes the weather is beautiful, he could happily live in such conditions. He believes that he will be granted leave on the 23 of January and warns that when he comes back, he&#39;ll eat a &#39;terrible feed of eggs and rashers.&#39;

Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This letter part of a collection of over ninety surviving letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Mooney Family Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3100</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-01-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1180">Ballincollig, Co. Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0342">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1970</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3100_img_2508_1"  type="Letter"  url="ad639f04d2789c9d14ded0c3a1e9663d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3100_img_2508_2"  type="Letter"  url="32e41d731b76568e0ba36f999be41289.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3100_img_2508_3"  type="Letter"  url="136e9ca4472d944a1d2328e49552a2af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3100_img_2508_4"  type="Envelope"  url="8271cd3af1b0de1c4011b39d3728f6e3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3100_img_2508_1"/>
             Jan 16 1916   Dear Katie,   I received all the<lb/> things you sent me alright<lb/> you are certainly minding<lb/> me very well. I think<lb/> we get leave on the 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi><lb/> of the month. The weather<lb/> here is glorious it is<lb/> lovely out in the mornings<lb/> with all the birds<lb/> singing in the trees I<lb/> could live here for a lifetime 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3100_img_2508_2"/>
             we were out with the<lb/> teams every day this<lb/> week. I am doing well<lb/> at the business and<lb/> enjoy it well. I am<lb/> sure Billy &amp; the <seg type="unclear">Cockey</seg><lb/> horse would cause<lb/> some row if they were<lb/> put in the teams.<lb/> I am very glad to see<lb/> you gave poor Charley<lb/> the pound he deserves<lb/> it. I will eat a terrible<lb/> feed of eggs &amp; rashers<lb/> when I get home. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3100_img_2508_3"/>
             I had not a letter from<lb/> the Paddock this long<lb/> time. I hope they are all<lb/> well. I wrote to them<lb/> last Sunday but I got no<lb/> reply yet. I will keep<lb/> out of old Dunnes way<lb/> when I get home he might<lb/> hit me with the meat<lb/> chopper. Tell Paddy I<lb/> was asking for him. The<lb/> days are getting grand &amp;<lb/> long now. I have no more<lb/> to say at present so Good—Bye<lb/> &amp; May God Bless you<lb/> all.   P. Mooney 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3100_img_2508_4"/>
             Miss K. Mooney <lb/>Caulstown <lb/>Dunboyne <lb/>Co. Meath 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>