<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1058">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from G O'Connell to the Earl of Shaftesbury, 1 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>[G O&#39;Connell]</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from G O&#39;Connell on behalf of the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland to the Earl of Shaftenbury, H.M. Lieutenant of Co. Antrim, concerning the appointment of Deputy Lieutenants for County Antrim. The Lord Lieutenant has directed the writer to enclose a list of the deputy lieutenants for Co Antrim and to state that there appear to be only two vacancies available, not four as suggested by the Earl. He also points out that Major Roger Casement is already an deputy lieutenant for Co Wicklow and that it is not usual for gentlemen to be D.L.s for two counties.Anthony Ashley Cooper (1869-1961), 9th Earl of Shaftsbury, served as Lord Lieutenant of Antrim from 1911 to 1916, Chancellor of Queen&#39;s University, and Lord Lieutenant of Dorset from 1916 to 1952. Cooper retired from the British Regular Army in 1899, but would continue to serve as captain, and later lieutenant colonel of the North of Ireland Imperial Yeomanry. During the Great War, Cooper held the temporary rank of brigadier-general, and was subsequently honoured with the rank in 1919.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP/3692/16, NAI CSO RP/3692/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1058</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0365">[G O&#39;Connell]</persName>
              <date>1916-02-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1010">Anthony Ashley-Cooper</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1949">Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1058_img_315_1"  type="Letter"  url="3a8075d1f9dd4ac36bd08cc0263d2fb4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1058_img_315_1"/>
                DUBLIN CASTLE,    1st February, 1916.   My Lord,   With reference to Your Lordship's letter of the 31st <lb/>December last proposing to appoint Mr. J.S.McCance, Mr.E.Coey, <lb/>Major Roger Casement and Captain John Patrick to be Deputy <lb/>Lieutenants for the County of Antrim, I am directed by the <lb/>Lord Lieutenant to transmit herewith a list of the Deputy <lb/>Lieutenants of the County and to state that there appear to <lb/>be only two vacancies.   His Excellency desires me to point out that Major <lb/>Roger Casement appears to be already a Deputy Lieutenant <lb/>for the County of Wicklow and that it is not usual to <lb/>approve of the appointment of the same gentleman to be <lb/>Deputy Lieutenant of two Counties.  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/>My Lord, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   EOFarrell   The Right Honourable   The Earl of Shaftesbury, K.P. , K.C.V.O. ,  H.M.Lieutenant of the Co.Antrim,  The Castle,   Belfast.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>