<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6618">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ellen Daly to her son Charlie Daly [Cormac Ó Dálaigh], December 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ellen Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Discussing family matters.

The letters in the Charlie Daly collection concern Irish republican Charlie Daly (in Irish: Cormac Ó Dálaigh). Charlie Daly was born in Knockaneculteen, Firies, Kerry, on 11 August 1896 into a family that was immersed in the Fenian tradition and the Irish Volunteer company in Kerry. Charlie Daly rejected the peace treaty with Britain and became involved in the 2nd Northern Division. Daly was subsequently captured and imprisoned at Drumboe Castle in County Donegal, where he was executed by firing squad on 14 March 1923 along with three other men; Dan Enright, Tim O’Sullivan, and Seán Larkin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41 MG2 B6 S4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6618</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">Irish</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1168">Ellen Daly</persName>
              <date>1922-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1964</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6618_img_None_1"  url="phpmCrk4h.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6618_img_0_1"/>
              P41/9/1/2    Mí na Nodlaig    Cormac a chróidhe   Is dóigh liom go mbeadh na<lb/>rudaí atá ins an litir seo níos maith leat na<lb/>cartaí Nodlaig agus na aon rud eile. Taim<lb/>ag foghluim cuid maith dein Gaedilg anois.<lb/>Sé Jimín Máire Thaidhg an leabhar atá<lb/>agam an bliadhan seo. B'fhearr liom é ná<lb/>aon leabhar eile a leigheamh riamh.  Ceap Joisie go mbeadh sí abaile <seg type="del">igom</seg><lb/>i gcomhair na Nodlaig. Bhí sí ana uaig-<lb/>neach núair bhí sí ag imtheacht. Táim ag<lb/>sgríobh cun mo cardaibh in Australia<lb/>fós. Ba mhór an tuaigh gur ní féidhthin<lb/>tú teacht abhaile i gcomhair na Nodlag.<lb/>Ac mar sinn féin sé ró old nuair tá<lb/>sé féidir leat chun dul Aifrionn agus<lb/>fuair traidíní, agus le conghnamh Dé<lb/>go mbeadh tú abhaile aris.  Ta na laideanna go leir maith<lb/>agus Judy agus Bill freisin. Níl aon<lb/>sceiil eile agam anois. Beannact Dé<lb/>agus Nodlag ort.  Slán leat anois<lb/>Nellie    Tá Nóra<lb/>ró leisce cun<lb/>sgriobh chugat<lb/> N         
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>