<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2229">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Edward Carson, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924), Unionist and Liberal, to Edward Carson (1854-1935), Unionist leader. Carson was a lawyer and a politician.Carson was the leading figure in Ulster Unionism. He had sanctioned the formation of the paramilitary Ulster Volunteer Force in January 1913 and he helped to found the Ulster provisional government of September 1913. In 1916 he was at the peak of his parliamentary influence and by December was appointed to the first lordship of the admiralty by Lloyd George (1863-1945). 
Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter regards negotiations about the position of the six counties in relation to Irish Home Rule, stating that John Redmond (1856-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, may repudiate his support for a six county plan. It goes on to discuss what Carson&#39;s position should be if invited into the negotiations, going on to discuss the threat of Home Rule. Montgomery also accounts his attendance at a meeting of the Unionist Alliance, at which Lloyd George MP (1883-1945), attended.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>D-627-429-27</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2229</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2229_img_1674_1"  type="Letter"  url="525eb9876ffc7c5f70fbbb59a8c92be4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2229_img_1674_2"  type="Letter"  url="4db65d1be23ecd9cf788dad6bafb5c75.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2229_img_1674_1"/>
            Copy  9th June 1916   My dear Carson,  The contents of this day's Nationalist papers look as <lb/> if we might have a repudiation of Redmond's provisional <lb/> consent to the six county plan before Monday, which would <lb/>save us from a considerable difficulty.    If this does not occur it will be obviously righ tactics <lb/>for us to authorise you to enter upon negotiations on the six <lb/>county basis.    I hope, however, that you will arrange to have a resolution <lb/>proposed which will make it quite clear that we only do this <lb/> under great stress on account of the war, and that we are not <lb/>bound by what we do on Monday under any other circumstances <lb/> that may arise.    The resolution should contain some plausible excuse <lb/> for breaking or stretching the terms of the Covenant, and (which <lb/> I think quite as important) for giving even an implied assent <lb/> to the setting up of Home Rule for any part of Ireland at the <lb/>present time, involving, as it does, most serious danger to the <lb/> Realm, and with which even implicit consent appears to me to <lb/>amount to an act of treason, which requires a very valid excuse. <lb/>I feel that it is as big a breach of my Oath of Allegiance as <lb/> the abandoning of the three counties is of the Covenant.    I attended the Unionist Alliance meeting yersterday. <lb/> Some of them had been seeing Lloyd George, and had received certain
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2229_img_1674_2"/>
            offers from him, after considering which, they passed the <lb/>resolution in to-day's papers. I got them to tone one part <lb/>of it, which I thought very unwise, down a little; but did <lb/>not try to prevent them issuing it. Not knowing, however, <lb/>what sort of resolution I might find myself obliged to vote <lb/>for on Monday, I left the room before the resolution was <lb/>put, and they have considerately omitted my name from the <lb/>list of those present.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>