<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2636">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Duffin to her aunts, 9 January 1916, </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

This is a long, chatty letter to her aunts. She writes about the last post getting lost, the weather, and thanks her aunts for a Christmas present. Continues the letter of 14 January after being ill. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/A/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2636</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1134">Emma Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1586">15th General Hospital, Alexandria, Egypt</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2636_img_2062_1"  type="Letter"  url="0a32da9bd1478d4a8ae3ed3f7200908a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2636_img_2062_2"  type="Letter"  url="5443cbd27e29d93c9b3ae4c6660c5fa9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2636_img_2062_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/A   15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Gen. Hosp. Alexandria    Jan 9 —/16.    My dearest Aunties   I have time to   in this whilst waiting for the<lb/>ambulance to take us on duty. Firstly thank you all very<lb/>much for the Xmas present which Mamma says she is sending<lb/>from you. Our last mail was less and we are anxiously<lb/>awaiting the next, it seems such an age since we got letters,<lb/>and you never quite get the news you have lost either.<lb/>One of your mails home was lost too, but as I don't know<lb/>which it is useless to try &amp; repeat any news there was.   It has been bitterly cold here with rain &amp; storms, and<lb/>when it does rain here it does it thoroughly. The amusing<lb/>part is how injured we all feel about it, we grumble &amp;<lb/>from as if we came from a county where there was no rain.<lb/>I have been in the sick room for 5 days but do not want any<lb/>sympathy wasted on me as after the first day I did not<lb/>really feel at all ill and rather enjoyed the rest.  Jan 14. This letter is going to be a bit scrappy I am afraid.<lb/>The weather is still horrid and I have had an awful <lb/>fall like a <sic>pumkin</sic>, I suppose I caught cold in it as I had<lb/>not had , it made me fell rather bad, <seg type="del">but</seg> and I thought<lb/>I would have to go off duty again, however it finished up by hurting<lb/>inside &amp; now I feel quite flourishing over here. We are very<lb/> <seg type="unclear"></seg> at the hospital here at present and I have not got nearly    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2636_img_2062_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline">2</hi>   enough to do which is very tiresome for of course they never would <lb/>dream of giving you extra time off and there we stand, or sit <lb/>if we have any luck, doing nothing when we might be out enjoying <lb/>ourselves, I must say I grudge it so I have never had a whole <lb/>day off since I came out except when I was in the sick room, <lb/>if they were busy I would not expect one. One of my patients <lb/>has got a beautiful bedouin knife that he got off a camel <lb/>they had shot down, the head is all <seg type="unclear">damascene</seg> work, and <lb/>the handle made of the horn of goat, and it has a wonderful <lb/>bead <seg type="unclear">scarbard</seg>, I cover it very much. One of them has <lb/> a Gurka's knife, an awful looking instrument, which if <lb/> they once draw they won't sheath<seg type="del">e</seg> till it has tasted blood.  I am going for a drive with Molly Carson this after— <lb/>noon, if it isn't raining, but the weather is still very shaky. <lb/>I had a letter from Terry who got the cigarettes I sent him <lb/> and my letter on Xmas day, which was good luck, for I <lb/>did not know how long it would take to reach him.   I have no news for you. I wish I could drop in and see <lb/> you all. Please give my love to cousin Minnie and say <lb/>how glad I was to hear she was better.   Best love to you all and best wishes for 1916   from your ever loving niece   <hi rend="underline">Emma</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>