<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5253">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Victoria Mary Tyrrell 21, May, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his sister.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5253</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5253_img_None_1"  url="b07dd09ab3d551862f48fa4ff1ad517f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5253_img_None_2"  url="5767d78c81348d4964206114ee45e265.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5253_img_0_1"/>
              Sunday 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> May    My dearest Minnie  no nouse but I suppose<lb/>you will be expecting a letter. I wonder have<lb/>you gone back to school yet. I have not<lb/>had a letter from you for the last couple<lb/>of days but that is on account of my<lb/>change of address. This is a very comfortable<lb/>place as I said in my last letter. The house evidently<lb/>belonged to some big bug as it is ver well<lb/>finished. Lots of big easy chairs and a v.<lb/>comfortable sofa. The weather is awfully hot now<lb/>and the dust pretty bad but it is better than<lb/>wet. I will send home all my winter clothes<lb/>v. soon. but not till I have had one tour<lb/>of the trenches so that I will be quite sure<lb/>exactly what I want. I was up in the front<lb/>trenches for a few hours having a look around<lb/>but the trenches are a considerable distance<lb/>apart so things are v. quite at present. I am<lb/>sending home  in a small parcel an article which 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5253_img_0_2"/>
             I find I no good out here! One can<lb/>fairly often get a horse to ride out here<lb/>but at present it is too hot. The<seg type="del">xxxfe</seg> you<lb/>are getting along with the riding. I do<lb/>not like the steel helmets much as they are<lb/>very hot and heavy. However we have to<lb/>wear them. If there are [??] of mine<lb/>about you might send me a couple. I have<lb/>only one and it is manly worn out.  The country round here is very <seg type="del">chilly</seg><lb/>hilly and all chalk so we are always<lb/>nice and white if not clean. Did I tell you<lb/>I had a card from Mr Boohey ? If I did you<lb/>will know it all the better now. The post<lb/>comes in and goes out just any old time<lb/>here but every day. A great number of<lb/>officers came out lately from the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Batt<lb/>but nearly all went to other battalions.  We see aeroplanes being [strafed] by [?]hells all<lb/>the time here but I did not see any come<lb/>down yet.  With v. best love and kisses from<lb/>Your most affec. brother  Willie       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>