<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0335">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Walsh to Alice Stopford Green, 27 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Walsh </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was addressed to Alice Stopford Green (1847-1929). Green was the wife of historian John Richard Green (1837-1883). In addition to this she was a nationalist, involved in the Howth gun-running and a historian in her own right. She was shocked by the 1916 Rising and horrified that Casement had been plotting to obtain German assistance. Nonetheless, she visited Casement in prison and lobbied hard to prevent his execution. Author of the letter James Walsh (b. 1880) was a clerk in Urlingford Union, County Kilkenny. The letter is in regard to a petition gathered by the Urlingsford Board of Guardians for clemency to be shown to Rodger Casement in response to his death sentence.Rodger Casement (1864-1916) had been imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. A campaign was launched featuring many prominent figures such as Alice Stopford Green, W. B. Yeats and George Bernard Shaw to secure a reprieve for Casement but he was hanged on 3 August 1916</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List N0. A15, Ms. 13,088/9/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/335</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1395">James Walsh </persName>
              <date>1916-07-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0408">Urlingford Union, Urlingford Town, County Kilkenney, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Stopford Green </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0398">36 Grosvenor Road, Westminster, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0335_img_1564_1"  type="Letter"  url="ce453c10c95266e0f63502b00afabda1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0335_img_1564_2"  type="Letter"  url="f8e42bbee71bd9daeba824e98e8de0cf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0335_img_1564_1"/>
                27th July, 1916    Mrs Stofford Green,  36 Grosvenor Road,  Westminster.   Madam,   By direction of the<lb/> Urlingford Board of<lb/> Guardians, and at the<lb/> suggestion of Mr J.F. Sweetman<lb/> of Mount St. Benedict,<lb/> Gorey, Co Wexford, I send<lb/> you herewith, the attached<lb/> Petition unanimously adopted<lb/><hi rend="underline">by</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0335_img_1564_2"/>
              by them at their meeting<lb/> today, on the proposition<lb/> of Mr. T. Harrington, J.P.Co.C.,<lb/> seconded by Mr W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> O'Connell, <lb/> J.P., D.C., pleading for<lb/> clemency for Roger <lb/> Casement, and urging<lb/> that the sentence passed<lb/> on him may not be<lb/> carried out. - <seg type="closer"> I am, Madam,<lb/> Your obedient Servant,  James Walsh, <lb/><hi rend="underline">Clerk of Union</hi></seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>