<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3176">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to his mother Alice Katherine Wynne, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles Wynne to his mother Alice Wynne thanking her for the mitts she sent him, saying the weather is becoming colder. He says that he misses home and wishes he could get leave soon. He hopes to get leave around Christmas time. He tells his mother about his fellow soldiers and discusses news of friends back home. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>TCD  Wynne papers MS 10247/1/789</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3176</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1267">Alice Katherine Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2050">The Cottage, Glendalough, Co Wicklow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3176_img_260_1"  type="Letter"  url="743a2cf809a9f1447c3bbe6f2c7992f2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3176_img_260_2"  type="Letter"  url="ea7cec62ef1d35498ee5e5e8c5f0faab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3176_img_260_3"  type="Letter"  url="5e59bd81d0092a711de70eb79740aa92.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3176_img_260_4"  type="Letter"  url="3fc219cd000fea22ef6cc8770c164aa5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3176_img_260_5"  type="Envelope"  url="20672e747db7d31f7214b3eda31b3740.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3176_img_260_6"  type="Envelope"  url="60520e59764a9603a65509928193e372.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3176_img_260_1"/>
             Dunree   <hi rend="underline">Sun</hi>    Dear Mother,   I'm afraid I've been<lb/>rather bad about writing<lb/>specially as I've had so many<lb/>letters lately. Many thanks<lb/>for the mits they are really<lb/>grand and if we have<lb/>much more weather like<lb/>we had up till a few days<lb/>ago <seg type="del">we</seg>  I  shall be very glad of<lb/>them, but I really hardly<lb/>think there'll be much colder<lb/>weather than that even at 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3176_img_260_2"/>
             Dunree.<lb/>It was freezing hard right through the day.  I must say Jack's news<lb/>was quite unexpected to me.<lb/>I was wondering when I<lb/>heard of his visit to Burnaby<lb/>Lodge — but I must say I did<lb/>not get to the explanation.  I am so glad for Jack<lb/>He's certainly lucky to get May.<lb/>I do hope he's in for some<lb/>good luck now — he surely<lb/>deserves it — poor old Jack.  I wish I was at home now<lb/>or had been. I wonder when<lb/>Jack will next get leave.<lb/>I have come to the conclusion<lb/>that I don't ask enough  for  leave.<lb/>I think I surely ought to get<lb/>some about Christmas time.  Fitzgerald is here now a<lb/>very nice man he seems.<lb/>though he has already asked<lb/>many times where the<lb/>nearest lunatic asylum is<lb/>and remarked when he<lb/>had been here two days that<lb/>it seemed two months.  It certainly seems to me<lb/>six since I came back from<lb/>Glendalough — though I believe<lb/>its only a fortnight really 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3176_img_260_3"/>
             Fitzgerald is a Wicklow man<lb/>the one Mullins knew and<lb/>comes I believe from Glenowen.<lb/>Will you please tell about<lb/>Glenowen and why the name<lb/>seems so like home to me?  The apples arrived in<lb/>splendid condition they were<lb/>really beautifully packed and<lb/>Lowry deserves great credit<lb/>I think : the apples were much<lb/>appreciated and are already<lb/>nearly finished. Also the jelly<lb/>and if the rate of consumption<lb/>is any test - there certainly isn't<lb/>much wrong. The mess say its<lb/>the best jelly they've tasted.<lb/>I got nothing much in Dublin<lb/>but intend soon to try and<lb/>find a dentist in Derry — if<lb/>so I'd get various things I<lb/>want.  The last day off I had I went<lb/>to a little lake fairly high up<lb/>on the hills to see if it was<lb/><seg type="unclear">bearing.</seg> — It was very nearly<lb/><seg type="unclear">bearing</seg> in places but the thaw<lb/>now will have melted all that.  It is hard work trudging through<lb/>the snow but it has almost<lb/>all gone now.  If you go back to Tyronny<lb/>and any of my contoured 1<hi rend="superscript"></hi><lb/>maps of Wicklow etc turn 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3176_img_260_4"/>
             up I should be very glad to<lb/>have them some time when<lb/>it's not too much bother.  By the way to what address<lb/>shall I send the wrist watch.<lb/>I think I must send it though<lb/>I shall be lost without it.  It was very good of Cousin<lb/>Frank to <seg type="del">send</seg>think of sending<lb/>me that book, though to tell<lb/>you the truth I haven't the<lb/>faintest idea what he was<lb/>talking about. However I should<lb/>be much interested and grateful<lb/>if he would like to send it.  Well now maybe I'm rather<lb/>stupid with sleep after last<lb/>night on watch anyway I<lb/>think I'll stop now. I think<lb/>I answered all questions haven't<lb/>I.  Your ever loving   <hi rend="underline">Charlie</hi>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3176_img_260_5"/>
             Mrs Wynne<lb/>The Cottage<lb/>Glendalough<lb/>Co.<hi rend="underline">Wicklow</hi> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3176_img_260_6"/>
            Ubique <lb/>quo fas et gloria ducunt
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>