<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4245">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 30 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter  from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/82</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4245</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4245_img_3612_1"  type="Letter"  url="b6212648cac7ac507e1657015ba8756a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4245_img_3612_2"  type="Letter"  url="3d69d08fc9532668bfe994d0c3be2f2a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4245_img_3612_1"/>
             Nov. 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   My p r   Delighted to get a nice long letter, tho' for some reason <lb/> the mail was very late, &amp; we got letters 16 hours later <lb/> instead of 2 hours earlier as we had expected !   I see your difficulties, &amp; think that they are rather <lb/> due to lack of work to do with so many helpers. Another idea <lb/> has struck me but it will need very careful working out <lb/> to be a success:-   It seems to me that now is the time to inculcate <lb/> a little thrift, &amp; of course the right &amp; obvious way to do so <lb/> is through the War Loan. My scheme is that your committee <lb/> should do this for the men, &amp; that just as they might (in <lb/> my opinion) act as Agents for purchasing stores, so might <lb/> they for the purchase of War loan bonds.   I can see all manner of difficulties but none that are <lb/> insurmountable :- first of all the men have got to have some- <lb/> one whom they absolutely trust; this means the signature of <lb/> the D or of Lady C (in additon to that of the Hon<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> Sec<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> <lb/> probably) but excluding at all costs that of some of the others.   A pamphlet will be <seg type="del">clear</seg>required making it absolutely <lb/> clear <hi rend="superscript">a)</hi>what you are prepared to do for the man ,&amp; <hi rend="superscript">b)</hi> what he must <lb/> do himself i e remit you certain sums announce the person to whom
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4245_img_3612_2"/>
            it should be delivered if he is killed etc <hi rend="superscript">3)</hi>the terms of interest etc.    My suggestion practically is that you open a branch of the <lb/> Post office for the sale of Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>loans &amp; that you act as trustees <lb/> for the men until their return.  It may be too complicated.    We had an appaling day for our move yesterday &amp; every- <lb/> thing looked intensely gloomy. Today however there has been breeze &amp; <lb/> sunshine —such a day as we have spent on some of our picnics <lb/>together, &amp; oh.....when shall we again?.   A useful fright. I <seg type="del">left</seg>lost this scrawl &amp; your last letter <lb/> &amp; could not think where they could be but found them on the <lb/> General's desk ! I reread them with much interest but think <lb/> on the whole it might have done him good to have read them.   The books have come, but something has gone wrong with <lb/>the mail as we have no papers &amp; no one else any papers. Clever <lb/> p r to get hers through. Perhaps the Censor thought it was extra nice. <lb/> I haven't had the chance of opening the books but best thanks.   Now I have to read other peoples' letters before the mail <lb/> goes &amp; when I would much rather be doing "something" else.   Tell Mater to go very cautious in regard to Mrs Stewart &amp; the D <lb/> as the former is very nice but  "sketchy" &amp; I would as soon <lb/> give her the management of your show as I would put M' Glll <!-- Gile? -->in <lb/> charge of the bank of England.    I haven't the least idea whether 24 or 29 is your address.    Your letters are certainly safest in your custody.    We have taken action already in telling COs to indent for <lb/> Socks etc etc &amp; not to write to you for <seg type="del">eq</seg>essentials, which are a <lb/>military issue   Love   Wilfrid BS. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>