<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1669">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Walsh to General Lovick Bransby Friend, 1 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Walsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from John Walsh, an auctioneer, to General Lovick Bransby Friend (1856-1944). General Friend was a appointed the Commander in Chief of Ireland in 1914, however he resigned form the position following the 1916 Easter Rising. The letter regards the reinstatement of a small holding to William Ryan (1840-?). It states that there is an enclosure of a newspaper clipping regarding Ryan&#39;s situation, in the hope that Friend could assist in getting the evicted tenant back in the holding. It goes on to state that Ryan has one son, James (1891-?) who has signed up for military service and is currently based in India. It goes on to state that it would have great effect on the country&#39;s current state if Ryan was reinstated in his holding. The enclosed clipping accounts Ryan&#39;s situation.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO/RP/1916/7012/5/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1669</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1433">John Walsh</persName>
              <date>1916-04-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0690">Main Street, Templemore, County Tipperary, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0593">Lovick Bransby Friend</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0169">Kilmainham, Dublin, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1669_img_1128_1"  type="Letter"  url="1d60f8722d707208d63b6fb53dcd848e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1669_img_1128_2"  type="Letter"  url="5b9c9287253b0245772bbc971e5a9b67.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1669_img_1128_3"  type="Letter"  url="ab04a2f29d706108bd3d9aad233db844.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1669_img_1128_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="ee778103f5ad5c143c6433dfe9642318.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1669_img_1128_1"/>
             Offices... Main Street, <lb/>Templemore,   1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> April 1916   General Friend <lb/>Commander of His Majestys <lb/>Forces in Ireland <lb/>Kilmainham <lb/>Dublin   Hon Sir   I respectfully presume <lb/>to send you the enclosed cutting <lb/>from the Tipperary "Star" <lb/>in the hope that you may be <lb/>graciously pleased to assist <lb/>in getting the Evicted Tenant <lb/>William Ryan back into
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1669_img_1128_2"/>
            his small holding. This <lb/>poor  ex  farmer <hi rend="underline">has only one</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">son</hi> who filled some minor <lb/>Civil Service position but <lb/>at the first call he volunteered <lb/>for active service and <lb/>is presently at Peshawar <lb/>India. The reinstatement <lb/>of William Ryan in his <lb/>little holding will have a <lb/>far reaching effect at the present <lb/>crises in our countrys affairs <lb/>around here, and will take <lb/>an argument out of the mouths <lb/>of our enemies. Apologizing <lb/>and asking you to pardon <lb/>me for presuming to obtrude <lb/>on your attention in this <lb/>matter.   I remain, Hon Sir, <lb/>Your <sic>obt servt</sic>   John Walsh  <lb/>National Director <lb/>U.I.L. for <lb/>Mid Tipperary
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1669_img_1128_3"/>
             I. G. <lb/>For refund in the case of <lb/>William Ryan <lb/><seg type="unclear">Ule</seg> <lb/>3/4  <lb/>Clonmel 6.4.16>lb/>I think this has reference to Tipperary NR. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Li to Loughorise</seg> <lb/>Nenagh   C.S.Clonmel <lb/>For repost <lb/>Wh O Connell <lb/>4-4-16 <seg type="unclear"> A. T. L.</seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1669_img_1128_4"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>