<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5309">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Resolution passed by the Staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast 3 March, 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Earls</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A resolution passed to mark the death of Francis C. Forth.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection> BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5309</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0494">John Earls</persName>
              <date>1919-03-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Family of Francis C. Forth</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5309_img_None_1"  url="f71d698533aa1511adf84591712d2a0a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5309_img_0_1"/>
              3/March/19.    MUNICIPAL TECHNICAL INSTITUTE BELFAST   RESOLUTION to be submitted at the Meeting of<lb/>the Permanent Staff and the Occasional Teachers at<lb/>the Municipal Technical Institute Belfast, on<lb/>MONDAY, 3rd March ,1999.<lb/>---------------------------------------------------------------------  RESOLVED<lb/>                  That we the Members of the Permanent Staff <lb/>and the Occasional Teachers of the Municipal Technical <lb/>Institute, Belfast, in meeting assembled, place on record <lb/>our deep regret and sorrow at th death of Captain F.C.<lb/>Forth, the late Principal of this Institute.  Since the inception of the Technical Instruction<lb/>Scheme in Belfast more than eighteen years ago he has <lb/>unsparingly devoted his oustanding powers of organisation,<lb/>his wide knowledge of educational affairs and his brilliant<lb/>mental gifts to the planning, erecting, equipping and <lb/>organising the great Institute which will always be his chief<lb/>and most fitting monument.   We also wish to express our admiration for, and<lb/>appreciation of, the impartiality, justice and consideration<lb/>which he always evinced in his dealings with the Staff.   We respectfully extend our most sincere sympathy<lb/>to his widow and family in the great bereavement they have<lb/>sustained.           ================================   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>