<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5829">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Francis Bernard (Earl of Bandon) to Lady Clonbrock, 23 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Francis Bernard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter was sent by the Earl of Bandon (1850-1924) to congratulate Augusta Lady Clonbrock and her husband, Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock, on their golden wedding anniversary. Bandon refers to a  gift sale that raised over £1300 and mentions the work that Lady Clonbrock has done for Irish soldiers in the Connaught Rangers, British army.

Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No 54; Ms 35,793 (9)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5829</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0419">James Francis Bernard</persName>
              <date>1916-07-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5829_img_93_1"  type="Letter"  url="3bad07bc2ed437e3c76bbf62fa1b1550.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5829_img_93_2"  type="Letter"  url="68b2b705736691f630bdff16fb0eb5a4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5829_img_93_3"  type="Letter"  url="3fe57e9c56c1b0535ce0ddc735c27a6c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5829_img_93_1"/>
             CASTLE BERNARD, <lb/>BANDON.   <hi rend="underline">July 23 1916</hi>   My dear Lady Clonbrock—   Will you &amp; Lord Clonbrock <lb/>accept our warmest <lb/>congratulations &amp; best <lb/>wishes for <sic>yr</sic> Golden Wedding. <lb/>I wish we could have <lb/>offered our congratulations <lb/>in person, it is so long <lb/>since we have met <lb/>I trust you are both
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5829_img_93_2"/>
            <lb/>very flourishing &amp; <lb/> that you &amp; Lord Clonbrock <lb/>will long be spared <lb/>to us all - you <lb/>both do so much <lb/>good, you set us all <lb/>an example —    I know you will be <lb/>glad to hear our <lb/>(Rent &amp; Tipperary Depot <lb/>for wounded &amp; disabled Irish Soldiers) <lb/>Gift Sale made over <lb/>£1300 — we were unlucky <lb/>in holding it on a very <lb/>showery day.   I often hear of all <lb/>you are doing for <lb/>the Connaught Rangers.   With my love &amp; renewed good wishes. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5829_img_93_3"/>
             Believe me <lb/>dear Lady Clonbrock <lb/><sic>yrs affly</sic>    <hi rend="underline">J. Bandon</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>