<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3882">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 30 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to his father, Hugh Doyle, regarding his activities before being sent to the front. Doyle recounts his first Christmas in the camp and remarks that camp life does not lend itself to the celebration of the Lord&#39;s nativity. After detailing the damage caused by the rain Doyle takes comfort in the fact that he spent the previous night sleeping in a proper bed with actual linen sheets. Before signing off Doyle informs his father that they are to march to Bordon camp on 1 January.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3882</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1915-12-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0728">Witley Camp, Surrey, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1210">Melrose, Dalkey, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3882_img_3261_1"  type="Letter"  url="8c13547216d390337e14931a5659399d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3882_img_3261_2"  type="Letter"  url="94e498182dff7cc86a9edfbb17fdea25.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3882_img_3261_3"  type="Letter"  url="001c3ce8be4780d1215419aa1772f64d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3882_img_3261_4"  type="Letter"  url="e1bd1ceb8ed14f276e9369e17fa2e8dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3882_img_3261_1"/>
             If cook wants a<lb/>job just send<lb/>her along here —<lb/>not too much to<lb/>do and 100,000<lb/>husbands. long &amp;<lb/>short, fat or thin<lb/>to pick from.<lb/>She must learn<lb/>the German goose<lb/>step first, however.   Witley Camp<lb/>Surrey.    30/12/15.    My dear Father,   I have spent a few strange Christmas<lb/>Days in my life, but I can safely say that<lb/>last Dec 25<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>in the wilds of Surrey will take<lb/>some beating. My first Xmas on the Continent<lb/>at Enghien was a memorable one, chiefly for<lb/>the absence of all one had been accustomed to<lb/>associate with this festive season, and Fr Chas.<lb/>will tell you that it was not a very gay time<lb/>at Tronchiennes after you had disposed of<lb/>your Christmas dinner, a dinner minus the<lb/>turkey, roast beef + plum pudding, at twelve<lb/>o'clock. Still these were red letter days compared<lb/>to this year. Camp life does not apparently<lb/>lend itself to the due celebration of our Lord's<lb/>Nativity, and in addition nearly all the<lb/>officers had leave of absence, of which I<lb/>could not avail myself; but to crown all<lb/>the rain seemed quite determined to make<lb/>an impression not only on the country <seg type="del">but</seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3882_img_3261_2"/>
             but on us as well. With the help of<lb/>top-hats, a military coat and a water-<lb/>proof I <sic>manage</sic> to reach the hut, where<lb/>I celebrate Mass, fairly dry in spots.<lb/>Then just as I was beginning to preach,<lb/>the flood gates were opened on the tin roof<lb/>of my church, and a master-piece of<lb/>pulpit eloquence was lost &amp; much to my<lb/>regret, you can imagine, as I was<lb/>quite ready for breakfast. I fancy, as<lb/>it was nearing the end of the year, the<lb/>Angels must have been having a wash-up<lb/>and pulled up the plugs of their wash tubs<lb/>all together; at least that is what it<lb/>sounded like. All the same I was never<lb/>in better spirits; I suppose the Lord<lb/>was making up in one way for what<lb/>He had taken in another.  I have had my reward for these privations<lb/>already in a way you will hardly<lb/>guess; I slept last night in a spring<lb/>bed <hi rend="underline">with real sheets</hi> !! Just think of<lb/>that luxury — clean, linen sheets !!! I<lb/>felt as happy as a sow half buried<lb/>in a manure heap, and absolutely wallowed. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3882_img_3261_3"/>
             You could not picture my happiness<lb/>unless you had been sleeping for the<lb/>past month with an army blanket tucked<lb/>under your chin; what material they are<lb/>made of I do not know, but when morning<lb/>comes you find there is little need to<lb/>shave as they have pretty well taken all the<lb/>beard, not to speak of skin, off your face.<lb/>My good fortune was the result of a visit<lb/>to the Jesuit home, or rather convalescent home,<lb/>at <seg type="unclear"></seg> , some 15 miles from here, where<lb/>I had a very pleasant day with old friends<lb/>and a glorious night minus military blankets<lb/>but plus sheets — two of them !! — their memory<lb/>haunts me still.   I generally get a good walk in the morning<lb/>so as to keep myself fit and in conditon for<lb/>the tramping before me. I have been able to<lb/>see a good deal of the country which is<lb/>very beautiful, even at this time of the<lb/>year, and in addition there is a magnificent<lb/>demesne belonging to Lord Pirrie  just beside us, famous<lb/>(or infamous?) for the fact that it was the<lb/>residence of Whittaker Wright who spent tens<lb/>of thousands of other people's money on the<lb/>place. Not far away lives Major <seg type="unclear">Rushhook</seg>, 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3882_img_3261_4"/>
             an excellent Catholic, who owns a district<lb/>bearing his name, not far from Queenstown.<lb/>It is a small world after all, so I thought<lb/>once more when I met Richard Nolan of<lb/>Killiney on the road this evening.  We have just got orders to march to Bordon<lb/>Camp, Hants, on Saturday, the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, much to<lb/>the indignation of both officers and men<lb/>who will lose their holiday and Sunday's<lb/>leave into the bargain. Bordon is about<lb/>14 miles from here but I am all right<lb/>as I intend to ride on my charger,<lb/><seg type="unclear">devoutly</seg>hoping that the beast won't<lb/>mind the charging part for one day at<lb/>least; if he does I will put him into<lb/>a few mud swamps which will soon<lb/>bring him to his senses. We join the<lb/>other three battalions of the 49<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Brigade at<lb/>Bordon, so I suppose we shall not have to<lb/>wait very long now for a move frontwards.<lb/>I have quite got over my cold now though<lb/>it was bad enough while it lasted; it was<lb/>bound to come so I am not sorry to have it over.  Wishing you every happiness and blessing in<lb/>the New Year, with let us hope a speedy peace to<lb/>unite us all again,<lb/>As ever, dearest Father<lb/>Your loving son<lb/>Willie. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>