<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2278">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Phyllis Ryan to James Ryan, Tuesday 6 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Phyllis Ryan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Philomena Frances Ryan (Phyllis O&#39;Kelly) (1895–1983) is the sister of James Ryan. The letter is part of a collection of letters sent to Dr James Ryan (1891–1970) received while interned after Easter Week.

Philomena Frances Kelly, neé Ryan,  was the sister of James Ryan. She served as a messenger for the GPO garrison during the Easter Rising. She later married future president of the free-state Seán T. Ó Ceallaigh.


James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>University College Dublin Finding List P88</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2278</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1444">Phyllis Ryan</persName>
              <date>1916-06-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1357">19 Ranelagh Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2278_img_172_1"  type="Letter"  url="97e3fe3e90c53450ae1f4988e982f131.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2278_img_172_2"  type="Letter"  url="44f580bc79d0d824b67b650fa489eb6c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2278_img_172_1"/>
             P.S. I have a long <lb/>letter from Sean T <lb/>just now. He is <lb/>in great form. H4No8 <lb/>he is. She saw <lb/>Liam also and <lb/>they are all fine. <lb/>They are Wandsworth <lb/>of course.    No more news. <lb/>I think now I shall <lb/>make Kit or Min <lb/>write soon and I <lb/>think we will send <lb/>a parcel tomorrow. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Phyllis.</hi>   19 Ranelagh Rd.   Tuesday 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916.   My dear Jim,   I got your letters safely, and am very <lb/>grateful to you indeed. Kit (as you may have heard) <lb/>came out of Mountjoy yesterday morning, also Kathleen <lb/>Browne, Miss Gifford, Miss Ffrench Mullen, and Miss <lb/>Higgins. We gave them a great reception coming <lb/>out, there were a great crowd of us up outside <lb/>the prison, a lot of university students, and <lb/>outsiders too. We took Kathleen &amp; Kit home here <hi rend="underline">in</hi> <lb/>a taxi and they are both here still. Nell is <lb/>not out yet. But I think she will be in a <lb/>day or two. The Count &amp; Countess Plunkett have <lb/>been ordered away to live in Oxford by the <lb/>10<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> June. &amp; Dr Kathleen Lynn to Bath by the <lb/>same date. Kit is lucky to get off anyway. <lb/>And I am sure we'll have Nell soon. <lb/>There's only yourself now. Otherwise there's not <lb/>much news now. All the prisoners that <lb/>are left are being deported tonight. Then <lb/>there will be about 8 left for trial. <lb/>Stack &amp; Collins and a few like that. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2278_img_172_2"/>
             The crowds are all coming in to see Kit <lb/>and Kathleen. Kit is going back to <lb/>University on Thursday, as usual with all her <lb/>work etc. Min is working away at the <lb/>National Aid Association. They are setting <lb/>up concerts and Pic-nics etc. Stan is <lb/>still in Rathfarnham. She may come <lb/>back now as Kit is out.   When are you coming home?    Chris is coming up at <seg type="unclear">week</seg> and to meet <lb/>Michael! Maura is coming back from <lb/>home on Wednesday. Min may be going <lb/>to London soon, if so of course she <lb/>will call to see you all. Nell is <lb/>writing ballads, as well as Fr P. Browne <lb/>and many another.   It gets harder &amp; harder to work every <lb/>day with the crowds coming in. I think <lb/>I have no other news at all. If Min <lb/>goes it will be next week I think.    Goodbye. Love from M Browne (she's here) <lb/>and from us all.   Yours,   Phyllis    Margaret Browne <lb/>Mrs S. McEntee  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>