<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1046">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegram from Samuel Davidson to Frederick Ponsonby, 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Cleland Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Telegram from Samuel Cleland Davidson (1846-1921) to Frederick Ponsonby (1867-1935) thanking the King and Queen for their sympathy regarding the death of his son, Captain James Davidson (1877-1916).Sir Samuel Cleland Davidson was an Irish inventor and founder of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast. During the First World War the Sirocco Engineering Works manufactured and exported equipment for cooling, drying, dust collecting, heating, ventilating, pneumatic conveyance for the Royal and Merchant Navy. Frederick Edward Ponsonby, first Baron Sysonby, was an author and courtier. From 1914 until 1935 Ponsonby served as the Keeper of the Privy Purse, introducing heavy reductions in the royal household&#39;s expenditure during the First World War. This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-1, Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1046</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1149">Samuel Cleland Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1035">Frederick Edward Ponsonby</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1677">Buckingham Palace, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1046_img_3134_1"  type="Letter"  url="ccdb913949fd90021549a2ab1bbe0d54.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1046_img_3134_1"/>
                From Davidson &amp; Co, Ltd., Sirocco Engineering Works, Belfast    The Keeper of the Privy Purse, 11/7/16.  Buckingham Palace,  London   TO:  I have just received your telegram of yesterday <lb/> evening please convey to their majesties the <lb/> King and Queen my deep appreciation <lb/> of their sympathy so graciously expressed. <seg type="closer"> S.C. Davidson   Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>