<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5708">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 30 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
James has visitors at his house his cousin and uncle. Speaks of the invite to London and declares he could not bear to lose her now.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5708</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2073">Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0203">Togherstown, Ballinea Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5708_img_810_1"  type="Letter"  url="4f07dcb77cacd2ed5dcdd6a8929df0cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5708_img_810_2"  type="Letter"  url="7a7d768cb1f8a213a71b6ecbefafb1c6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5708_img_810_1"/>
             Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar   March 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    My dearest James   Your letter this morning was indeed very<lb/>welcome you were very good to write I don’t know what<lb/>I’ll do if my poor man is brought off to London I<lb/>hope you won’t any way I’ll be very anxious about you<lb/>until you will be landed safe home again but perhaps<lb/>you won’t be obliged to go yet.  Yes! I think we may decide on the <hi rend="underline">first of June</hi> it<lb/>was not my mother it was myself was putting off deciding<lb/>because I was afraid of having to change the day it is so<lb/>unlucky I <hi rend="underline">hear</hi>. You are a darling man to be planning<lb/>improvements on the house for me I will never half appreciate<lb/>your goodness the only reward I ever can offer you is my<lb/>few very poor indeed prayers, nothing else it is not my<lb/>heart is stopping me, there are a hundred things I would like<lb/>to do if only <hi rend="superscript">had</hi> half the goodness in me, but alas I have nothing<lb/>at all but my youth and the wish for all the <hi rend="superscript">other</hi> necessaries<lb/>to enter on married life. I did not think on any of my<lb/>dress points yet the white silk I know would be very<lb/>nice but when I think of poor Jennie so far away 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5708_img_810_2"/>
             I know she would love to see me married but I think<lb/>it would make her extra lonely if she heard of me in<lb/>white silk she would like to <hi rend="underline">pluck</hi> me when I have<lb/>it on &amp; make me look well I dread for that reason to have<lb/>any little fuss- she is <hi rend="underline">such</hi> a <hi rend="underline">child</hi> (the old woman talking)<lb/>I commenced to feel &amp; see those things so many years<lb/>ago that it is no wonder I feel such an <hi rend="underline">ancient piece</hi><lb/>of <hi rend="underline">good</hi>, and if I guess rightly it is one of the things<lb/>old people dislike in <hi rend="superscript">the</hi> young is being what they call <seg type="del">old</seg><lb/>“an ould fashioned lassie” I am sure you often heard<lb/>it said.  Mrs Seery has just called, she told me thank you<lb/>for enquiring so soon about Johnnie he had a letter<lb/>to day about from Meagher who gave him very good<lb/>hopes I hope he will get the job any way the poor<lb/>thing ought to be old sick of <hi rend="underline">country charms</hi>.  I have not a bit of news so I will say a fond<lb/>&amp; loving bye to my dearest man  From his loving girl   May<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>     I dreamt last night I was getting <hi rend="superscript"> married </hi> not to you but<lb/>I had you as a guest you might be the better<lb/>off man too.<lb/>I’m off to the post with<lb/>this. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>