<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4347">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles F Down to Edward Carson, 8 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles F Down</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles F Down to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4347</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0208">Charles F Down</persName>
              <date>1916-06-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1925">Culloden, Craigavad, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4347_img_3704_1"  type="Letter"  url="d1b9a9268a1f6e473b19df88b693ac6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4347_img_3704_2"  type="Letter"  url="d8cd1e9058aa2a2ddd537fe1653ac131.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4347_img_3704_3"  type="Letter"  url="f352702f3fdc8d2650723980fe6f489f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4347_img_3704_4"  type="Letter"  url="16f2328ea5f4e7031ae01c8057a41893.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4347_img_3704_1"/>
             PAGE 2 OF 2   STATION, CULTRA. <lb/>TELEGRAMS. CRAIGDAVID. <lb/>TELEPHONE, CRAIGDAVID, 18.   CULLODEN, <lb/>CRAIGAVAD, <lb/>CO. DOWN.   <hi rend="underline">July 8. 1916</hi>   My Dear Sir Edward   I ought to have answered <lb/>your letter sooner, but I have <lb/>been from home &amp; intensely busy   My conviction is that the <lb/>line you have taken is perfectly <lb/>right. If Home Rule is <lb/>coming, as seems certain, <lb/>the only possible way of <lb/>securing any peace or security <lb/>in Ireland is to exclude <lb/>the six counties. The <lb/>Ulstermen cannot be forced <lb/>in. Now, more than ever, <lb/>this has become impossible.   The Southern Unionists &amp;
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4347_img_3704_2"/>
            others who are trying to wreck <lb/>the settlement are either <lb/>clinging to a hope of wrecking <lb/>Home Rule altogether, or are <lb/>bitterly vexed at what seems to <lb/>them the privileged position of <lb/>Ulster. All this talk about <lb/>the partition of Ireland is <lb/>nonsense. Ireland is partitioned <lb/>already. The only way to <lb/>preserve unity in Ireland is to <lb/>preserve the Union with England. <lb/>But if a real unity is ever to <lb/>come by internal co-operation <lb/>it will come much more <lb/>speedily through a frank <lb/>recognition of the real facts <lb/>than by any effort to force <lb/>the warring elements into an <lb/>artificial combination. I <lb/>feel ashamed of some of the
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4347_img_3704_3"/>
            efforts that are being made <lb/>to create trouble &amp; to prevent <lb/>a settlement. The <hi rend="underline">Church of</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland Gazette</hi> Is specially <lb/>mischievous &amp; is showing a <lb/>very bad spirit. It <lb/>was largely responsible <lb/>for the trouble at the <lb/>Synod.   As to the Bishop's re- <lb/>solution, I am sorry I <lb/>was not at the meeting: <lb/>but, as you know, I did <lb/>not receive the summons <lb/>&amp; knew nothing of its <lb/>doings until afterwards.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4347_img_3704_4"/>
            There was no use in my <lb/>trying to secure any <lb/>modification afterwards. It <lb/>would have been impossible <lb/>&amp; I felt that it was wiser <lb/>to say nothing. The <lb/>resolution was really a <lb/>most ambiguous statement <lb/>&amp; I have not met anyone <lb/>who knows exactly what <lb/> it means. Here <lb/>we all feel that it is <lb/>better to hold our tongues. <lb/>We follow your lead &amp; <lb/>that of the  Ulster Unionist Council.   Yours very faithfully.   <hi rend="underline">Charles F. Down.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>