<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4410">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Humphrey Pearson to Robert Chalmers, 21 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Humphrey Haines Pearson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Humphrey Pearson to Sir Robert Chalmers regarding the payment of expenses to the witness in a court case.  The witness does not feel that the expenses sufficiently cover the inconvenience and the out of pocket expenses that their attendance at court caused.

In 1916 Humphrey Haines Pearson was serving as rector in St. Multose Church, Kinsale, Co. Cork.
   
Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was appointed under-secretary of Ireland in 1916, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the Easter Rising.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10511</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4410</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0686">Humphrey Haines Pearson</persName>
              <date>1916-06-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0106">Kinsale, Co. Cork, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4410_img_3762_1"  type="Letter"  url="3050a149b9797ed435ae2f45c92232ed.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4410_img_3762_1"/>
             June 21st 1916   To The Under Secretary for Ireland <lb/>Dublin Castle <lb/>Knight &amp; Atkinson <lb/><hi rend="underline">Dublin Commission</hi>   Dear Sir   I have this day received an order <lb/>for £12.10.0 expenses as witness in   case.   I have to say that I feel the Treasure Scale <lb/>does not at all compensate me for the great <lb/>inconvenience &amp; expense I was put to in <lb/>attending twice within a fortnight in Dublin <lb/>first at the Police Court &amp; then at Green St.   I had to travel on each occasion nearly <lb/>400 miles &amp; to make provision for duty in <lb/>this important parish, on the last occasion <lb/>I had to provide a substitute for Sunday duty <lb/>£2.12.6 including <seg type="unclear">Ring</seg> family.   I trust that you will see your way to give <lb/>my case special consideration &amp; to make a <lb/>grant that will cover this out of pocket expense <lb/>&amp; the great inconvenience I was put to. I may say <lb/>I put another <seg type="unclear">day</seg> &amp;    on the 25 April when I <lb/>attempted to go up on first occasion to Police Court.   Faithfully Yours <lb/>H.W. Pearson 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>