<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0872">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas H. Kenny to the Under Secretary of Ireland, 22 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas H Kenny</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Hugh Kenny (1842-1927),a solicitor from Limerick, to the under secretary of Ireland requesting the services of a magistrate. The magistrate is needed to appear at the petty sessions in response to a summons issued by a County Surveyor against Patrick Wall in connection with a road building project.At the time this letter was written Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 -1938) was serving as the under secretary of Ireland. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as a replacement for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5618-12550</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/872</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0865">Thomas H Kenny</persName>
              <date>1916-07-22T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1821">55 George Street, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0872_img_2436_1"  type="Letter"  url="c7cc6d3b4894d9777677eadb1aafc6f8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0872_img_2436_1"/>
                55 George Street,  Limerick,    22 July    Sir   I am requested by Lord Emly to request that a Resident <lb/>Magistrate or if possible two should attend at the Patrick Wall Petty Sessions <lb/>on Tuesday next, as questions will arise on a Summons issued against  him <lb/>by the County Surveyor for permission to enter his land at Carriggunnell <lb/>  take stone for some 30 miles of Road. <seg type="del">and</seg> compulsorily and a <lb/>strong Bench of the most impartial character is very desirable. <seg type="closer"> I am Sir <lb/>Your o<sic>bdt servt</sic>  Tho<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> H Kenny   The Under Secretary  The Castle  Dublin  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>