<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0547">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from C. O'Connell Fitzsimon to Henry Arthur Wynne, 4 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>C. O&#39;Connell Fitzsimon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Christopher O&#39;Connell Fitzsimon (1860 - 1947), a solicitor from Queen&#39;s County. The letter was addressed to Sir Henry Arthur Wynne (1867 - 1945). Wynne was appointed to the vacant post of chief crown solicitor for Ireland following the death of Sir Malachy Kelly (1851-1916).This letter concerns the application of William Phelan, of Ballinakill Queen&#39;s County, for an extension of his six-day early closing licence under the Licensing Act, 1902.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-1551-1, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-1551-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/547</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0491">C. O&#39;Connell Fitzsimon</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0617">Abbeyleix, County Laois, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0815">Henry Arthur Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0547_img_1928_1"  type="Letter"  url="3370c204b7b3c750f0f0456234369050.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0547_img_1928_1"/>
                ABBEYLEIX.    4th July, 1916.   Dear Sir,   On the 26th June last an application was was made on behalf <lb/>of Wm. Phelan of Ballinakill, Queen's County, the Holder of <lb/>a six—day early closing licence for an ordinary six—day <lb/>licence, and said application was granted by the Justices at <lb/>Abbeyleix Quarter Sessions under the impression that Section <lb/>2 of the Licensing Act, 1902, authorised the granting of <lb/>such a certificate.   Since the Order was granted, the cases decided on the <lb/>Act have been looked into, and the applicant, being satisfied <lb/>that there was no jurisdiction to make the order in his <lb/>favour, instructs me to inform you that he does not propose <lb/>to take any advantage of the order or apply to the Inland <lb/>Revenue for any extension of his licence, and will, if it is <lb/>considered necessary, consent to the said order being <lb/>quashed.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  C OConnell Fitzsimon   The Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland,  The Castle,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>