<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0700">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Seamus Fitzgerald to his mother Alice Fitzgerald, 10 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Seamus Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Seamus Fitzgerald (1896–1972) to his mother, Alice. Seamus writes that he received no letter from her but got a parcel of biscuits from Bob and comments that &#39;Only for what we receive from outside we would never be able to live here at all&#39;. One hundred men have been transferred to Frongoch &#39;concentration camp&#39; and he doesn&#39;t know if he will have to go. There has been no word about his appeal and he fears the Queenstown Police are blocking it. He has lost his appetite and has become very melancholy musing that those involved in the fighting have been set free and the innocent ones are still imprisoned. Séamus Fitzgerald (1896-1972) was an Irish business man and politician. Apprenticing at a dock yard, Fitzgerald joined the Irish Volunteers and Sinn Fein after Easter week and was subsequently arrested and interned in Frongoch camp. He would enter politics upon his release.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork City and County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of Seamus Fitzgerald (1876-1972) PR/6/11, Papers of Seamus Fitzgerald (1876-1972) PR/6/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/700</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1323">Seamus Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-06-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1691">Wakefield Prison, West Yorkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1349">Alice Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0055">3 East Hill, Queenstown, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0700_img_2191_1"  type="Letter"  url="3347caeef2ccffd2624fd8eae6cb92ce.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0700_img_2191_2"  type="Letter"  url="88603374da96717422f12fd1a2b89807.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0700_img_2191_1"/>
              <lb/>C1/27 <lb/>I P 1036 <lb/> PR/6/11   Address to reply to â  C1036 James Fitzgerald,  Irish Prisoner,  (Wakefield)  c/o Chief Postal Censor, London      Wakefield Prison    Sat. 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916   My Dearest Mother,   It is strange that, <lb/>I have not had any letter from you <lb/>since the <seg type="del">PC you sent with the clothes <lb/> I had got in all </seg> one you sent with <lb/> the money order. I have got in all, <lb/> five PCs and one letter from Bob. You <lb/> must thank him for the parcel which <lb/> I received yesterday containing biscuits. <lb/> Only for what we receive from outside we <lb/> would never be able to live here at all.  Well, Mother, I have news to hand, but <lb/> I can't say that it is good news. One <lb/> hundred are leaving here this morning for <lb/> a concentration camp in North Wales (called <lb/> Frongoch). I was included with them at <lb/> first by mistake, but am still here. <lb/> Nevertheless I can't say how long more we  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0700_img_2191_2"/>
              <lb/>may be here. It is said a lot more are <lb/> to go to concentration camps. This means <lb/> of course that the first appeal that these men <lb/>made for release has been dismissed and <lb/> they are given one week more to make a <lb/> second and final appeal. If this appeal <lb/> fails, in all probability they will be <lb/> imprisoned for an indefinite period. I hope <lb/> so that my appeal will be taken, altho' my <lb/>hopes have been shattered a litttle. You see <lb/> it all depends on the charges which the police <lb/> of the district have manufactured against <lb/> them and I'm sure those in Q'town haven't <lb/> any qualms of conscience for me.  The imprisonment is beginning to tell a <lb/> little now on us. I have lost my appetite <lb/> and feel rather melancholy now and then. <lb/> It is a long time to be imprisoned and <lb/> it has been  all  anxiety from the start. <lb/> It is especially distressing to see a lot <lb/> of those who were fighting escaping scot <lb/> free and innocent men being kept a <lb/> good deal longer in prison. Not of <lb/> course that I wouldn't like to see <lb/> everyone free, but it isn't fair and <lb/> shows the blundering of the Government, <cb/><lb/>or, what is a good deal more probable, <lb/> the spite which the police bear <lb/> a lot of those men and the harm which <lb/> they are undoubtedly trying to do <lb/>then. That is why I fear if such will <lb/> be my case or not.   I asked you to send on some food, <lb/> as I am greatly in need of it. Yet <lb/> I never got any from you, altho' Lily and <lb/> Bob sent me some. I would like you <lb/> now to send me some money instead <lb/> say 15/-, as they would not allow us the <lb/> even pounds but keep them until our release.  I saw on the Cork Exam. of the <lb/> loss of Patrick. It is a terrible blow to <lb/> us all. I pray for him every day, and <lb/> hope he is in Heaven(P G.)  The weather is very cold and <lb/> dismal. I had a letter from Willie Farrell. <lb/> I hope all at home are well and that <lb/> ye received all the letters I sent. <lb/> I sent one to Patk, Lily, You and Bob <lb/> this week. No more news, so goodbye <lb/> for the present,  <seg type="closer"> I remain, my dearest Mother, <lb/> Your loving son,   Jim </seg> P.S. Excuse writing <lb/>, it is quite dark Jim  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>