<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0758">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 9 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter Spender writes that he will be moving to a new position the next day. He also briefly mentions Ulster politics, his mother&#39;s health, and the generous positivity of The Times&#39; representation of the Ulster Division. He revels in the thought of Lillian &#39;on the seashore with Sredward (Edward Carson) and Lady C, getting pinker and pinker in the hot sun&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/339</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/758</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0758_img_2290_1"  type="Letter"  url="5a62f10029b1483d9bc4517590e982d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0758_img_2290_2"  type="Letter"  url="f6f8e4eef38b6a501c6dd4549d96a19d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0758_img_2290_3"  type="Letter"  url="37ab7cb754f9c730ab2a2a0334d286bc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0758_img_2290_1"/>
                9July   My Dear Lil   A perfect day &amp; we seem <lb/> miles away from the events of <lb/>last week. The letters from <lb/>home help to complete the <lb/><seg type="del">dil></seg> illusion.   Elsie's letters show <lb/>immense pleasure in her <lb/>work. I'm so glad.   Singleton &amp; I leave early <lb/> tomorrow for a new destination. <lb/>We hope it only means that <lb/>the Division is being taken <lb/><seg type="del">up</seg> somewhere to reorganize, <lb/>&amp; that we shall again return <lb/>to the more pleasant country <lb/>where we now are.   I have just read the MP <lb/>leader - Friday's - which must <lb/>be unpleasant reading to BL, <lb/>because every word of it rings  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0758_img_2290_2"/>
              out it truth. In this world <lb/>the honest man - such as I <lb/>still believe BL to be - has <lb/>no chance against the Squiffy <lb/>crew.   I am not writing to <lb/>Burlington tho' I think of <lb/>you on the sea <hi rend="superscript">shore</hi> with Siredward <lb/>&amp; Lady C, getting pinker &amp; <lb/>pinker I the hot sun.   It is wonderful to me how <lb/> Mater has stood the past <lb/>week so well . I think she <lb/>feels that the responsibility is <lb/>on you, &amp; if you manage <seg type="del">the</seg> all <lb/>right she can.   The Times has certainly let <lb/>itself go over the Ulster Div- <lb/>far more than the MP . Perhaps <lb/>it feels some qualms &amp; hopes <lb/>to soothe them.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0758_img_2290_3"/>
              It is very curious that <lb/> the Times should have <lb/>been generous in its praise <lb/>&amp; not the MP, but the <lb/>latter is probably waiting <lb/>for details. I hope so any- <lb/>how or I shall be greatly <lb/> disappointed. Perhaps one of <lb/>the 2 families will have <lb/> kept the cuttings in Tuesday <lb/>&amp; Wednesday's Times &amp; <lb/>I may see the Belfast <lb/>Whig too which is sent to <lb/>Henry.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>