<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5104">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Colm O'Neill to Ellen Daly, 26 November 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Colm O&#39;Neill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/4/6/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5104</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0615">Colm O&#39;Neill</persName>
              <date>1923-11-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0723">188 Parnell Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5104_img_None_1"  url="00025fe702278df9a8a26413575669aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5104_img_None_2"  url="9b46291cefa019734a213241d48aee9e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5104_img_0_1"/>
             P41/4/6/18   188, Parnell. St., Dublin.    26/11/23    A Chara   I regret not having answered your very nice<lb/>letter sooner, but having had a rather bad cold I felt<lb/>out of form for letter writing. I am in deed<lb/>very grateful for your promise of photo and<lb/>memory card and am looking forward to getting<lb/>them when you can conveniently send them.<lb/>It is too bad to be bothering you so much in the<lb/>matter, but you will, I'm sure understand, how very<lb/>anxious I am that our dear hero lads should be<lb/>remembered and honoured. -----------  And your other boys. thank God one was<lb/>released, but the other what of him? Is he<lb/>still in enemy hands, &amp; if so, now the hunger<lb/>strike is off can I do anything for him. Remember 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5104_img_0_2"/>
             I shall be only too pleased to render any<lb/>service in my power, ------- How<lb/>you and yours have suffered in Ireland's<lb/>holy cause ! But please God, you will live<lb/>to all the powers of the foreigner broken, and the<lb/>traitor going shamed &amp; disgraced before the world.<lb/>England's agents at the present moment are actively<lb/>though quietly engaged, in finding out exactly what<lb/>strength of <seg type="del">our</seg> volunteer army can be relied on from<lb/>Ireland, to help The Empire in the campaign against<lb/>France, which is likely to commence in the near<lb/>future - Needless to say, the Freemason government<lb/>in Merrion St, must (being oath-bound) - though they're<lb/>noted for oath-breaking help <seg type="unclear">to</seg> their brother Freemasons<lb/>in England. Consequently it is necessary to keep<lb/>in prison those who might infure their cause -  Oh Good. bye. sure I've been saying too much<lb/>and again thanking you &amp; hoping that the future<lb/>holds much happiness for you all.  <seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign">????</seg></seg>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>