<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4220">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to her sister Ruth, 3 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her sister, Ruth Duffin.

Celia Duffin, born in 1888, was one of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She attended the Cheltenham Ladies College. She served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#34;Escape Poem&#34; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell &amp; Co. Ltd in 1929. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers, D2109/9/4/B/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4220</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1375">Ruth Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0733">3rd London General Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4220_img_3590_1"  type="Letter"  url="3132db0f76d4a4d4138c2bb96df59d11.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4220_img_3590_2"  type="Letter"  url="ec19f5016c9c92ac7b4c58fad35b0cb1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4220_img_3590_1"/>
             Nov. 9th 1915   To <seg type="unclear">Middle Hall</seg> <lb/>3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi><seg type="unclear">London General</seg>   Dear Ruth   I have owed you a letter for some time to really its hard <lb/>to find time to write to all the family they are so scattered at <lb/>present. I wonder how you are getting on, I have heard little of you, <lb/>write and tell me about the students. How many have you got <lb/>now? Do you find it hard to keep them in order? Its funny to think <lb/>of Biddy being there. Mrs MacLeod was enquiring about her. I <lb/>went to her again last half day. It was pouring outside and I was <lb/>very tired, so I ended up in a big chair by the fire and she recited to <lb/>me for ages. She must have a wonderful memory. You don't know <lb/>how nice an armchair and a fire are until you have been <lb/>running about on your feet all week. I didn't bother to talk <lb/>much and stayed for dinner. A Mrs Brown was there for <lb/>tea who made pretty speeches about my poems. I would love to get <lb/>home for Xmas, but of course there is no chance of it. I have been <lb/>here 5 months now and suppose will be asked to sign on again <lb/>soon. They asked some of us to volunteer for a hospital ship yes— <lb/>terday but I didn't think I was a good enough sailor. I think when <lb/>my 6 months are up I shall try to join Emma in Egypt —   We get quite responsible work to do now, always under supervision <lb/>of course. I expect to spend this afternoon in the theatre, but <lb/>none o#f the operations are bad ones, and I am getting rather <lb/>good with people's tonsils and noses. One of the men has
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4220_img_3590_2"/>
            written a lovely poem about me and the ear syringe, I must get <lb/>a copy of it. Mrs MacLeod was going to tea with Mrs <lb/>Harker and was so surprised when I told her I had <lb/>first been there. I spent an evening with Miss July who <lb/>was all over me and <hi rend="underline">kissed</hi> me when I was going away, <lb/>she <hi rend="underline">loves</hi> her work, and though offered a good post by the <lb/>War Office would not leave for anything! A queer little <lb/>French nun who knows no English looks after her rooms, and <lb/>we had supper with all the other boarders, a queer — <lb/>looking crew. The Mother Superior apologised for '<seg type="foreign">pas de viande</seg>' <lb/>as it was a fast day.   I went with Mrs Monaghan <lb/>to have tea and dinner with her people at Ealing. I wasn't <lb/>much taken with them, though they were very kind, and <seg type="unclear">are</seg> <lb/>  is very pretty. Marjorie is cook at one of the hostels <lb/>here and gets £1 a week, which is pretty good. She is a great <lb/>talker, rather fat and jolly, and business like — I have <lb/>just have an affectionate letter from Evelyn Henry asking me <lb/>to <seg type="unclear">Hurlingham</seg> again but I have booked up my next two or <lb/>3 half days and it is too far to go in my 3 hours off.   I want to get the St John overcoat &amp; hat, this cloak is a <lb/>miserable garment and very cold now, but will have to wait till <lb/>I get my next month's pay, as I suppose <seg type="unclear">Garrold's</seg> would <lb/>expect cash. I never write a line, what have you been <lb/>doing? Please send me a copy of the "Lovers Toll" for Mrs MacLeod <lb/>the next time you write.   Best love,   Celia. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>