<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0705">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 28 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme. James was born in 1877.James writes that he expects to be moving from holding the line in the next day or two to undergo strenuous training, indicating that he would not have time to write as much. He also writes that he had recently been spent a day at the French machine gun school. He is sending clothing home and asks to have other items mailed to him.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/50</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/705</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-05-28</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0705_img_2199_1"  type="Letter"  url="b180313d2eca4911871ebd7841e706b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0705_img_2199_2"  type="Letter"  url="0b14bf7d4209dbc2777025a96778175c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0705_img_2199_3"  type="Letter"  url="02d448a4e0329994111d61a9d677a92d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0705_img_2199_4"  type="Letter"  url="c35006cb2456fd3fd431cfd603831e88.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0705_img_2199_5"  type="Letter"  url="df94238fffbc23a10134083719d8a567.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0705_img_2199_6"  type="Envelope"  url="1e35201fcb98da802d6debf595e41773.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0705_img_2199_1"/>
                28/5/16   My dearest Mother,   I have not been treating <lb/>you well recently in the <lb/>way of letters but really <lb/> it has been impossible <lb/> to find time for writing. <lb/> Every day it is in the same <lb/> from early morning till <lb/>late at night, one continual <lb/> rush.   I was so <lb/>sorry dear Mother that <lb/> you have had so much <lb/> worry with cooks <seg type="unclear">etc</seg><lb/> I do wish you could <lb/> find someone who would <lb/> suit.  Was glad to get <lb/> a letter also from Father <lb/>with news of the pistol. <lb/> If I have time I will  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0705_img_2199_2"/>
              <lb/>write him a line separately.   We are probably moving <lb/> back from the Line to— <lb/>morrow or day after. <lb/>You see we dont get <lb/>much notice, for even <lb/> yet it is not definite. <lb/> We only go a short <lb/>distance &amp;, as I understand, <lb/> for a short time, in order <lb/> to go through some <lb/>special training of a <lb/> rather strenuous nature, <lb/>so it wont mean much <lb/>rest. However it will <lb/> be  a little relief from <lb/> the responsibility of <lb/> holding the Line.   The weather has not <lb/> been quite so hot last <lb/> few days &amp; there has  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0705_img_2199_3"/>
              <lb/>been some rain which <lb/> was really badly needed <lb/> to lay the dust! The <lb/> Germans too have been <lb/> less vicious so things <lb/> have been more or less <lb/> peaceful &amp; it has given <lb/> us a good opportunity <lb/> to push on with a lot of <lb/>rather difficult work.    I spent a most interesting <lb/> day this week at the <lb/>French Machine Gun School <lb/> some miles from here. <lb/> Went with 2 other officers <lb/>in a Div. motor &amp; got <lb/>back same day. Saw <lb/>no end of interesting <lb/> things &amp; the French <lb/>officers took no end <lb/> of trouble to show &amp;  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0705_img_2199_4"/>
              <lb/>explain everything.    Have sent off a parcel <lb/> of warm underclothing <lb/> today &amp; hope it will l<lb/> turn up all right. <lb/>Will have some more <lb/> to send later.    By the <lb/> way the lining you <lb/>sent for my waterproof <lb/>was not the right one. <lb/> It belonged to one of <lb/>my coats at home. <lb/> The correct one is very <lb/> similar &amp; you could <lb/> easily make a mistake <lb/> with them. You can <lb/>recognise the one I <lb/> want as there are <lb/> elastic bands at <lb/> wrists &amp; it is rather <lb/> shorter than the one  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0705_img_2199_5"/>
              <lb/>you sent. Would you <lb/> please have the other <lb/> sent off &amp; then when <lb/> it arrives I will send <lb/> back the one I have. <lb/> The parcels from Fureys <lb/>&amp; Malcolmsons don't <lb/> arrive so regularly as <lb/> they used too but I am <lb/> sure it is entirely the <lb/> fault of the P.O.    Now dearest Mother <lb/>goodbye. Don't be <lb/> alarmed if you do not <lb/> hear from me for some <lb/> days as if we <hi rend="underline">do</hi> move <lb/> it will mean a busy <lb/> time for me.  <seg type="closer"> Hoping <lb/>you are all well &amp; with <lb/>fondest love <lb/>Your loving son   Jim </seg> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0705_img_2199_6"/>
               On Active Service <lb/>written 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May —   2nd June <lb/>19/16   Mrs. S. C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  <lb/>JsDavidson 28 May 1916   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>