<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4633">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to Ignatius O'Brien, 12 July 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

Ignatius John O&#39;Brien, 1st Baron Shandon (31 July 1857 – 10 September 1930), known as Sir Ignatius O&#39;Brien between 1916 and 1918, was an Irish lawyer and politician. He served as Lord Chancellor of Ireland between 1913 and 1918.﻿﻿</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-245</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4633</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1917-07-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ignatius O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1648">The Four Courts, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4633_img_3973_1"  type="Letter"  url="b7e37847e7765696ab9f96b65a0da30c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4633_img_3973_2"  type="Letter"  url="54a73f62df2da1d315ade29cb930ee31.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4633_img_3973_3"  type="Letter"  url="9ac7b59fc5dd565777c96f3118241659.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4633_img_3973_4"  type="Letter"  url="2e4e5645185aefd66ca1b9940d525337.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4633_img_3973_1"/>
             RCPI/2/3/2/13/245 1   13th July 17.    To<lb/>The Right Hon.    The Lord Chancellor of Ireland,<lb/>Four Courts, Dublin.    My Lord,   I am requested by the President and Fellows<lb/>of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to<lb/>inform you that, owing to the resignation of Mr.T.<lb/>W. Kinahan, the post of Auditor of accounts of the<lb/>late Sir Patrick Dun's estate is now vacant.  Under the terms of the School of Physic Act<lb/>(40Goo.III.,cap. 84., sec. XI.) this appointment rests<lb/>in the hands of the Visitors of this College (The<lb/>Lord Chancellor, The Lord Chief Justice and<lb/>The Lord Chief Baron), and the President and Fellows<lb/>will feel greatly obliged if your Lordship will at<lb/>your convenience nominate some competent person to 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4633_img_3973_2"/>
             (2).<lb/>fill the vacancy.  Herewith, I enclose a copy of hitherto<lb/>signed by the Visitors on making the appointment.  Should the presence of the clerk to the Trust<lb/>Estate be required he will wait upon your Lordships<lb/>at such time and place as you desire.  I have to the honour to be,   My Lord,    Your Lordship's obedient servant,     Fellow &amp; Registrar.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4633_img_3973_3"/>
             By an Act passed in the 40th year of the Reign of his<lb/>late Majesty GEORGE III. Chapter 84, Section XL.,<lb/>entitled : An Act for establishing a complete School<lb/>of Physic in this Kingdom(amongst other things) it<lb/>is enacted, That the President and Fellows of the<lb/>King and Queen's College of Physicians herein named<lb/>shall, once in every year, render a true, just and full  account of the<lb/>receipts and <seg type="del">disbursements</seg> expenditures of the issues and profits<lb/>of the real and personal estates of  the said  Sir Patrick Dunn,<lb/>and of the application of the appropriated and unappro-<lb/>priated surplus thoroof, before the said Visitors, or<lb/><seg type="del">any</seg>  some  two of them, or such person or personals as shall<lb/>be for that purpose appoint by  the  said Visitors, or any<lb/>two of them, by writing, signed by them, or any two of<lb/>them     and after  the  said Account has been duly examined,<lb/>rectified, and settled by  the  said Visitors, or <seg type="del">by</seg> any two<lb/>of them, or by the person   of persons so  <seg type="del">to be</seg> appointed, as aforesaid,<lb/>it shall be signed and allowed by  the  said Visitors, or any<lb/>two of them, and entered or copied into the books of the<lb/>said College. Now we, The Right Honourable Sir Ignatius<lb/>John O'Brien, Bart., Lord Chancellor of Ireland, The<lb/>Right Honorable Sir James Henry Musson Campbell, Bart.,<lb/>Lord Chief of Justice of Ireland and The Right Honorable<lb/>Christopher Palles, Lord Chief Baron of the Exchequer<lb/>in Ireland, the Visitors of the said College in pursu-<lb/>ance of the Powers vested in us under said Act, Do<lb/>hereby appoint<lb/>of the City of Dublin Esquire on our behalf and in our 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4633_img_3973_4"/>
             RCPI/2/3/2/13/245  <seg type="unclear">(a).</seg> (3).  stead to examine, rectify and settle the Annual Accounts<lb/>relating to the aforesaid Estates with the President and<lb/>Fellows according to the provisions of said Act of 40th<lb/>Geo.III., and for that purpose we do hereby require the<lb/>proper officers of said College lay before  the  said  copies of the yearly accounts of receipts<lb/>and disbursements of  the  said Estates, and also copies of the<lb/>yearly accounts of the Land Agents of  the  said Estates, as<lb/>exhibited by him to the said College, together with such<lb/>vouchers ads the said<lb/>shall deem requisite to verify  the  said Accounts, And we<lb/>also require the proper officers of  the  said College to give<lb/>to  the said  such information generally as<lb/>he shall deem necessary to enable him to make a full and<lb/>detailed report of the State of  the  said  <seg type="del">the</seg>  Estates showing the<lb/>Balances of the several Accounts between the said Presi-<lb/>dent and Fellows and  the  said Estates as well as the Balances<lb/>remaining due by the tenants of the said Estates. ______<lb/>Dated this..... 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>