<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2468">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. J. Heverin to the under-secretary, 3 August 1916 </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. J. Heverin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from M.J. Heverin, Secretary, Roscommon County Council to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), the under-secretary for ireland. Chalmers succeeded Sir Matthew Nathan who resigned on 3 May, 1916 due to his failure to prevent the Easter Rising.

Mr. Heverin encloses a resolution passed unanimously by Roscommon County Council. The resolution refers to previous difficulties in relation to uneven distribution of land in the county which led to the deployment of large numbers of military and police to the area. As these matters have been settled the Council calls for the withdrawal of these forces.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5620/13368</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2468</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0856">M. J. Heverin </persName>
              <date>1916-08-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0674">Roscommon County Council, Courthouse, Roscommon, County Roscommon, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2468_img_1904_1"  type="Letter"  url="85590c8060d7f5719148d182b6e73dba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2468_img_1904_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="cf81ee03632d896d14efe9fd92941dbe.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2468_img_1904_1"/>
              Roscommon County Council <lb/>SECRETARY'S OFFICE, <lb/>COURTHOUSE. <lb/>ROSCOMMON   3rd August 1916   encl.   Sir/    I herewith enclose copy resolution which was <lb/>passed unanimously by the Roscommon County Council <lb/>at their Meeting on the 1st instant.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   M J Heverin </seg>  The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   Asst. Under Secretary <lb/>Submitted to see <lb/>on return the resolution will <lb/>be <sic>ackd.</sic> <lb/>W.O.H. <lb/>4/8/16   Chief Secretary <lb/>U.S. to see Resolution,Co Council <lb/>Eof <lb/>4.8.16 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2468_img_1904_2"/>
             ROSCOMMON COUNTY COUNCIL   RESOLUTION   Proposed by Councillor Patrick Murray,   Seconded by Councillor M. McDonnell,   And Resolved — "That we call the attention of the <lb/>Government to the fact that the discontent of the <lb/>people of the Parish of Moore which recently found <lb/><hi rend="underline">expression</hi> <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>  was due to the want of economic farms on <lb/>the part of hundreds of small farmers in that part of <lb/>the county whilst one man possesses 3,500 acres of land <lb/>in the Union of Ballinasloe. The late agitation for <lb/>meadow land for the present season has ceased owing to <lb/>a settlement, but a large force of military and police <lb/>is still retained there <sic>unecessarily</sic>, and this <hi rend="underline">martial</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">law</hi> is a source of <hi rend="underline">irritation to the local people</hi>, and <lb/>we request the Government to immediately remove them.<lb/>  1. By injuring 17 RIC, one seriously. <lb/>RIC 4/8/16   At the Meeting of the County Council held this 1st day of August 1916 <lb/>the above Resolution was (a) Carried <lb/>Signature of Presiding Chairman M. H. Grogan.   (a) Insert here "Carried" or "Lost" ; if on a Division add the word "by a majority of ........... <lb/>votes against............... votes," the names of those voting being—  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>