<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5923">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William S. McKee to Frederick Hugh Crawford, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William S. McKee</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from William s. McKee (b. 1836) to Frederick Hugh Crawford (1854-1935) in which he thanks Carson for appreciating his work for the starch manufacturing firm, A. Crawford and Sons. McKee discusses his positive relationships with his colleagues and with Crawford during his employment. However, McKee doubts if he would be able to continue visiting the office, beyond the occasional instance, due to his poor health. He thanks Crawford for holding him in high regard.Frederick Hugh Crawford was born in Belfast to a strong Methodist family. He was a soldier, gun-runner and electrical engineer. In 1914 he smuggled guns for the Ulster Volunteer Force into Larne, Bangor and Donaghadee, County Down. He was also appointed OC Royal Army Service Corps for Northern Ireland during the First World War. William S. McKee was a Wesleyan Methodist from Bangor, County Down. He was the manager of A. Crawford and Sons, a company founded by Frederick Hugh Crawford&#39;s grandfather which manufactured starch.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Crawford Papers, D/1700/5/17/1/130</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5923</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0176">William S. McKee</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1206">Mossvale, Bangor, County Down , Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0900">Frederick Hugh Crawford</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2090">Victoria Barracks, Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5923_img_1763_1"  type="Letter"  url="b7ccea1a023606dbd5d93d85b56e209c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5923_img_1763_2"  type="Letter"  url="43c327c3d39b348c4fe8da8b1127dd95.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5923_img_1763_3"  type="Letter"  url="75688ba5d70da49a0266df4703d45a8d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5923_img_1763_4"  type="Envelope"  url="219b869a01301585cc857bdef59fa4f5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5923_img_1763_1"/>
                Mossvale,  Bangor,  Co. Down.     March 31/16    Dear Col Crawford,   Your very kind letter of <lb/> 28th Inst. has gratified me <lb/> very much. Your good opinion <lb/> of my service in the firm of <lb/> A.C.S. is more than I deserve. <lb/> I have only attempted to do <lb/> my duty as far as I am able, <lb/> and I can sincerely say, that <lb/> I have received from every <lb/> member of the firm, a more <lb/> than ample reward for anything  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5923_img_1763_2"/>
              I have done. I am however <lb/> more than happy in believing <lb/> that I have been considered by <lb/> each member of the firm as a <lb/> friend, as well as an employee &amp; <lb/> I have reciprocated this feeling to <lb/> the very fullest extent.    My personal relations with <lb/> yourself have always been of <lb/> the warmest and closest kind <lb/> I have been proud of your <lb/> confidence, &amp; sorry that it <lb/> was not in my power to help you more effectually in the trials <lb/> and difficulties of a very unusual <lb/> kind it has been your lot to <lb/> experience.   With reference to the office, when <lb/> the weather gets warmer I hope to <lb/> be able to pay an occasional <lb/> visit but I am afraid I cannot <lb/> count much on my strength <lb/> for the time to come, I feel <lb/> all right when I an sitting <lb/> at the fire or reading, or at the <lb/> microscope <seg type="unclear">Ic.</seg> but the slightest <lb/> physical exertion seems beyond <lb/> my strength. Besides I have small <lb/> little ailments, which while not <lb/> very painful or acute keep me  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5923_img_1763_3"/>
              in a condition of more or less <lb/> anxiety. However I must not take <lb/> a gloomy view of things but <lb/> endeavour to justify my optimistic <lb/> propensities to the last breath. <lb/> I must close &amp; cannot avoid <lb/> repeating that I consider your <lb/> letter a testimonial which I <lb/> value beyond all price  <seg type="closer"> Yours ever  <hi rend="underline">WS McKee.</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5923_img_1763_4"/>
               Bangor 31 March 16 <lb/><hi rend="underline">Private</hi>    Colonel F.H. Crawford  Army Service Corps,  Victoria Barracks,   Belfast.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>