<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1653">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 4 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Marie Martin (1892-1975), to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle. She was called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France. Marie later founded the Medical Missionaries of Mary.

In this letter Marie tells her mother about how busy she has been lately due to the numerous cases of nephritis among the men. Marie then goes on to describe the trouble she has been having with her feet and her need to obtain supports for the long night shifts. Before signing off  her letter, Marie informs her mother about the move of the hospital at which her Aunt Lily works.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/1/38/1916/04/04</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1653</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-04-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1653_img_1113_1"  type="Letter"  url="689761faec9fbcd559dd0f1cba771af1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1653_img_1113_2"  type="Letter"  url="4dce1f582530b9a3750e5a80f38d2e3d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1653_img_1113_3"  type="Letter"  url="c3a911312204adc6df28e9cd48444837.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1653_img_1113_4"  type="Letter"  url="0c740ce7a378fb90f1264d1e16c78c59.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1653_img_1113_5"  type="Envelope"  url="aaa520ea677aa3bf89e37c67662902c2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1653_img_1113_1"/>
             4th March  <lb/>(April) <lb/>(see envelope)  My very dearest Mother,   A thousand thanks for your<lb/> very long letter, I was delighted to get it<lb/> as I am getting very few letters now<lb/> except you &amp; I must really thank<lb/> you ever so much for writing so<lb/> often &amp; such long letters as I know how<lb/> busy &amp; how many letters you have to<lb/> write. I have been changed from A block<lb/> to H so have been kept fairly busy<lb/> as there are a good few men fairly<lb/> bad with nephritis &amp; need <sic>polticing</sic><lb/> etc during night so with this &amp; getting<lb/> the Sisters meals &amp; washing up after them<lb/> there is not much time &amp; I generally<lb/> go to bed about 10 o'clock &amp; get up &amp; <lb/> go for walk which is most necessary<lb/> on night duty unfortunately these last<lb/> few days I have not been off &amp; as <lb/> my feet have been very bad &amp; I am<lb/> great afraid &amp; sorry to have to say I <lb/> am going very flat footed. Matron<lb/> who is a dear saw me about them<lb/> yesterday &amp; says I had better get supports<lb/> which I hope to do when I come<lb/> of night duty &amp; have time to go
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1653_img_1113_2"/>
            into Valletta. I am at present doing<lb/> Swedish exercising with my toes. My<lb/> Sister, <seg type="unclear">Trowess,</seg> very kindly messaged<lb/> them yesterday which made them much<lb/> better, she says it is partly Rheumatic<lb/> &amp; that the foot had gone fairly<lb/> flat. Sister Trower I am sorry<lb/> to say is off all night duty &amp; we<lb/> have a horrible common one instead.<lb/> I am glad to say Matron is<lb/> taking me off after the month<lb/> as she does not approve of VADs<lb/> being on longer. Matron is<lb/> charming &amp; her one delight is<lb/> to see every one happy. She is going<lb/> to put me in Sister Trowess' ward<lb/> when I go on day duty so I expect<lb/> to have a nice month before we<lb/> go home. I do not know what is<lb/> going to happen to us the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> lot of<lb/> V.A.Ds went of Friday, it did make<lb/> us all feel home sick. Ah but two<lb/> of these who have signed on again<lb/> were sent home <seg type="del">expect</seg> so it looks like<lb/> as if they they are keeping very few<lb/> us in Malta. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1653_img_1113_3"/>
             Do you think there is anyone who<lb/> would like me to do any commissions<lb/> for the in the way of lace because<lb/> if so do not leave it too late in letting<lb/> me know. Also if you want to give<lb/> me any instruction about journey going<lb/> home let me know early &amp; also the<lb/> answer in my last letter about<lb/> signing on whilst in London for France<lb/> when wanted! I have not heard<lb/> a word from Gerald since he<lb/> has been home perhaps his letter<lb/> was in the <sic>torpetoed</sic> one. I hope he<lb/> is safe &amp; well. Aunt Lily was up<lb/> here yesterday so I suppose you have<lb/> heard her whole Hospital has been<lb/> close, it is hard luck on her<lb/> There are 1 of the Florence Sisters<lb/> arriving here today. I wonder if she<lb/> will be among the crowd. It<lb/> is just hopeless here at present<lb/> as all the sisters from the hospital<lb/> that are closing were dumped here<lb/> because everything but I am <seg type="unclear">very tired</seg><lb/> the spelling is <seg type="unclear">weird</seg> I know so do<lb/> not show it round &amp; all the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> part<lb/> is just as such only know by you
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1653_img_1113_4"/>
             I hope by this you have had good <lb/>news of Charlie also Tommy &amp; I <lb/>wonder if he will come across <lb/> Irene G.   With every loving thought, good <lb/>wish &amp; blessing. <lb/>Hoping you are all very <lb/>well.   You ever loving daughter   Marie   It is getting very hot but I <lb/> am feeling much better <lb/><hi rend="underline">Love M</hi> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1653_img_1113_5"/>
             On Active Service   Mrs Martin, <lb/>Greenbank <lb/>Monkstown, <lb/>Co Dublin <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>