<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5100">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 19, December, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his mother. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5100</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-12-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5100_img_None_1"  url="ec94dbf1edbf4c989cfd15f0e135eb18.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5100_img_None_2"  url="b50e69438f6a8a80361352d208a4bb7d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5100_img_None_3"  url="3568f100d640358116c8325519d976c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5100_img_None_4"  url="d45917908bea9de7ae56f27351025186.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5100_img_0_1"/>
              19<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><hi rend="superscript"> </hi>1917    My dear Mamy.   I was delighted to get your<lb/>letter of 12<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>on the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which was<lb/>very quick. we did not get any<lb/>letters yesterday on the day before<lb/>on account of the snow and<lb/>moving. We have had a heavy fall<lb/>of snow and now very heavy frost.  The snow has drifted and is 6 feet<lb/>deep in <seg type="unclear"></seg> in some places.  I think we have toms to rest at least<lb/>after all our moving about and are<lb/>in a nice little village and quite<lb/>comfortable. I wil be able to get letters <seg type="unclear">washed</seg> and everything.  I told you in my last letter that<lb/>I was on ahead of the regiment. Well! After I left their destination was changed but there was no way    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5100_img_0_2"/>
             of letting me know so I<lb/>walked up and down the road<lb/>all night waiting for them and<lb/>only found out at 10 next morning<lb/>that they were in another village 10 miles away - I had a great<lb/>tramp through the snow. I had<lb/>Morgan Moore with me as he was<lb/>on his <hi rend="superscript"> way </hi> back and heard the<lb/>batallion were going to the same<lb/>place I was in so he came along.  I think I got all the parcels you<lb/>sent alright except of course the<lb/>last trifle which could not<lb/>possibly have arrived yet.  The plum pudding I could not<lb/>keep till Xmas so we just eat it.<lb/>It was delicious and 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5100_img_0_3"/>
             it was awfully good of you to send<lb/><seg type="del">them</seg> it + particularly the brandy<lb/>sauce. I am sure the turkey will<lb/>be delicious too. There are only<lb/>three of us in the company so we<lb/>will have a fine feed.  My kit did not come last night<lb/>so I had no blankets. I had a nice<lb/>big bed and two mattresses so I<lb/>just got in between the two and was<lb/>as warm as toast. I also had a big<lb/>fire so what more could I want.  I wrote a few Xmas letters but fear<lb/>they will all be late as it was<lb/>impossible to get them posted <seg type="del">the ar</seg> when<lb/>we were moving. Things will probably<lb/>be more regular now as we will be<lb/>here for quite a while I expect.  Certainly till next year.  No more news and I will write<lb/>soon again. I hope you all 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5100_img_0_4"/>
             got Xmas over successfully.   Best love to all    Your most affec Son   <hi rend="underline"> Willie </hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>