<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5165">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 10, October, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his mother.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5165</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-10-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5165_img_None_1"  url="84f012dcc4a485f1fa52a4f74159a2ad.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5165_img_None_2"  url="893038b8ab3c269cce91ed9ea1d63d0f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5165_img_0_1"/>
              10 October 1917    My dear Mamy   Here we are still but having a<lb/>very easy time. Nothing to do but eat<lb/>and sleep &amp; you may be quite sure<lb/>we do plenty of both. I was delighted<lb/>to get your long letter last night and<lb/>I am sure the apples will come tonight so<lb/>I will have a real good feed.  I hear there was a great show at<lb/>Ypres again yesterday but no details<lb/>have come in yet.  I am very glad Miss Joly is<lb/>going down to see you. She will be<lb/>company for you.  Next time  to  you see Mr Bodel ask<lb/>him if he remembers a fellow named<lb/>R.A Young whom he married some time<lb/>ago. He is Capt in this battalion &amp;<lb/> is an awfully nice fellow. He comes<lb/>from somewhere near Belfast and 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5165_img_0_2"/>
             is home on leave at present.  There was quite a frost here two<lb/>nights ago but the general rule<lb/>is rain &amp; the trenches are very wet.  I cannot write a long letter<lb/>as there is no place to get news<lb/>except from Johnny over the way<lb/>and he is not communicative as<lb/>a rule.  With very best love to all from   Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>