<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1782">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Howell Davies to Augustine Birrell, 10 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Howell Davies</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from William Howell Davies (1851-1932) a British politician to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), the chief secretary of Ireland.  Davis held a seat in Westminster for the South Bristol district.  The letter is written in the context of the death of Chief Crown Solicitor Malachy Kelly (1850-1916). The letter references an enclosed letter Davies is sending on as an application for the vacant position, however Davies does not claim to know the qualifications of the man in question.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/6463/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1782</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0520">William Howell Davies</persName>
              <date>1916-04-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0598">Down House, Stoke Bishop, Bristol, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1198">Irish Office, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1932</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1782_img_1237_1"  type="Letter"  url="2ade8a4b28622120f72dd22b8a45035d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1782_img_1237_1"/>
             DOWN HOUSE, <lb/>STOKE BISHOP <lb/>BRISTOL.   April 10th,16 .  My dear Birrell,   The enclosed speaks for itself. <lb/>I know of the qualifications of the gentleman <lb/>who is applying for the office of Chief Crown Solicitor <lb/>of Ireland, and I am merely sending his name on to you <lb/>at the request of the writer of the enclosed letter. <lb/>I have no doubt you will give the application your consi- <lb/>deration.   Yours very truly,   Wm Howell Davies  <lb/>Rt. Hon. A. Birrell, K.C., M.P.,  Irish Office, <lb/>LONDON .
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>