<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2998">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Last Will and Testament of Countess Constance Markievicz, 30 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Constance Markievicz</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Countess Constance Markievicz (1868-1927) was a militant republican, a labour activist, a suffragist and a politician. She was an executive member of the radical women&#39;s nationalist movement Inghinidhe na hÉireann, the nationalist Boy Scouts movement Na Fianna Éireann, the Irish Neutrality League, and the revolutionary socialist movement the Citizen Army. During Easter Week of 1916, Markievicz served as second-in-command of the St. Stephen&#39;s Green Citizen Army garrison. In 1918, she became the first woman to be elected to the British parliament, and in 1919, she became the second woman in Europe to serve as a cabinet minister.

This document is last will and testament written by Markievicz at the end of Easter week in the Royal College of Surgeons as her garrison was surrounded by British troops and she faced the possibility of imminent death. The will was witnessed by Michael Mallin and Madeleine ffrench-Mullen.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Brother Allen Collection, Kathleen Lynn Collection, IE/AL/KL/1/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2998</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1231">Constance Markievicz</persName>
              <date>1916-04-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1446">Royal College of Surgeons, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName >None</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName >None</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Last Letters before Death</item>
               <item n="topic">Last Letters before Death</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2998_img_2400_1"  type="Letter"  url="f240464fd9ad3a2891671086551704f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2998_img_2400_2"  type="Letter"  url="45e654454943691bc666a31461371906.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2998_img_2400_1"/>
             This is the last will &amp; <lb/>testament of me, Constance <lb/>de Markievicz.   I leave to my husband <lb/>Casimir de Markievicz the <lb/>sum of £100 pounds, to <lb/>my stepson Stanislas de <lb/>Markievicz the sum of £100 <lb/>to Bessie Lynch who lived <lb/>with me £25   Everything else I possess, <lb/>to my daughter, <lb/>Medb Alys de Markievicz   Constance de Markievicz <lb/>written in the presence of <lb/>Michael Mallin <lb/>M. ffrench Mullen   April 30 1916 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2998_img_2400_2"/>
             Will of Countess Markievicz drawn up in the College <lb/>of Surgeons on  30th April 1916 : Witnessed by <lb/>Michael Mallin and by <hi rend="underline">Madeline ffrench Mullen</hi>   Presented to the OConnell <lb/>School museum by <lb/><hi rend="underline">Doctor K.Lynn</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>