<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3142">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to her mother, Thursday November,1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Celia Duffin writes to her mother talking about her work in a hospital,in the letter she describes her patients aswell as some new people she has met since her previous letter.She also tells her mother how much she misses her and how it will be quiet Christmas without her company.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>D2109/9/4/B/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3142</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Celia Duffin&#39;s Mother</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3142_img_2560_1"  type="Letter"  url="6edcf32eca588226029c5d55fdd9c55d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3142_img_2560_2"  type="Letter"  url="b8814d47065cdd1c32ab9bcf89fd1de5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3142_img_2560_3"  type="Letter"  url="8a244ca36b9340b2eb2f877edbc9603c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3142_img_2560_4"  type="Letter"  url="969dac8f60b9ef8909e71e68d6c6067f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3142_img_2560_5"  type="Letter"  url="23986fd229844ad660fcfaa7e82ed9d4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3142_img_2560_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/B.   Thursday<lb/>Nov,1915    Dearest Mammy,   Thank you very much for the<lb/>washing square, it will do splendidly and is<lb/>quite soft enough if you make the<lb/>others the same. We have 31 beds and so does the<lb/>next door ward. The men are supposed to<lb/>give them up when they go out and we boil<lb/>them up for the next patient; but they often<lb/>take them with them, so you can see we need<lb/>a good many. Auntie B. forwarded one<lb/>or two which are already in use.  <lb/>Now that the family are scattered it’s<lb/>hard to find time to write lettters of them all.<lb/>You say no <hi rend="underline">more</hi> news of Terry, but have<lb/>heard absolutely nothing except that he has 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3142_img_2560_2"/>
             arrived in France and would like to know<lb/>a little about what he is doing.  We are allowed two fires a week in<lb/>our rooms, and as this is my evening off, I am<lb/>luxuriating in one,  and  as it really has been<lb/>a very cold day.  I looked up Miss Monaghan to-night, a<lb/>nice big rosy-faced girl, and found her very<lb/>busy in the new orderlies hostel, getting their<lb/>dinners ready. That is her job, but she hopes<lb/>to get into the hospital soon. It is my half<lb/>day to-morrow, so I am going home with her<lb/>to Eailing. I had a nice letter from<lb/>Mrs Bruce at Airlie Gardens asking me<lb/>there, <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> I really find my half days<lb/>booked up for some time, but must go and<lb/>see her some time.  I would like to spend my evenings off<lb/>at home; it is too dark to go any place,<lb/>and I want some of the family to talk to—  I arranged to have tea with Miss<lb/>Juhr twice, but had to put off both times.<lb/>She has asked me again next Saturday to<lb/>meet E. Andrews who is staying at Streatham,<lb/>I must really try to go this time. She says<lb/>you are so good about writing to her,<lb/>and that she is very happy. I went to leave<lb/>a note in the other day and such a funny<lb/>little French nun <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> opened the door,<lb/>and talked French so quickly to me<lb/>I couldn’t understand what she said—  I have such a nice ex-taxi-cab driver<lb/>in the ward now, he is quite a friend of<lb/>mine, and does all sorts of jobs for<lb/>me. One queer little man who was shot<lb/>through the throat and can talk in nothing<lb/>but whispers, will call me nothing but “Phyllis”,    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3142_img_2560_3"/>
             I don't know why. He is like a little gnome<lb/>in a red coat and small brown cap and<lb/>is always squatting on the floor. Another<lb/>very young boy is so frightened of me and<lb/>the ear syringe that he always disappears<lb/>when it is his turn for treatment, and I<lb/>have to keep a very severe eye on him.<lb/>He had an operation for adenoids to-day<lb/>and for once was quiet and asleep when I<lb/>left. Another operation patient to-day who<lb/>is generally as quiet and good as anything<lb/>was very obstreperous coming round and tried<lb/>to get out of bed and swore like anything.<lb/>You never know how they will behave.  I liked the Somewhere in France poem<lb/>very much.Such an annoying thing happened<lb/>to your last enclosure. I got the letter<lb/>just when I was due on the ward, read<lb/>yours hastily and put the rest in my<lb/>apron pocket to read when I got home,<lb/> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3142_img_2560_4"/>
             I left with it in my pocket and must<lb/>have dropped it in the street, as I had lost<lb/>it when I got back, and could find it no<lb/>place though I hunted all round.  I am going to be rather a bother and<lb/>ask you to send me a rug, or a blanket<lb/>off my bed. I have two and an<lb/>under one here, but being a chilly person<lb/>I don't find it enough and would like<lb/>another for winter. I am afraid it<lb/>will be an awkward thing to send.<lb/>Please address to 5 Henderson Rd. and<lb/>not the hospital.  I got my travelling expenses last week,<lb/>rather a nice surprise, as I had almost<lb/>given them up, and I expect we will get<lb/>some washing money soon. Lately we have<lb/>been getting £1-13-4 a month, but we<lb/>expect to get more later.  Emma seems to be having a pretty hard<lb/>  D2109/9/4/B 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3142_img_2560_5"/>
             time at Alexandria, I wish we had been<lb/>nursing together.  Best love dear, I hope you are<lb/>keeping well, it will be a queer Christmas<lb/>for us all.  Yours ever  <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>