<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2876">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 6 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

This brief letter apologises for the delay between letters, and refers to the successes of the Ulster Division in comparison to the rest of the army.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/337</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2876</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2876_img_2288_1"  type="NULL"  url="64856da869fb34014a0c36765120f87a.JPG"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2876_img_2288_2"  type="NULL"  url="6af4a484e2c5c52b99aee981a7a27372.JPG"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2876_img_2288_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/337   6 July    My pr   I really cannot write<lb/>letters now tho' I have time,<lb/>I think you will understand.<lb/>You too, poor old thing will<lb/>also find it hard but I am<lb/>anxious to get one line to<lb/>say that you know I am safe<lb/>though so far. I'm afraid there<lb/>may have been 2 days gap<lb/>when I know the pr will have<lb/>had none too easy a time, but<lb/>hope it may have passed quickly<lb/>with all her work.  If you are with Edward<lb/>whe this letter arrives he<lb/>will be interested in the enclosed 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2876_img_2288_2"/>
             by Falls which tho' based largely<lb/>on what I told him, is very<lb/>much better than anything I<lb/>could write myself.  I have not seen the papers<lb/>today so do not know if<lb/>the Division has been given<lb/>- not its due for that is impossible<lb/>-but some  small  share of the praise<lb/>it has earned. I hear on many<lb/>sides that other troops recognise<lb/>that the Ulstermen did far the<lb/>best.  I wish John Gough was here<lb/>to see how true his appreciation<lb/>of these men really was.  The French man done much<lb/>better than the British up to date<lb/>but at 1/10th of the losses.  Don't overtax yourself win for<lb/>the sake of the Ulster brave; for their<lb/>(sa)kes keep yourself fit.  Your love W Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>