<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0224">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate English to Patrick English, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate English</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Kate English (b. 1855) to her son Patrick (1894-1970). Kate writes concerning parcels that she had sent to Patrick and mentions additional packages that she intends sending to him. She writes about what is happening in Dublin, mentioning Patrick&#39;s brother David and a young boarder in their home Laurence Godfrey. Kate continues that she is lonely at home and raises the possibility of house-keeping for David Shandl. The letter ends with Patrick&#39;s siblings sending their love.This letter was written by Kate to Patrick English while he was interned. Patrick had been stationed in the G.P.O for the Rising. Following the surrender he was sent to Stafford Prison before being moved to Frongoch internment camp in Wales. He had at least six cousins fighting with the British Army in France during his incarceration.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/224</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0077">Kate English</persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0099">Castleknock, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0224_img_1381_1"  type="Letter"  url="406891376f43a53ed331e29d84141609.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0224_img_1381_2"  type="Letter"  url="11f487986cffa2a45be6a60ec09023a7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0224_img_1381_3"  type="Letter"  url="0eaf986835073af8576aa82278a7ee56.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0224_img_1381_1"/>
                   Castle Knock.    3.6.16   My Dear Patrick   I received your <lb/>ever welcome letter glad to <lb/> hear you are going on well. <lb/> I am glad to hear you <sic>recieved</sic><lb/> the parcel alright. I have <lb/> sent you on another parcel <lb/> which contains cake. 3 packets <lb/> of <sic>ciggarettes</sic>. prayer book. pencil. <lb/>handkerchief. note paper. &amp; 3 <lb/> stamps. let me know in your <lb/> next letter if your <sic>recieved</sic><lb/> them <sic>allright</sic>. Davie told  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0224_img_1381_2"/>
              <lb/>mother that he wrote to you <lb/> I recieved a P.C. from Sister <lb/> Vincent and she said you <lb/> were all right. For myself <lb/> I am keeping splendid <lb/> the only thing that upsets <lb/> me is the <sic>loniless</sic> here at <lb/> night .It is such a lonely <lb/> place I am thinking strongly <lb/> of giving up the place and <lb/> going over to live with David <lb/> Shandley. he has me tormented <lb/>to go over so dont be surprised <lb/> if <seg type="del">I</seg>you hear of me going <lb/> over to him I still have <lb/><sic>Lawerence</sic> with me he <lb/> is not a bad chap at all.<cb/><lb/>I am <sic>shure</sic> you are a <lb/> splendid Laundress I would <lb/> have to scream laughing <lb/> If I saw you washing your <lb/> shirt I am shure it comes <lb/> strange to you.  Let me know when you are <lb/> writing again what would <lb/>you think of me giving up <lb/> the place and going over to <lb/> housekeep for Davie Shandly <lb/> I would like to have your <lb/>opinion on it what would <lb/> be the best to do he has <lb/> plenty of room over <lb/> there. how are you keeping  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0224_img_1381_3"/>
              <lb/>yourself I hope you are <lb/> keeping up your poor old <lb/> heart and not fretting to <lb/> much about me as I will <lb/> be all right. Katie. Nellie. <lb/>Jamesy. &amp; all the rest join <lb/> in sending their every best <lb/> love to you and trust in <lb/> God to meet soon again. <lb/> Good - Bye &amp; God Bless you. <seg type="closer"> I remain Dear Patrick. <lb/>Your Ever Loving Mother  Mrs <hi rend="underline">K. English.</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>