<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4333">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles F. Down to Edward Carson, 28 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles F. Down</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles. F Down to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/31</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4333</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0090">Charles F. Down</persName>
              <date>1916-06-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1925">Culloden, Craigavad, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4333_img_3692_1"  type="Letter"  url="d3dd573c47b4011187e0e832f2a8c1e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4333_img_3692_2"  type="Letter"  url="ef20f2cc61b0e50cef8c7a1ca6fe03de.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4333_img_3692_1"/>
             STATION, CULTRA. <lb/>TELEGRAMS, CRAIGAVAD. <lb/>TELEPHONE, CRAIGAVAD, 18.   <hi rend="underline">Confidential</hi>   CULLODEN, <lb/>CRAIGAVAD, <lb/>CO. DOWN.   June 28.1916    My dear Sir Edward   With reference to the resolution <lb/>passed by the Irish Church Bishops, <lb/>I think, you ought to know some <lb/>of the circumstances. I was <lb/>not at the meeting, as by reason <lb/>of my engagements The summons <lb/>did not reach me in Time ,— it <lb/>was hastily summoned — but I know <lb/>what happened.   Most of our Bishops are of <lb/>the other three Provinces, &amp; they, like <lb/>other Southern Unionists, feel aggrieved <lb/>at the revival of The Home Rule <lb/>question during the war. Also, it <lb/>must be confessed, most of them <lb/>do not like the exclusion of Ulster. <lb/> They were determined to pass a <lb/>resolution &amp; it was clear that, <lb/>being a majority, they could pass <lb/>any resolution they pleased.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4333_img_3692_2"/>
            It was due to the very strong <lb/>influence of the Primate that <lb/>the resolution passed took <lb/>the shape it did, &amp; not one <lb/>which would have been <lb/>much more unfavourable to <lb/>the proposed settlement.   As regards the exclusion <lb/>of Ulster, if the settlement goes <lb/>through, it will certainly — in my <lb/> opinion — receive the support of <lb/>the Bishops in the excluded area. <lb/>The Primate, the Bishop of Derry, <lb/>&amp; myself, are those specially <lb/>affected ; &amp; I know you <lb/>can rely on our support.   I write on my own responsibility <lb/><hi rend="underline">entirely</hi> &amp; without consultation <lb/>with any other Bishop. But I think <lb/>You ought to know the position.   Yours very faithfully   <hi rend="underline">Charles F. Down</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>