<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3102">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eamonn T. Dore to James Ryan, c. September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eamonn T. Dore</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.
Eamon Dore was a member of the Irish Volunteers and served as a bodyguard to Sean MacDiarmada. one of the leaders of the Rising. He was subsequently imprisoned in Frongach internment camp.
In the letter Dore asks Ryan, who had already been released from Frongach, about family and friends at home and also refers to some of his fellow prisoners.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/36/3-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3102</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0295">Eamonn T. Dore</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1879">Frongach internment camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3102_img_251_1"  type="Letter"  url="22c54a24327bdda7e7bad7ffd62760bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3102_img_251_2"  type="Letter"  url="11a3abd86a4030cd64720f61756486dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3102_img_251_1"/>
            <name>Eamonn T Dore</name> 1704,   The Internment Camp,    Frongoch,<lb/>Near Bala,<lb/>Wales <lb/><lb/> Saturday <lb/><lb/> My dear Jim,   Received yours on yesterday<lb/>and was delighted to hear your intended<lb/>mending your ways. Of course I know<lb/>it will take some exertion but even so<lb/>if you intend getting quallified in March<lb/>you had better start and lead a good<lb/>life. I am very much afraid your present<lb/>company will corrupt you. Nevertheless<lb/>when you are down and out think of<lb/>the correct life we lead in town last year.  Tell Roisin I was very sorry to<lb/>hear she was ill. I hope she be on the<lb/><seg type="del">on</seg> way to recovery before this reaches<lb/>Dublin. Do the two little Paddys <seg type="del">kno</seg><lb/>knock around as usual? How did Mul.<lb/>get on at the March exam? Joe Murray<lb/>will be a dab at Anatomy soon. George's<lb/>hair is getting on fine. The gum right enough   a open about my writing<lb/>there. Goodbye old man<lb/>for a few more weeks.<lb/>F.Shouldice wishes to be<lb/>remembered to you.<lb/> Yrs. Eamonn <lb/> P.S.Liam O'B. got<lb/>your letter. <lb/>  Eamonn.   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3102_img_251_2"/>
             stopped its growth for a while. He is no <lb/> longer like Jack Johnson. Who is that <lb/> young lady that said she would ask fo <lb/> Eddie Dore when she came to Frongoch? It <lb/> is not right to keep a fellow in suspense.   Tell that young lady you saw with me <lb/> at the top of Grafton Street I enquired <lb/> for her. I must confess I do not know <lb/> who you mean. I am sending this <seg type="del">tho</seg> <lb/> through the Camp Censor so I want it to <lb/> go direct fearing you would send on <lb/> that Halliburton. You need not send <lb/> it as I got one from home some time <lb/> ago. Tell Mul. the Cunninghams arrived <lb/> alright. Any chance of "Mahon's Notes".   All the boys are in the pink. Liam <lb/> O'B. wrote to Maureen and was surpris— <lb/>ed to hear his letter did not arrive in <lb/> Ballyshannon. Do not forget to tell her <lb/> he wrote. Seán Neeson and Morkan <lb/> and some others left for Reading on <lb/> yesterday. When writing to Seán T. tell <lb/> him I enquired particularly for him. <lb/> Remember me to all the old crowd. <lb/> Hope all yours <seg type="del"> </seg>are as well as <lb/> I would wish them to be. Do not <lb/> forget to tell Roisin what I said. I met <lb/> her a few times. I will write to the Convent <lb/> of Mercy in a few days. You need not kick up  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>