<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0296">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mary O'Nolan to Alice Stopford Green, 25 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mary O&#39;Nolan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Mary O&#39;Nolan, address 5 Warwick Terrace, Leeson Park, Dublin to Alice Stopford Green, (1847-1929), historian, nationalist and friend of Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). Mary O&#39;Nolan is busily campaigning for Roger Casement, attempting to have his death sentence commuted. Casement had been arrested on Banna Strand on the eve of the Easter Rising and tried for treason. She mentions the king, the US government, John Redmond and Colonel Moore in Buswells Hotel.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, 13,088/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/296</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0373">Mary O&#39;Nolan</persName>
              <date>1916-07-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1500">5 Warwick Terrace, Leeson Park, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0296_img_1513_1"  type="Letter"  url="455f05cd31e926fa8e9c23536de3fbb5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0296_img_1513_2"  type="Letter"  url="a67b1432845ad739ee0495a36aa304ae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0296_img_1513_3"  type="Letter"  url="ad4f99d69f9cf3902bcb41b42401dc3d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0296_img_1513_4"  type="Letter"  url="6eddab739e7b4fde06a7bdc8a32c32ea.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0296_img_1513_1"/>
                5 Warwick Terrace Leeson Park  Dublin    25th July   Dear Mrs. Green   We are shocked to see the date fixed for <lb/>the execution. Still we do not give up hope, <lb/>&amp; are working still hard for reprieve. <lb/>I enclose copy of letter sent by <lb/>our Reprieve Com. to the King today. <lb/>Also copy of cablegram to Botha. <lb/>Could you also petition King to <lb/>exercise prerogative of mercy, <lb/>&amp; could you get at Botha &amp; <lb/>other Colonial premiers? Is U.S. Government <lb/> doing nothing? I see mass <lb/>petitions are being sent in by <lb/>A.O.H. &amp; other Irish American bodies, <lb/>but will the U.S. Government   move? <lb/>These horrible slanders on our <lb/> friend have injured our prospects <lb/>of success. Unhappily many  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0296_img_1513_2"/>
              <lb/>who do not know him personally believe <lb/>them. Time will indicate his <lb/>character without doubt, but it is of <lb/>urgent importance that the <lb/>vindication should be immediate, <lb/> if possible. I wrote to Mr. Gavan <lb/>Duffy asking if you or he would <lb/>write to the Times on this subject.   Will you do so? And would anyone <lb/>else whose word carries weight <lb/>do so? We sent another batch of <lb/>signed petitions to-day to Prime <lb/>Minister - the <seg type="unclear">third batch</seg>, containing <lb/>many influential signatures <lb/>&amp; we will continue sending in <lb/>petitions till we hear the matter <lb/>is finally settled — numbers <lb/>of these petitions are being <lb/>circulated through the country <lb/>&amp; are being <seg type="unclear">extensively</seg> signed, <lb/>Miss <seg type="unclear">French Mullen</seg> who is in <lb/>charge of our petition is crossing <lb/>tonight to London with a big  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0296_img_1513_3"/>
              <lb/>batch of signed petitions. She has <lb/>been working on more democratic <lb/>lines than our Com. went on, <lb/>&amp; it has got on easier. We only <lb/> asked people of position at first; <lb/>then we got out a second kind of <lb/>petition which we are sending <lb/><seg type="unclear">broad cast</seg> to less important people — <lb/>the Lord Mayor &amp; 28 members <lb/>of Dublin Corporation have <lb/> signed. Col. Moore has written press— <lb/>ingly to John Redmond on the <lb/>subject, &amp; is going to Ed. Freeman <lb/> tonight to urge him to deal editor— <lb/>ially with matter, as well as to publish <lb/>letters from him. I am going to Ed. Independent. <lb/> If you are writing please reply <lb/>to Col. Moore - Buswell's Hotel. He &amp; <lb/> I are doing the correspondence <lb/> between us — but I'll be absent from <lb/> Dublin from 27th to 30th  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0296_img_1513_4"/>
              Hoping most earnestly our united <lb/>efforts will be crowned with success. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely <lb/> Mary O'Nolan </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>