<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1175">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 28 November 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the death of Father Fitzgibbon. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/36, IJA/CHPI/54/36</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1175</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-11-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1175_img_3852_1"  type="Letter"  url="13c1b2792b71c172bc48f0a1edfd62ee.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1175_img_3852_1"/>
                Mesopotamia    28 Nov. 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   Seventeen Masses for Father Farley during November.  I can hardly believe that Father Fitzgibbon has been killed. He certainly made the best <lb/>of the time given him. Five chaplains, F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi><lb/>O'Sullivan, F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Dan Roche, f<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>Frank Browne, F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi><lb/>Fitzgibbon, and myself got our appointments in <lb/>France on the same day, and we made a promise <lb/>to remember one another always at Mass. F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi><lb/>O'Sullivan and Fitzgibbon are now in the <lb/>Memento for the dead.  There is no talk yet of leaving this country, <lb/>but I imagine they will try to get us away <lb/>before next hot weather, which begins in <lb/>June, and is worst in July and august. It <lb/>won't be my fault if I am delayed in my return. <lb/>Your Reverence's cablegram was very welcome, <lb/>and may keep on things a bit.  It will be very interesting to follow the discussions, <lb/>if they are made public, which will begin when the <lb/>cleverest rogues of the world meet at the great <lb/>Peace Conference.  I recommend myself to the prayers of all. <seg type="closer"> Yours in Christ,  Francis M Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>