<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2737">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to Sara Montgomery, 23 December, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2737</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0922">William Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1915-12-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sara Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2095">Monacherra, Malone Park,Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2737_img_2157_1"  type="Letter"  url="552dfe7f8f1e06d75d64ec9a762f4388.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2737_img_2157_2"  type="Letter"  url="a04dd48715ef9bbda0afb974c067022a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2737_img_2157_3"  type="Envelope"  url="a7432cb4ec5c05043a4de4789e411414.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2737_img_2157_1"/>
             23/2/1915   Dear Montgomery,   You know that there is a<lb/> lot of important work to be done before we come<lb/> out this time, &amp; you know how handicapped I<lb/> am without Haigh; I am going back for a<lb/> <seg type="unclear">lesson</seg>is to let Sinclair take "a" till we <lb/> get back to <seg type="unclear">Fucerrile</seg> after <seg type="del">his</seg> your boy is<lb/> Released by C tomorrow &amp; <seg type="unclear">you've</seg> to tackle new <lb/> direction of working <seg type="unclear">parties</seg>, in <seg type="unclear">your</seg> own way &amp;<seg type="unclear">your</seg><lb/> own time I'm wont a etc Redeem etc. I know <lb/> that you have already had a hell of a time, but <lb/> I am sure that if you direct the work <seg type="unclear">every</seg> <lb/> energy would be saved; at the same time <lb/> you can by delegating jobs to <seg type="unclear">others</seg> get some<lb/> <seg type="unclear">sleep</seg>; when you are in C day <seg type="unclear">out</seg>. <lb/> Will this end in views I am <seg type="unclear">Telling</seg> C &amp; D to <lb/> let you know by 6 AM what news you can have <lb/> In work, <seg type="del">time its</seg> in the care of C til they <lb/> Relieve you in the care of D till they relieve B.<lb/> After that C can tell you what they can give <lb/> you daily and B as well also A <lb/> the General expects a lot, but this is a penalty<lb/>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2737_img_2157_2"/>
            We pay for a good Reputation, but I am <lb/>sure that in your hands the Reputation we <lb/>have for    can be well maintained. <lb/>I am telling B to lend C 2 offers you wish <lb/>in trenches generally, as they <seg type="unclear">have had good</seg> <lb/>dug outs.   The more the men work the sector they remain <lb/>I am sure.   Yours  <lb/>Wm M 1am  22/23x11   A party of INCO &amp; 12 men S Lancs are <lb/>to report HQ at 5pm till   when <lb/>you want them sent. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2737_img_2157_3"/>
             Replied  23 January 1916    Mrs HH Montgomery <lb/>Monacherra <lb/>Malone Road <lb/>Belfast 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>