<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0805">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 25 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender worries that Lillian has overburdened herself with work, threatening to write to her employer and have her sacked if she does not take a holiday promptly. He mentions that his promotion has not yet been announced in the Gazette, and notes that they will both it will be extremely embarrassing if he is returned to the rank of Captain. He writes that he has resubmitted his dispatch, of which he is proud. Spender recounts a visit from &#39;Crichton&#39;, a King&#39;s Messenger and the brother of the late 4th Earl Erne, whose identity Spender did not realise until the visit had ended. He mentions that he has several times been startled by somebody whistling a familiar tune in the middle of the night, and speculates on the whistler&#39;s identity. Finally, he wonders how the dispatch he is writing can &#39;deal with a fortnight&#39;s almost uninterrupted failures at the end of July&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/397</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/805</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0805_img_2347_1"  type="NULL"  url="aca921a7f017a6f3c7b0aab185925fd5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0805_img_2347_2"  type="NULL"  url="c4a444ab2f97803b39724cfc002ada08.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0805_img_2347_3"  type="NULL"  url="82fedb18b692992de18ff0614722d39a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0805_img_2347_4"  type="NULL"  url="89709e5f83b8ff08ba4cde5e8db5aa8a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0805_img_2347_5"  type="NULL"  url="b97a6a4a06c35dc5d948b7d0b96ee557.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0805_img_2347_6"  type="NULL"  url="d5b19abc1b89ad6a2a366133f57d6438.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0805_img_2347_1"/>
                August 25th <seg type="del">July</seg>   My pr   Got your letter of 22nd this evening <hi rend="superscript">24th</hi> . No <lb/> old thing it won't do. If you aren't feeling better <lb/> when you get this &amp; tell me so I shall write to <lb/>Lady R &amp; tell her she must get someone to <lb/> take on from the first week in September.  I have written to <seg type="unclear">Rex</seg> and told him <seg type="unclear">Jin</seg><lb/>will manage <seg type="del">your</seg> his parcels and we will settle <lb/> up with her.  In your next letter tell me how you stand <lb/>in regard to our business and do no more. I <lb/>can arrange nearly everything with Maguire <lb/>from here. <seg type="unclear">The lending</seg> to the Government is <lb/>rather urgent though as I believe it has to be done  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0805_img_2347_2"/>
              by the 1 Sept so I enclose a letter to Mr <lb/>Maguire for you to forward if you have not <lb/>already <seg type="del">done</seg> written.  But the first thing is your holiday <lb/>&amp; I tell you flat I shall write to Ruby <lb/>&amp; have you sacked if you are not very <lb/>good! I am thinking of asking Jessie to <lb/> vet you but hitherto I have been able to <lb/> trust my pr to tell me the truth of how <lb/>she feels and so won't take extreme measures yet.  As for your holiday you need not go <lb/>on economical lines this time as I want it <lb/>to be a real holiday.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0805_img_2347_3"/>
              I haven't yet appeared in the Gazette â an <lb/>unusually long wait! Supposing I am sent <lb/>back to Capt again what a bw and pr we shall be <lb/> it will be a case of pppr! I hope my exalted <lb/>encomium â shan't talk of pay now! â begins <lb/> from the date of my duties, an extra 9/- a day <lb/>I believe I get which ought to pay for a <lb/> pr's chocolate even on a holiday!  I resubmitted the dispatch 19 May to <lb/>16 July to K today but I shall not hear what <lb/>he thinks for a day or two, &amp; shall be very <lb/>depressed in consequence I expect for I really <lb/> have tried hard, &amp; only want a pr to make <lb/> it quite a success. I wish I could take it home  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0805_img_2347_4"/>
              on leave and do it there tho' I see  there would be  difficulties <lb/>about maps, of which I have several square <lb/>yards for each day of the month to look <lb/>at!   Yesterday someone came in for a <seg type="unclear">break</seg><lb/>said he came from Fermanagh talked of gun <lb/> running, and Fermanagh but I could not place <lb/>him even when he said something which showed <lb/>his brother had died &amp; been a peer. Very interesting <lb/>it was but I wish I had known before he left <lb/>that it was Crichton â who is now a King's <lb/>messenger and whom I hope to see out here <lb/>again.  Several times at night I have been <lb/>startled by someone who whistles some of <lb/> my special tunes â Autumn the apple blossom  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0805_img_2347_5"/>
              <lb/>and the dirge of <lb/><seg type="unclear">Colquoolan</seg> (??) you <lb/> will love my spelling <lb/>of this! I expect it <lb/>must be one of the <lb/>Artists rifles who form <lb/>the body guard here <lb/>a safe but not very <lb/>glorious role.  I wish K would <lb/>let me know what <lb/>he thinks of the dispatch <lb/>up to date. I must <lb/>go and see him tomorrow <lb/>to know how I am to  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0805_img_2347_6"/>
              <lb/>deal with a fortnights <lb/>almost uninterrupted <lb/>failures at the end <lb/> of July! Things are <lb/>better again now, &amp; will <lb/> be easier but not <lb/>the intermediate period.  I don't want long <lb/>letters now old thing <lb/>nor to give you anymore <lb/>business. Please look <lb/>after yourself as your <lb/>payment of the many <lb/>good marks you owe <lb/> â you say â to your <lb/> <seg type="closer"> bw.<lb/>WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>