<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6713">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Michael Flanagan to Canon Doorley, 9 December 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr Michael O&#39;Flanagan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Fr Michael O&#39;Flanagan (1876-1942) was a Catholic priest, republican activist, and president of Sinn Féin from October 1917. Canon Doorley had written to complain that Fr. O’Flanagan did not account for funding from Cliffoney parish. Fr. O’Flanagan wondering if he was referring to £27.6.8. that was in Hibernan Bank in joint names of Frs. Shannon, Keane and Clancy. The deposit receipt was lost. Or in the Cliffoney cheque account in joint names of Bishop and Fr. Shannon and Fr. O’Flanagan, which bishop has. He was now forwarding up to date statement. There were no cheques drawn in his time. There was a question of a ball court being erected but in the meantime Fr. O’Reilly changed to another parish. £13.13.6. was collected for the Irish Volunteers which was  given to them for equipment purchased.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O&#39;Flanagan Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6713</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0313">Fr Michael O&#39;Flanagan</persName>
              <date>1916-12-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0514">Crosna, Boyle, Co. Roscommon.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Canon Doorly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1385">St. Mary's, Co. Sligo</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1942</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6713_img_None_1"  url="php5PrqFG.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6713_img_None_2"  url="phpm38Psz.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6713_img_None_3"  url="phpPOYQiW.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6713_img_None_4"  url="phpUo1GmW.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6713_img_0_1"/>
              Croena <lb/> Boyle <lb/> Dec 9th 1916.    My dear Canon Doorly   I had a letter<lb/>from Dr. Coyne a few days ago<lb/>telling me that you informed<lb/>him that I had some Cliffoney<lb/>Parish Funds that I had not<lb/>handed over to you.  There is only one thing that<lb/>I know that you can refer to.  A sum of £27-4-8 was<lb/>held in the Hibernian Bank<lb/>in the joint names of Father<lb/>Shannon Father Michael Keane<lb/>and Mr Bernard Clancy. This<lb/>deposit receipt was lost or<lb/>mislaid. In Dec. 1914 I got<lb/>the three named, to sign an<lb/>indemnity form for the amount 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6713_img_0_2"/>
             The Cliffoney Church Account<lb/>is in the joint names of the<lb/>Bishop Father Shannon and<lb/>myself. The Bishop retained<lb/>posseion of Bank Book and<lb/>Cheque Book. As this account is,<lb/>as I understand, overdrawn,<lb/>it can be transferred without<lb/>consulting me. You will remember<lb/>that I spoke to you about it last<lb/>Summer, but at the time you did<lb/>not wish to assume liability for<lb/>it. Until you were prepared to do<lb/>so, I did not feel called upon to<lb/>make any other returns to you. I<lb/>now send you a statement of<lb/>Cash Transactions up to the time<lb/>I left Cliffoney. No Cheques were<lb/>drawn upon the Bank Account<lb/>during my time, but two deposits<lb/>were made amounting to £84-13-9.<lb/>There are two bills to be paid, one for<lb/>£5-8-11 to Mr. D. Hanly of Sligo, and<lb/>the balance shown £5-11-5 to me. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6713_img_0_3"/>
             and Mr. McCaffrey issued a<lb/>new deposit receipt in the<lb/>names of Father Shannon<lb/>Mr. Clancy and myself. The<lb/>interest accruing at the<lb/>time was £2-14-7, making<lb/>when added to the principal<lb/>a sum of £29-19-3.  Father Keane told me that<lb/>this money was collected by<lb/>Father O'Reilly for the purpose<lb/>of building a ball court. Before<lb/>the ball court could be erected<lb/>Father O'Reilly was charged,<lb/>and so the matter has not<lb/>been attended to ever since.  At the time that I got this<lb/>money I had on hand a sum<lb/>of £13-13-6 collected for the<lb/>Volunteers. Not wishing to<lb/>have too many separate deposits<lb/>in the Bank, I put in this  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6713_img_0_4"/>
             last named sum alone with<lb/>the other, and so the new<lb/>deposit receipt dated Jan 9th<lb/>1915 was made out for the<lb/>sum of £43-12-9.  Afterwards the Volunteers<lb/>called upon me for the £13-13-6<lb/>to pay for equipment which<lb/>they had purchased. I knew<lb/>if I sent the receipt to<lb/>Father Shannon for signature,<lb/>that it would lie in danger<lb/>of being lost like the other<lb/>one, and so I was unable to<lb/>get the money at the time. Now<lb/>I hope to get the Bank to transfer<lb/>the money without Father Sahnnon's<lb/>signature, when I shall be<lb/>happy to turn over the £29-19-3<lb/>and interest, to you and Mr<lb/>Clancy, and any one else that<lb/>you may name. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>