<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1069">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Heyward to the Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 10 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Heyward</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Henry Heyward (1852-1934) to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) applying to be added to the membership list of the RCPI. Enclosed with the letter are a recommendation and the necessary certificates.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T87, RCPI-2-3-1-58-T87</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1069</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0256">Henry Heyward</persName>
              <date>1916-08-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0230">Castlemaine Avenue, Croydon, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1069_img_3207_1"  type="Letter"  url="697e38ea4a00890b4eec4da18bd8bfa9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1069_img_3207_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="1d215efe7070ab70d92caa1afddd267c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1069_img_3207_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="6568f1da931769876472055c2079bc21.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1069_img_3207_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="f4aecae855ed415af8758019a134b4dd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1069_img_3207_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="e7e8167d76837def6f3324c9fd92218f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1069_img_3207_1"/>
                August10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    Eversholt,  Castlemaine Avenue,  Croydon.   Dear Sir,   I am writing to ask that my <lb/>name may be added to the Membership list <lb/>of the Royal College of Physicians Dublin <lb/>and herewith enclose the certificates it is <lb/>necessary for me to forward including <lb/>one as to professional and moral character <lb/>from D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> F. Wethered Fellow of the Royal <lb/>College of Physicians, London. <seg type="closer"> I remain, <lb/>Yours truly,  Henry Heyward.   The Registrar,  Royal College of Physicians  Ireland.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1069_img_3207_2"/>
                83, HARLEY STREET. W.    July 26:/16.    I have great pleasure <lb/>in testifying to the <lb/>professional conduct <lb/>&amp; moral character <lb/>of D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Henry Heyward <lb/>whom I have known <lb/>for many years. <seg type="closer"> Frank J. Wethered. <lb/>Fellow of the College. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1069_img_3207_3"/>
              I hereby declare that I am not engaged in <lb/>trade; that I do not dispense medicine <lb/>or make any engagement with a chemist <lb/>or any other person for the supply of <lb/>medicines and that I do not practice <lb/>Medicine or Surgery in partnership by <lb/>deed or otherwise. <seg type="closer"> Henry Heyward    Eversholt,  Castlemaine Avenue,  Croydon.    July 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916  </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1069_img_3207_4"/>
              XXIV.  Declaration. Every Candidate, before being enrolled a Mem— <lb/>ber of the College, shall subscribe the following <lb/>Declaration in the presence of the President and <lb/>Fellows :—  'I do hereby solemnly and sincerely promise that I <lb/>will observe and obey the Statutes, ;By—Laws, and Regula— <lb/>tions of this College, relating to Members, and will submit <lb/>to such penalties as may be lawfully imposed for any <lb/>neglect or infringement of them.  'I further promise and declare that I will, to the <lb/>best of my ability, do all things in the practice of my <lb/>Profession for the homour of the College and the gooad of <lb/>the Public.  'I hereby authorise the President and Fellows of <lb/>the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to erase <lb/>my name from the List of Members, and I consent <lb/>to surrender the Diploma received from the College, if I <lb/>shall, after having obtained the Membership, engage in <lb/>trade, or if I shall dispense Medicine, or make any <lb/>engagement with a Chemist or other person for the <lb/>supply of Medicines, or if I shall practise Medicine or <lb/>Surgery in partnership, by deed or otherwise.' <seg type="closer"> Henry Heyward </seg> Declared at Folkes lane <lb/>in the county of Kent this <lb/>10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day of August 1916 <lb/>Before me <lb/><hi rend="underline">Gantrill</hi><lb/>A Commissioner for Oaths.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1069_img_3207_5"/>
              Each Paper shall be set, and the answers thereto <lb/>be examined, conjointly, by two Examiners. Each <lb/>Paper shall consist of six questions.  There shall be Three hours given for answering <lb/>each Paper — three hours in the forenoon, and three <lb/>in the afternoon, of the first day's Examination.  2. The Clinical Examination shall be conducted <lb/>in one of the Metropolitan Clinical Hospitals in the <lb/>forenoon of the second day, the Candidates being <lb/>informed of the Hospital a short time before the <lb/>hour of Examination. This portion of the Exami— <lb/>nation shall be conducted by two Examiners other <lb/>than those who set the Papers.  3. The Oral Examinations shall be conducted, in <lb/>the afternoon of the second day, by the four Exami— <lb/>ners who set the Papers; the subjects of Examina— <lb/>tion to be the same as those dealt with in the Paper <lb/>Examination; it shall also include the investiga— <lb/>tion of morbid specimens; the qualitative analysis of <lb/>animal products; the detection of poisons; and the <lb/>use of the microscope.  XXII.  Candidates who have successfully passed the <lb/>Examination for the Membership will be required <lb/>to attend at the College on the Friday following, to <lb/>subscribe the Declaration in the presence of the <lb/>College, and to sign the Roll of Members.  XXIII.  If the Examiners be not satisfied with the <lb/>answering of a Candidate, the College may admit <lb/>him to re—examination at the next quarterly <lb/>Examination.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>