<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2654">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maria Duffin to Celia Duffin, 19 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

Celia Duffin was a VAD with the 3rd London General Hospital in Wandsworth which opened in 1914. She was an accomplished poet, publishing, amongst other volumes, a book of poetry with her sister Ruth.

This is a letter from mother to daughter in which she gives all the news from home. She has news of a death, an engagement and a military promotion and she tells of various people she has met or visited recently and of illnesses. She writes about a bureau she has recently acquired.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2654</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2654_img_2079_1"  type="Letter"  url="97db6334e3482437977e9ce413d03143.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2654_img_2079_2"  type="Letter"  url="6cbd12f11cd91172779d5b4e8a6441b2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2654_img_2079_3"  type="Letter"  url="ea322a35706776bb1e272dc41234865f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2654_img_2079_4"  type="Letter"  url="9d5cf1fb74a39d69de734912155e21a3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2654_img_2079_5"  type="Letter"  url="66dd4a74fcd77cea6097d7ed605f63ae.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2654_img_2079_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/C   DUNOWEN,<lb/>BELFAST.    March 19'1916.    My dearest Celia.   This week is a<lb/>blank as to anything doing<lb/>and, I suppose, you will<lb/>soon get a sight of Dorothy<lb/>who crossed by   on<lb/>Friday night, en route for<lb/>the Garretts' as Hilda had<lb/>been in contact with Measles<lb/>and she thought it better<lb/>to take <seg type="unclear">Andrews</seg> first, in<lb/>case of complications.   Ruth came yesterday, but<lb/>may have to join Marjorie<lb/>tomorrow as Sam &amp; Iva go and<lb/>Charlie is at Aldershot. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2654_img_2079_2"/>
             She is lunching with Dora today. <lb/>I saw poor old Mrs Riddel <lb/>on Monday. a perfect wreck. <lb/>So much worse. than on the <lb/>day of the funeral. I really <lb/><hi rend="underline">could </hi> not leave them if I <lb/>were Marjorie. I think she <lb/>has made no plans yet, but <lb/>may, after she has seen Charlie. <lb/>He is wanted over. for some <lb/>arrangements. Aunt Margaret <lb/>has left him the big car and <lb/>I suppose there are other things. <lb/>However, these is no need to <lb/>move anything at present.    Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Leviney had an <lb/>operation yesterday for a <lb/>tumour and appendicitis. <lb/>I am anxious to hear about <lb/>her. Such an unfortunate time. <lb/>We have had M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Garrett <lb/>Campbell and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Poliyard <lb/>and reveal much letters. <lb/>A very nice one from Mayor <lb/>Boylan Smith.   I am glad you had your day <lb/>at Eastbourne. Olive would be <lb/>glad to see you.   My bureau has arrived. It is not <lb/>an "antique" as I had fancied <lb/>but is quite nice. We have <lb/>put the sofa into the hollow <lb/> of the piano, at Smyth's suggestion <lb/>and. I think it is a great <lb/>improvement.   I am glad the verses arrived <lb/>safely. I will pay for them <lb/>the next time I am that <lb/>way. They were to fund <lb/>out postage. I sent you a <lb/>currant loaf, but, in future
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2654_img_2079_3"/>
             I think a postal order to buy <lb/>one will be better, the postage <lb/>mounts up beyond its worth. <lb/>Shall I send some more soup <lb/>and what is the best?   Yesterday. I did a little "forking <lb/>up" in the garden. but today <lb/>it is raining again.   Old M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> "P" Davidson is dead <lb/>and was quite queer for <lb/>some time before. I have heard <lb/>nothing of Willie Ewing, but <lb/>must go and see Minnie <lb/>this week, now that she is <lb/>alone.   Aunt Charlotte is still in <lb/>Craig's hands about her ears <lb/>and Ruth still complains <lb/>of "ringing" while my ears <lb/>are much the same alas!   Why do complaints seem to
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2654_img_2079_4"/>
             DUNOWEN,<lb/>BELFAST.  come in batches?  Peter is very good. except when<lb/>he goes <seg type="foreign">fautee</seg>. He keeps me<lb/>very nervous about the kittens<lb/>One of them is a darling.  Elsie<seg type="unclear"> Kingan's</seg> engagement<lb/>is announced and Captain<lb/>Dane is now a Brigadier General!<lb/>I had tea with M<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rs</hi></hi> Lindan<lb/>on Sunday; we are very great<lb/>now. I hear Effie is at<lb/>Hoylalne with a Miss Rogers<lb/>and a nurse and writing<lb/>quite cheerfully. I believe Ben<lb/>is much better also and<lb/>that they like Carneoure.<lb/>I have paid no country 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2654_img_2079_5"/>
             visits yet, but must soon, <lb/>if the weather improves.   No letter from Emma or Jerry <lb/>this week. I suppose she is <lb/>staying on. I hear Emmie <lb/>Eggan is likely to go to the <lb/>Hills, it is thought too dangerous <lb/>to return. Colonel Buchanan <lb/>brought his wife and little <lb/>girl here last Sunday. She <lb/>was a Miss Harland and is <lb/>still very nice looking. She <lb/> looks much younger than he <lb/>does.   Now. goodbye darling: <lb/>Much love   Your ever loving <lb/>Mammy 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>