<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1362">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lord Wimborne to Sir John Maxwell, 1 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ivor Churchill Guest</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939) to Sir John Grenfell Maxwell (1859-1929). The letter was written after the suppression of the Easter Rising and two days before the first executions of the leaders. Wimborne praises the steps taken by Maxwell to restore &#39;normal conditions&#39; and hopes that they will not be opposed by the &#39;authorities&#39;. He also requests a meeting with Maxwell and some of his staff when things have settled down and expresses regret that Maxwell has experienced &#39;serious domestic trouble&#39;. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918. Sir John Henry Grenfell Maxwell was appointed commander in chief of the British forces in Ireland after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. Before 1916, Maxwell briefly held command of British troops in Egypt, where he successfully organised defences against a Turkish attack in February 1915 and presided over the huge expansion of his command as Egypt became a major British imperial military base. In March 1916, having been superseded as general officer commanding in Egypt, he was recalled home when the Easter Rising broke out.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera papers, P150/512</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1362</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date>1916-05-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1362_img_714_1"  type="Letter"  url="d3caf0dde8c5bf9748ce5d6ff27e1e44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1362_img_714_2"  type="Letter"  url="12eb3e8539b49a3e460af96136f14daa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1362_img_714_3"  type="Letter"  url="8a43d5c573afad01fc25230125633edb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1362_img_714_4"  type="Letter"  url="b68e9165f5fc2e0e1f7f9c9d687da14b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1362_img_714_1"/>
                May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, 1916   Dear Sir John Maxwell,   I add a private note <lb/> of congratulations and relief <lb/> that it is over.  I note all the steps you are <lb/> taking to restore normal <lb/> conditions which seem <lb/>to me if I may say so  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1362_img_714_2"/>
              admirably conceived  I appreciate and <lb/> applaud your intention <lb/> to recommend an alleviative <lb/> expiation in active service <lb/> in quiet districts.  I indicated this intention <lb/> of yours to the Prime  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1362_img_714_3"/>
              <lb/>Minister last night and <lb/> hope that it will not <lb/> be opposed by the authorities.  When we are a little <lb/> more settled down <lb/> His Excellency and <lb/> myself hope to see you <lb/> here and meet other <lb/> members of your staff  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1362_img_714_4"/>
              I much regret to hear that <lb/> in the midst of all these <lb/> anxieties you have had <lb/> serious domestic trouble <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/>Yours sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Wimborne</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>