<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3868">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 20 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane (1861-1934) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding an enquiry into the death of Hannah&#39;s husband, Francis Sheehy Skeffington. According to Vane the Prime Minister has reiterated his commitment to a public enquiry but Vane would prefer a royal commission over an enquiry. Along with the letter Vane sends Skeffington a copy of Pax Britannica in an attempt to offer her comfort. Before signing off Vane outlines his conduct in the matter and requests that she makes his position clear in any interviews she may give as he believes his case greatly strengthens hers.

Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane was a British officer in command of Portobello Barracks. When he learned about the activities of Captain J.C.Bowen-Colthurst during Easter Week he reported the matter to his superiors but, sensing a cover-up, he went to London and reported it directly to Lord Kitchener and Maurice Bonham Carter, Private Secretary to the Prime Minister. Although Bowen-Colthurst was court-martialled and found guilty, Vane was &#39;retired&#39; from the military for his actions. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,608/1-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3868</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0659">Francis Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1916-07-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1846">National Liberal Club, Whitehall Place, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3868_img_3248_1"  type="Letter"  url="498602ca998dbf0edf12ae4867453ab6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3868_img_3248_2"  type="Letter"  url="861b80961a75e6440b61f81ba70e0a22.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3868_img_3248_3"  type="Letter"  url="69117e390933561d4f0b6d54e9e00a94.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3868_img_3248_1"/>
              National Liberal Club <lb/>Whitehall. S.W. <lb/>20th July 1916      My dear Mrs. Skeffington,     I am very glad to see in tonights Parl. <lb/>news that the P.M has again reiterated his <lb/>statement that a <hi rend="underline">public</hi> inquiry is to be <lb/>held — as soon as the necessary machinery <lb/>could be settled. Do not understand what <seg type="del"> </seg> is <lb/>meant by machinery unless some people probably <lb/>meant a slippery machine. Now I have written <lb/>to the editor of the 'Manchester Guardian', who <lb/>I have known for 16 years, and put it very plainly <lb/>before him and will see Gardiner of the Daily <lb/>News and probably the Editor of the 'Evening <lb/>'Standard' (who curiously enough seems very <lb/>sympathetic) about having a Royal Commission <lb/>instead of an Enquiry. I really think the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3868_img_3248_2"/>
            <lb/> Hamsworth Press aught to be seen— for though I <lb/>disagree with them on most things, like every <lb/>party there is some right in them and above all <lb/>they are out to settle the Irish Question now. <lb/>I am sending you a copy of Pax Britannica— <lb/>in memory of sad experiences together, <seg type="del">beca</seg> <lb/>and because I believe that had your poor <lb/>husband been as I have been, bred a solider, <lb/>and had he been through the S.A. War. he <lb/>would in all probability have followed the same <lb/>line as I do. For mine was not an ignoble <lb/>one out there, yet a very difficult part to play— <lb/>and God helping me I played the game.   But I send you this book on one condition that <lb/>you let me keep "Michael Davitt" — I have been <lb/>I have been immensely interested in it — more especially as <lb/>I knew very intimately a friend of his, Josephine Butler, <lb/>from whom I heard much of him — Will you, please? <lb/>Now as to my action in the matter in point. <lb/>1.  I have demanded an inquiry( which may probably <lb/>be consolidated <seg type="del">in you</seg> in yours,) as to <lb/>2 The report on my action in<seg type="unclear">Relief</seg>in Convoy <lb/>and <seg type="unclear">attack</seg> on South Dublin Union. <lb/>( 27 April 1916. Colonel Mac  C.PO et al.) <lb/><seg type="unclear">3</seg> <seg type="del"> </seg>My report on the murders which was <lb/>approved of by S<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Kitchener and the P.M. <lb/>4 The fact that the report was suppressed and <lb/>did not therefore arrive at War Office <hi rend="underline">and in <lb/>lieu of it General Maxwell sent in one <lb/>saying that he had no more use of my <lb/>services in Ireland.</hi> 11 days before Court <lb/>Martial — namely 26th May 1916.!!   Pretty damming this to suppress the report of an <lb/>eye witness. The Senior officer in an Engagement, <lb/>who recommended me for distinguished services
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3868_img_3248_3"/>
            <lb/>in the field. and to substitute for it a report <lb/>from himself (General Maxwell) which would <lb/>induce the belief that I was of no use at all. <lb/>I would ask you in your probable interviews with <lb/>Editors to make my position clear to them <lb/>so that we may be prepared to act strongly <lb/>when the moment arises. My case strengthens <lb/>yours immensely. For they have made every <lb/>blunder which human stupidity can     Please give my best love to our knight <lb/>Grant, Owen    Yours sincerely <lb/>and with my wife's best remembrances  <lb/> Francis Fletcher Vane <lb/>of Hutton   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>