<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5112">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kathleen to May Daly, 17 April 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen   </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/5/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5112</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0689">Kathleen   </persName>
              <date>1923-04-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0634">&#39;An Coláiste, Our Lady of Mercy College, Carysfort, Blackrock, Dublin, Ireland &#39;</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0946">May Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5112_img_None_1"  url="135b1d09f8c1716c8da2ebb006277979.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5112_img_None_2"  url="16b59f04a94b0044dd56ace687b16dec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5112_img_0_1"/>
               <seg type="unclear">Susi</seg> had a<lb/>long letter<lb/>from her<lb/>Australian <lb/>friend Frank<lb/>Murphy, he<lb/>is a mad<lb/>Republican &amp;<lb/>if his prayers<lb/>for the F State<lb/>are heard<lb/>it won't be<lb/>a long liver     Grad aris<lb/>Caitlin    <hi rend="underline"> How is Cornlie?  </hi>   An Colaiste <lb/> 17ad Aibrean 1923     P41/5/4    A Mhaire Dil,   Many thanks for your very welcome note<lb/>which came to-day. You were very good to<lb/>write considering all your trouble, I was<lb/>delighted to get it, and to see that you are<lb/>all bearing up so well  Susie came in last evening and she<lb/>looks real well, she is a bit thin, that is<lb/>no wonder at all considering she was so<lb/>ill, but she fells quite strong now. She did<lb/>all her exams to-day. She was examined<lb/>first thing in teaching - she got an Irish<lb/>Lesson   Naomh Colm Cille, I was let in as a<lb/>special favour to hear it, and she<lb/>certainly did splendidly, Sr Francis Xavier &amp;<lb/>the other nuns were delighted she did so well, indeed Irish is no trouble to Susie,<lb/>she got through her reading and oral<lb/>Irish well too, So Mother Malachy has<lb/>given her until Monday week (the science<lb/><seg type="unclear">exam</seg>) and if she needs another week<lb/>she will get it too, so that when she<lb/>returns for good she will be strong enough<lb/>to study for her final exam. She is<lb/>just now gone to Dunleary to see Sheila .O'B. She is going to stay at Whelan's to-night<lb/>and Florrie O'Mahony and herself intend<lb/>to go to Galvins tomorrow. The Galvins are<lb/>very nice to her. She gets any amount of    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5112_img_0_2"/>
             drives round the country! and they seem to do <lb/>everything possible to make her feel bright, indeed <lb/>she is a marvel she took the bad news so well <lb/>but when I think of Charlie's lovely letter, you <lb/>couldn't do otherwise, indeed he was a model <lb/>in everyway.  There was a letter from Tomas awaiting<lb/>her here, but on opening it found that the <lb/>censor had been generous enough to cut the <lb/>letter in two, anyway in the part that came <lb/>Tomas said he was in the best of health, &amp; <lb/>seemed to be getting on well.  How are your Mother and Father?<lb/>I am sure they both proud of the <lb/>great honour they have though indeed <lb/>your poor Mother will feel it for many a long <lb/>day   Susie was delighted to have your letters <lb/>Nellie's made her laugh, she was a bit <lb/>disappointed though, that your Mother <lb/>did not write, but I am sure it is <lb/>very hard for her. I do hope she<lb/>is feeling well and not worrying Charlie's <lb/>letter to her should be the greatest<lb/>consolation.  I must finish now, hoping you <lb/>are all in good form.    le grad mor <lb/>Kathleen     I forgot to tell <lb/>you that Susie's new<lb/>black dress is very <lb/>nice, it makes her <lb/>look real tall <lb/>Love to Nellie <lb/>Nora &amp; Nancy O <lb/><seg type="unclear">​​​​​​​from K</seg> <lb/>     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>