<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0418">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John R. Johnson to Lord Wimborne, 18 November, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John R. Johnson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from John R. Johnson to Ivor Churchill Guest (1873-1939). Johnson is aware that Kerry County Council has made, or is about to make, a written submission to the Lord Lieutenant requesting him to change the criteria for appointment of members to the management committee of the Tralee and Dingle Light Railway. The letter suggests that the County Council has appointed its own members, who are not qualified, to the management committee, and are now trying to legitimise the appointments.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/19612/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/418</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0871">John R. Johnson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2010">Kilquane, Dingle, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0418_img_1713_1"  type="Letter"  url="26472a4e9c5227deb91fa2af8053c331.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0418_img_1713_2"  type="Letter"  url="b2334370b4758f8e291401dfeae87b27.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0418_img_1713_3"  type="Letter"  url="d7bd1824ba25fa0fd9d889d6eb8c3a07.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0418_img_1713_4"  type="Letter"  url="d5b699b30e3a32ee2f724b6d6c40b45e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0418_img_1713_1"/>
                Kilquane, Dingle    Nov. 18th 1915   To His Excellency The Lord Lieutenant of Ireland   May it please Your Excellency <lb/> to be informed that a resolution of <lb/> the County Council of Kerry has been <lb/> or is about to be forwarded to <lb/> you praying that Your Excellency <lb/> might be induced to amend <lb/> or remove from the order in <lb/> Council which governs the <lb/> qualifications etc. of membership <lb/> of the Committee of management <lb/> of the Tralee &amp; Dingle Light <lb/> Railway anything that would <lb/> prevent the members of the <lb/> said Co. Council from sitting <lb/> &amp; acting on the said Committee. <lb/> As Your Excellency may see from <lb/> the said order in Council a <lb/> member must have at least <lb/> £20 valuation must be <lb/> resident in the <sic>Guarrantying</sic><lb/>area  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0418_img_1713_2"/>
              in order to be <sic>elligible</sic><lb/> for membership on that Com <hi rend="underline">mittee.</hi><lb/> Nothing would be easier than <lb/> to find in the <sic>Guarrantying</sic><lb/> area men possessing the above <lb/> qualifications and those men <lb/> would be most willing to act <lb/> as members of this Committee <lb/> to safeguard their own pockets <lb/> if selected by the County <lb/> Council: the Tralee &amp; Dingle <lb/> Railway 30 miles or so in <lb/> length and under the control <lb/> of the present Committee of <lb/> management in the year <lb/> 1914 there was a <sic>difficiency</sic><lb/> of £5500- It was by reason <lb/> of this <sic>allarming</sic><sic>difficiency</sic><lb/> that this action of Moriarty <lb/> versus O'Donnell was brought <lb/> to the Kings Bench Court  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0418_img_1713_3"/>
              which decided that O'Donnell <lb/> was wrong in so far as he <lb/> was a paid officer, being <lb/> in receipt of a Salary together <lb/> with a free pass over this <lb/> line which is the gift of the <lb/> County Council of which he <lb/> was a member;   Now the County Council have <lb/> begged of Your Excellency by <lb/> resolution to continue them <lb/> on this committee so that they <lb/> may use the said railway <lb/> for their own interest and to <lb/> the financial detriment of <lb/> the Ratepayers of West Kerry. <lb/> Please see cutting from Kerry <lb/> Paper enclosed  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0418_img_1713_4"/>
              This Committee consists of six <lb/> members and only three (3) of <lb/> the six have the necessary <lb/> valuation namely £20. <lb/> I trust Your Excellency being <lb/> given the above facts will <lb/> abstain in the interest of the <lb/> over taxed ratepayers from <lb/> altering the order referred <lb/> to, to suit the convenience <lb/> of those Gentlemen who want <lb/> this railway for their own <lb/> use and purpose. That Your <lb/> Excellency will leave the order <lb/> in Council as it stands <lb/> and relieve the ratepayers <lb/> of a <sic>burthen</sic> for which they <lb/> will forever continue to bless <lb/> Your Excellency. With apologies <lb/> for troubling Your Excellency <lb/> at such length  <seg type="closer"> I remain your obt. <lb/> servant  <lb/> John R. Johnson <lb/>R.D.C.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>