<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1715">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from P. Burrowes Shiel to Augustine Birrell, Chief Secretary for Ireland, 27 March 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>P. Burrowes Shiel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Peter Burrowes Shiel (c.1874-1939), a solicitor, to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Birrell was the Chief Secretary for Ireland from 1907 until his retirement in 1916 following the aftermath of the Easter Rising, for which Birrell accepted responsibility. The letter notes that in 1915 Burrowes had made an application for a government position but there had been none available. Following the death of the former Chief Crown Solicitor, Malachy Kelly (1851-1916), Burrowes requests that he be considered for the vacant position.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registerede Papers; CSORP/1916/5593/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1715</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1315">P. Burrowes Shiel</persName>
              <date>1916-03-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1726">Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0777">London, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1715_img_1172_1"  type="Letter"  url="8483096ad7c38f1295db523d0b39ac4f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1715_img_1172_1"/>
             8 Earlsfort Mansions, <lb/>Dublin,   27th March 1916   Sir,   In August last year I transmitted to you my application for a Govern- <lb/>ment position supported by the letters of recommendation of the Vice- <lb/>President of the Local Government Board Ireland and a statement of my <lb/>qualifications, and I was favored by your reply in acknowledgement that <lb/>at that date there was no post or opportunity available to you to <lb/>offer me.   A vacancy now exists in the Chief Crown Solicitorship at Dublin, and <lb/>will you permit me to remind you of my the application of which you <lb/>stated a record had been made, and in regard to that vacancy to now be <lb/>your consideration of my request,   I remain, Sir, <lb/>your obedient servant,   P. Burrowes Shiel  <lb/>To, <lb/>the Right Hon Aug us tine Birrell. PC.MP.  Irish Office. <lb/>London. SW. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>