<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6234">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charlie Daly to May Daly, 21 February 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charlie Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/2/3/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6234</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date>1923-02-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1693">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Tirconail, Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">May Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1923</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6234_img_None_1"  url="32efd5261c6d8c2961af362592a26999.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6234_img_None_2"  url="17b048acd5062f0e61c73880c1199755.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6234_img_0_1"/>
             Quill. one of the Listowel chaps who was here<lb/>but got captured early in the campaign. He<lb/>was in M<hi rend="superscript">t </hi>joy when Tomas arrived there &amp;<lb/>was speaking to him. He said that he Tomas<lb/>was in good form. Paddy Clifford had been<lb/>with Quill in the joy but was not removed<lb/>with him. He must be still there for he's not<lb/>in N.bridge or here there are several Kerry<lb/>men &amp; nearly all the chaps from this Co. I<lb/>had a letter from one of the latter yesterday.<lb/>Pity you didn't give me Will's address for<lb/>I want to write to him. Even though you<lb/>didn't tell him about my trial hes almost<lb/>certain to have heard about it for Quill &amp;<lb/>those with him did. Perhaps he thought that<lb/>you at home were ignorant of it and like you<lb/>he didn't care to mention it when writing.<lb/>I got the letter that my mother wrote on Sun. week<lb/>as she said you were to write I didnt mind<lb/>answering it so that I could do both together.<lb/>Anyway I had only written her a day or two<lb/>before it came. Those snaps you sent are 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6234_img_0_2"/>
             very good. I hope that you get the others soon.<lb/>Im glad that Sean Healy writes as often. I'd<lb/>have written him but have forgotten his no.<lb/>but I suppose Douglas St. would get him al-<lb/>right. Remember me to him &amp; the others anyhow.<lb/>Perhaps I will write him soon. Yes Dan C's<lb/>letter was in his usual style. I answered<lb/>it a few day's ago. Told him to give my regards<lb/>to the R. field people. Didn't know that those lads<lb/>were so until I got Jess's letter. However,<lb/>'auld lang syne' &amp; other menbers of the family<lb/>can't be forgotten. Glad Corn paid them a<lb/>visit and that they &amp; Pat are well. Give my<lb/>thanks &amp; good wishes to all those friends<lb/>who have been calling to enquire about me<lb/>Gosh! it must have been something like a<lb/>wake or funeral. Sorry to hear that about<lb/>Stephen L. Rather narrow minded of them<lb/>I would not have expected that, Best<lb/>wishes to all the 'Gougane' crowd   Cormac  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>