<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1383">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Malachy Kelly to the Administrative Area Officer, 16 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Malachy Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Malachy J. Kelly to the Administrative area Officer regarding an applicant.The letter states that if the applicant is incapable of work he should be awarded 50 percent of his weekly wage. If the applicant is under 21 and receives 2a/- a week he should be awarded 100 percent.Sir Malachy J. Kelly (1851-1916) was the Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland. He was appointed Crown Solicitor for Mayo in 1884 and was involved in a number of high profile cases. In 1905, he was appointed Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland and moved to Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3785</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1383</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0509">Malachy Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-03-16</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1383_img_749_1"  type="Letter"  url="2637169581a65ce8809f0750976a98ed.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1383_img_749_1"/>
                16th March 1916  <lb/>Ref. No.92 <lb/>Subject - Injury to Patrick Sheehan  Sir,   Referring to your letter of 14th instant the applicant should <lb/>be required in accordance with the Act to submit himself for <lb/>examination free of cost by one of your Medical Officers and if <lb/>the latter's report verifies the applicant's total incapacity to <lb/>work he would be entitledto be paid during such incapacity a sum <lb/>not exceeding 50 per cent of his average weekly earnings for any <lb/>period during which he has been employed such weekly payments not <lb/>to exceed £1.  If the Applicant is under 21 years of age and his average <lb/>weekly earnings are less than 20s/ - he would be entitled to 100 <lb/>per cent but the weekly payment in such case should not exceed <lb/>10s/ - <seg type="del">and</seg> in case the applicant is only partially incapacitated <lb/>the papers should be resubmitted to me with the medical report. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  M Kelly <lb/>The Administrative Area Officer.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>