<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5473">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. Holmes to Gertrude Bannister, 23 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A. Holmes</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from A. Holmes of Queen Anne&#39;s School in London to Gertrude Bannister (later Parry), a cousin of Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written while Casement was imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. Bannister was heavily involved in raising public support for Casement during his trial for treason.

Bannister had been employed by the school and the writer informs her that the guardian of the school will terminate her contract as she has received widespread publicity for her Casement campaign and it reflected poorly on the school. The writer had tried to prevent the termination and expresses regret at the end of her employment there.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,075 /1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5473</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1159">A. Holmes</persName>
              <date>1916-07-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1735">Queen Anne&#39;s School,Haversham, Reading, England, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1365">Gertrude Bannister</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5473_img_506_1"  type="Letter"  url="50db4aaf55de1c74ae7e87c926fca6be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5473_img_506_2"  type="Letter"  url="8339a08cc157e5d114e9b7aa542e725e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5473_img_506_3"  type="Letter"  url="912f1cb7884479d967a2cb07f6992fd0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5473_img_506_1"/>
             July 23 1916   Queen Anne's School, <lb/> Caversham, <lb/>Reading.   My Dear Miss Bannister   I have a very sad letter to <lb/> write to you, but I am sure you would <lb/> rather that I wrote than that you <lb/> should hear from anyone else.   The Committee feel that it would not <lb/> wish that you should come back here <lb/> and are, I believe, going to write to you after <lb/> next Thursday's meeting. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5473_img_506_2"/>
             You can't know how hard this is for me <lb/> to write like this <!-- author uses dashes instead of periods or commas -->—- the loss to me and <lb/> to the school is very heavy, and I did <lb/> everything I could to prevent it. <lb/>The fact is that your name has come <lb/> out so publicly, that disagreeable <lb/> things are being said about the school, <lb/> so I have been told. I have never heard <lb/> anything of the sort here — and it is <lb/> thought that it would be better to ask <lb/> you to resign.   The Committee I know are going to consider <lb/> your salary etc.   We are all very sad f; we hoped to <lb/> have you amongst us again, but <lb/> at the same time we hope &amp; believe that <lb/> something good will come to you, and <lb/> think that you might have found it <lb/> almost impossible to come back as usual. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5473_img_506_3"/>
             I feel as if I were writing in such <lb/> a matter of fact way— but I was very <lb/> much upset by it — I am beginning to think <lb/> now that God has arranged it, &amp; will <lb/> surely do something to help you to <lb/> take up your life, &amp; that it will in <lb/> the end therefore be a happier thing for you. <lb/>I hope I shall see you in the holidays. <lb/> We go off on Wednesday— I  or Saturday,  to Oxford for a <lb/> week, &amp; then I don't know where.  <lb/>Much love to you <lb/> Yours affectionately   <lb/><hi rend="underline">A. Holmes</hi>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>