<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3785">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Basil Blackwood, secretary to Lord Wimbourne, to Matthew Nathan, 28 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Lord Basil Blackwood</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Basil Blackwood, secretary to Lord Wimbourne, to Matthew Nathan, Under-Secretary for Ireland. It concerns the sending of press cutting to the Lord Lieutenant. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP/1916/3703/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3785</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0920">Lord Basil Blackwood</persName>
              <date>1916-02-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Matthew Nathan, Under-Secretary for Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3785_img_317_1"  type="Letter"  url="1d43a07d072f33a1c6c3ffc9a13becad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3785_img_317_1"/>
              3703   Telephone 2094  Vice Regal Lodge,<lb/>Dublin   28th February, 1916   Dear Sir Matthew,   With reference to my letter of<lb/>last night, I made some further enquiries. It<lb/>seems that in addition to my telegram to Maitland<lb/>from London, His Excellency wrote to him himself,<lb/>and that in consequence he was particularly alive to<lb/>the necessity of sending press cuttings daily. He<lb/>found they did not arrive daily, and twice telephoned<lb/>on the subject to the Registrar before he communicated<lb/>with Sir Edward O'Farrell. The envelope I referred<lb/>to yesterday was the third instance of an accumulation<lb/>of cuttings arriving by the same post. That five or<lb/>six days cuttings arrived together is quite evidently<lb/>an exaggeration. The fact that each days cuttings<lb/>are in two batches, recruiting and ordinary, gives the<lb/>appearance of greater accumulation than is really the case.   Yours sincerely, <lb/> Basil Blackwood     I Wm <seg type="unclear"></seg> to see    <lb/>II     seen<lb/>WMC<lb/>29/2   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>