<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2726">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his father, Harford Hugh Montgomery, 18 December, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.

William Montgomery is writing to his father to inform him that Horace (Major Haslett) has been injured.  He has been shot, a bullet entered his left ear and exited his eye.  He has lost his left eye and has been evacuated.  William has spoken to the doctor who advised that &#34;Horace was quite conscious, likely to recover, and he did not think he would lose the sight of his other eye&#34;.  William is arranging to have Horace&#39;s things collected and fowarded to Messrs Cox &amp; Co, Bankers, 18 Charing Cross, London.  William will write to Ida tonight. He asks his father to convey the contents of the letter to Jim Haslett and Ida but believes Ida may be in London with Horace by the time his father receives this letter.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2726</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0922">William Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1915-12-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2095">Monacherra, Malone Park,Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_1"  type="Letter"  url="e7cb55feb403ff8245c7d77ec17a8aa8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_2"  type="Letter"  url="9dfff7532e90a99a00abc78dc6b27199.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_3"  type="Letter"  url="949b7dfd9db3dc4856ba0725b9260ec6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_4"  type="Envelope"  url="d733d7869a2c34d4f5406e3e41d0ece6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_5"  type="Letter"  url="f9d37180576e73a2089b76fa0208aada.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_6"  type="Letter"  url="5b4f8333cfbd733f83ffc7079cae12b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2726_img_2147_7"  type="Letter"  url="6776953a0fcd5f4c80efee5f095a2efa.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_1"/>
             In the Field<lb/> 18th Dec. 1915. <lb/><lb/> My Dear Father/   It was with<lb/>feelings of the greatest<lb/>possible sorrow that I had<lb/>to send you the following<lb/>wire this morning:-<lb/><lb/>Assessors Belfast<lb/>Horace seriously wounded<lb/>Seventeenth. lost right eye.<lb/>left believed uninjured.<lb/>no immediate danger to life.<lb/>Montgomery  I was with Horace when<lb/>he was wounded. He had<lb/>asked me to look at some<lb/>work which he had done to<lb/>his trench the previous<lb/>day. We had looked at this 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_2"/>
             work, <seg type="del">and had turned</seg> and<lb/>had turned to walk away<lb/>across a place which has<lb/>been freely and safely<lb/>used day and night for<lb/>some weeks past when<lb/>we were sniped at. We<lb/>were alone at the time.<lb/>Horace called out Ah! Is<lb/>it a big hole. Better me<lb/>than you. I saw he<lb/>was badly hit and called<lb/>out to one of his sergeants<lb/>whom I caught sight of<lb/>to send for bearers and a<lb/>Doctor and come out and<lb/>help me. We got a field<lb/>dressing on at once.  Joch Stevenson and another<lb/>Sergeant came out overground<lb/>with the stretcher and<lb/>bearers. Horace was quite 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_3"/>
             4<lb/>we were still open to fire.  He has been evacuated<lb/>very rapidly right away<lb/>from near the firing line.  I called last night in<lb/>the first collecting station<lb/>some miles from where he<lb/>had been hit and found<lb/>that he had left there<lb/>about half an hour<lb/>previously. (I could do so<lb/>because as it happened we<lb/>moved there into billets<lb/>last night). I waw this<lb/>Doctor who attended to him<lb/>and he told me, Horace was<lb/>quite conscious, likely to<lb/>recover, and that he did<lb/>not think he would lose<lb/>the sight of his other eye.<lb/>The bullet passed in   TD 2770 D2794/1/1/5  <seg type="unclear"> punt </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_4"/>
             5<lb/>under his left ear and<lb/>out <seg type="del">under</seg> through his<lb/>right eye. The eye is quite<lb/>gone. He has had a<lb/>most marvellous escape<lb/>with his life. I never<lb/>knew just what this phrase<lb/>meant until this occurred.<lb/>I shall never forget how<lb/>Stevenson and <seg type="del">Horace's Coy</seg><lb/>the N.C.O.'s of Horace's Coy<lb/>came out under a very<lb/>accurate fire and brought<lb/>poor old Horace in.  l have officially reported<lb/>on their conduct. Horace's<lb/>whole Coy. were very upset.  All the officers of the<lb/>Battalion have expressed<lb/>their sincere sorrow 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_5"/>
             6.<lb/>and have asked that their<lb/>sympathy be conveyed<lb/>to Ida and his other<lb/>relatives. It was generally<lb/>and unanimously agreed<lb/>last night that the officer<lb/>who could least be spared<lb/>was taken first.  Major Crozier, now commanding<lb/>the Battalion, has written<lb/>Ida direct.  I am having all Horace's<lb/>things collected and handed<lb/>over to the proper Authority.<lb/>They will be forwarded<lb/>eventually to Messrs Cox<lb/>&amp; Co, Bankers, 18 Charing Cross<lb/>London.  I am writing Ida    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_6"/>
             7<lb/>direct tonight. I need hardly add Father<lb/>just how terribly upset I have been<lb/>myself by the whole affair. <seg type="del">I was</seg>  Please convey the contents of this<lb/>to Jim Haslett and <seg type="del">Ita</seg> Ida as speedily<lb/>as possible. It is possible however<lb/>that Ida may be with Horace in<lb/>England before this letter reaches you.   Your affectionate son <lb/><hi rend="underline"> Wm Montgomery </hi><lb/><lb/>I am untouched    
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2726_img_2147_7"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">Urgent</hi> <lb/> Harford H Montgomery Esq <lb/>Monacherra <lb/>Malone Park <lb/>Belfast. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>