<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0199">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Daulat Ram Kalia, 10 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Daulat Ram Kalia</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Indian student Daulat Ram Kalia to Dublin Castle. The letter was written in the hope that it would be passed on to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939). Kalia writes to Wimborne to thank him for the action taken and the sympathy displayed to the Indian students. Kalia had previously written to complain about the newspaper &#39;The Eye-Opener&#39;. The paper caused much controversy in 1916 when it printed an article with the heading &#39;Black Peril&#39; which attacked Indian students and indeed all people of dark skin. The paper not only claimed that &#39;coloured people&#39; were savage but also that any white person seen in their company was a disgrace. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/6388/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/199</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0290">Daulat Ram Kalia</persName>
              <date>1916-04-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0154">21 Synge Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0199_img_1342_1"  type="Letter"  url="64daa5eff7f6c1c5edc7e43ab16a8008.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0199_img_1342_2"  type="Letter"  url="33cfcd4e5177c350d1ba7f3c031909b7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0199_img_1342_1"/>
               Dear sir   I have to acknowledge the <lb/> receipt of your letter No. 5575 dated 6.4.15 <lb/> with many thanks.   I do not know how to thank <lb/> His Excellency for the sympathy he has shown <lb/> with the Indian students &amp; for the <lb/> action he has so kindly taken.   The Indian students with whom I <lb/> have met have expressed their gratefu <lb/> -lness to Lord Wimborne &amp; highly ap <lb/> -preciated his kindness.   This step of His Excellency will <lb/> have a far reaching effect is as much <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0199_img_1342_2"/>
              as these students (who or at least some <lb/> of whom are to be the leaders of the Indian <lb/> public opinion in time to come) <lb/> will remember this favour &amp; kindness of His Excellency throughout their lives. <lb/> Some small events sometimes produce <lb/> very great &amp; far reaching results &amp; the present one is <lb/> surely one of them.   May I ask you to kindly convey my heartfelt <lb/> thanks to His Excellency for all this.   I have also to thank yourself so much <lb/> for the kindly interest you have taken <lb/> in the matter &amp; assure you that the <lb/> Indians never forget kindness shown to <lb/> them &amp; they have the virtue of being <lb/> grateful.   Thanking you once more <seg type="closer"> Yours Very Obediently  D. R. Kalia </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>