<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4287">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William R. Young to Edward Carson, 2 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Robert Young</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Robert Young (1856-1933) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. William Robert Young, linen merchant, politician and philanthropist, was a prominent Unionist. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4287</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1100">William Robert Young</persName>
              <date>1915-11-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0288">34 Bedford Street, Belfast, Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4287_img_3650_1"  type="Letter"  url="88dd23fd9bbe9155ebd2e574e8c81aa4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4287_img_3650_2"  type="Letter"  url="4d9d48ab39d9919ac40cefd05b2171fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4287_img_3650_3"  type="Letter"  url="1d098025a057915b3fe7118c4e1b92ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4287_img_3650_4"  type="Letter"  url="f33af5abcd736ccd2f0cd02901d81c3d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4287_img_3650_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>  34 Bedford Street, <lb/> Belfast   Nov.2.1915   Dear Sir Edward,   Re the new recruitment scheme <lb/>and Ulster's position, of which Bates has <lb/>been keeping you informed up to date, <lb/>you will be glad to hear that arrange- <lb/>ments have to-day been made which <lb/>will I think put Ulster Unionists &amp; <lb/>the Ulster Division in the right position. <lb/>Bates showed me your letter and <lb/>allowed me to show it to the Lord Mayor — <lb/>A new advertisement (recruiting) comes <lb/>out tomorrow in which men are invited <lb/>to enlist in any battalion or Division <lb/>they select, no regiments or battalions <lb/>being mentioned —   The Lord Mayor is appointed <seg type="del">L</seg> Sole <lb/>Director for Ulster — All papers signed <lb/>in Ulster are to be handed him
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4287_img_3650_2"/>
             (2)  <lb/>to be dealt with by a Committee <seg type="unclear">re</seg> <lb/>appointed by him —    The mistake in the first instance, <lb/>or the intention of Dublin, to divert <lb/>Ulstermen to the Reserve Battalions <lb/>of the Irish Divisions, has been rectified — <lb/><seg type="del">and</seg>Ulstermen now can select battalions <lb/>of the Ulster Division as they wish —   Up to last night, ( I have not <lb/>seen todays return ), there were about <lb/>1000 answers to  the  misleading recruiting <lb/>appeals, three quarters of which <lb/>were for the Ulster Division, the <lb/>signers taking the precaution of <lb/>adding Ulster Division to Royal Irish <lb/>Rifles — of the other quarter the <lb/>Dublin authorities at once agreed to <lb/>day to give the signer the option of <lb/>adding Ulster Division when inadvertently
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4287_img_3650_3"/>
             (3)   34 Bedford Street, <lb/>Belfast  <lb/>left out —    So you see matters have now been <lb/>put straight —    Excuse this letter but as I have <lb/>been so mixed up in the negotiations <lb/>of the last two days I thought you <lb/>might like to know results —    The Lord Mayor is Thoroughly aware <lb/>of the position and will see that <lb/>the Ulster Division interests are well <lb/>safeguarded —    Yours sincerely   Willie R Young. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4287_img_3650_4"/>
            <seg type="del">D 1507/1/1915/62</seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>