<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1146">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí, 17 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to his son Piaras Béaslaí(1881–1965). The father fills his son in on various pieces of family news as Béaslaí is imprisoned at the time of writing. Responding to his son&#39;s previous enquiry about the book collection of the Irish Journalists Association, Piaras&#39;s father tells him that while the building was damaged during the &#39;Dublin trouble&#39;, the association managed to rescue the books and records. Besides this, the father recommends a particular edition of the Iliad and Dante, referring to the fact that his son has both Latin and French, which will help as he learns Spanish. Béaslaí was an English-born influential member of the IRB. He joined the Irish Volunteers on their foundation late in 1913. When visiting his parents he smuggled guns to Ireland. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers.Béaslaí was an officer during the Easter Rising. He was court-martialled and sentenced to five years’ for his part. In prison he wrote and memorised poems about his captivity. This letter is part of a collection of letters by Piaras’ parents, mostly during Béaslai’s internment. After his release he soon became involved in politics.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, NLI33973/5/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1146</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-07-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1070">Cheshire</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1146_img_38_1"  type="Letter"  url="d47bcbdc999b29698116968b018cd6e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1146_img_38_2"  type="Letter"  url="5f30a51eaa16e0887bf09400fae3bc80.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1146_img_38_3"  type="Letter"  url="b5045c938ef4e7427d4a4ff9de5ee968.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1146_img_38_1"/>
              q116 <lb/> P. <hi rend="underline">Beazley</hi>    Glengariff,  Rudgrave Square,  Egremont,  Cheshire    17 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> July, 1916.    My dearest Pierce,   Though impatient to write to you, I have deâ <lb/>layed answering your letter, first in order, as you sugâ <lb/>gested, that I might get more news about friends, and <lb/> secondly, not to leave too much time between the <lb/> receipt of this and the answer to your next letter, which <lb/> we hope to receive in September. I need not assure you <lb/> that mother and I have been thinking of you every day <lb/> and every hour of the day and praying that God may conâ <lb/>tinue to give you good health and all the happiness <lb/> that can be attained under the conditions. Your letter <lb/> was a great pleasure and comfort to us, for, besides givâ <lb/>ing us the most welcome intelligence that your health <lb/> was good, it was written in a spirit which showed that <lb/> you were bearing your lot with fortitude. It was a <lb/> great consolation too to know that you are so well <lb/> provided for spiritually and intellectually and that the <lb/> food is good and the work not too hard. It was very <lb/> kind of the Bishop to pay the visit. From what I hear, <lb/> he is a man of high capacity and good presence. I have <lb/> had letters at various times from his brother who is <lb/> a medical doctor in Plymouth. It is a blessing too that <lb/> you find the chaplain to be, as you say, a charming man. <lb/> A kind disposition is like a perpetual ray of sunshine. <lb/> I have not yet taken my holidays and probably will not do so <lb/> till next month. I had resolved to go and see you, but after <lb/> having carefully considered what you said in your letter, I <lb/> decided that it is best to be content with writing to you. <lb/> It is better that you should be able to write the extra <lb/> letter. One could not say very much during a visit of <lb/> twenty minutes. I am exceedingly glad that there is such <lb/> a good library, but I would utter a word of caution against  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1146_img_38_2"/>
              anything like hard study. When one has manual work <lb/> to do tis well not to tax the brain heavily, but <lb/> light intellectual work is beneficial. If you are going <lb/> through the Iliad you will find it a delight, especially <lb/> if there is an edition with good notes. Anthon's, though <lb/> not at all critical, is very useful through saving the trouble <lb/> of a dictionary in the earlier books. Knowing Latin and <lb/> French, you will find Italian and Spanish quite easy. Dante <lb/> is as interesting as Homer and as difficult to interpret. <lb/> You will, I am sure, be glad to know that the number of <lb/> friends who have been enquiring about you and desire <lb/> to be remembered affectionately to you is very large. <lb/> Father James, in letters I have had from him, has shown <lb/> that he is most anxious to hear as often as possible how <lb/> you are. His letters of enquiry are extremely kind. He <lb/> has just been at the annual Clerical Retreat in Killarney. <lb/> He has not yet told me when or where he is going on his <lb/> holidays. Since I wrote this I have had a letter from him <lb/> in which he says he is going to Bray on the 23<hi rend="underline">rd</hi> He wants <lb/> me to go there also for my holidays. I may be able to ar <lb/>range to go there about the 29<hi rend="underline">th</hi>. The only drawback is <lb/> that mother will not be able to come, but she is, thank God, <lb/> in very good health and insists that I must go. Father <lb/> James has sent a card for you which I enclose, hoping you <lb/> may be allowed to receive it. He says a number of relatives <lb/> and other friends asked to be remembered to you. With his <lb/> letter came one from Mr. J.J. O'Kelly. His expressions of regard <lb/> for you are most warmâhearted. He has not yet had an <lb/> opportunity of reading your novel, but he hopes to have <lb/> time to do so soon and that it may be possible to pub <lb/>lish it. He enclosed a note from Mr. Foley who writes: <lb/> 'When writing to Liverpool do not fail to say how delighted <lb/><hi rend="underline">we all</hi> are about our devoted P.B. Let him be told that <lb/> his friends at the Bailey are always asking me for items <lb/> about him and that they want their kindest regards to be  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1146_img_38_3"/>
              conveyed.' Both Mr. O'Kelly and Mr. Foley are anxious to send <lb/> books but I shall tell them they are not permitted. I think I told <lb/> you in my last letter that Mr. O'Kelly said (in a previous letter) <lb/> that good care should be taken of your manuscripts. You will <lb/> be sorry, he says, to hear that the mothers of Padraig O'Maille and <lb/> Owen O'Brien died recently. He adds that John O'Keeffe is no longer <lb/> staying with the old lady in Prince's street and has started in bus <lb/>iness for himself. Michael Murphy called on me the other day. He <lb/> said Nellie, Norah, and Kitty desired to be warmly remembered to you. <lb/> Norah has finished her first year at Hull. He said they were com <lb/>ing to see us in a few days, but they have not come yet. John <lb/> Smyth often talks about you and wishes me to send his kind <lb/>est remembrances; also Mrs. McLoughlin. Her daughter is now <lb/> married and happy. I met D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Niven in Dale Street a week ago. <lb/> He made kind enquiries about you. His daughters, he told me, have <lb/> grown into young women. Annie, the younger, is studying <lb/> medicine and will, no doubt, be helpful to him when she is <lb/> qualified as a doctor. I have put off mentioning Langford <lb/> as we have been expecting him to arrive for his holidays to <lb/>day. I have, however, had a letter from him just now, saying <lb/> business will not allow him to come for another week. He <lb/> mentions you affectionately in every letter. In answer to <lb/> your enquiry about the books of the Irish Journalists' Asso <lb/>ciation, for which you were Secretary, he says : 'The building <lb/> was partially damaged during the Dublin trouble, but the <lb/> Association has all the books and records and nothing <lb/> needs clearing up.' He adds that Jack Clancy is in Dublin <lb/> but he does not know whether Maud is in Dublin, <lb/> London or <sic>Timbuctoo</sic>. Now I am drawing to a close as I <lb/> am leaving the next page to mother. Let me assure you <lb/> again, though I know it is not necessary, that we think <lb/> of you continually and pray that God may bless and comfort <lb/> you. Mother, Langford and myself are all, thank God, in ex <lb/>cellent health. We earnestly hope that your health and spirits <lb/> continue good and that we shall all be well when we meet again. <lb/> <seg type="closer"> With fondest love from all three &amp; from many friends <lb/> I remain ever affectionately   Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>