<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2742">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his parents, Harford and  Sara Montgomery, 29 December, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Montgomery to his parents about his life at the front, including a lecture he attended on the battle of Loos in which it was reported that although secrecy was kept tight &#34;the Huns knew the frontage, times, disposition and even the names of the regiments allotted....&#34; He describes sleeping conditions and sleeping though an artillery barrage on the enemy trenches 24 yards away. He thanks his parents for Christmas presents and states that some letters have not arrived even 14 days after their being posted. He reports he was in the trenches on Christmas day and expects to be there on New Year&#39;s Eve and day. 

He drinks tea and cocoa but little alcohol. Reports on a new  primus stove from supplies but fuel is short and they are dissuaded from buying it locally as it interferes with  civilian supplies. He mentions a new telephone that is capable of listening into messages through the earthwires but claims &#34;the Hun is too clever to but their earth wires near the front line.&#34; 

He describes a battle including the sound and effects of the enemy machine guns writing &#34;450 rounds per minute is enough to make anyone duck&#34;. He writes of of the German snipers, their skills and patience, including their receiving a bounty of £2.10.0 (50 marks) for shooting an officer. He comments on discipline imposed by severe penalties and implications of pain. He writes of prisoners of war. 

The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2742</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1915-12-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery and Sara Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0158">Monacherra, Malone Park, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_1"  type="Letter"  url="5b1ba46e0da4024b37fff66ee05366d4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_2"  type="Letter"  url="2f04ab36036f7cf2e22946d2a0f3f31c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_3"  type="Letter"  url="6a893faa5a3d58a3c3c8729d3275c251.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_4"  type="Letter"  url="a101049e803b094c42fd9badd7d910c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_5"  type="Letter"  url="c6a56210e3783c586f69de3768e437a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_6"  type="Letter"  url="fe39c961c65e929406cb228bc487cdae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_7"  type="Letter"  url="08921cf87b5baa93a640588a0f058e4b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_8"  type="Letter"  url="2b81109093b8463e205fd847bc1c2cbb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_9"  type="Letter"  url="4fb26f5fd5420c42331b2bb219e3d3b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_10"  type="Letter"  url="4b0aaf1a2c718965b194f4051151c30e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_11"  type="Letter"  url="cdb5b37973ed2eb63bc6e5860ebcdf8c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_12"  type="Letter"  url="a4e36bfafd672e55bf1c1a242dc1db17.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_13"  type="Letter"  url="aba68f5a0d07462560b21f41e4ab72cf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_14"  type="Letter"  url="041006ba0f8f963a0472b6bdc2251dd4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_15"  type="Letter"  url="51bd2ebd45fc526c19b0d2e677c7f8fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_16"  type="Letter"  url="2d8b99e7f4814680bd3db618c7d1d601.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_17"  type="Letter"  url="135e9db64b3721dfc3c2f4da8d8b74c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_18"  type="Letter"  url="bab26231f09d135dc79b9f5a0cc15224.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2742_img_2161_19"  type="Letter"  url="e26b62f45e024b12b181abbc6cb66838.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_1"/>
             In the Field   29.12.15   My Dear Father &amp; Mother   I have <lb/> Fathers' letter dated on last<lb/> page with stamp 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> inst.   There seems to be a fate<lb/> about wires of a vital<lb/> nature addressed to the <lb/> office. I was very annoyed<lb/> that Jack McConnell's wire<lb/> got <sic>thro'</sic> first. As the wire to<lb/> you, the wire to Lizzie Hanna<lb/> and the wire Crozier sent<lb/> were all handed by me to<lb/> <hi rend="underline">an Officer</hi>at the one time<lb/> who handed them to a<lb/> special Brigade Office<lb/>Despatch rider to take at<lb/> top speed to an authorised<lb/> Post Office for civilian
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_2"/>
            wires. A great deal of<lb/> very necessary formality<lb/> has to be gone <sic>thro'</sic> in order<lb/> to get a wire away at all. <lb/> This is because behind our<lb/> front lines living in our<lb/> midst are many I fear<lb/> very many clever brave<lb/> spies who undoubtedly<lb/> manage in marvellous<lb/> ways to communicate<lb/>very quickly &amp; very fully<lb/> accurate information of <lb/> almost everything that<lb/> goes on. I was taken<lb/> after dark last night to <lb/>the — Army Headquarters<lb/> in a motor bus to hear a <lb/> lecture on the Battle of <seg type="unclear">Soos.</seg>   At that lecture which was
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_3"/>
            3.<lb/> given in the presence of several hundred<lb/> officers all of ranks <seg type="del">up</seg> of Lieutenant or<lb/> upwards ( nearly all Captains at least.) &amp;<lb/> included a very famous Army Commander, <lb/> the statement was definitely made that<lb/> altho' everything was kept absolutely<lb/> secret right up to the last moment even from<lb/> many of the high Commanders when the attack<lb/> was actually launched the Huns knew<lb/> the frontage, time, dispositions, and even<lb/> the names of the Regiments allotted to<lb/> different sectors &amp; their particular position<lb/> in the assault. They of course were<lb/> all ready in the place which we
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_4"/>
            fondly believed <seg type="del">were</seg> we<lb/> would take with "benefit" of<lb/> surprise. I could if I dare<lb/> tell you other things about<lb/> the Battle of Loos which I<lb/> don't think you have heard.   I send you the enclosed<lb/> note from my C.O. I was<lb/> just about to destroy it when<lb/> it occurred to me that you<lb/> might like to have it. You<lb/> always possessed a strong family sentiment which I<lb/> often, I fear ridiculed but really <lb/>admired. It is a simple<lb/> note, put very nicely but it is<lb/> nevertheless an order to carry on<lb/> for another 48 hours with<lb/> practically no sleep after I had<lb/> just had a spell of what old<lb/> W.J Jefferson would call<lb/> responsible work for a young<lb/> fellow which lasted 65 hours,<lb/> 6 of which I slept &amp; then it was<lb/> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_5"/>
            5<lb/> on no down bed. 3/9 X 1 <hi rend="superscript">1/2</hi><lb/> planks propped up on <lb/> biscuit tins of various<lb/> heights under a leaky dug<lb/> out roof. My pillow Maynard<lb/> Sinclairs wet British <seg type="unclear">Warm</seg><lb/> &amp; my covering wet shin<lb/> coat &amp; a much wetter Burberry.<lb/> So much for my bed &amp; I <hi rend="underline">did</hi> <lb/> enjoy it too. After I woke<lb/> from my second spell<lb/>Maynard Sinclair ( poor wee <lb/> devil) just sat &amp; "turned over"<lb/> to me &amp; put his head down<lb/> among the debris of our<lb/>mess table &amp; in 10 seconds<lb/> was sound asleep. He wakened, <lb/> I remember with the brand <lb/> of a much advertised<lb/> brand of cigarettes on his<lb/>brow, caused by making<lb/> a pillow of a tin of cigarettes.
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_6"/>
            6<lb/> He did look funny. He is<lb/> just 19 Father but the <lb/> purest of pure pure gold.   The business man who <lb/> tells me a young fellow<lb/> mustn't be trusted with<lb/> responsibility in the future<lb/> will be surprised at what <lb/> I tell him. I have trusted<lb/> <seg type="del">the</seg>one to turn on Artillery<lb/> against an enemy whose<lb/> nearest trench<seg type="del">es</seg> are 24<lb/> yards from ours and <hi rend="underline">slept</hi>through it. My servant &amp; <lb/> I are thoroughly enjoying<lb/> ourselves with the Autostrop <lb/> razor you were so thoughtful<lb/> as to send me. I am getting<lb/> quite good with it. I am<lb/> very satisfied with it &amp; <lb/> don't want to change it.
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_7"/>
            7.<lb/> I have had I think all<lb/> Mothers lovely parcels for <lb/> which I am very grateful<lb/> some which have bee advised<lb/> from other people as sent<lb/> 14 days ago haven't turned<lb/>up yet.  I just <hi rend="underline">love</hi>to hear some<lb/> of the Firms business "shop."<lb/> It is such a relief from <lb/>ours. Please let me have<lb/> letters abut it just like<lb/> your last. I thank you <lb/> for your good wishes in the <lb/> New Year which I heartily<lb/> reciprocate. I shall be<lb/> in the trenches on New Year's <lb/> eve &amp; New Year's Day. I was<lb/> also in on Xmas Day.   In fact to make it worse<lb/> we were relieved that
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_8"/>
            8.<lb/> day. This pen is the <lb/> greatest possible luxury.    I had a very nice letter <lb/> from Horace from hospital<lb/> in Rouen dated 26/12/15.<lb/> It is written in ink in<lb/> his own handwriting. It <lb/> has been passed round his<lb/> coy &amp; the officers so that they<lb/> can see for themselves that<lb/> Horace can see too. I<lb/> <hi rend="underline">almost</hi> stood myself a <lb/> drink when I got it. I <lb/> go very shy of drink. I <lb/> never drink water of course<lb/> without a little whisky or<lb/> chloride of lime or petrie<lb/> or all three in it. But beyond<lb/> that no spirits not even a<lb/> tot of rum. Then if I do<lb/> happen to get really badly<lb/> 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_9"/>
            chilled and foundered I will <lb/> get the benefit of it. But <lb/> I really believe hot cocoa <lb/> or tea is better &amp; I drink <lb/> oceans of both. I sent to <lb/> the A &amp; N Stores &amp; got a <lb/> pocket primus stove from <lb/> them, which will help in <lb/> the culinary department <lb/>very considerably. The fuel <lb/>question with us is very <lb/> acute now. There is some <lb/> hitch about the supply &amp; <lb/> in consequence our men <lb/>are suffering damnably.   We are now forbidden to <lb/>buy locally as it upsets <lb/> supplies available to <lb/>civilians but — a lot of <lb/> things happen in the Army
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_10"/>
            You might tell Charlie <lb/> McGann &amp; Miss McDermott <lb/> I haven't had their long <lb/> looked for letters yet.   One meets all sorts of <lb/>people here continually <lb/> For instance Bass Copper <lb/> called in my mess today <lb/>to see me but I was out &amp; <lb/> he didn't wait &amp; he didn't <lb/> even take the trouble to <lb/> tell any of my officers <lb/> where he was stationed.   I also entertained Charlie <lb/> McGanns pal Lindsay <lb/> from Lough Neagh &amp; we <lb/> were talking about Charlie <lb/>&amp; yacht boating in my <lb/>dug out just before Lindsay <lb/> went out to try some <lb/> new Telephone Instrument
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_11"/>
            Coy means of which it is possible to top<lb/> messages thro' their earths. He got his <lb/> earth pin in within 2 yards of the Bosch<lb/> Defence wire but couldn't catch any<lb/> messages "on earth". The Hun is too<lb/> intelligent to put his earth pins in <lb/> within at least a hundred yards of<lb/> his front line. All he got was a good<lb/> wetting, his trousers practically torn off him<lb/> and a real war with snipers all on his<lb/> own. He wasn't hit coming back &amp; <lb/> when he got in to report return to me<lb/> he was perfectly at ease &amp; happy. in to report return to me<lb/>he was perfectly at ease &amp; happy.
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_12"/>
            10<lb/> The Hun has worked this<lb/> earth trick on us more<lb/> than once &amp; go <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the<lb/> messages that passed for<lb/> days. I have the greatest<lb/> possible respect for them.   I Iike them least when<lb/> they are quietest.    Two of our officers have<lb/> been recommended for awards of honour - Stevenson<lb/> and Gould - Jack Stevenson<lb/> is well worth a D.S.O. &amp; <lb/> Gould a military cross.<lb/> Both for patrol work.<lb/> Stevenson carried in a <lb/> wounded man under heavy<lb/> fire a distance of 300 yards<lb/> after his own revolver had <lb/> had knocked out of his <lb/> 
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_13"/>
            hand by a rifle bullet.   The wounded man was<lb/> hit again when Stevenson<lb/> was carrying him &amp; died<lb/> a few hours after he got<lb/> in. He couldn't have lived<lb/> anyway as he had hideous<lb/> abdominal injuries caused<lb/> by a bomb explosion.    There was "some war"<lb/> that night tween lines.    We don't know &amp; I don't <lb/> expect the Borsches know <lb/> exactly what did happen <lb/> but it started by a strong<lb/> patrol of ours colliding <lb/> with a strong patrol of<lb/> theirs in absolute darkness.<lb/> They all opened fire on<lb/> each other at once with<lb/> bombs revolvers &amp; rifles or
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_14"/>
            14<lb/> It was all quite plain<lb/> &amp; straight sailing but our<lb/> people getting the worst of<lb/> it were ordered to retire <lb/> as we saw reinforcements <lb/> arrive for the Bosch who<lb/> were even then easily<lb/> twice our strength. We<lb/> retired but a new war<lb/> started immediately &amp; the<lb/> last we saw of the performance<lb/> was the two Bosch parties<lb/> busy killing each other. <lb/> They actually got hand<lb/> to hand at the finish.<lb/> They are reported to have<lb/> done the thing thoroughly.    I was listening to the <lb/> performance comfortably<lb/> on my front line <seg type="unclear">fire step</seg> 
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_15"/>
            15<lb/> and they certainly took their time at it.    I of course thought it was us &amp; them<lb/> otherwise I should have helped them<lb/> to a speedy understanding by turning<lb/> one of the two machine guns now at<lb/> my own disposal on to them.    A sudden burst of machine gun<lb/> fire traversing along your fire<lb/> parapet at night when your working<lb/> parties are usually up on top is enough <lb/> to make even the dead roots of my<lb/> top hair tingle. It is a hideous<lb/> sound. The Hun Gun is slower than 
            <pb n="16" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_16"/>
            16<lb/> our gun but 450 rounds<lb/> per minute form nowhere<lb/> arriving everywhere is <lb/> quite fast enough to make<lb/> me duck. Although what <lb/> good ducking is when<lb/> one hears the <hi rend="underline">crack</hi> of the<lb/> bullet I don't know.   A man never hears the <lb/>one that hits him. I<lb/> heard the one that got<lb/> Horace. I hear it yet.   A damned horrible thing<lb/> happened to the Batt of Regulars<lb/> we relieved last time on the<lb/> day we relieved. Their C.O.<lb/> was going along the line.<lb/> He met a soldier in a <lb/> narrow place. The soldier<lb/> got up on the fire step to <lb/> make way. He forgot the<lb/> 
            <pb n="17" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_17"/>
            17<lb/> was damaged at<lb/> that point. He lost the<lb/> side of his head and of <lb/> course his life. The C.O.<lb/> was upset about it. Organisation<lb/> of German snipers is marvellous.<lb/> And the patience of the <lb/> blighters is horrible. They<lb/> wont fire for days just to<lb/> encourage you &amp; then<lb/> when you have got lulled<lb/> into a feeling of <hi rend="underline">very</hi><lb/> false security they play<lb/> some most ingenious trick<lb/> and get someone or perhaps<lb/> more. It is known they <lb/> have a sliding scale of<lb/> Head money. It is said to<lb/> be £2-10-0 (50 Marks)<lb/> for an officer. I wish I
            <pb n="18" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_18"/>
            18<lb/> could make a prisoner of<lb/> the one that got Horace. I <lb/> should have him escorted<lb/> to safety by men from D<lb/> Coy. These of course sound<lb/> awful things by a warm <lb/> fire in a comfortable<lb/> room, but Father, men<lb/> who have seen a loved officer<lb/> shot before their eyes are <lb/> never quite the same<lb/> again. They are human<lb/> beings &amp; war - this war - does<lb/> not elevate. It is too scientific.   Discipline among our <lb/> own troops is only maintained<lb/> by awfully severe physical<lb/> punishment and the<lb/> infliction of pain.   Thinking it over I don't <lb/> believe I would hand him<lb/> to D Coy to escort. It is
            <pb n="19" facs="L1916_2742_img_2161_19"/>
            19<lb/> whispered that prisoners get shot after<lb/> capture sometimes "when endeavouring<lb/> to escape." I couldn't <hi rend="underline">really</hi> permit<lb/> coldblooded murder to be done knowingly.<lb/> Some of it <hi rend="underline">is</hi> horrible.   I must close now with love to <lb/> all. No press or public please.   Your loving son.  W.A Montgomery
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>