<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4203">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Shaw to Martha Shaw, 19 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Samuel Shaw to his mother, Martha Shaw, apologising for the increasing time periods between letters as they have been very busy in the trenches lately. Samuel explains to his mother the difficulties of writing letters in the trenches.

Samuel Henry Shaw (1896-1967) was a sergeant with the 10th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers. He volunteered for active service in September 1914. Before enlisting Samuel was a member of the Portstewart Company, Coleraine Battalion, North Derry Regiment, Ulster Volunteer Force. Samuel served in France, and was wounded during the Battle of the Somme in July 1916 and again in early 1917 and in 1918. Before the War he was employed as a ironmonger&#39;s assistant. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4203</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0493">Samuel Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-02-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Martha Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1967</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4203_img_3574_1"  type="Letter"  url="39967dfaec295e1fd9726820911e4c6f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4203_img_3574_2"  type="Letter"  url="9987198c5d108aa0de011c495700b28f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4203_img_3574_1"/>
             Same Address   18 — 2 — 16   My Dear <lb/>Mother,   Just a few lines to let you know <lb/>I am well. I can't write so often now as <lb/>we are very busy we fare in the trenches. <lb/>we hear nothing but the roar of the <lb/>artillery, bombs &amp; trench mortars. I suppose <lb/>you saw in the paper where Millar <lb/>Hutton was home. Tell Jean I got <lb/>her letter all right, she said I started <lb/>Dear Sister &amp; ended Your Loving Son, I <lb/>intended the letter for you, but the <lb/>writing on the back of the card put <lb/>me wrong &amp; the trenches is not the <lb/>best place to write a letter in. One of <lb/>our chaps got a letter From his sweet <lb/>heart &amp; she was on to him. Some of <lb/>the boys were arguing which was <lb/>the most dangerous street (trench) <lb/>in our part of the lines he told <lb/>her in the letter by mistake
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4203_img_3574_2"/>
            Is the fishing or the weather improving <lb/>any. Tell everybody I was asking for <lb/>them. I think this is all at present. <lb/>With love to all.   I remain <lb/>Your Loving Son   Sammie.   P. S. Excuse the scribble as the <lb/>pencil was bad. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>