<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2620">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Ruth Duffin, 6 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her sister Ruth (1877-1968) concerning Celia&#39;s daily life in the London hospital. Celia discusses her difficulties with her shifts and new accommodation, meeting with her sister Dorothy and taking care of Australian and New Zealand soldiers arriving in from the Dardanelles. Additionally, she mentions that the majority of VADs working with her will most likely sign on again despite difficulties with the matron. 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/C/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2620</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0733">3rd London General Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1375">Ruth Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2620_img_2045_1"  type="Letter"  url="8c592200ea3d0c392acd1c3ab34314d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2620_img_2045_2"  type="Letter"  url="789d5523d1e9d058ea586e793a7818df.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2620_img_2045_1"/>
             3<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> London General   Dec. 6<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> 1915   Dear Ruth,   Here I am, unfortunately on night duty again. I went to get <lb/>my day off which I had arranged to spend with Dorothy and <lb/>was told I was to go on night. So at two o'clock I went off <lb/>to bed, and was on duty again at 7.30 in an enteric <lb/>ward which I hate. Not only this but I have had to change <lb/>my billetts and go into a house where the nurses are on <lb/>night. I have been spoilt so far with a single room and <lb/>now have to share one instead; fortunately my stable com- <lb/>panion seems a nice girl, her brother, Capt: Josse is the <lb/>registrar at the hospital, but I am disgusted at the <lb/>whole thing, and liked my old ward so much. I suppose <lb/>shall spend Xmas day in bed this year for a change.   I went up to town for an hour this morning to meet <lb/>Dorothy who was spending the night at the Grosvenor. She <lb/>was looking very well, but think very doubtful about <lb/>the engagement. I don't know what she intends doing, <lb/>apparently nothing at present. She went down to <lb/>Eastbourne to-day to see O. and talks of going on to <lb/>Cirencester. Mrs Lecky was taking me to the <lb/>theatre next week, but of course I can't go now.   There is an intake to-night and motors are driving up to <lb/>the door all the time. As my ward is full, I shan't be
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2620_img_2045_2"/>
            disturbed. All these men seem to be Australians or New <lb/>Zealanders from the Dardanelles, and most of them are convales- <lb/>cent, only one on <seg type="del">on</seg> 3 hourly feeds, but they all have to have <lb/>temperatures, respirations and pulses taken in the mornings, and <lb/>then I go across to the next-door ward and help <hi rend="underline">there</hi> too, as <lb/>some of the cases there are bad. One of the patients <lb/>seems to be quite mad and kept everybody awake all <lb/>night singing songs, and this morning refused to be <lb/>washed, so a man orderely had to be sent for.   We have been told to take all the red covers off the lamps <lb/>and wrap them in brown paper instead, so I suppose <lb/>zeppelins are expected to-night.   I wonder how you are getting on in your hotel. Will <lb/>you be full up next term. It must be a pretty big <lb/>job.   I think a good many of the V.A.D's here are going to <lb/>sign on again. I would like to go home in between, <lb/>but that seems impossible, and the matron won't take any- <lb/>body back here again who does. I suppose everybody <lb/>would rush off if she did. One nice <seg type="del">is</seg> surprise is, <lb/>that we are now to get at least £2 a <seg type="del">week</seg> month allowance <lb/>money as well as our £20. a year. What is happening <lb/>about Xmas presents this year. Are we giving to each other or <lb/>not this year. Please let me know.   I have no news, and only hope I won't be on <lb/>night work long.   Best love from   Celia. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>