<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0613">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí , 27 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley; 1881–1965) from his father, Patrick Langford Beazley. After enquiring after Piaras&#39;s sea journey to Dublin, Patrick writes about the increased employment opportunities for women. He claims that they are getting a good wage but not as high as the men they have replaced. Béaslaí was an English-born, influential member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fáinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/613</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-01-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0613_img_203_1"  type="Letter"  url="a78cd7184f26cada9aa9d8d1df52130a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0613_img_203_2"  type="Letter"  url="a5735d1ea76635fbab877c9c43404716.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0613_img_203_1"/>
                Glengariff,  Rudgrave Square,  Egremont,  Cheshire,    27<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Jan., 1916.   My dearest Pierce,   I hope you got through<lb/> your journey to Dublin <lb/><sic>allright</sic>. We were hoping <lb/> to have a line from you; <lb/> I have no doubt it will<lb/> come in a day or so. The<lb/> weather was, I think, pleasâ<lb/>ant for travelling, and I <lb/>dare say the sea was fairly<lb/> calm. If you had gone <lb/> the previous day you would <lb/> have found it pretty rough, if <lb/>one may judge from the conâ  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0613_img_203_2"/>
              dition of the <seg type="unclear">waves</seg>. We are <lb/> both well, thank God, but have<lb/> no news. There can be no <lb/> doubt that the women here<lb/> are taking advantage of the<lb/> chances offered them. They are <lb/> crowding into all the outâ<lb/>door employments in which <lb/> their services are demanded and <lb/> in a great many of the offiâ<lb/>ces they are performing the <lb/> work of clerks and bookâ<lb/>keepers. They are getting very <lb/>good wages, but not such high <lb/>pay as the men whom they reâ<lb/>place got. It is probable there <lb/> will be ructions on the subject <lb/> after the war.   Take good care of your health <lb/> and write. <seg type="closer"> With fondest love from mother and myself,<lb/> Ever affectionately   Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>