<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4303">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Horace Plunkett to Edward Carson, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Horace Plunkett</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Horace Plunkett (1854-1932) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Sir Horace Curzon Plunkett, Unionist MP, was an Anglo-Irish agricultural reformer, pioneer of agricultural cooperatives, supporter of Home Rule, and author.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4303</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0570">Horace Plunkett</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1025">The Plunkett House, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1932</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4303_img_3665_1"  type="Letter"  url="38c3048b1e88f348c047698ce68e01a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4303_img_3665_2"  type="Letter"  url="ae82b1a03637cf881239a7fb0f2fd032.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4303_img_3665_3"  type="Letter"  url="f48392a32e8b0adac7bba19d10350e4e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4303_img_3665_1"/>
             Plunkett 1916  15   THE PLUNKETT HOUSE,<lb/>DUBLIN.<lb/>Telegraphic Address:<lb/>Organise, Dublin.<lb/>3Telephone No. 1090.   D1507/A/16/4<lb/>PAGE 1 OF 3   4th May, 1916.    My dear Carson,   You have no doubt good reason to distrust my judgement<lb/>in political matters, but I do not think you have ever ques—<lb/>tioned my motives. At any rate you have always been glad to<lb/>listen to what I had to say, and, as I have a strong conviction<lb/>as to the great service which you might render to this coun—<lb/>try at the present moment, I am sure you will wish me to say<lb/>all that is in my mind.  I have been in Dublin every day, since the rebellion<lb/>broke out, on public duty of various kinds. Consequently, I have<lb/>a good deal of first—hand knowledge as to what is moving in the<lb/>minds of well—informed people who are as deeply concerned as<lb/>I am to find means by which the evil consequences of this de—<lb/>plorable affair may be minimised. Many exceptional mea—<lb/>sures will, of course, have to be resorted to. But there is one<lb/>which will immensely facilitate all the other efforts to bring<lb/>about co—operation between different sections of Irishmen<lb/>which the country had never needed so much as now.  Under martial law, the arms of the Irish Volunteers,<lb/>the Sinn Feiners and the Citizen Army are called in. As a<lb/>lawyer and as an Irish statesman you will realise that impossi— 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4303_img_3665_2"/>
             D1507/A/16/4  16   —:2:—   PAGE 2 OF 3  bility of carrying out such an order effectively. There will<lb/>be <hi rend="underline">b</hi> a great transfer of weapons not, I am afraid, to the<lb/>Government. In any case, the mere fact of leaving arms in<lb/>the hands of other irregular organisations who, however<lb/>loyal to what we believe to be the cause of Ireland, are<lb/>under no governmental control, might well do nearly as much<lb/>harm as the search for weapons will do good. If a Proclamation<lb/>were issued, calling upon us all, North and South, to hand in<lb/>to the Authorities any lethal weapons we possess, except of<lb/>course such as we are using in the service of the Government,<lb/>and if this were done at once, I believe an overwhelming<lb/>majority of the people would give their cordial approval. Of<lb/>course, immediately thereafter, regulations would be published<lb/>for giving permission to use guns for the destruction of<lb/>vermin and for  other  necessary purposes.  Such a measure would only be possible if you and<lb/>Redmond agreed to support it; and I think it would be better,<lb/>from every point of view, that the proposal should come from<lb/>you in the first instance, because it is obvious that your<lb/>followers in Ulster might say that they ought not to suffer on<lb/>account of happenings in which their Province had had no part.<lb/>But, my instinct tells me that if you came forward in the man—<lb/>ner proposed, three results would follow:— the immediate situa—<lb/>tion in all the disturbed parts of Ireland would be immensely<lb/>relieved; the mutual understanding of North and South, when 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4303_img_3665_3"/>
             D1507/17/16/4  17  PAGE 3 OF 3   —:3:—   <lb/>Ireland has to face the re—construction problems after  <lb/>war, would be at least hopeful, and your own influence, as<lb/>Leader of the Irish Unionists, would be strengthened both in<lb/>Ireland and in Great Britain.   Yours sincerely,<lb/>Horace Plunkett   The Right Honble.<lb/>Sir Edward Carson, K. C. M. P.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>