<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0690">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his father, Harford Hugh Montgomery, 29 September, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Montgomery (d. 1932) to his father, Harford Hugh (1866-1933). William writes of his postal arrangements. He explains that communication is becoming more difficult due to the problems with espionage behind the lines. To illustrate this he describes a meeting he attended concerning the Battle of Loos (September 1915) and an information leak which resulted in &#39;the Huns&#39; (Germans) knowing all the details and logistics of attack. William goes on to describe his living conditions in the trenches, including details of the difficulties they are experiencing with supplies as the men are forbidden to buy locally because it upsets the supply chain for civilians. When writing this letter William expresses respect for &#39;the Boches&#39; (Germans) on a number of occasions. This extends to his description of the techniques employed by German snipers. Montgomery also describes an incident of a night-time collision between both sides between lines.The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs in Belfast. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William Alexander, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sarah Montgomery, throughout the war. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/690</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-09-26</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2095">Monacherra, Malone Park,Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_1"  type="Letter"  url="1365d24ede24c1cf215ac09dee59f4e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_2"  type="Letter"  url="4dd7d66d9394dab34eb51131c731b19a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_3"  type="Letter"  url="cdbb818d7c1189e94526b52f976c7b1a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_4"  type="Letter"  url="17bde99219e859e7cd8992c9f6d43303.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_5"  type="Letter"  url="dd490f0c02eecfa2598c8b6fd8ad2305.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_6"  type="Letter"  url="ee7064240e16e8e41b3afd3eb056e451.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_7"  type="Letter"  url="38116cff285c267d86fd054a2c8032d6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_8"  type="Letter"  url="8c829270dbcf137b535bfc9b5677965b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_9"  type="Letter"  url="fa696d0963fba8acba6d10d17a92a30c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_10"  type="Letter"  url="f294927917a1434aa37e351dacc436a5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_11"  type="Letter"  url="6129bf78bc688b6c84e10110d43b9c49.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_12"  type="Letter"  url="167dddf9d539f3a9a7b4b2d7bf473e3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_13"  type="Letter"  url="a8b89f0f4ca71f17386c45151ac6cbd8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_14"  type="Letter"  url="5c4d7b1b04b9b15754853b59ebc4cad5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_15"  type="Letter"  url="f24e53d64e30d0dc348d105adda8c6a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_16"  type="Letter"  url="322b522befda2166aa9a3383070b33b2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_17"  type="Letter"  url="c76c275834621c17181c11fed61b2680.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_18"  type="Letter"  url="f5303df7ee553a710bfb36af0b9a62cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0690_img_2181_19"  type="Letter"  url="d1d4986ad373196e69573d5cea4a6ea8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_1"/>
                In the Field    29.12.15.   My dear Father &amp; <hi rend="underline">Mother</hi>   I have <lb/>father's letter dated on last <lb/>page with stamp 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> inst.   There seems to be a fate <lb/>about wires of a vital <lb/>nature addressed to the <lb/>office. I was very annoyed <lb/>that Jock McConnell's wire <lb/>got <sic>thro</sic> first. As the wire to <lb/>you the wire to Lizzie Hanna <lb/>and the wire Crozier sent. <lb/>were all handed by me to <lb/><hi rend="underline">an officer</hi> at the one time <lb/>who handed them to a <lb/>special Brigade office <lb/>Despatch rider to take at <lb/>top speed to an authorised <lb/>Post office for civilian  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_2"/>
              wires. A great deal of <lb/>very necessary formality <lb/>has to be gone thro' in order <lb/>to get a wire away at all. <lb/>This is because behind our <lb/>front lines living in our <lb/>midst are many I fear <lb/>very many clever brave <lb/>spies who undoubtedly <lb/>manage in marvellous <lb/>ways to communicate <lb/>very quickly &amp; very fully <lb/>accurate information of <lb/>almost everything that <lb/>goes on. I was taken <lb/>after dark last night to <lb/>the — Army Headquarters <lb/>in a motor bus to hear a <lb/>lecture on the Battle of Loos.   At that lecture which was  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_3"/>
              given in the presence of several hundred <lb/>officers all of ranks <seg type="del">up</seg> of lieutenant or <lb/>upwards (nearly all Captains at least) &amp; <lb/>included a very famous Army Commander, <lb/>the statement was definitely made that <lb/>altho' everything was kept absolutely <lb/>secret right up to the last moment even from <lb/>many of the high commanders when the attack <lb/> was actually launched the Huns <seg type="del">he</seg> knew <lb/>the frontage, time, dispositions, and even <lb/>the names of the regiments allotted to <lb/>different sectors &amp; their particular position <lb/>in the assault. They of course were <lb/>all ready in the place which we  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_4"/>
              fondly believed <seg type="del">were</seg> we <lb/>would take with 'benefit of <lb/>surprise. I could if I dare <lb/>tell, you other things about <lb/>the Battle of Loos which I <lb/>don't <hi rend="underline">think</hi> you have yet heard.   I send you the enclosed <lb/>note from my C.O. I was <lb/>just about to destroy it when <lb/>it occurred to me that you <lb/>might like to have it. You <lb/>always possessed a strong <lb/>family sentiment which I <lb/>often, I fear, ridiculed but really <lb/>admired. It is a simple <lb/>note put very nicely, but it is <lb/>nevertheless an order to 'carry on' <lb/>for another 48 hours with <lb/>practically no sleep after I had <lb/>just had a spell of what old <lb/>W. J. Jefferson would call <lb/>responsible work for a young <lb/>fellow which lasted 65 hours, <lb/>6 of which I slept &amp; then it was  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_5"/>
              on no down bed. 3/9 x 1 1/2 <lb/>planks propped up on <lb/>biscuit tins of various <lb/>heights a under leaky dug <lb/>out roof. My pillow Maynard <lb/>Sinclair's wet British <seg type="unclear">Warm</seg><lb/> &amp; my covering a wet shin <lb/>coat &amp; a much wetter Burberry. <lb/>So much for my bed &amp; I <hi rend="underline">did</hi><lb/>enjoy it too. After I woke <lb/>from my second spell <lb/>Maynard Sinclair (poor wee <lb/>devil) just sat &amp; 'turned over' <lb/>to me &amp; put his head down <lb/>among the debris of our <lb/>mess table &amp; in 10 seconds <lb/>was sound asleep. He wakened, <lb/>I remember, with the brand <lb/>of a much advertised <lb/>brand of cigarettes on his <lb/>brow, caused by making <lb/>a pillow of a tin of cigarettes  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_6"/>
              He did look funny. He is <lb/>just 19 father but the <lb/>purest of pure gold.   The business man who <lb/>tells me a young fellow <lb/>mustn't be trusted with <lb/>responsibility in the future <lb/>will be surprised at what <lb/>I tell him. I have trusted <lb/>this one to turn an Artillery <lb/>against an enemy whose <lb/>nearest trenches are 24 <lb/>yards from ours and <hi rend="underline">slept</hi><lb/>through it. My servant &amp; <lb/>I are thoroughly enjoying <lb/>ourselves with the Autostrap <lb/>razor you were so thoughtful <lb/>as to send me. I am getting <lb/>quite good with it. I am <lb/>very satisfied with it &amp; <lb/>don't want to change it   
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_7"/>
              I have had I think all <lb/>mother's lovely parcels for <lb/>which I am very grateful <lb/>some which have been advised <lb/>from other people as sent <lb/>14 days ago havent turned <lb/>up yet.   I just <hi rend="underline">love</hi> to hear some <lb/>of the Firms business 'shop' <lb/>It is such a relief from <lb/>ours. Please let me have <lb/> letters about it just like <lb/>your last. I thank you <lb/>for your good wishes in the <lb/>New year which I heartily <lb/>reciprocate. I shall be <lb/>in the trenches on new years <lb/>eve &amp; new year's day<seg type="del">s</seg> I was <lb/>also in on Xmas day.  In fact to make it worse <lb/>we were relieved that  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_8"/>
              day. This pen is the <lb/>greatest possible luxury.   I had a very nice letter from Horace from hospital <lb/>in Rouen dated 26/12/15.   It is written in ink in <lb/>his own handwriting. It <lb/>has been passed round his <lb/>coy &amp; and the officers so that they <lb/>can see for themselves that <lb/>Horace can see too. I <lb/><hi rend="underline">almost</hi> stood myself a <lb/>drink when I got it. I <lb/>go very shy of drink. I <lb/>never drink water of course <lb/>without a little whisky or <lb/>chloride of lime or petrol <lb/>or all three in it. But beyond <lb/>that no spirits not even a <lb/>tot of rum. Then if I do <lb/>happen to get really badly  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_9"/>
              chilled and foundered I will <lb/>get the benefit of it. But <lb/>I really believe hot cocoa <lb/>or tea is better &amp; I drink <lb/>oceans of both. I sent to <lb/>the A&amp;N Stores &amp; got a <lb/>pocket primus stove from <lb/>them, which will help in <lb/>the culinary department <lb/>very considerably. The fuel <lb/>question with us is very <lb/>acute now. There is some <lb/>hitch about the supply &amp; <lb/>in consequence our men <lb/>are suffering damnably.   We are now forbidden to <lb/>buy locally as it upsets <lb/>supplies available to <lb/>civilians but — a lot of <lb/>things happen in the Army   
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_10"/>
              You might tell Charlie <lb/>McCann &amp; Miss McDermott <lb/>I haven't had their long <lb/>looked for letters yet.   One meets all sorts of <lb/>people here continually <lb/>for instance Bass Copper <lb/>called in my mess today <lb/>to see me but I was out &amp; <lb/>he didnt wait &amp; he didnt <lb/>even take the trouble to <lb/>tell any of my officers <lb/>where he was stationed.   I also entertained Charlie <lb/>McCanns pal Lindsay <lb/>from lough Neagh &amp; we <lb/>were talking about Charlie <lb/>&amp;yacht boating in my <lb/>dug out just before Lindsay <lb/>went out to try some <lb/>new telephone instrument  
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_11"/>
              by means of which it is possible to tap <lb/>messages thro' their earths. He got his <lb/>earthpin in within 2 yards of the Bosch <lb/>Defence wire but couldn't catch any <lb/>messages 'on earth'. The Hun <lb/>is too intelligent to put his earth pin in <lb/>within at least a hundred yards of <lb/>his front line. All he got was a good <lb/>wetting, his trousers practically torn off him <lb/>and a real war with snipers all on his <lb/>own. He wasnt hit coming back &amp; <lb/>when he got in to report return to me <lb/>he was perfectly at ease &amp; happy.   
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_12"/>
              The Hun has worked this <lb/>earth trick on us more <lb/>than once &amp; got <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the <lb/>messages that passed for <lb/>days. I have the greatest <lb/>possible respect for them.   I like them least when <lb/>they are quietest.   Two of our officers have <lb/>been recommended for <lb/>awards of honour — Stevenson <lb/>and Gould — Jock Stevenson <lb/>is well worth a D.S.O. &amp; <lb/>Gould a military cross. <lb/>Both for patrol work. <lb/>Stevenson carried in a <lb/>wounded man under heavy <lb/>fire a distance of 300 yards <lb/>after his own revolver had <lb/><seg type="unclear">died</seg> knocked out of his  
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_13"/>
              hand by a rifle bullet.  The wounded man was <lb/>hit again when Stevenson <lb/>was carrying him &amp; died <lb/>a few hours after he got <lb/>in. He couldn't have lived <lb/>anyway as he had hideous <lb/>abdominal injuries caused <lb/>by a bomb explosion.   There was 'some war' <lb/>that night 'tween lines'.   We don't know &amp; I don't <lb/>expect the Bosches know <lb/>exactly what did happen, <lb/>but it started by a strong <lb/>patrol of ours colliding <lb/>with a strong patrol of <lb/>theirs in absolute darkness. <lb/>They all opened fire on <lb/>each other at once with <lb/>bombs revolvers &amp; rifles   
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_14"/>
              This was all quite plain <lb/>&amp; straight sailing but our <lb/>people getting the worst of <lb/>it were ordered to retire <lb/>as we saw reinforcements <lb/>arrive for the Bosch who <lb/>were even then easily <lb/>twice our strength. We <lb/>retired but a new war <lb/>started immediately &amp; the <lb/>last we saw of the performance <lb/>was the two Bosch parties <lb/>busy killing each other.   They actually got hand <lb/>to hand at the finish. <lb/>They are reported to have <lb/>done the thing thoroughly.   I was listening to the <lb/>performance comfortably <lb/>on my front line <seg type="unclear">firestep</seg>  
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_15"/>
              and they certainly took their time at it.  I of course thought it was us &amp; them <lb/>otherwise I should have helped them <lb/>to a speedy understanding by turning <lb/>one of the two machine guns now at <lb/>my own disposal on to them.   A sudden burst of machine gun <lb/>fire traversing along your fire <lb/>parapet at night when your working <lb/>parties are usually up on top is enough <lb/>to make even the dead roots of my <lb/>top hair tingle. It is a hideous <lb/>sound. The Hun Gun is slower than  
            <pb n="16" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_16"/>
              our gun but 450 rounds <lb/>per minute from nowhere <lb/>arriving everywhere is <lb/>quite fast enough to make <lb/>one duck. Although what <lb/>good ducking is when <lb/>one hears the <hi rend="underline">crack</hi> of the <lb/>bullet I don't know.  A man never hears the <lb/>one that hits him. I <lb/>heard the one that got <lb/>Horace. I hear it yet.  A damned horrible thing <lb/>happened to the Batt. of regulars <lb/>we relieved last time on the <lb/>day we relieved. Their C.O. <lb/>was going along the line <lb/>he met a soldier in a <lb/>narrow place. The soldier <lb/>got up on the firestep to <lb/>make way. He forgot the  
            <pb n="17" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_17"/>
              parapet was damaged at <lb/>that point He lost the <lb/>side of his head and, of <lb/>course, his life. The C.O. <lb/>was upset about it. Organisation <lb/>of German snipers is marvellous. <lb/>And the patience of the <lb/>blighters is horrible. They <lb/>wont fire for days just to <lb/>encourage you &amp; then <lb/>when you have got lulled <lb/>into a feeling of <hi rend="underline">very</hi><lb/>false security they play <lb/>some most ingenious trick <lb/>and get someone or perhaps <lb/>more. It is known they <lb/>have a sliding scale of <lb/>Head money. It is said to <lb/>be Â£2-10-0 (50 marks) <lb/>for an officer. I wish I  
            <pb n="18" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_18"/>
              could make a prisoner of <lb/>the one that got Horace. I <lb/>should have him escorted <lb/>to safety by men from D <lb/>Coy. These of course sound <lb/>awful things by a warm <lb/>fine in a comfortable <lb/>room, but father, men <lb/>who have seen a loved officer <lb/>shot before their eyes are <lb/>never quite the same <lb/>again. They are human <lb/>beings &amp; war — this war — does <lb/>not elevate. It is too scientific.  Discipline among our <lb/>own troops is only maintained <lb/>by awfully severe physical <lb/>punishment and the <lb/>infliction of pain.  Thinking it over I don't <lb/>believe I would hand him <lb/>to D Coy. to escort. It is  
            <pb n="19" facs="L1916_0690_img_2181_19"/>
              whispered that prisoners get shot after <lb/>capture sometimes 'when endeavouring <lb/>to escape' . I couldn't <hi rend="underline">really</hi> permit <lb/>coldblooded murder to be done knowingly. <lb/> Some of it <hi rend="underline">is</hi> horrible.  I must close now with love to <lb/>all. No press or public please. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son.   <hi rend="underline">W. Montgomery</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>