<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1233">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nannie Beazley (née Hickey) to Piaras Béaslaí, 17 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nannie Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Nannie Beazley to her son Piaras Béaslaí (1881–1965). Nannie fills her interned son in on happenings back home. She has settled his account with his landlady and she is organising his affairs and property back home. In general, the content is mainly of a trivial nature. She reminds him to always act as gentlemen despite his current situation. Béaslaí was an English born influential member of the IRB. He joined the Irish Volunteers on their foundation late in 1913. When visiting his parents he smuggled guns to Ireland. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers.Béaslaí was an officer during the Easter Rising. He was court-martialled and sentenced to five years’ for his part. In prison he wrote and memorised poems about his captivity. This letter is part of a collection of letters by Piaras’ parents, mostly during Béaslai’s internment. After his release he soon became involved in politics.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Collection List 44, MS 33973-5-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1233</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0676">Nannie Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-07-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1233_img_42_1"  type="Letter"  url="4d0ae3ddd74cee079b3d589da9ed1024.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1233_img_42_1"/>
                July 17-1916   My darling boy,   It seems strange to write to you as you<lb/> are; but thank God you are cheerful &amp; well &amp; no<lb/> matter how you are situated you will always remember<lb/> you are a gentleman &amp; act accordingly. Father has<lb/> told you every scrap of news, so I must confine myself to<lb/> strictly business matters. We have settled that small<lb/> account with your late Landlady, &amp; have recieved all your<lb/> belongings. They were all carefully packed, &amp; arrived safely.<lb/> I got no books except some publications of your own.<lb/> I have been troubled over the books &amp; then fancied you<lb/> might have left them at your office; but Langford does not<lb/> mention anything about them. I believe ha has got your<lb/> 'Bike' and is trying to trace your watch and chain, &amp; silver cigarette<lb/> case etc. I got from Portland your grey navy suit, boots, socks<lb/> &amp; hat. I have got some of your clothes cleaned, &amp; will get<lb/> every thing in order for you in your room against your<lb/> return. I am bearing up well, &amp; find my garden<lb/> &amp; greenhouse a great comfort. I have had a most<lb/> magnificent show of roses this summer, &amp; everything else<lb/> has flourished as will in the garden &amp; greenhouse. We<lb/> are expecting Langford for his holidays on Sunday next<lb/> &amp; father is going to Bray on Uncle James invitation,<lb/> I could not go for I have to meet Lang. They are<lb/> expecting Charlie O'Callaghan home from London next<lb/> month and his mother is seriously ill. Frank crosses<lb/> over often from Dublin. Things are awfully quiet here<lb/> now so many people in mourning, no one going<lb/> away for holidays. I am hoping to see the Murphy<lb/> cousins one of these days before Norah returns to<lb/> college. A great many friends are interested in<lb/> you, &amp; are always <sic>enquiring</sic> about you. Of course we<lb/> have no fresh news. God bless you son my darling boy! Keep<lb/> your spirits up! The time won't be long slipping by and we shall <lb/> all be happy again at home. <seg type="closer"> With my hearts love, yours fondly  Mother. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>