<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4252">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 3 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/89</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4252</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4252_img_3619_1"  type="Letter"  url="1b39f448e80419190ec50d1ff7588ec2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4252_img_3619_2"  type="Letter"  url="024b5a25aac213780a4c089fec11f30d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4252_img_3619_1"/>
             3 Dec   My x the p r   Such a nice long letter form p r last night quite bucked <lb/> up the b w , &amp; as it was dated Tuesday there ought to be an <lb/>accumulation of 3 extra letters en route. Letters come in a most <lb/> erratic way, &amp; it may be the Xmas disorganisation already felt.   Would you let Sir E know that I think the brewing <lb/> troubles between our men &amp; the Nationalists seem to have <lb/> blown over &amp; I have every hope there will be no trouble <lb/> unless J.R makes another visit or speech of a provocative nature. <lb/> This caution especially applies to Xmas when our men will <lb/> be a little on their metal.<!-- mettle -->   Would you let Gen' P know that Gen H P is leaving <lb/> this week or next &amp; is expecting an appointment at home in <lb/> a higher rank. If he is given one &amp; not Gen P it will be <lb/> one of the most disgraceful things possible. He has not been <lb/> fit either physically (or mentally owing to physical causes) <lb/> since he came out, &amp; there can be no comparison in the <lb/> relative value of the 2 men. If he is supposed to have had <lb/> practical experience out here, I can only state that Gen P saw <lb/> more in his 2 days than the other in his 2 months. I should <lb/> like Gen P to be told this frankly.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4252_img_3619_2"/>
             I had a 75 motor drive last <lb/> night,&amp; ought to have had <lb/> a violent end. We stopped to let some waggons go bye, &amp; started <lb/> again, when White, who luckily was driving us thought <lb/> something was wrong &amp; pulled up, <seg type="del">we </seg> we found our 2 front wheels <lb/> had become uncoupled ! If we had been moving fast ! !   I see in today's gazette that the man who succeeded me <lb/> at the War Office &amp; who has been there ever since has been made <lb/> a brevet Lieut Colonel. He has no war experience &amp; was considered <lb/> rather a rotter!   Please give my best Salaams to Sir George &amp;  &amp; Lady <lb/> R &amp; to all our old friends whom you may meet   In view of what we have given I think you may have <lb/> your  travelling  exes paid if they again press it, but not otherwise, i e do not <lb/> remind them or put them down.   I am writing a home letter, &amp; also to Sir Edward to <lb/> let him know that Comyn Maim &amp; Ryan are all good chaps, <lb/> in case your remark to Lady C may do them mischief.   I watch the wind now with the greatest interest, <lb/> poor little p r — peagreen reptile I fear — ! But I think it <lb/> plucky of you &amp; that you have done the right thing.   I do like to think of you with all the others, but how long <lb/> you will manage not to take sides I don't know, in spite of <lb/> all your cleverness    Your B W   WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>