<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2727">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Tate to his mother, Millicent Tate (née Farren), 6 August, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Tate</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Tate to his mother in which he writes about his unit, the 3rd Sappers and the natives helpers. Their task is  is bridge building, scheduled for completion by Christmas. He spends time fishing but gave up swimming since he heard sharks come up all the way to Bhagdad.He also mentions that  the Ulster Division got &#34;pretty badly cut up&#34;

This letter is from the Alec C Tate collection. Tate served with British army in India before he married Millicent Farren and started a family in Whiteabbey Co. Antrim. Their sons, James and William continued the military tradition and enlisted with the British army with James serving as a Second Lieutenant with the Indian Expeditionary Force. James spent the majority of the war in India during which time the Indian Expeditionary Force was dispatched to Mesopotamia. This letter is part of a collection that he wrote to his parents detailing his movements and his day to day experience.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Tate Papers, D2859/2/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2727</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0347">James Tate</persName>
              <date>1916-08-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0868">I.E.F.D.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Millicent Tate</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1676">Slieve na Failthe, Whiteabbey, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2727_img_2148_1"  type="Letter"  url="e26c7bbfc1ec04acc03225cab35228ce.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2727_img_2148_2"  type="Letter"  url="2b393bc027e0455643f2ea400da7225c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2727_img_2148_3"  type="Envelope"  url="a0f5474be7d80b55c2cd6c1d84e62253.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2727_img_2148_1"/>
             I.E.F.D   6/8/16   My Dear Mother   Thank you very much for your letter of last <lb/>week. I am very sorry indeed to hear that <lb/>you have been having such a bad <lb/>time all round with people going sick <lb/>and I hope they are all going on as well <lb/>as can be expected. Things are just going <lb/>along here same as usual. In fact the days <lb/>are so alike that I thought tis was Wednesday. <lb/>It seems that it is Saturday &amp; a mail day so <lb/>I got a shock. I have got more used to the ways <lb/>of the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> sappers. I was most awful fed <lb/> up with the whole <sic>bussiness</sic> at first as <lb/>I like the madrasses much better than <lb/>all the other sorts of niggers put together. <lb/>He always smiles &amp; nothing worries him — also <lb/>he is not afraid to do hared work now <lb/>&amp; then. Also of course I was very fed up <lb/>leaving Prince who was an awfully nice man <lb/>&amp; a great C.O. However things have more or less <lb/>shaken themselves down &amp; are going fine. <lb/>The bridge shows no sign of being finished
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2727_img_2148_2"/>
            before Xmas anyway but it is hoped that we <lb/>get away before that anyway.   I have been fishing a lot but have given up <lb/>bathing till I hear more about it as there is a <lb/>yarn going that a man got nabbed by a shark <lb/>the other day near here. Sharks go right up <lb/>to Baghdad not big ones but quite big enough <lb/>to take out a nasty <seg type="del">bight</seg> bite.   I see Bundie is wounded &amp; missing they must have <lb/>had a very warm time at the front &amp; I hope <lb/> they make good. Judging by the casualties <lb/>the Water Division must have been pretty badly <lb/>cut up.   Well the mail boat may come anytime <lb/>now so I will shut up as there is really <lb/>no news. I am still very well <lb/>&amp; I hope you are having an easier <lb/>time than when I heard last. <lb/>With love to all at home.   <hi rend="underline">From you loving son Jimmy</hi> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2727_img_2148_3"/>
             Mrs A.C. Tate <lb/>Slieve —na —Failthe <lb/>Whiteabbey <lb/>Co Antrim <lb/>IRELAND 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>