<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3758">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Captain Wilfrid Spender to Colonel James Craig, 4 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Copy of a letter from Captain Wilfrid Spender (1876-1960) to Colonel James Craig (1871-1940) regarding opening events at the Battle of the Somme. Spender writes that he has no news of Craig&#39;s brother, Major Clarence Craig (1864-1938), but praises the spirit with which the 36th (Ulster) Division displayed. Spender fears that due to their lack of success the military endeavour of the 36th will go unrecognised but that the Ulster spirit is determined to serve the Empire regardless of recognition. Spender then wishes Craig luck with his negotiations on Ulster&#39;s behalf.

Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.

Sir James Craig threw himself into the creation and development of the 36th (Ulster) Division following the outbreak of war in 1914. However, due to illness Craig was not able to leave for the front with his division and was forced to resign his commission in April 1916. Following this he went to Westminster to fight for the acceptance of a permanent six-county exclusion during the Lloyd George diplomatic offensive of the early summer of 1916. Craig would go on to become the first Prime Minister of Northern Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers D3642-A-2-5-5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3758</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1198">James Craig</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3758_img_3144_1"  type="Letter"  url="3ef880c9f3a3d19396cdbe064c41d499.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3758_img_3144_1"/>
             Copy of letter from Capt. Spender<lb/>to Colonel James Craig.  <lb/><hi rend="underline"></hi>  4th JULY, 1916.    My dear Colonel:—   I have been trying to obtain more definite<lb/>news of your brother before writing, but beyond the bare state—<lb/>ment that he was wounded, and left in the German lines on the<lb/>retirement, I can get nothing definite, and have been unable to<lb/>go and make enquiries on the spot from the battalion. I have no<lb/>doubt you are being given all possible information available<lb/>direct by the battalion.  I am very sorry for your anxiety.  Your brother's field company is now attached<lb/>for duty to another Division for defensive purposes.  I cannot write much of the battle. Our men<lb/>behave as never man have done before. Nothing could stop them,<lb/>and they won right through up to the last German lines of Defence.<lb/>Neither of our flanking divisions were able to advance at all,<lb/>and we were thus in a narrow salient two miles into the German<lb/>lines, unable to send up supplies, and raked on the right and left<lb/>with every form of devilment, including glass bombs. When the<lb/>division was withdrawn and replaced, we were able to hand over<lb/>two of the German lines, and the third cannot be occupied by either<lb/>side.  I had to watch the fight powerless to help.<lb/>Everyone who was there belonging to other Corps was dumbfounded<lb/>by what our men did. Half of the Infantry of the Division deserved<lb/>the V.C. Nothing I believe has been done like it before — and<lb/>that is all one can say.  The facts will never be given out I fear, as everyone<lb/>dislikes being associated with lack of success. It seems the<lb/>Ulstermen's fate to do the most incredi ble deeds for the Empire,<lb/>and to get no recognition, but I would rather be an Ulsterman than<lb/>a Peer of the realm, after what I saw.   It is impossible for me to write details. Some day<lb/>perhaps I may be able to give you a tale of the battle as the<lb/>men rushed forward shouting No surrender boys, but not now.  May your present negotiations bring prosperity to<lb/>Ulster.  Forgive this very poor scrawl, but my eyes are only<lb/>just recovering from lachrymatory shell effects.<lb/>The General refused to select any battalion for special<lb/>mention, maintaining that the Devision as a whole has done.<lb/>He also says no other troops could have done what our men did.   Yours ever, <lb/>W.B.W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>