<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2255">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Hubert Montgomery to Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery, 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Hubert Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Charles Hubert Montgomery (1876-1942) to his father Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924). Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Hugh Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland. His son Charles Hubert, was a civil servant and diplomat and master of the ceremonies, an important diplomatic position, in 1916.
In the letter Montgomery discusses a letter which his father had drafted and was considering publishing in the &#39;Times&#39; newspaper. He also discusses the possibility of a settlement of the Irish question after the Easter Rising and the position of Ulster Unionism.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2255</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1224">Charles Hubert Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1816">Pyrford Green, Woking, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName >None</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1942</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2255_img_1699_1"  type="Letter"  url="ccc9c7d0f64acd86e2ae073491eb51ed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2255_img_1699_2"  type="Letter"  url="929a818f722fa6b1d5e46cff5190f2bd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2255_img_1699_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>  Pyrford Green, <lb/>Woking.   29th May, 1916.   My dear Father,   So far as I myself am concerned I should not care at <lb/>all about any results that the letter that you thought of <lb/>sending to the "Times" might have, from my point of view; but, <lb/>though I think it is a perfectly correct analysis of the <lb/>situation, I think it would probably be better tactics not to <lb/>publish it now. I quite agree that this idea of pushing through <lb/>a lasting settlement on the top of the Rebellion is insane : if <lb/>anything came of it it would be putting a direct premium on <lb/>Rebellion and, as you say, enabling the (very properly shot) <lb/>rebels to be held up as martyrs and heroes; but it does not <lb/>seem to me that, unless Carson and the other Unionists, with <lb/>whom I suppose there will be a consultation, have gone off their <lb/>chump any settlement (if by settlement is meant some sort <lb/>of Home Rule at once) can be arrived at. I should think much <lb/>the best plan would be that you and others should rub into <lb/>everyone on our side who is likely to be consulted the views <lb/>expressed in your letter, and get them to stick out on those <lb/>lines - that is to say the disasterous effect at home and abroad <lb/>of what would really be a concession to the shades of the shot <lb/>Sinn Feiners. If they use <hi rend="underline">that</hi> as their platform rather than <lb/>the die hard Home Rule attitude, it will be much more difficult, <lb/>in fact, if properly put, it ought to be impossible for the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2255_img_1699_2"/>
            Nationalists to manoeuvre them into the position of being the party <lb/> which opposes a settlement and, (they, the Nationalists, &amp; their <lb/> radical friends would no doubt say) hampers the Government from <lb/>their own selfish point of view: that is the line which the <lb/> Nationalists seem to me to be sure to try and take, and it ought <lb/> to be carefully guarded against : and any utterances in the press <lb/> that they can use for the same line of argument are sure to be <lb/> snatched at by Home Rulers.   If I were you I would concentrate on getting these points <lb/> rubbed into anyone that Lloyd George is likely to come at - <lb/>beginning with Carson. I suppose there are a good many other <lb/> people who will be consulted as well as he and a good many of <lb/> them may need bringing up, as they may be distracted by the <lb/> idea that they should not be uncompromising for fear of hampering <lb/>the conduct of war.    Yours   H. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>