<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1463">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Lynch to Mabel FitzGerald, 28 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Lynch</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A Letter from Robert Lynch to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). The writer expresses sorrow at the &#39;horrible sentence&#39; imposed on her husband. He admires the way that Desmond FitzGerald and The O&#39;Rahilly, (1875-1916), &#39;went in&#39; (to the GPO) having initially tried to stop the Rising. The writer promises to make representations on Mr FitzGerald&#39;s behalf and expresses that an amnesty will see him free when Home Rule is established. He writes that the English were unwise to carryout the executions as the only served to dignify the insurgents. He regrets the loss of his friend, John MacDermott (Seán MacDiarmada, 1883-1916, executed on 12 May 1916) but the bitterest losses were James Connolly (1868-1916, executed 12 May 1916), and Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916). The writer criticises Patrick Pearse (1879-1916, one of the Rising leaders, also executed on 3 May 1916) for his &#39;bloodshed gospel&#39;, which he describes as &#39;a wild delusion.&#39;Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1591/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1463</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0566">Robert Lynch</persName>
              <date>1916-05-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0513">Hampstead, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1463_img_913_1"  type="Letter"  url="7b84475c0e88bd7cef78046f57f7c5c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1463_img_913_2"  type="Letter"  url="53b2ae5b7fc892e81f2d1c20f52d0a7f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1463_img_913_1"/>
                14 <seg type="unclear">telegraph</seg> Hill,   Hampstead,  N.W.    28th May, 1916   My dear Mabel,   I have been wanting to write to you for some <lb/>time best to say how sorry I was about the horrible <lb/>sentence on Fitz. You probably guess what I thought of <lb/>Pearse &amp; the leaders, but the way Fitz &amp; the O'Rahilly <lb/>went in after trying to stop the affair was the sort of <lb/>heroic thing to which we all have to take off our hats. <lb/>I'll certainly get the facts of Fitz's behaviour &amp; of his <lb/>non-combatancy put before any people of influence I <lb/>can get at. He <seg type="del">cautiously</seg>ought to be treated as a <lb/>political prisoner at once, &amp; an amnesty is certain, <lb/>I should say, within a very short time of a <lb/>Home Rule Parliament's coming into existence. I feel <lb/>exactly as you do about the executions. The English, <lb/>I think, were mad to permit them from their own <lb/>point-of-view. They seem to me to have given the <lb/>movement a <seg type="unclear">national</seg> dignity it would not have <lb/>had if Asquith or Maxwell or Redmond or any- <lb/>body had been as wise as Botha. Poor John Mac <lb/>Dermott, I knew him best &amp; liked him best of <lb/> them all, but I feel Connolly is the bitterest <lb/> loss. He &amp; Skeffington. Pearse obviously died like <lb/> a hero, but I have always thought his 'blood-  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1463_img_913_2"/>
              shed' gospel of nationalism a wild delusion &amp; a break <lb/>away from everything for which Davis stood. However, I <lb/>mustn't be controversial while you're in the midst of <lb/>this horror &amp; trouble. I do hope it won't be long <lb/>till Fitz is safe at home again.   I'm sending you one or two <hi rend="underline">Statesmans</hi>&amp; <hi rend="underline">Nations</hi>. <lb/> I've been able to write very little about the in- <lb/>surrection myself. Shaw had a wonderful letter in the <lb/><hi rend="underline">Daily News</hi>, which I'll send you. I hope the babies <lb/>are well again. Perhaps, we'll see you in Dublin <lb/>in July. We'll get over if we possibly can, babies <lb/>&amp; all. I'm so glad you liked Sylvia's novel. She's <lb/>got a book of verse &amp; sketches coming out in the <lb/>Autumn. I'd write more, only I've about half- <lb/>a-dozen other letters to get off before supper.   With all the good wishes &amp; hopes in the world. <seg type="closer"> Yours ever  Robert Lynch </seg> Miss Dryhurst saw Griffith &amp; Alderman Cole <lb/>in Wandsworth Prison this week. I've written to <lb/>Griffith to know if I might go &amp; see him, <lb/>but perhaps he would rather not as I know he looks <lb/>on me as a renegade.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>