<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0433">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (1866-1955). In this letter, Marie thanks her mother for sending news of her family and also for sending tobacco, which Marie is keeping for &#39;her Paddies&#39;. Marie also describes her role as a VAD in great detail.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>France Letters, France Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/433</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1543">Hardelot, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1257">Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_1"  type="Letter"  url="a83f4ed5c5109d211bad361da8fb1ee8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_2"  type="Letter"  url="d4037ea56fa19dad4fdd692156d8729b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_3"  type="Letter"  url="0b7149635ff7f04c86a62b56ff32662c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_4"  type="Letter"  url="4536940065214d3ea51f082bd0433389.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_5"  type="Letter"  url="e478339a6ff3df616973886b95fbdbe9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_6"  type="Letter"  url="a5a0ea12efa8ad55fa295a30f4279f6f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_7"  type="Letter"  url="955770211b6e799d678a594ed1f43a65.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_8"  type="Letter"  url="75eb759eb59e2fdc0910e7d9f1a4df93.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_9"  type="Letter"  url="6425ca4d8bc1c13da610a53926cd714a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0433_img_1768_10"  type="Letter"  url="d0a1b799ac53b4885cdfb19959a1179a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_1"/>
                25 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> G. Hospital   <hi rend="underline">B. E. F.</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Wednesday</hi> My very dearest Mother,   It is ages since I <lb/> wrote to you but I think I <lb/> warned you in my last letter <lb/> that I might not have time <lb/> to write. I have a great deal <lb/> to say &amp; tell you in this letter <lb/> but must start off by thanking <lb/> you a 1000 times for sending <lb/> me the wire. I was greatly <lb/> relieved to hear Gerald was alright <lb/> but sorry to think of him being <lb/> back on duty, however we must <lb/> trust in Our Lord that he &amp; all those <lb/> most dear to us may come safely <lb/> through. I hope you have had good  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_2"/>
              news from Tommy lately &amp; that he <lb/> is still out of danger zone. I am <lb/> afraid he &amp; Dicke will find the <lb/> heat very much. I must also <lb/> thank you Ethel &amp; Desmond for <lb/> the parcels with vegetables etc. I <lb/> have not had time to cook peas <lb/> yet as they just arrived when <lb/> we got very busy. The Tobacco <lb/> arrived safely last night what <lb/> ripping stuff &amp; how they will enjoy <lb/> it. I am keeping it for my <lb/> Paddies. The Photos also arrived <lb/> last night &amp; I think on the whole <lb/> they are quite good much better <lb/> than the last I like the Oval <lb/> full face by far the best in fact <lb/> every one here does &amp; thinks it very <lb/> good. I also rather like the sitting <lb/> down one only it makes me <lb/> look like the mother of 12.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_3"/>
               2 <lb/> the way I am sitting, the 3/4 length <lb/> is not bad but as you say very <lb/> like the 1 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> lot, if you think it <lb/> wise to get a few different yet <lb/> whichever of the 3/4 length you <lb/> like best, but I would put nearly <lb/> all of the Oval Full Face — &amp; <lb/> when they come, will you please <lb/> give one to Uncle Charlie, he is <lb/> such a dear to me I had <lb/> such a nice long letter from <lb/> him <sic>to night</sic>. Aunt Lissy does <lb/> not seem so well since they <lb/> went to Howth. I really think <lb/> the sea air is very bad for <lb/> Rheumatic people —   Now I better start off by telling <lb/> you all about my life here.   Since last writing I have had <lb/> a change — to the Tents.   On Friday last Matron came up <lb/> about 5.30 to know if I would <lb/> go down to the Medical Tents to  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_4"/>
              Bed Bath 8 bad gas cases. I understood <lb/> when going down it was only <lb/> for the evening so next morning went <lb/> on duty as usual &amp; about 7.45 <lb/> Matron came up &amp; said she wish- <lb/> ed me to go down to Tents S.7. <lb/> which were just being opened &amp; <lb/> a convoy in them, so down I <lb/> ran to find every bed full noth <lb/> ing ready &amp; only a staff nurse <lb/> we had not even a dressing <lb/> lotion or any thing only just a <lb/> bar table in the dressing tent <lb/> but I am glad to say most of <lb/> the beds had sheets &amp; blankets <lb/> on so the men were able to <lb/> get to bed after their baths <lb/> those that were not able to <lb/> walk about. at about 12 p.m. <lb/> we had things fairly straight <lb/> &amp;and the M. O. came round. I cannot <lb/> describe to you how they all  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_5"/>
              look &amp; their dressings &amp; wounds <lb/> just covered with mud, which <lb/> had just to be taken off so <lb/> as not to keep the M.O. waiting <lb/> there were 3 with bullets in their <lb/> legs, so he said nurse, run off <lb/> for the freezing stuff &amp; scalpel <lb/> &amp; then &amp; there he operated &amp; <lb/> took out the bullets. I do not <lb/> know how the men stood it. <lb/> We spent till six <sic>O'ck</sic> that <lb/> evening doing dressings &amp; after <lb/> that there was all the ordinary <lb/> work cleaning up &amp; beds to <lb/> make so of course except for <lb/> our meals we did not get off <lb/> the whole Hospital was in the <lb/> same condition only of course <lb/> they had been running &amp; opened <lb/> for some time. The next  day  was <lb/> much the same. Then Matron <lb/> came along &amp; told Sister she wish  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_6"/>
              ed me to be responsible for S. 8 Link <lb/> when they were opened, this is simply <lb/> ripping &amp; only hope I shall work <lb/> it alright it has not been opened <lb/> yet so I am still in S.7. but <lb/> am trying to get it fairly well <lb/> settled so as not to have to <lb/> rush when another big convoy <lb/> comes. Sister Mackenzie who I <lb/> worked for 1st of all must have <lb/> given Matron a very good <lb/> report of me because when I <lb/> went the other day to sign <lb/> on Matron was charming and <lb/> told me she was very satisfied <lb/> and considered me one of the senior <lb/> &amp; responsible V.A,D.'s. I need not <lb/> tell you I immediately thought <lb/> of you &amp; felt it might be a <lb/> pleasure for you to hear this <lb/> after all the care worry &amp; <lb/> trouble you have had in bringing <lb/> up. It is really very lucky  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_7"/>
              on my part my present Sister <lb/> is charming, there are three of us <lb/> in J 7 Tents now which is 1/2 a <lb/> division and S8 will be the other <lb/> half which will be mine when <lb/> open. I am always on alone in <lb/> the afternoon or evening. The <lb/> fighting seems terrible but up <lb/> to this we have been doing <lb/> very well and hope shall continue <lb/> and end it quickly. How soon <lb/> do you think it will be over? <lb/> I had such a nice long letter <lb/> from Gerald M. to-night he <lb/> seems to be having a very <lb/> busy time but writes in great <lb/> form and seems to be enjoying it.   I have destroyed my hands <lb/> with creasot the other day by <lb/> using it too strong they have <lb/> all cracked &amp; are stinging. hurt  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_8"/>
              terrible but it is all in a life <lb/> time. The tents are very nice in <lb/> sun shine but on wet days they <lb/> are awful it is pouring here <lb/> with a terrible gale.    I hope you have not forgotten <lb/> about your change of air.- <lb/> I hear Ethel is off to Lough <lb/> Derg what a saint I hope <lb/> she will not forget a sinner <lb/> like me. I had to miss Mass <lb/> Sunday we were so busy <lb/> If you are getting any one of the standing <seg type="del">photos</seg><lb/> photos there is a little bit of hair <lb/> on the left side of both prints. <lb/> arranging my hair is by far <lb/> the nicest in the sick face but <lb/> I look rather a lot in it ?   Now I must close. It is very late <lb/> hoping this will not bore you it <lb/> seems to be all self but as always <lb/> think any praise I get it is you  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_9"/>
              I have to thank for it. I only <lb/> hope I shall continue &amp; be of <lb/> the same use Matron thinks I <lb/> am. We got a great fright the <lb/> other day as someone said <lb/> we had to do a months probation <lb/> as before but I am glad <lb/> to say we only signed on for <lb/> six months since the 17th of <lb/> June so D. V. I shall be at <lb/> home with you all again for <lb/> Xmas. - when I hope the war <lb/> will be over.   With my fondest love&amp; <lb/> ever in my thoughts. <lb/> I hope that the relations <lb/> are well especially Granny . Auntie <lb/> Sissy Aunt May B.N. Frank and my <lb/> God-child. Will you tell them I shall <lb/> try &amp; write soon <seg type="unclear">tactually</seg> are <lb/> we hasty as they will    
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0433_img_1768_10"/>
              casualty list <lb/> With heaps of love to <lb/> Desmond &amp; Andrew <lb/> Please thank Nana for <lb/> her nice letter also Ethel  <seg type="closer"> Your most loving &amp; <lb/> grateful daughter in haste.   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>