<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4175">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Carey to the District Manager, Post Office Telephones, Cork, 15 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Carey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Carey to the District Manager, Post Office Telephones, Cork regarding payment orders. Carey reminds the district manage that the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians are no longer responsible for the calls of the Presbytery and Dr O&#39;Sullivan. 

Patrick Carey (1853-1934) was the Union Clerk for the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians. Poor law unions and their workhouses were established by the Poor Law (Ireland) Act, 1838, as a response to widespread poverty, and were each governed by a Board of Guardians. This letter comes from the Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians Minute Book.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians BG104/B/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4175</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1557">Patrick Carey</persName>
              <date>1915-12-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1721">Killarney, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0611">Post Office, South Mall, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4175_img_3548_1"  type="Letter"  url="1ef27d48a8e0222c1034a9e8722bd3b2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4175_img_3548_1"/>
              15th Decr 1915,   <hi rend="underline">Excess Calls.</hi>   <seg type="del">Dear</seg> Sir,     Referring to your Communication of yesterday <lb/> I enclose Paying Order for £1.19.0 as requested in your <lb/> letter of <seg type="del"> yesterday </seg>  19 11 15  . Will you kindly inform me how <lb/> the £3 cashed by you on the 29th June has been dealt <lb/> with.    I need scarcely remind you that the Guardians <lb/> are not longer responsible for the calls of the <lb/>Presbytery and Dr O'Sullivan.     I am, Sir, <lb/> Your Obedient Servant.     Clerk of Union.    <seg type="del">The Supt for Ireland,</seg>   The Dist Mgr  <lb/> Post Office Telephones, <lb/> <seg type="del">General Post Office,</seg>   South Mall   <lb/> <seg type="del">Dublin, </seg>  Cork  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>