<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3569">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alfreda Helen Baker to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 11 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alfreda Baker</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Alfreda Helen Baker (b. 1893) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), Alfreda expresses her condolences regarding the death of her husband, Francis. Alfreda offers words of comfort and implores Hanna to tell her how she is doing.

Alfreda Helen Baker was a consulting surgeon who graduated from Queen&#39;s University Belfast who worked at a number of hospitals in England and Northern Ireland.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-30</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3569</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0299">Alfreda Baker</persName>
              <date>1916-05-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1909">Trevena, Cornwall, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3569_img_2971_1"  type="Letter"  url="124437f9d7832fb55bd2d6ada42c15bd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3569_img_2971_2"  type="Letter"  url="e11e96688e2e0c701cd3d9d6cb03524c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3569_img_2971_1"/>
             Travena  <hi rend="underline"> May 11: '16 </hi>   Darling Friend   When I wrote to you, I knew no details—<lb/>now that some news is forthcoming, I must<lb/>write to you to tell you that my heart is brim—<lb/>img over with sorrow and sympathy for you<lb/>and little Owen. I wish that I could see you,<lb/>you dear thing — do keep holding on to the thought<lb/>of the reality and truth of the fact of life being<lb/>only just begun here, in this world we call<lb/>Earth. Dear Mr Skeffington is alive more truly<lb/>than when here, and had been spared what<lb/>falls to the lot of most of us, a long illness, and<lb/>a gradual decay of his powers— It must be<lb/>well-nigh impossible for you to bear your life<lb/>from day to day — even from hour ot hour — but<lb/>a brave woman, honored by being the wife—<lb/>comrade of such a brave man, has much to<lb/>live—up—to hasn't she? The cruelity of the separation<lb/>and the butter loneliness are oh! so hard for you—<lb/>my heart is wrung to even think of it — 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3569_img_2971_2"/>
             I saw the obituary notice in The Irish Times and<lb/>I don't think anything could be better than the<lb/>R.I.P, provided The I.P. does not exclude full<lb/>and joyful and unimpeded energy and vital<lb/>force, which, I believe he now has, in a very<lb/>much fuller sense than ever. My grief is for<lb/>you, and what are you doing? How do your<lb/>days pass?  The children join me in warm love,   dear<lb/>Mrs Skeffington— Always,<seg type="unclear"></seg>dear.  Yours lovingly—   <hi rend="underline">Alfreda</hi>   Mrs MacBride asks me to send you her love<lb/>and deep sympathy. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>