<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1487">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kathleen Lynn to Nancy O'Rahilly, 23 November 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Lynn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A note from Dr Kathleen Lynn (1874-1955) advising Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961) that he will be calling on her to vaccinate the baby and he advises her on what to prepare for the visit.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later. Dr Kathleen Lynn was a medical practitioner, a suffragist, a nationalist, and a revolutionary. Lynn was Chief Medical Officer of the Irish Citizen Army during Easter 1916 and was a part of the City Hall garrison, of which she took command of the garrison after the death of Seán Connolly on the first day of the Rising. After independence, Lynn dedicated much time and energy towards the improvement of public health, and played a significant role in the eradication of tuberculosis in Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/092/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1487</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1086">Kathleen Lynn</persName>
              <date>1916-11-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0992">9 Belgrave Road, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1487_img_940_1"  type="Letter"  url="85fce79a2b78db5cbf3d187569fbb0cb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1487_img_940_1"/>
                9 Belgrave Road  , Rathmines  Telephone 220 Rathmines    23.11.16   Dear Madam O'Rahilly   I shall be <lb/> very pleased to <lb/> call at your <lb/> house on Monday <lb/> next at 12.30 <lb/> to vaccinate the <lb/> baby. I shall want <lb/>a small enamelled <lb/> saucepan to <lb/>boil my things  <seg type="closer"> Yrs sincerely  K.Lynn </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>