<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0249">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joe to James Ryan, 25 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joe</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Joe to James Ryan (1891-1970). The letter was written after James Ryan had been sent to Stafford detention camp in England (the writer learned of this in the &#39;Freeman&#39;s Journal&#39; newspaper). The letter recommends that Ryan visit him in Rathfarnham after his release. &#39;Kate and Nellie&#39; are mentioned who had been imprisoned in Mountjoy after the Rising on &#39;suspicion&#39;. The letter also refers to Ryan&#39;s sisters Min, Phyllis and Agnes. Furthermore, the letter mentions Denis McCullough, a member of the IRB and the executive of the Irish Volunteers who was opposed to the Easter Rising but was arrested in its aftermath. Agnes and Denis were married in August.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P88/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/249</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0673">Joe</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1878">Rathfarnham, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0663">Stafford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0249_img_143_1"  type="Letter"  url="943f8fda292eab4755eda819f278b205.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0249_img_143_2"  type="Letter"  url="4b7f464012332d32de839e049fc471f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0249_img_143_3"  type="Letter"  url="439af9bfcd52b2b83b9fa0d39ae93893.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0249_img_143_4"  type="Letter"  url="c19011a8a985190e0bfd71f8efdae4dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0249_img_143_1"/>
                Rathfarnham    25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916   Dearest Jim.   When I saw by the Freeman<lb/> that you has been deported<lb/> to Stratford. I wrote you a long<lb/> letter but did not send it as<lb/> I was not sure of the address.<lb/> Since then I have seen Martin<lb/> and others and I am going to<lb/> write you another one and send<lb/> it to you through him.  I came here on the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May<lb/> and I hear now I am to remain<lb/> here this term.This is a<lb/> lovely place I don't think  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0249_img_143_2"/>
              you were ever here but if you<lb/> are back soon as we all hope<lb/> you will be you will come to see<lb/> me. Martin came up to Dublin<lb/> on Monday to see Katie &amp; Nellie<lb/> and see about their release from<lb/> Mountjoy. I fancy they will be<lb/> out in a few days now as they<lb/> were only arrested on suspicion.<lb/> I don't know whether he has<lb/> gone home yet or no. He<lb/> was here on Monday &amp;<lb/> Tuesday but not yesterday.<lb/> All the members of the family<lb/> are quite well &amp; we were<lb/> all delighted to get your<lb/> long letter &amp; to learn that  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0249_img_143_3"/>
              you are quite well after all<lb/> the vicissitudes of the last<lb/> few weeks. Work hard at<lb/> the medicine now Jim &amp; say<lb/> your prayers and you will<lb/> not feel the time passing.  Phyllis is working hard I<lb/> think. I saw herself &amp; Min<lb/> last Sunday. Fr. P. Browne<lb/> came out with them. Chris came<lb/> out here too on her way<lb/> from Galway and was looking<lb/> awfully well. You will<lb/> be home for the wedding<lb/> any how. I don't know yet<lb/> about Agnes &amp; Denis. Agnes<lb/> is at home &amp; Denis immediate  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0249_img_143_4"/>
              future is still uncertain. He<lb/> is still in Richmond B. and so is<lb/> Sean T I think. Martin was<lb/> to see them all yesterday.  I hope you get plenty of cakes<lb/> and good things. The country<lb/> looks prosperous over here. I<lb/> believe they are working hard<lb/> at home.  You need not bother answering<lb/> this direct. Just send a few<lb/> lines enclosed in Min's the next<lb/> time you are writing to her &amp; she<lb/> will pass on to me. Have they<lb/> sent you stamps?  I will write to you again later on<lb/> when I have more news. <seg type="closer"> Best love dearest Jim from  Joe </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>