<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1904">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Barry C. Galvin to Sir Robert Chalmers, 10 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Barry C. Galvin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter form a Cork based solicitor Barry C. Galvin to Under-Secretary Sir Robert Chalmers (1858–1938). After the Easter Rising of 1916 Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), his chief secretary. The letter is letting Chalmers know that the have also sent an enclosed petition from a Mrs Ellen Regan for permission to trade until the Annual Licensing Sessions.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7933</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1904</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1179">Barry C. Galvin</persName>
              <date>1916-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1725">36 South Mall, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1904_img_1355_1"  type="Letter"  url="7eb9be624aadea45e98028653cb1e78a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1904_img_1355_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="307bc9737893e13562586b436cf97d85.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1904_img_1355_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="d1ddf073df55da860778e0c940980e84.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1904_img_1355_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="a72994d30c9bb5c0e6e3ec0c6d8ff529.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1904_img_1355_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="f234e74bc4e2de3f3df1cce421bc60c6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1904_img_1355_1"/>
            <lb/>Encl.  Offices. <lb/>36 South Mall, Cork   10th May 1916  <lb/> Sir, <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Licensing Act.</hi>  We beg to enclose a Petition do His Excellency The <lb/>Lord Lieutenant from Mrs. Ellen Regan of Rea, Inniscarra, Co. Cork, <lb/>widow, for the permission to trade until the Annual Licensing Sessions.   We are, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servants,    Barry C. Galvin &amp; Son. The Under Secretary <lb/> Lord Lieutenant<lb/> <lb/>Dublin Castle
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1904_img_1355_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Dated  10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day of May 1916 </hi> <lb/> Petition <lb/>OF <lb/>Mrs. Ellen Regan <lb/>TO <lb/>His Excellency The <lb/>Lord Lieutenant <lb/><hi rend="underline">of Ireland</hi>
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1904_img_1355_3"/>
            <hi rend="underline">To</hi> His Excellency <lb/>The Right Honourable Ivor Churchill <lb/>Baron Wimborne <lb/>Lord Lieutenant General and General <lb/>Governor of Ireland <lb/>Dublin Castle. <lb/>The Humble Petition <lb/>of <lb/>Ellen Regan of Rea, Inniscarra, <lb/>Co. Cork, Widow <lb/>Sheweth: -  That your Petitioner is the widow of Daniel <lb/>Regan late of Rea, aforesaid, Licensed Publican.   That the said Daniel Regan died at <lb/>Rea aforesaid   on the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day of March <lb/>1916 leaving his widow (Your Petitioner) and <lb/>four children, namely Hannah (aged 12) Timothy <lb/>(aged 11) Nora (aged 10) and Jeremiah (aged 8) <lb/>him surviving.   That the said Daniel Regan died in <lb/>poor circumstances, his only means of support <lb/>being the profits of the publicans business carried <lb/>on by him at Rea aforesaid and those profits <lb/>were barely sufficient to provide the necessaries <lb/>of life for himself and his family.   That your Petitioner being anxious to <lb/>continue the business of publican as carried <lb/>on by her late husband, but being too poor to <lb/>employ a solicitor to act for her in the matter <lb/>applied in person at the District Probate Registry <lb/>for a Grant of Administration of said <sic>deceaseds</sic> <lb/>personal estate to enable her obtain a transfer of <lb/>the license attached to said premises into her <lb/>own name and on the 5th day of April 1916.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1904_img_1355_4"/>
            <lb/>she applied at Coachford Petty Sessions Court for <lb/>and obtained an ad interim transfer of said <lb/>license.   That your Petitioner at the time of her <lb/>application for said ad interim transfer was <lb/>erroneously under the impression that the <lb/>next Licensing Sessions for the County of Cork, <lb/>East Riding, at which she would apply to the <lb/>County County Judge for the transfer of said <lb/>license, would be held some time in June.   That your Petitioner has now ascertained <lb/>that the next Licensing Sessions will be held on <lb/>the 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> day of May instant and as the <lb/>Licensing notices in connection with her <lb/>application should have been served twenty <lb/>one clear days before the said 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> day of <lb/>May she is debarred from applying for the <lb/>transfer until the <seg type="unclear">following</seg> Licensing Sessions <lb/>which wont be held until the  18th day of <lb/>October next.   That under the circumstances as stated <lb/>your petitioner will be obliged to cease carrying <lb/>on the trade of publican in the premises <lb/>until next October unless Your Excellency <lb/>will graciously order that she may be at <lb/>liberty to continue to carry on said trade in <lb/>the meantime and thus enable her to maintain <lb/>herself and her said four children.   That if she will be obliged to close <lb/>the premises until next October she will be <lb/>deprived of her only means of livelihood for <lb/>herself and said children. Both she and her <lb/>said children would then be in destitute <lb/>circumstances and would have no alternative <lb/>but to seek poor law relief on enter the workhouse.   Your Petitioner therefore
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1904_img_1355_5"/>
            humbly prays that your Excellency <lb/>may order that she be at <lb/>liberty to continue to carry on <lb/>the trade of licensed publican <lb/>in said premises pending her <lb/>application for a transfer of said <lb/>license at the Licensing Sessions <lb/>for Cork County E.R. to be <lb/>holden on 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> October next.  <lb/>Dated this 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day of May 1916  Ellen Regan 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>