<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0671">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 16 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary, describing life in the field, weather conditions, and the lack of food and provisions. Thus he very much welcomes parcels from home. James sends congratulations and best wishes back to his newborn niece.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/671</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0671_img_2164_1"  type="Letter"  url="97197812c844e3f6b931721583d1e3b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0671_img_2164_2"  type="Letter"  url="e6a8c4f4d746bb931c4f31e8179fed09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0671_img_2164_3"  type="Letter"  url="e231a87884b529eb2bff729fd729f5b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0671_img_2164_4"  type="Letter"  url="c05311c18fcb36b28dfc2d1b269b95d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0671_img_2164_5"  type="Envelope"  url="3bbcfad3d489ee84abff6fec3115ae67.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0671_img_2164_1"/>
                16/11/15   My dearest Mother   — Since I wrote <lb/>you on Sat. last I have been having a <lb/>very busy time of it. The Brigade <lb/>left for the Trenches on Sunday which <lb/>meant no end of a fuss all round &amp; <lb/>then the details left behind by the Baths <lb/>at the various villages arrived in here <lb/>&amp;I had to see to them being billeted <lb/>&amp;c. As usual of course with these <lb/>sudden moves rations &amp;fuel got <lb/>wrong &amp;this took some straightening <lb/>out but thank goodness things are <lb/>now running fairly smoothly. <lb/> I have nearly 300 men left behind <lb/> for special courses in Bombing &amp; <lb/>machine gun work &amp;c but if <lb/>present weather continues we shall <lb/>not do much in that line. The <lb/>Winter has come in with a vengeance. <lb/> We wakened up on Sunday morning  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0671_img_2164_2"/>
              <lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0671_img_2164_3"/>
              <lb/>with the result that we dont get any <lb/>letters or parcels till Thursday. Am <lb/> also looking anxiously for the tubes <lb/>of toothpaste &amp;shaving soap. My <lb/>supply is absolutely finished &amp;one <lb/>cant get any of these things about here. <lb/>The big box of fruit came yest. &amp; <lb/>the fruit was in splendid condition, <lb/>which Berry will be pleased to know. <lb/>There are 10 other officers remaining <lb/>with details so I have distributed <lb/>most of the fruit &amp;it has been <lb/>greatly enjoyed. If however you <lb/>can send some more later on <lb/>it would be better to only make <lb/>up a small parcel of say 1 doz <lb/>apples or pears which would go <lb/>by post as a large box takes so <lb/>long to come &amp;has to be delivered <lb/>by the A.S.C.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0671_img_2164_4"/>
              I seem to be always worrying you <lb/>dear Mother about sending things <lb/>but really for anything outside our <lb/>Govt. rations one has to depend on <lb/>getting supplies from home. <lb/>Hope Kathleen &amp; Baby are both <lb/>flourishing — am looking forward <lb/>to hearing all about them when <lb/>mail arrives on Thurs.   If this weather continues we wont <lb/>do much training with the guns but <lb/> indeed as far as I can see I wont <lb/> have much time to give any instruction <lb/> with so many other matters to attend <lb/> to &amp; I shall simply have to leave <lb/> things to the <seg type="unclear">Sect.</seg> officer. With <lb/> fondest love to all &amp; to my little <lb/>new niece. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  Jim </seg>  Have just realised that Babys birthday <lb/>and K's birthday were almost the same. <lb/>My love &amp;best wishes to them for many <lb/> happy returns.   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0671_img_2164_5"/>
              <lb/>On Active Service   Mrs. S.C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland   16/11/15 <lb/>J. Davidson   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>