<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4674">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to William Boxwell, 8 December 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

William Boxwell (1875-1943) was a physician at the Meath Hospital, Dublin from 1911 until 1943. Boxwell served in France during the First World War, rising to lieutenant-colonel in the Royal Army Medical Corps. Following the war Boxwell was appointed professor of pathology and bacteriology at the Royal College of Surgeons. He would later be elected president of the Royal College of Physicians (1937–40). </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-265</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4674</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1917-12-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Boxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4674_img_4013_1"  type="Letter"  url="64c4e394d8dc9e4a2fbeb83a5b6192f4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4674_img_4013_1"/>
             8th December 17   W.Boxwell, Esq.,M.D., <lb/>Hon.-Sec.Biological club, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I am directed by the President and Fellows of the <lb/>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to inform you that at <lb/>a recent meeting of the College they have decided to charge <lb/>the Biological cClub a rent of £15:15/- per annum for the <lb/>accomdation afforded to the Club in the College.   This rent is the same in amount as that charged to the <lb/>Royal Academy of Medicines in Ireland. I presume that the new <lb/>rent will not come into force till next season, 1918/19.   Yours faithfully, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>