<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0777">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí with £1 to celebrate St. Patrick's day 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the father of Piaras Béaslaí to Piaras with £1 to celebrate St. Patrick&#39;s day 1916, wishing him and Longford well.Patrick Langford Beazley was born near Killarney, Co. Kerry, son of a tenant who had been evicted from the Lansdowne estate. The Beazleys were an old family in Kerry, of English origin. Married with Nancy (Nanny) Hickey, he was the father of Piaras Béaslaí. He was the editor of the Catholic Times from 1884 until his death in the early 1920s.Piaras Béaslaí (1881–1965) was born Percy (later Pierce, Piaras) Beazley on 15 February 1881 in Liverpool. He was an English born influential member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He was writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, and journalist.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/777</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0777_img_231_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc665c0e5143a26dc4498a39323ff9c4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0777_img_231_1"/>
                ''GLENGARIFF'',  RUDGRAVE SQUARE,  EGREMONT,  CHESHIRE    19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March, 1916.   My dearest Pierce,   The enclosed pound<lb/> is a little expression of feeling,<lb/> prompted by the recurrence<lb/> of St Patricks Day. We<lb/> are always uneasy when <lb/> we don't get word of<lb/> acknowledgement.  I hope you and Lang-<lb/> ford are in good health and <lb/> spirits. We are quite well<lb/> thank God.  With proudest love from<lb/> Mother &amp; myself, <seg type="closer"> Always affectionately.   Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>