<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4395">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to Maria Duffin, November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers; D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4395</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1885">7 Westcliff, Eastbrough, Sussex, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4395_img_3749_1"  type="Letter"  url="aa8bfe65d74f44b28433330e04c03c6f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4395_img_3749_2"  type="Letter"  url="4af6180df00a5b36e552ad71b7c8adcd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4395_img_3749_3"  type="Letter"  url="c35ee5a4b5665c309a00be3373f4e79a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4395_img_3749_1"/>
              D2109/9/4/B.    7 West Cliff,   Sunday   Nov 1915    Dearest Mamma,   I begin a letter <seg type="unclear">even</seg> though<lb/>there really seems little to tall this week.<lb/>Miss Constance Charles is here now which is<lb/>rather a relief, she is a pleasant unexciting woman<lb/>&amp; it breaks our <seg type="foreign">tete a tete</seg>. Mr. &amp; Mrs. <seg type="unclear">Hollins</seg> &amp;<lb/>Eunice are arriving on Wed. <seg type="unclear">Liam Ho </seg>for a few<lb/>days &amp; I believe Eunice is to remain with us<lb/>for a bit. Yesterday we went to a very fine concert<lb/>Ysaye, Pachmann, &amp; <seg type="unclear">Stralia</seg> all together. It was<lb/>rather wasted on me I am afraid, but nothing will<lb/>persuade Miss Roberts that I am very unmusical.<lb/>Certainly, even I could recognise it was beautiful<lb/>music. We were at another concert this week where<lb/>I was very much bored!  Yesterday morning was a perfect, writers' morning<lb/>with a hard first &amp; bright sun, &amp; Mrs Daniel rang me<lb/>up early &amp; took me to Polegale by train &amp; from there<lb/>a really lovely walk through little villages in the<lb/>Downs &amp; home to Eastbourne over the Downs. It was<lb/>nice to see some more of the country, its really<lb/><seg type="unclear">is</seg> lonely up there in <seg type="unclear">Umber</seg> to walk by oneself.<lb/>Poor Mrs. D. had just heard of the death of a very 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4395_img_3749_2"/>
              D2109/9/4/B   old &amp; dear friend of hers, Major Riddel, he was killed<lb/>in the Persian Gulf. She seemed to feel it more<lb/>deeply that I thought her capable of feeling anything.<lb/>She &amp; Winnie are not quite on bad terms but they<lb/>are quite apart, &amp; unintimate. Winnie is making<lb/>bad friends &amp; getting into bad ways &amp; I tell Mrs.<lb/>D. she ought to take her away, but she says Winnie<lb/>has always bad taste in friends and would pick<lb/>up more wherever she took her!  I made friends with Mrs Loughlin who was staying<lb/>here, such a nice woman. I am sorry she is gone.<lb/>Henry Hollins &amp; I are now great friends &amp; I enjoy<lb/>having him on Sundays, he has just gone off to<lb/>Church with Miss Charley &amp; I am having a Sunday<lb/>at home. I see something of Violet Hollins &amp;<lb/>Anabel Robertson, &amp; like them both very much &amp; it<lb/>is so nice to have a young person to talk to in<lb/>skin. Anabel had a nice brother at home for a<lb/>bit, he was blown right into the air a year ago (he is<lb/>a gunner) &amp; his back a mass of shrapnel which has<lb/>been coming out every since. Ralph <seg type="unclear">Hurley</seg>, Violets' brother<lb/>who was in hospital at <seg type="unclear">Presen</seg>, is home again now,<lb/>he has arthritis &amp; will probably not be sent abroad<lb/>again at present, her fiance is at Salonika.  Dorothy says she <hi rend="underline">may</hi> arrive on Wed: but is<lb/>uncertain &amp; will wire from London. <seg type="unclear">Some ch</seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4395_img_3749_3"/>
              D2109/9/4/B.   here for a night or two. She talks of <seg type="unclear">Chicester</seg> but I<lb/>will advise her not to go there at present. Hilda is<lb/>at work again &amp; I see no object in it.  I have settled to come over about Xmas time but<lb/>dont know yet when or for how long, but look<lb/>forward to it very much.  It has been bitterly cold here, but dry &amp; sunny. I am afraid<lb/>D. must be perished at Treport.  They are getting plenty of recruits here now I belie<seg type="del">f</seg>ve, I<lb/>am starting classes for training women to take their<lb/>places in shops etc.  I am sorry <seg type="unclear">that</seg> old Mrs. Wals is gone, she was<lb/>always most kind to me. Annie &amp; Harold will<lb/>miss her sadly.  I am looking forward to seeing <seg type="unclear">Dowling</seg> soon &amp; hearing<lb/>a little more about Leslie &amp; future prospects.  Much love toall   Your loving   Olive.  <seg type="unclear">The potatoe</seg> bread has come yet, it does not matter<lb/>but I supplose its' not lost - en route    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>