<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0986">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Agnes Sheehan to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 6 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Agnes Sheehan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Agnes Sheehan to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946). Sheehan sends a thank you to Skeffington for tickets to a lecture and mentions that she will try call into the Irish Women&#39;s Franchise League some Tuesday evening but it will be difficult seeing as her Irish class is on the same night. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47;, MS 33,604/15-5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/986</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1118">Agnes Sheehan</persName>
              <date>1916-01-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0986_img_2833_1"  type="Letter"  url="0bf8df462c06d028f38ea4b8a5fe18c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0986_img_2833_2"  type="Letter"  url="8678987ce7b572434bd49f1fec2e1ef8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0986_img_2833_3"  type="Letter"  url="ad863e68b04b99742b2e812b3626640c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0986_img_2833_1"/>
                109 Lr Baggot St.  Dublin    6th Jan. '16   My dear Hanna,   I hope you will <lb/>forgive my unintentional <lb/>rudeness for not having <lb/>acknowledged receipt <lb/>of tickets before this. It was <lb/>very good of you to send <lb/>them to me. I enjoyed <lb/>the lecture very much <lb/>indeed &amp; am more than <lb/>glad to see how well <lb/>our Dublin 'felon' is  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0986_img_2833_2"/>
              looking, his American <lb/>trip must have done <lb/>him a lot of good <lb/>physically as well as <lb/>in other ways. I enclose <lb/>2/— for tickets which <lb/>I should have sent <lb/>before this but I thought <lb/>I should have seen <lb/>more of you last <lb/>night. I must try <lb/>to go round to the <lb/>I.W.F.L. <hi rend="underline">some</hi> Tues. <lb/>evening, but as <lb/>Tues. is an Irish class <lb/>night I find it  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0986_img_2833_3"/>
              hard to get away.  Wishing you &amp; Mr <lb/>Skeffington every happiness &amp; <lb/>good luck luck in the New <lb/>year,  <seg type="closer"> Your sincere friend  Úna Ní Síotcáin, </seg><seg type="postscript"> (Agnes Sheehan) </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>