<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5156">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell, 2 August 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell is experiencing heavy rain in the trenches.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5156</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5156_img_None_1"  url="7540d8cb7474441f6b102215224c6e4b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5156_img_None_2"  url="b63388974f6affa0d479f5f099ce939a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5156_img_0_1"/>
              2 August 17    My dearest Mamy   No news at all but just a<lb/>line as usual. It is still pouring<lb/>rain. It has been raining steadily<lb/>for 40 hours now. It is really too<lb/>bad that it should start at such a time.  We have just got the papers now<lb/>and things seem to be going splendidly<lb/>but I am afraid they will be seriously<lb/>hampered by the wet. This is such<lb/>an awful country for mud when it<lb/>does rain. Also the harvest is just<lb/>coming in and now it is all getting<lb/>lodged.  However it may clear up again &amp;<lb/>then all will be well.  I have not got any letters yet since<lb/>Sunday but will get them all in a<lb/>bunch very soon - probably today  I hop you have been getting mine    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5156_img_0_2"/>
             alright.  I wrote a long letter to Jasper<lb/>today as I had plenty of time.  Sorry to hear Dr. Waters has<lb/>been so ill again. I wrote to<lb/>Mrs Waters also today. Put a piece<lb/>of soap in a parcel soon please.  No news but best love to all<lb/>from<lb/> Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>