<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3784">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Rev. Thoms Gray to Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 21 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Gray</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Rev. Thomas Thompson Gray (1832-1924) to the registrar of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) regarding an effort to repeal the School of Physic Act. 

Rev. Thomas Thompson Gray served as the vice-provost of Trinity from 1916 until he resigned in 1924, a few weeks before his death. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T62</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3784</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0044">Thomas Gray</persName>
              <date>1916-02-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2038">Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0320">Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3784_img_3169_1"  type="Letter"  url="ed8a90673bf1fcb0e164799433f490da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3784_img_3169_2"  type="Letter"  url="fe90c41f1c65a772f408d639f4af9581.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3784_img_3169_1"/>
             REGISTRAR'S OFFICE, <lb/>TRINITY COLLEGE, DUBLIN.   Feb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. 21, 1916.   Dear Sir,   I am directed by the <lb/>Board of Trinity College to <lb/>enquire if the Royal College <lb/>of Physicians is willing to <lb/>act jointly with Trinity College <lb/>in an effort of obtain a repeal <lb/>of the School of Physic Act, on <lb/>the lines of the joint agreement
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3784_img_3169_2"/>
            between the Board of Trinity and <lb/>the Fellows of the Royal College of <lb/>Physicians, laid before the recent <lb/>Royal Commission (on Trinity College <lb/>Dublin &amp; on the University of Dublin), <lb/>and approved of, and recommended <lb/>by, that Commission.   Will you kindly log this letter before <lb/>your board.    Very Truly yours   Thomas J. Gray,  <lb/>Reg<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>.  Mr. Registrar <lb/>Royal College of Physicians.   Macd.C. 5.III.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>