<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0550">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lord Newton to the Under Secretary of Ireland, 19 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Wodehouse Legh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Wodehouse Legh, 2nd Baron Newton, (1857-1942) to the Under Secretary of Ireland, Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) referring to correspondence from Mrs Manning concerning the repayment of a sum from the British Relief Funds. Enclosed with the letter is a statement explaining Mrs Manning’s inability to repay the sum due to her son’s enlistment in the army and her failure to receive a dependent’s allowance. In recognition of the service of several of her sons Mrs Manning hopes that Newton will consider the debt repaid. In the letter Mrs Manning&#39;s youngest son was noted as being a member of the &#39;famous Pals Battalion which...suffered so much last August in the Dardanelles.&#39; Said Pals Battalion were the members of D company, 7th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers. Referred to as the &#39;Toffs in the Toughs,&#39; many of their volunteers came from the Irish rugby team, and the students and staff of Trinity college. They suffered heavy casualties during the August offensive at Suvla Bay, Gallipoli.In 1916 Lord Newton became assistant under secretary of state for foreign affairs, and was put in charge of two departments at the Foreign Office, one dealing with foreign propaganda and the other with prisoners of war. Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell (1871-1941), his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-12477-1, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-12477-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/550</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1017">Thomas Wodehouse Legh</persName>
              <date>1916-07-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1469">Foreign Office, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0550_img_1931_1"  type="Letter"  url="4133e3d5aa5376abcca6701f63f61ba3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0550_img_1931_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="621617dfe80e1e60f555485517182ce4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0550_img_1931_1"/>
                FOREIGN OFFICE    19 JUL 1916   Sir:â   I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to <lb/>transmit herewith a copy of a letter which has been <lb/>received from Mrs. Manning of 4, Pembroke Road, <lb/>Dublin, in response to a request by this Department <lb/>for repayment of a sum advanced to her daughter <lb/>while the latter was in Germany from British Relief <lb/>Funds held at the disposal of the United States <lb/>Ambassador at Berlin.  Before deciding as to what course should be <lb/>adopted in regard to the recovery of the sum in <lb/>question, I am to request that Sir E. Grey may be <lb/>informed as to whether the facts set forth by Mrs. <lb/>Manning are correct. <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your most obedient <lb/> humble Servant,  Newton   The Under Secretary  Irish Office.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0550_img_1931_2"/>
              Copy <lb/>(83688/14/P)    4, PEMBROKE ROAD,  DUBLIN.    Mrs. Manning's compliments to the Under â <lb/>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, begs to <lb/> state she cannot send a further instalment at <lb/> present, her eldest son from whom she got her chief <lb/>support has joined the Army and is now in the 2nd <lb/>South African Field Ambulance stationed at <lb/>Kilindini, British East Africa, when he joined last <lb/> December he advised her she should (as a dependent) <lb/> get a seperation allowance since that time she <lb/> has <hi rend="underline">never</hi> received a penny which leaves her in <lb/> great want of means and quite unable to meet her <lb/>engagements at present.  Mrs. Manning now has two sons fighting for <lb/>King and Country her youngest son having joined the <lb/> Army in September 1914 and is one the <hi rend="underline">few</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">survivors</hi> of the famous Pals Battalion which <lb/> Battalion went through so much, and suffered so much <lb/> last August in the Dardanelles.  Mrs. Manning thinks under existing circumstances <lb/> and in consideration of her want of means it would <lb/> be a very gracious act on the part of the Under <lb/> Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to consider <lb/>the debt paid. <seg type="closer">  The Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>