<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0799">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí after the Rising</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the father of Patrick Langford Beazley to his son, Piaras (1881-1965), after his arrest and imprisonment after the Rising. It details the strain his parents were under before they heard that Piaras was unhurt. The letter gives accounts of the Irish neighbours in the Cheshire area calling to the family home for support. It includes details on looking after Piaras&#39;s personal belongings as well as encouraging him to keep his spirits up.Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley) was an English born writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, journalist and a member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He wrote twenty plays between 1913 and 1939. Patrick Langford Beazley was born near Killarney, Co. Kerry, son of a tenant who had been evicted from the Lansdowne estate. The Beazleys were an old family in Kerry, of English origin. He was the editor of the Catholic Times from 1884 until his death in the early 1920s.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 33,972 / 11, MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/799</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0799_img_234_1"  type="Letter"  url="40f15357b0e9fec7b2c60e55bc6da2c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0799_img_234_2"  type="Letter"  url="6b06ebdcafaeac976bda399b0953e217.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0799_img_234_3"  type="Letter"  url="b8bf1da82714e8fe45b0b07eb162fe70.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0799_img_234_4"  type="Letter"  url="06c761793a7e890e10330faff8d30e38.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0799_img_234_5"  type="Letter"  url="ff831bbcdcb5d8c2c8fe43acf8b82897.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0799_img_234_6"  type="Letter"  url="26ce6b3f10a5830e0617e703bf875095.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0799_img_234_1"/>
                'GLENNGARIFF.'  RUDGRAVE SQUARE,  EGREMONT,  CHESHIRE.    25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, 1916.   My dearest Pierce,   It was such a delight <lb/> to mother and myself to <lb/> get your long letter. Langâ <lb/> ford, having gone back after <lb/> his holiday, had written <lb/> once and we were exâ <lb/> pecting that in his next <lb/> letter he might be able to <lb/> tell us where you were. Moâ <lb/> ther and I were just disâ <lb/> cussing the matter at <lb/> dinner on Monday last, May <lb/> 22, and impatient at not <lb/> hearing from Langford when <lb/> Nellie brought in from the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0799_img_234_2"/>
              <lb/>postman a letter in hand <lb/> writing that I did not know. <lb/> I opened it carelessly and <lb/> saw a printed form. I <lb/> began to wonder whether I <lb/> had received a summons for <lb/> something or other when I <lb/> turned it and lo, there were <lb/> your own handwriting and <lb/> signature. As you can <lb/> imagine the strain on me <lb/> for some time previously was <lb/> pretty severe, but this was <lb/> the first time I gave way <lb/> to the weakness of tears. It <lb/> was like having you with <lb/> us again for a while. Of <lb/> course Mother and I read <lb/> and re-read the letter and in <lb/> deed were charmed with the <cb/><lb/> spirit of it. It is just the <lb/> kind of letter we hoped for â <lb/> bright, brave, cheerful and <lb/> showing a disposition to <lb/> accept <seg type="unclear">exerting</seg> conditions con- <lb/> tentedly. I cannot say how <lb/> glad I was to find not only <lb/> that you were well, thank <lb/> God, but that you were accep <lb/> ting your position philoâ <lb/> sophically and resolved to <lb/> comply with the rules. Wherevâ <lb/> er one is one can be happy by <lb/> striving to do God's Will!  You will be anxious to <lb/> know how Mother is and <lb/> how she bears up. Thank <lb/> God she is quite well and <lb/> has borne up wonderfully. <lb/> Indeed everybody who has <lb/> come to see her has been <lb/> gratified to find how well  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0799_img_234_3"/>
              <lb/>she has kept up her spirits. <lb/> Of course she and I have <lb/> thought much about you, <lb/> have been thinking of you <lb/> every day and every hour ; but <lb/> your assurances that you are <lb/> in the best of health, that the <lb/> place in which are is very <lb/> healthy, being close to the sea, <lb/> that the prison is admirably <lb/> managed, that everybody <lb/> seems to be fairly treated, <lb/> that the food is good and <lb/> sufficient and the work not <lb/> too hard, and that you are <lb/> allowed books to read in <lb/> spare moments, have given <lb/> us great comfort. We have <lb/> had quite a number of visitors <lb/> during the past few weeks. <lb/> Mrs. O'Callaghan and <seg type="unclear">Mat</seg><lb/> came and spent an evening <lb/> with us. She is as vivacious  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0799_img_234_4"/>
                  'GLENGARIFF.'   REDGRAVE SQUARE,   EGREMONT,    CHESHIRE.    <lb/> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0799_img_234_5"/>
              <lb/> and his wife came last Sunâ <lb/> day. We have had a very <lb/> warm-hearted letter from <lb/> Father James and Aunt <lb/> Ellie has sent a couple of <lb/> long letters during the <lb/> past fortnight. The Longs <lb/> have all had a rather bad <lb/> attack of influenza, but they <lb/> are now better. We have <lb/> been hearing of course from <lb/> Carey and I have a very kind <lb/> note from Canon Walsh of <lb/> Liscard. Nora Murphy and <lb/> Mr. Lamble dropped in one <lb/> evening. Nora was to return <lb/> to the college at Hull next <lb/> day. She is not keeping up <lb/> correspondence with the old <lb/> man now.   Langford had quite a singular <lb/> experience in returning <cb/><lb/> from his holiday. On Bank Holiâ <lb/> day he went as far as Holyâ <lb/> head but found he could not <lb/> go farther and returned on <lb/> Tuesday. He remained here till <lb/> Friday and then went as far <lb/> as Kingstown, but returned <lb/> again and remained for anâ <lb/>other week. Like the dove <lb/> of the Ark, when he went <lb/> a third time he did not <lb/> return. He wrote once and <lb/> said he was hard worked. We <lb/> are expecting a second letter <lb/> from him. I have written to <lb/> your landlady, asking her <lb/> to send the bill and I have <lb/> asked Langford to call on her <lb/> for your clothes, etc. I am writing <lb/> to Mr. J.J.O'Kelly, of M.H. <lb/> Gill and Son, telling him, as <lb/> you have requested, that you <lb/> have given him power to do  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0799_img_234_6"/>
              <lb/>as he likes with the manuâ <lb/> scripts you left with him.  Many friends of yours have <lb/> been enquiring about your <lb/> health and of course I have <lb/> been happy to tell them you <lb/> are very well and to give them <lb/> your kind regards. I have asked <lb/> Langford to do likewise.  And now that I am drawâ <lb/>ing to a close, I would say : Keep <lb/> your spirits up and be of good <lb/> cheer. God is good. We are well <lb/> and shall try to keep well <lb/> till you come back, please God, <lb/> and I am sure you will be as <lb/> careful of your health as you <lb/> can. You will, no doubt, be able <lb/> to let me know through the Govâ <lb/> ernor when I can see you and I <lb/> shall do so at any cost or trouble. <lb/>The garden is nice now, but we <lb/> shall, please God, have it nicer when <lb/> you come. Langford has talked &amp; thought <lb/> much of you. May God give you every <lb/> pleasure. With the fondest love of our <lb/> hearts from Mother him and myself  <seg type="closer"> I am ever &amp; ever affectionately   Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>