<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0109">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 18 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Helena Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin. Marie writes to thank her mother for the long letter she sent and feels guilty because she cannot help her through this difficult time. Marie empathises with her mother as her younger brother Andrew (1907-?) is suffering from the mumps. In the letter Marie gives a very detailed description of the work she carries out and the varieties of medical treatment that they use in the field. She also writes about her colleagues and friendMarie Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF169-1916-10-012, BF169-1916-10-012</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/109</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0618">Marie Helena Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-10-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_1"  type="Letter"  url="a5e4c1706dd5dc18553c4a8647f350c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_2"  type="Letter"  url="0683df7520090129594f03235baacd5f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_3"  type="Letter"  url="d420231bd1539e81c0252a5439ffdf06.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_4"  type="Letter"  url="4630ae91ef63423b9a294e58573afbed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_5"  type="Letter"  url="b506df6c3e30b52e05ef089803747c25.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_6"  type="Letter"  url="5a55c117cee8fc5661cd3664b36081fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_7"  type="Letter"  url="6806102baf54245d8e02513029cbadfb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_8"  type="Letter"  url="16cd72b600b0d5b829c689608e435bbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_9"  type="Letter"  url="4f1037e142c16106b4fdc0f302d28556.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_10"  type="Letter"  url="719e2d0b09ed3aa5900ceb4219bfe087.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_11"  type="Letter"  url="4a91df922bc8a2a06ce815284295538c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0109_img_1191_12"  type="Letter"  url="2830409eafd6297e7814f5480a701448.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_1"/>
                12.10.16   My very dearest Mother   A Thousand thanks <lb/>for your very nice long letter of t <lb/>the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Oct. I cannot tell you <lb/>how delighted i was to get it, <lb/>but frightfully sorry to hear you <lb/> are having such a terrible time <lb/>with the Mumps &amp;&amp; that my <lb/>darling Andrew has it. I sincerely <lb/> hope he is better by <lb/> this also poor Cecil. Really you have <lb/> had a terrible hard time since <lb/> I left &amp;&amp; it has kept you <lb/> so isolated from the rest of <lb/> the family. I feel I have <lb/> been so slack about writing <lb/> but really we have not had <lb/> time for anything but work <lb/>&amp; when i get off for an hour  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_2"/>
              I need to generally lie down so as <lb/>to go on fresh. I shall try &amp; <lb/> give you an idea what I have <lb/>been doing since the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Sep: <lb/>when our big rush really started <lb/>here but I do not want you to think <lb/> I am being over worked, as you know <lb/> I have had a good week spring <lb/> cleaning an empty ward before <lb/>the rush —- I am glad to say I felt <lb/>a.1. at the time &amp; seem quite able <lb/>for the long hours. I think it is <lb/>working under canvas as that is so <lb/>healthy &amp; one does not get nearly <lb/>so tired. On Monday Sep 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>I had had my usual day work in <lb/>my own tent &amp; was going off <lb/>duty for the evening when I received <lb/>a message from Matron to say I <lb/>was to go to S.8. Surgical tent  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_3"/>
              open again when I got over <lb/> There was Sister St. Leger and another <lb/> V.A.D. the two tents were full of <lb/> wounded some very bad others only <lb/> slight hurt most of them &amp; had <lb/> to have baths so all had to <lb/> be washed in the wards. this <lb/>was getting on to 6 o'clock &amp; none <lb/> of the dressings had been touched <lb/> so we started off &amp; did all the <lb/> worst &amp; found a great number <lb/> had haemorrhage on the way others <lb/> were found with Gas Gangrene <lb/> which meant immediate operation <lb/> which had to be done that night <lb/> I think we got off about 10 o' clock <lb/> leaving one poor man named <lb/> Wood very bad they found <lb/> he had Septic absorption it had gone <lb/> too far for amputation &amp; the only <lb/> chance was to drain the leg &amp; they  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_4"/>
              &amp; get rid of poisoning. Next morning <lb/> we came on to hear that he had been <lb/> to the theatre during the night <lb/> again &amp; that the M.O. was going <lb/> to give a transfusion which is <lb/> a terrible job in itself &amp; so many <lb/> of the others were very bad we really <lb/> did not know where to begin <lb/> I forgot to tell you that that he had <lb/> had a Ensol transfusion the night <lb/> before which I believe is the latest <lb/> treatment for these Gas Gangrene <lb/> in some case I believe it has proved <lb/><seg type="unclear">invaluable</seg> but it seems Gods will <lb/> this man should not live. He <lb/> lingered on for three days, every <lb/> thing possible was done for him <lb/> but he died very quietly on the <lb/> 3rd night, it is a very sad thing <lb/> to watch. the patient is so frightfully <lb/> restless &amp; has to be watched all <lb/> the time he was quite unconscious <lb/> on the last day &amp; spoke in such a  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_5"/>
              weird way. Well things went on <lb/> fairly well operations after operations <lb/> but they seem to be getting <lb/> on very well, A great number <lb/> of arms and legs were saved with <lb/> G. Gangrene that they thought would <lb/> have to be amputated on the 1st <lb/> Oct. one of our tents was turned <lb/> into the accute Ward for the whole <lb/> surgical division which of course <lb/> made us very busy again <lb/> as we got all the worst cases <lb/>from the Hospital after operations. <lb/> Really we were dressing from <lb/> 8 in the morning till 8 at night <lb/> &amp; the three of us on duty all <lb/> the time except for one day <lb/> when we each got an hour. <lb/> Still we all felt wonderful &amp; <lb/> it was such a joy to see them <lb/> all improving. but we had some <lb/> nasty frights one man started hammering  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_6"/>
              banging one night and in the end <lb/> had to get the M.O. to stop it after <lb/> having the orderly help for 15 min. <lb/> by Sister &amp; myself he lost pints that <lb/> night so he haemorrhaged twice <lb/> but was sent to the line the next <lb/> day. I wonder how the poor man <lb/> got on. Well things were beginning <lb/> to get quieter &amp; the work a little <lb/> lighter when a very large convoy <lb/> of skin cases arrived &amp; my old <lb/> tents all 8 were open &amp; I got a <lb/> message to go down there &amp; take <lb/> charge again. What a change to <lb/> go &amp; see these terribly disfigured <lb/> men covered with Scabies Impetigo <lb/> &amp; the Lord know what after having <lb/> the most interesting work in the <lb/> whole hospital, so again I found <lb/> myself with 56 patients &amp; one <lb/> orderly which meant no off <lb/> duty till I got help which arrived  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_7"/>
              two days ago. So we are able to <lb/> relieve each other now. I really <lb/> do not care for skins very much <lb/> The fact of the matter is I know <lb/> nothing about them except what <lb/> I have learned this past week. <lb/> Sometimes I feel quite sea sick <lb/> pulling off these horrible scabs <lb/> but I feel heartily sorry for <lb/> the men and someone has to look <lb/> after them. I believe this hospital <lb/> will be nothing but skins after <lb/> the 1 Nov: but by then I shall <lb/> know more about them. One <lb/> is dressing all day long as <lb/> one case sometimes takes <lb/> over an hour to do, especially <lb/> if it is a face case when its <lb/> the crust   to be removed <lb/> We have two skin specialists <lb/> here who are frightfully keen <lb/> &amp; expect you to be the same.  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_8"/>
              I must try and get up my <lb/> interest I cannot help thinking <lb/> of Uncle Charlie every time I <lb/> am dressing them his disgust <lb/> if he saw them with the big <lb/> sores all over them I do not think <lb/> he would ever kiss me again. <lb/> It is really sad to think there <lb/> is so much of it among our <lb/> troops the only good thing <lb/> is they can cure scabies in <lb/> three days if taken in time but <lb/> then it is so terribly infectious <lb/> Our staff has increased a great <lb/> deal but we are still rather under <lb/> staffed for our numbers. I have not <lb/> heard from Gerald G. since he <lb/> ought to be getting leave very <lb/> soon now, as it is open I <lb/> wonder if he will pass through <lb/> B.-- I may see him if so  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_9"/>
              did you ever send me those <lb/> two photos I asked you I want <lb/> to give one to Sister H Seger who <lb/>this morning present me with <lb/> a sweet gold brooch in remem- <lb/>brance of the happy and rosy time <lb/> we had to-gether etc. It was very <lb/> sweet of her and I did not <lb/>deserve it I only did my <lb/> duty - really mother I am very <lb/> lucky and always seem to be <lb/>sent to places where the work <lb/> is good and interest so I must <lb/>not grumble at the <seg type="unclear">skin</seg> which <lb/> I am sure to like just as much <lb/>when I know more about them. <lb/> I hope you are feeling well. <lb/> It is too bad you should <lb/> have the shortage from the  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_10"/>
              company this year when every <lb/> thing is so dear however we <lb/> must all look forward to <lb/> brighter days soon as, as Gerald <lb/> said when I sent him the Photo <lb/> of Green bank Roses, which he <lb/> very greedily kept, he said they <lb/> look topping but we will all make <lb/> up for these bad times when the <lb/> war is over. I hope he will go &amp; <lb/> see you on his way home when <lb/> he gets leave. Mrs Gartlan wrote <lb/> me such a nice letter with all <lb/> their news. I do feel for her being <lb/> left all alone but am glad her <lb/> anxiety is lessened with Gerald's <lb/> appointment. I must close <lb/> now hoping you will be able <lb/> to read this awful scrawl. <lb/> written in a hurry as I just <lb/> had two hours off this morning to  
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_11"/>
              give Mrs Paul my help on half <lb/> day I had one yesterday <lb/> but had to go into Boulogne <lb/> to get another hut. as we are <lb/> not allowed to wear straw <lb/>after the 1st Oct. I got such <lb/> a nice useful sailor for 20 francs <lb/> My very fondest love to every <lb/> one &amp; tell them <seg type="unclear">all my thoughts</seg><lb/> I do not have much time <lb/> for writing. I am always <lb/> thinking &amp; wondering what they <lb/> are doing &amp; how they are. <lb/> With every good wish love &amp; thought <seg type="closer">  I remain always dearest Mother <lb/> Your most grateful &amp; loving <lb/> daughter  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg><seg type="postscript"> I hope you continue to have <lb/> good news of Tommy. how </seg> 
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_0109_img_1191_12"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> wish we could get him home <lb/> I am very anxious to hear <lb/> the results of poor Uncle Frank. <lb/> Love <lb/><hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>  You must be bored with <lb/> this but I just feel today <lb/> how I would love to be at <lb/> home have dear old chat <lb/> with you so if I have written <lb/> nonsense you know how I <lb/> am feeling. I am writing this <lb/> with your photo before me &amp; <lb/> trying to imagine I am speaking <lb/> to you dearest Mother.   Cheer Up the war will soon <lb/> be over I hope <lb/><hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>