<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2517">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter  from Jim Ellis to James Ryan</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jim Ellis</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Reply to James Ryan from his friend Jim Ellis. Ellis hadn&#39;t known where Ryan was until he received his letter. He tells Ryan about how their common acquaintances from UCD are getting on in  different Dublin Hospitals. He comments on the rough treatment Ryan had received in Stafford prison before being moved to Frongoch, where he was at the time writing. He mentions not wanting to write about political matters in case the letter is censored.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>P88/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2517</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0777">Jim Ellis</persName>
              <date>1916-06-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1565">489 St. Benedict&#39;s Gardens, Phibsborough</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Ryan (Jim)</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1908">Frongoch Prison, Wales </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2517_img_195_1"  type="Letter"  url="bc5bf65747fe336b64e069f3a7324874.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2517_img_195_2"  type="Letter"  url="17b8b39f3200315da6f2eb04f94ce579.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2517_img_195_3"  type="Letter"  url="46180afa3739df018f9fd7494a7e00bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2517_img_195_4"  type="Letter"  url="71303487cf750294711d27a8f3740eda.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2517_img_195_1"/>
             P88/22  1   489 St. Benedict's Gardens,<lb/>Phibsborough.    Friday <lb/><lb/> send some from the<lb/>insiders in a few<lb/>days. write soon<lb/>won't you. I'll save<lb/>up news now &amp;<lb/>when I hear from you<lb/>again I'll send you<lb/>all — <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>   All good wishes,<lb/>your old friend<lb/> Jim Ellis    <lb/><lb/> My Dear Jim,   I got your letter<lb/>yesterday &amp; I was delighted to hear<lb/>from you. I have been trying to<lb/>find out your address for weeks<lb/>but no one seemed to know your<lb/>where about.— I didn't meet any<lb/>of your girl friends or rather<lb/>I didn't know any of them. I<lb/>asked you a long time ago for an<lb/>intro to one of them &amp; you didn't<lb/>give it. aren't you sorry now that<lb/>his majesty has extended his<lb/>hospitality to you. I would look<lb/>after them for you.  I was certainly<lb/>surprised at the Rebellion. <seg type="unclear">Belloe</seg> has<lb/>blundered badly.— your spelling<lb/>of the gentlemans name was faulty— 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2517_img_195_2"/>
             but he was often wrong before &amp; <lb/> will again. I suppose there isnt <lb/> much use in telling you anything <lb/> that hasnt already appeared in <lb/> our West Briton press. The Censor <lb/>might be melted to tears &amp; dry <lb/> them with my letter. This much <lb/> is true that Dunleavy who hasnt <lb/> been to mass for seven years has <lb/> been to all the requiems.    The staff <lb/> here is alright except mac &amp; you <lb/> know his views arent up to very <lb/>much. He didnt make a statement <lb/> in the school however only in the <lb/> theatre where we went as far as <lb/> we could with the remembrance <lb/>of September before our Eyes. Tobin <lb/> is fine. He pays all kinds of tribute <lb/> to the bravery of the Volunteers.    The <lb/>scam is over. fine were up. <lb/> Miss <seg type="del">D</seg>Farrel got 1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> 2<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">nd</hi></hi> Honours  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2517_img_195_3"/>
             Landers Walsh &amp; OMahony got it. <lb/> &amp; Murphy was stuck again in <lb/> medicine. no one else was up. <lb/> Courtney is still in Vincent's He is <lb/> acting in the capacity of Chiropodist <lb/> to the Hospital. He amputated <seg type="del">a</seg> nurses <lb/> corn. It went septic &amp; she was three <lb/> days in bed.  Then  He was caught in the <lb/> ward with D Ryan the other night &amp;   <lb/> gave him hell. Ryan told her that <lb/> Courtney was working from 'the Rising <lb/> of the Sun till the going down there off" <lb/> Ryan is in Vincent's now. Very few <lb/>joined. Blake is the only recent <lb/> recruit. There were a few to go from the <lb/> mater. Lynch &amp; Stokes among the <lb/> number. I dont think they are going now. <lb/> I told Delaney &amp; Spain to write to you <lb/> &amp; also <seg type="del">I</seg> told Meskel among others <lb/>that you send your love to them. I gave <lb/> the message individually. Meskel got <lb/> your address. so I hope to congratulate <lb/> you when I see you again.    I was <lb/>sorry your sisters got such rough  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2517_img_195_4"/>
             treatment. They are out now &amp; not<lb/>looking any the worse. Of course <hi rend="underline">I was</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">surprised</hi> at arrests of ladies. If I want<lb/>you to get the letter I had better say nothing<lb/>more. Probably the Censor doesnt swear<lb/>himself &amp; beside as our leader John Redmond<lb/>says I wouldnt say anything that would<lb/>interfere with the friendly relation now<lb/>existing <hi rend="underline">between</hi> the <hi rend="underline">sister countries</hi>  However<lb/>Jim I wish you were back. I'd beat<lb/>you at snooker now. I'm getting to be a dub<lb/>at it. I might wait &amp; be up with<lb/>you in March but Johnny will have<lb/>to give me permission in September.<lb/>If he doesnt I'll make you my assistant<lb/><seg type="del">woeks</seg> you must have been almost<lb/>mad for the first three weeks you were<lb/>away. The treatment evidently was not<lb/>even as good as that given to criminals<lb/>at least I hope you will be much better<lb/>off in Wales. I suppose you was sadly<lb/>disappointed at the treatment you got. you<lb/>never expected such did you?  There arent<lb/>any Volunteers in Vincents. There was a<lb/>young girl there who was in the Surgeons<lb/>&amp; she was arrested but as she wasnt<lb/>better.— she was wounded — Kennedy kicked<lb/>up a row &amp; she was sent back again.<lb/>She was taken without his knowledge.  I'm<lb/>sending you some cigarettes now. we will 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>