<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0130">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Bridie O'Rahilly to Anna O'Rahilly, 25 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Bridie O&#39;Rahilly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Bridie O&#39;Rahilly (d. 1971) to Anna O&#39;Rahilly (d. 1958). In the letter Bridie offers Anna sympathy on the death of her brother Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). Bridie writes that the people in her area seem to be proud that Michael came from their village, Ballylongford (County Kerry) and that Michael&#39;s sister, Nell, had been released from prison.Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/122/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/130</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0135">Bridie O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1330">Listowel, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0130_img_1219_1"  type="Letter"  url="90f883c938988788410b16b77d49097e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0130_img_1219_2"  type="Letter"  url="005a7ca825c26ef403721fc053f52193.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0130_img_1219_1"/>
              <seg type="del">All Letters to be addressed to the Agent</seg>    Bank of Ireland Office,  Listowel    25th May 1916.   My dear Anna,   It is time for me to write to you, but <lb/> it is not from want of thought that I <lb/> have deferred writing until now. I have <lb/> scarcely ceased thinking of you all <lb/>since I heard the terribly sad news <lb/> about poor Michael; and I have prayed <lb/>fervently for him and for you all every day <lb/>since. This was the only small way in <lb/> which I could assist you. Sometimes I <lb/>wonder how the rest of you managed <lb/> to survive these past few weeks at all. <lb/> But with the Cross God gives the <lb/>needful grace, I suppose.  It would have only added to <lb/> your grief, if possible, could you have <lb/> seen how the country people round <lb/> here took poor Michael's death. Except I <lb/> had been on the spot I could not have <lb/>credited it. They seemed to have been <lb/> very proud that this was his native <lb/> district; and I know that he will <lb/>have a most impressive funeral when <lb/>he is brought down to the Abbey. R.I.P.  I am very glad, indeed, that <lb/>Nell is released again. I hope she  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0130_img_1219_2"/>
              is not feeling very done up after the <lb/>prison treatment. Or perhaps the <lb/>women are treated somewhat better. <lb/> Mother told me, too, that you have <lb/>heard Dick is well. D.G. If he were <lb/> in Dublin even it would be a relief <lb/> to you.  A Miss Barrett from Ballylongford told <lb/>me she heard from you. She wept <lb/>when speaking of Michael, but, indeed, I <lb/> have seen many others do the same. <lb/>He has the prayers of all the country- <lb/>side round here. But I am sure he <lb/> is now happy with God. He was so v. <lb/> kind to others always that God will not <lb/> be outdone in generosity.  Ml. McEllistrem of Ballylongford is dying <lb/> at present. I believe he is some relation <lb/>of the family?  I hope I will see you when I am home <lb/> on holidays next month.  With deepest and heartfelt sympathy to <lb/> you, Nell and Nannie and with much <lb/>love. <seg type="closer"> I am, dear Anna, <lb/>Your affectionate cousin, <lb/> Bridie <hi rend="underline">O'Rahilly</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>