<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0073">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ernest Blythe to George Gavan Duffy, 12 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ernest Blythe</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Ernest Blythe (1889-1975) to George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951). Only the first page of the letter has survived. Blythe has been detained in Brixton Prison, England, and he has seven days to make representations. He asks Duffy to advise and assist him. George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising. Earnest Blythe was an organiser for the Irish Volunteers. He had been arrested under the Defence of the Realm Act. He was released from prison in England before the Easter Rising but was rearrested there during Easter week 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD/45/3/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/73</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1286">Ernest Blythe</persName>
              <date>1916-05-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0091">Brixton Prison, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0073_img_1142_1"  type="Letter"  url="9037d7666456cf3661212a46666ce8d2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0073_img_1142_1"/>
              In replying to this letter, please write on the envelope:-    Number <hi rend="underline">313</hi> Name <hi rend="underline">Blythe E</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Brixton</hi> Prison     <hi rend="underline">12 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May </hi> 1916    Dear Mr. Gavin Duffy,   I was <lb/>interned here on Wednesday <lb/>by order of the Home Secretary. <lb/>I am allowed, within seven <lb/> days, to make representations <lb/>against the provisions of the <lb/>order and I think it better <lb/>to have your advice and <lb/> assistance in doing so. As   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>