<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5933">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate English to Patrick English in prison, c. June/July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate English </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Kate English to her son Patrick. In this letter Kate informs Patrick that their family will be moving to the enclosed address as his sister, Nellie, has taken a big house for the family. In his application for a state pension, in recognition of his service, Patrick would later state that his family were evicted from their home in Dunsink as a result of his service during Easter Week. Kate also informs Michael of the local news before ending the letter with the enclosure of a PO for one shilling so Patrick can buy some cigarettes.This letter was written by Kate (b. 1855) to Patrick English (1894-1970) while he was interned. Patrick had been stationed in the G.P.O for the Rising. Following the surrender he was sent to Stafford Prison before being moved to Frongoch internment camp in Wales.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5933</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0694">Kate English </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0146">Blackhorse Lane, Phoenix Park, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5933_img_1393_1"  type="Letter"  url="25a5afd2625bbc6180bbc65337d80732.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5933_img_1393_2"  type="Letter"  url="a6499a20bda7e8c936cb42e073a4c878.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5933_img_1393_3"  type="Letter"  url="36d0c4d7c3ef7354d08ce7791a696a0b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5933_img_1393_4"  type="Letter"  url="090bea4b784aa2c812e3c64d2f33f7da.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5933_img_1393_1"/>
                No 2 Ashtown Villa.  Blackhorse Lane,  <hi rend="underline">Phoenix Park.</hi>    My dear Patrick    I was delighted to get your <lb/> letter Saturday morning but <lb/> I am very disappointed you were <lb/> not here yourself but we cant help <lb/> You must only wait your turn <lb/> Mickey Dolan arrived home on <lb/> Friday. I am leaving here <lb/> and going to live with Nellie<lb/> in the above address. She has <lb/> taken a big house so that <lb/> will be our home when you <lb/> arrive, it is just at Smiths  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5933_img_1393_2"/>
              the dairy people, so if you <lb/> get this letter before you come <lb/> I will be gone but I am not <lb/> sure what day I am going <lb/> yet I am delighted you are able <lb/> to get to mass every day <lb/> that alone will cheer you up <lb/> and when you are in the <lb/> best of health we have <lb/> a lot to be thankful for <lb/> but I trust in God you will <lb/> be home soon for I am dying <lb/> to see you once more <lb/> I am grand myself I feel <lb/> young again since the nice  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5933_img_1393_3"/>
              weather has come in. All <lb/> the doolans looks fine <seg type="del">that</seg><lb/> Poor Mikey is limping <lb/> still but he wont be long <lb/> until he is alright. I was <lb/> speaking to the Mc Nultys they <lb/> told me I won't know you <lb/> when you come home you <lb/> are quite <seg type="del">official</seg> a favourite <lb/> with all Jamesy sends his <lb/> best love and Marie Katie &amp; Nellie <lb/> Frank they are delighted <lb/> with their new home it is <lb/> so convenient to everything  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5933_img_1393_4"/>
              I think I will say no more <lb/> now only I hope by the <lb/> time this reaches you <lb/> you will be home here <lb/> if possible <lb/> but it could happen. <seg type="closer"> Good Bye dear Son <lb/> write soon if you are <lb/> there with Love from <lb/> <hi rend="underline">all your Fond Mother</hi> .</seg><seg type="postscript"> PS. Enclosed is a PO. for 1s. <lb/> to get <hi rend="underline">cigarettes</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>