<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0774">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 23 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Spender gives an account of his departure from the Ulster Volunteers and his journey to Calais. He gives details of the &#39;excitement and sadness&#39; he felt upon leaving, the unpleasantness of saying goodbye, the &#39;strained politeness&#39; of British and French officials, and the denouement of his conflicted relationship with another of the staff. Spender relates a humorous anecdote from his journey, and asks Lillian to send a newspaper (&#39;the MP&#39;) to his brother Rex, recently arrived in the trenches.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/358</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/774</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1794">Calais, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0774_img_2307_1"  type="NULL"  url="b898836c5d3a4e34ce458d5f0cc9e8b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0774_img_2307_2"  type="NULL"  url="c2a1c7f482fe71a7976d719cccf1ec2e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0774_img_2307_3"  type="NULL"  url="7a868175bef07a4b7f1da6926e71dd72.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0774_img_2307_4"  type="Letter"  url="5cf1716accf5911bb7315ef135f7fd02.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0774_img_2307_5"  type="NULL"  url="b898836c5d3a4e34ce458d5f0cc9e8b5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0774_img_2307_1"/>
              (posted 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>)    22 July   My Pr   I am writing this at Calais! I think the <lb/> censor will pass this as I shall be miles away in a <lb/> few hours. In fact I shall have made a tour of the <lb/> front &amp; have been  almost in sight of old England.  There is a certain kind of excitement about today <lb/>which relieves it's sadness. The goodbyes were unpleasant <lb/> as they always are more especially to Bruce Comyn  &amp; the <lb/> men. The former was I think quite touched as <lb/> were some of the clerks. P suddenly became rather <lb/>effusive of the help I had given. It didn't sound <lb/> quite real. He talked too much about my opportunities.   Any qualms I had about my going â except <lb/> those in respect of Rex â have gone after my <lb/> interview with W. I went to see him on my <lb/> return from seeing Rex, <seg type="unclear">W</seg> said I hear you are  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0774_img_2307_2"/>
              <lb/>going &amp; am sorry it should have happened after <lb/> what has occurred. We then talked over the <sic>affaire</sic><lb/> &amp; he hoped it would be a lesson to me â It  not  being <lb/> double promotion presumably - . It was obvious at <lb/>any rate he was completely out of rapport, &amp; I do <lb/> not know how many months  or years  it would take to <lb/> put things right, if ever. He also afterwards tried<lb/> to inform the occasion of one's great possibilities â to <lb/> help one's friends I think â this as an afterthought.<lb/> I write now in some bitterness. Now as to <lb/>the amusement   At 2 where I took the train Comyn &amp; I <lb/>had lunch together. There was a Major in the <lb/> staff â <seg type="unclear">Ry stuff</seg> â elderly but nice just a trifle <lb/> inclined to do the superior officer. Not wishing <lb/> to turn up in <seg type="unclear">false guise</seg> Douglas' suggestion of  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0774_img_2307_3"/>
              <lb/>alteration of rank was carried out &amp; the Div <seg type="unclear">armour </seg><lb/> changed for the Army one. Who should be at the station <lb/>but this same Major who proceeded to hunt the poor wretched <lb/> Col all over the place with an interpreter for his luggage <lb/>another officer for his ticket, etc. Neither Douglas nor <lb/>I minding the carrying of our own trappings as you <lb/>knowâ. He was puzzled &amp; at last came to the <lb/> conclusion that I was the same man , I think, <lb/>which must have been rather a shock. Since <lb/>then I have been in a constant state of strained <lb/>politeness with elderly French officers, &amp; British officers <lb/>of all ranks who regard me as a strange kind of <lb/>specimen, which doesn't quite please me, but I <lb/>expect at the end of the war when I return to <lb/>a mere Captain I shouldn't like the 2 step fall <lb/>even tho' I don't appreciate the 2 step rise now <lb/>very much.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0774_img_2307_4"/>
               I found time to write to Mater after all, &amp; <lb/> hope she will be able to crow a little to you when <lb/> you go to let her know. You won't mind &amp; it <lb/> pleases me to think that she will not feel a pr <lb/>has entirely <seg type="del">rubbed her nose out of joint</seg> just robbed her of her son.   Would you send the MP on to Rex 12 R Ir Rif <lb/>this next week in the evenings until he has <lb/>time to order his own paper. I know what a <lb/>luxury this will be to him in the trenches, &amp; <lb/>it is a Kindness which the pr will undertake tho' <lb/>it does mean trouble. Next week his own paper <lb/>will have bee. ordered by me I hope, if he does not <lb/>get any Company mess papers.   By the way Rex has a curious idea about Lil's <lb/><seg type="unclear">horn</seg> .  I am to enquire if you are sure as to Daisy's <lb/>age soundness &amp; sex !   This is written in the train. I do not arrive till <lb/> 2 P.M. <seg type="closer"> Your  b w<lb/> WB Spender </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0774_img_2307_5"/>
               added to page 1 <seg type="postscript"> The next few days are likely to <lb/> be wildly busy so expect few or <lb/> no letters. <lb/>I am 'attached to the 15 Corps' to which please address letters </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>