<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0770">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 21 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender discusses a slur which he has recently suffered, speculating as to the perpetrator&#39;s identity and motivation. He warns that the newspapers&#39; optimism on the war&#39;s progress is unfounded, that recent victories have been only partial, and that the fighting could well last for another year. He writes that he will be returning to the trenches quite soon. Spender relates a conversation he had with a sapper, Craig, which exemplified Craig&#39;s patriotism and dedication to the cause. He warns that if loyal soldiers of Craig&#39;s type are swamped by unwilling conscripts, the results will not be good - particularly if all the conscripts are recruited towards the end of the war, and not throughout.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/354</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/770</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0770_img_2303_1"  type="NULL"  url="497a01ffc9b59b5922c44c8766f44607.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0770_img_2303_2"  type="NULL"  url="8837f4956d2f6f2f8bdd20f7a43298bb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0770_img_2303_3"  type="NULL"  url="7f039e9415495c336eec7d72fa9065ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0770_img_2303_4"  type="NULL"  url="5f576b937361baa25e80fc385673becd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0770_img_2303_1"/>
                21 July 1916   My pr   I have just got your <hi rend="underline">extra nice</hi> letter. You by all <lb/>means tell the family or any one you like, provided that it <lb/>does not lead to an appeal which tho' kindly intended <lb/> would make me very angry, &amp; would almost certainly do <lb/> more harm than good. Anyhow I would not attempt one <lb/> myself nor any explanation. If one year's intercourse <lb/>cannot absorb one from their kind of misunderstandings I'm <lb/>hanged if it is worthwhile attempting any reconciliation.  I am not sure now who has done this stupidity, whether <lb/>G.C. Wrawfor or so I think Genl P. <seg type="del">to</seg> via  Sir G.. Perhaps <lb/>it is as well. All of them have behaved in a peculiar way, <lb/>but I like them too well to cause them the great <lb/><sic>distain</sic> which they would feel if they knew.  Old fat S rather enjoys stirring up mud &amp; began to <lb/>run me down for being too polite to the Corps etc at <lb/>dinner. 'You ought to be firm'. The thing that I had not <lb/>been firm about was in not protesting against Div H A  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0770_img_2303_2"/>
              being moved at 1 days' notice, as if it didn't care what <lb/>happened to our battalions &amp; men who had to march but <lb/>protested about our precious <seg type="unclear">selves</seg> who have motors &amp; <lb/>lorries. G also supported old S that I ought to protest <lb/>against the inconvenience but C who is a soldier at any <lb/>rate, said that if we did not move to the new place <lb/>someone else would &amp; that we should then be between <lb/>2 stools, so I carried my way but not pleasantly. Old <lb/> S is as selfish as they make them &amp; pampers  selfishness  in others, <lb/>&amp; will get promoted in consequence. Perhaps he earns it for it <lb/>must be unpleasant   I think you have caught the newspaper optimism. If <lb/>you get the chance tell Sredward that in my view the <lb/>situation is much more critical than it has been for a <lb/>year past &amp; that partial success now means another <lb/> year's delay &amp; then equally no progress at the present <lb/> rate of preparation. I would go further &amp; say that unless <lb/>the nation is prepared at once to redouble its efforts, making  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0770_img_2303_3"/>
              <lb/>the whole empire work at full stretch &amp; no half measures  it is no good going on.   I look upon our present action as absolutely inadequate <lb/>&amp; think we shall get into a worse instead of a better position <lb/>if things drift on, &amp; that unless we can make our minds <lb/>at once to tighten up every screw it would be better to <lb/>finish at once. I have less confidence in the Government <lb/>now that ever before &amp; really think that unless Sredward <lb/>does what he told you he can do he had better let them <lb/>give terms which I understand are now <seg type="del">obtainable</seg> dictatable.   As you know I am not a pessimist but as things <lb/>stand now it seems to me that Balfour is trying to make <lb/>the nation face what we are really up against instead of <lb/><seg type="unclear">mistaking</seg> our costly success was taking the most patriotic <lb/>course. The present policy of partial effort will mean a <lb/>far more inconclusive finish <seg type="del">when</seg> than is now possible <lb/>when every one has come to the end of their resources, <lb/>except our Yankee cousins.   Some of our men will be in the trenches again tomorrow <lb/>and it is only a matter of days before we follow. I cannot of <lb/>course tell <seg type="del">wh</seg> you what part of the country we are in, but <lb/>it is more fertile &amp; the people nicer that I had been led  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0770_img_2303_4"/>
              to expect    I had tea with the sapper Craig yesterday . He is a <lb/>nice chap &amp; seems fairly satisfied about Charles being all <lb/>right. He was left for 8 days in our old area when the <lb/>Division moved &amp; &amp; spoke guardedly but very strongly about <lb/>the difference between our men &amp; theirs, &amp; there is no <lb/>doubt in my mind that we <seg type="del">shall get a</seg> cannot expect <lb/>anything from future elements in comparison with the original <lb/>new armies who were inspired by partition. The swarms <lb/>of unwilling conscripts will undoubtedly swamp the old <lb/> type by being saved till the end instead of being <lb/>mixed with them in moderate quantities earlier.   I must not let this letter end without lifting up <lb/>the <seg type="del">wrap</seg> curtain a little to the p v, to let her peep under &amp; see <lb/>what a very different bw is behind thanks to her help. <lb/>She knows this jolly well but never objects being told ! <lb/>It is a beautiful summer day when we could have a <lb/>great romp, I don't think the weather will matter <lb/>much when we are together again. I'm glad your work <lb/> is a little less &amp; that the money is coming in for you <lb/>must need it all. By the way some of our Ulster Div men <lb/><seg type="del">may</seg> now have been transferred to other Divisions but you <lb/>will of course look after them just the same. <seg type="closer"> Your  b w WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>