<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6662">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from H. J. Kavanagh to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 23 February 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>H. J. Kavanagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter H. J. Kavanagh tells Joseph Cyrillus Walsh about the duty of the Canadians to support the Irish cause, although this would simultaneously mean suffering with the Irish.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph Cyrillus Walsh Papers. Letters: Jenkinson - Lee</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6662</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0411">H. J. Kavanagh</persName>
              <date>1920-02-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0319">Provincial Bank Building, 7 Place d&#39;Armes Montreal, Canada</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0347">4 11 Fifth Avenue, New York, New York, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6662_img_None_1"  url="php4pMVyW.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6662_img_None_2"  url="php3XMZ1L.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6662_img_0_1"/>
             Kavanagh Lajoie &amp; Lacoste  Advocates  M.J Kavanagh, K.C.,  H Gerin-Lajoie, K.C.,  Paul Lacoste, K.C.,  Alex Lacoste, L.L.B,  Henri Gerin-Lajoie, B.C.L.,  Alexandre Gerin-Lajoie, L.L.L.  Hon Sir Alexandre Lacoste, K.C., Counsel  7/C   Cable Address LALOI, Belle Telephones: MAin 8675    Provincial Bank Building, 7 Place d'Armes, Montreal    February 23rd 1920   J.C. Walsh Esq.,  American Commission on Irish Independence,  411 Fifth Avenue,  New York, U.S.A.   Dear Walsh:-   I wrote Mr. Frank P. Walsh thanking him for<lb/>the three copies of his report he sent me at your request;<lb/>now, let me thank you. They are properly placed; do send me<lb/>some more . -- Gratitude a sense of favours to come !  I hope Lord Shaughnessy will propose Canada, and<lb/>McKenzie-King will answer; that Ireland will be proposed by<lb/>the speaker from the United States, and Guerin's suggestion is<lb/>that the answer should be by Mr. O'Farrell who, you remember,<lb/>was with T.P.O'Connor when the latter made that amusing <sic>speach</sic><lb/>at the Canadian Club some years ago.  About a month ago there was a meeting in my office to<lb/>determine Self Determination. Doctor Guerin, Emmet Walsh,<lb/>Quirk, Trihey, Wickham and Arthur Phelan were here. Then, there<lb/>was a meeting of delegates from societies, and the Irish Canadian<lb/>National League was projected. As our friends in the States have<lb/>been careful to be American, we are and must be Canadian. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6662_img_0_2"/>
             Kavanagh Lajoie &amp; Lacoste  -2-  If their impulse is sentiment, our impelling motive is the same<lb/>plus our duty as citizens of a part of what used to be known as<lb/>the British Empire, and which is now spoken of as the Commonwealth,<lb/>and with whose reputation the English part of it is playing the<lb/>devil. if this be so, <sic>is'nt</sic> it the duty of this country and of<lb/>its citizens to protest against the devilish game as strongly<lb/>as our weakness will allow. Canadians have a duty in this which<lb/>Americans have not. On the one hand, there is difficulty in<lb/>being <sic>undetstood</sic> by some of our own people, and on the other<lb/>hand there will be greater difficulty in making our protest<lb/>understood by Canadians who have no sympathy with us. I am<lb/>told that the activities of our new organization will probably<lb/>hurt us all. <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">Tant mieux</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi></hi> Sympathy with the suffering Irish<lb/>means suffering with them. <sic>Is'nt</sic> that the etymology of the<lb/>word ? And, by way of putting principles into practice and<lb/>making you <sic>practise </sic>them, don't let me hear you growl if<lb/>you have to suffer these lenghty luc<seg type="del">r</seg>ub r ations, <seg type="del">and that</seg> as that<lb/>dear old Tory, Father Prout, would sneeringly call them.  With kindest regards to yourself, and <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">mes </hi></hi><hi rend="underline"></hi>  <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"></hi></hi><hi rend="underline"></hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">salutations respectueuses à Madame</hi>,</hi>  <hi rend="underline"></hi>Yours faithfully,  Henry J. Kavanagh 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>