<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3805">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A.J. Cockington to the Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A.J. Cockington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from A.J. Cockington, on the behalf of the General Council of Medical Education &amp; Registration for the United Kingdom, to the acting registrar of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) regarding the admission of Dr R. Fraser as a member of the college and the change of name relating to the former Dr Myer Cohen. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T78-8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3805</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0563">A.J. Cockington</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0329">299 Oxford Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3805_img_3188_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc0554b69fd021546c8e4c6456bf18ad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3805_img_3188_1"/>
             General Council of <lb/>Medical Education &amp; Registration <lb/>of the United Kingdom, <lb/>44, Hallam Street, Portland Place, London, W.   11th July, 1916.   The Registrar, <lb/>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, <lb/>Kildare Street, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I have to acknowledge with thanks the receipt of <lb/>your letter of the 8th inst., received this morning, inform- <lb/>ing me that Dr. R.F. Frazer has been admitted a Member of <lb/>your College; and also that the name of Mr. Meyer Cohen, <lb/>L.R.C.P. &amp; S I., has been changed to Myles Colt at his request, <lb/>for which I am much obliged. I have had previous correspondence <lb/>in regard to Mr. Cohen's change of name in the Medical Register.   Yours faithfully,   AJ Cockington,   <lb/>Acting Registrar.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>