<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0516">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cecil Pim to E. A. Aston, 15 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cecil Pim</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Cecil Pim, owner of the Greenmount Factory, to E. A. Aston, Inspector of the Local Government Board (LGB), Dublin, replying to Aston&#39;s letter of 11 March. Pim provides reasons for the reduction of working hours in the spinning and weaving factories in Belfast. He also provides reasons for the reduction in output in the weaving industry since the outbreak of the war, including difficulties in obtaining raw materials and the price of those materials. While obtaining coal has not been a problem up to now, he speculates that a shortage may be a problem in future.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, NAI-CSORP-1916-7443-16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/516</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1170">Cecil Pim</persName>
              <date>1916-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1772">Greenmount Factory, Harold&#39;s Cross, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">E. A. Aston</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1501">Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0516_img_1888_1"  type="Letter"  url="54b8c7e05ed8bea7cd9b92de3faae8f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0516_img_1888_2"  type="Letter"  url="9dbe3a357eb4bddc34ccf982998eedd4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0516_img_1888_3"  type="Letter"  url="7b88f642c5573f8dd4e4a9d25e51b06c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0516_img_1888_1"/>
               TELEGRAMS   GREENMOUNT DUBLIN   TELEPHONE   6 RATHMINES     GREENMOUNT FACTORY  HAROLDS CROSS  DUBLIN     15th March 1916   Dear Mr Aston,   In reply to your letter of the 11th inst.   The Spinning &amp; Weaving Factories in Belfast have been <lb/> working nominally 40 hours a week for the past twelve months.<lb/> In some cases ( in the Weaving Factories ) the hours worked were, for a <lb/> short time, considerably less. <sic>Tha</sic> majority of the factories are <lb/> working now I should say about 47 hours a week.- A few may be running <lb/> less than this. On the other hand, several are working full time.   The causes in reduction of output were several - first<seg type="del">deleted text</seg>ly <lb/> the difficulties in getting supplies of raw materials after the outbreak <lb/> of war were such that it was thought better to restrict the output <lb/> to a considerable extent. Secondly, owing to these difficulties, <lb/> the prices of the raw material rose with great rapidity. In addition <lb/> freights advanced to an enormous extent, and when the cost of War Risk <lb/> Insurance is added to this, the advance in the <hi rend="underline">finished article</hi> is <lb/><hi rend="underline">anything up to 50%</hi>, consequently buyers were extremely loth to buy, <lb/> and the <hi rend="underline">orders received for many months by the weaving trade were very <lb/> much less than their ordinary production of cloth</hi>.  This refers in particular to the <hi rend="underline">American trade</hi>, which<lb/> is as you now, our chief market, and many looms suitable for this trade <lb/> had to be stopped altogether, but <hi rend="underline">this I think shows signs of improve- ment</hi>.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0516_img_1888_2"/>
              The volume of orders which has been coming into Belfast for <lb/> the past two months has been large, and the trade would be in a <lb/> fairly satisfactory condition were it not again for the great difficulty <lb/> in getting raw materials. Not only is the supply of linen yarn limited <lb/> but the price has advanced to a point which makes it almost prohibitive <lb/> consequently an enormous number of looms are now weaving cotton and <lb/> union goods, and here again we are in great difficulty, as it is <lb/> becoming more and more difficult to get cotton yarns from Lancashire <lb/> owing to the congestion on the English Railways. I think I mentioned <lb/> this point to you last week when we met.-    The forgoing remarks apply altogether to Weaving Factories. <lb/> With regard to the Spinning Mills I am afraid I can give you <lb/> very little information as we are no longer spinners ourselves. <lb/> They have as I said, been running 40 hours a week, but some of the <lb/> fine spinners have now received permission from the Association to <lb/> work longer hours. In this connection I may mention that the <lb/> Spinners Association is now an incorporated body, and all the members <lb/> have to conform to the decisions of the Council as regards hours of <lb/> work etc.,under fairly heavy penalties. On the other hand,  in the case of  the <lb/> weavers, not yet being incorporated, it is very hard to tell exactly <lb/> what is being done, as there is no means of enforcing the recommendat- ions of the Council, and many factories I think act solely as suits <lb/> their individual arrangements.  As to the question of <hi rend="underline">coal</hi>, I have not heard of any mills <lb/> or factories having to reduce their hours of work owing to a shortage  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0516_img_1888_3"/>
              of coal, and I doubt very much that such has occurred. On the other <lb/> hand, this is going to be one of the greatest difficulties for the <lb/> next twelve months, and I <hi rend="underline">very much fear that there will be serious <lb/> trouble, but up to the present I think no actual stoppage or <lb/> curtailment of time has occurred owing to this cause.</hi> <seg type="closer"> Yours Faithfully  <hi rend="underline">Cecil Pim</hi> </seg> <hi rend="underline">E A Aston</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>