<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5287">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to William Tyrrell Sr., 27 October 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

Summary of the present letter:

Soldiers from another country are staying with Willie&#39;s regiment. He is amused at the language barrier. The regiment has recently been assigned a very good cook. A recent advance near Ypres is mentioned.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5287</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-10-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Tyrrell Sr.</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5287_img_None_1"  url="6e8461a76cb3b4ec66b3f052f0339e89.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5287_img_None_2"  url="21fcfc120e068bbb876f8c04574f31f6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5287_img_0_1"/>
              Saturday 27th Oct 17    My dear Daddy   I was delighted to get your grand<lb/>long letter last evening even if there is<lb/>no news. I am very glad that Bernie<lb/>got an extension of his leave.  I am not yet near Garrettt and I do<lb/>not know when we are to move yet.  I was out all day long yesterday on<lb/>a working party and it rained in torrents<lb/>the whole time so we were like<lb/>drowned rats when we got back.  This is a lovely fine day but a<lb/>bit frosty. Of course we are getting<lb/>well on towards winter now as it is<lb/>almost November.  We have got a great number of<lb/>new officers just lately from all<lb/>sorts of places including one transferred<lb/>from A.S.C.  This is a splendid village where we 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5287_img_0_2"/>
             can get absolutely anything we want<lb/>and the people are awfully good to <lb/>us.  It is not a bit knocked about<lb/>and you would never know there<lb/>was a war on at all.  I do not think it is any harm to    <lb/>say that we had some soldiers of<lb/>another nation attached to <seg type="del">yo</seg> us<lb/>in the trenches for instruction.  It was<lb/>very amusing because they could not<lb/>speak our language and we could<lb/>not speak theirs.  Will you please send  out<lb/>the recipe for potato cakes because<lb/>we have got a very good cook<lb/>and I am sure he could make them.  There seems to have been another<lb/>big advance at Ypes yesterday<lb/>No news at all and I will<lb/>write soon again.   With best love<lb/>Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>