<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1421">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mabel FitzGerald to Brigadier General, Richmond Barracks, 22 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mabel FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Mabel FitzGerald (1884-1957) to the Brigadier General, Richmond Barracks. Mabel writes to query the sentence imposed on her husband, Desmond FitzGerald, (1888-1947), politician, poet, and revolutionary. He was sentenced at Court-Martial to 20 years Penal Servitude, later reduced to 10 years. Mrs FitzGerald protests as, she claims, while her husband was present in the G.P.O. during the fighting, he was a non-combatant. Furthermore, she writes, he wasn&#39;t involved in the planning of the Rising. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers. P80/1577/1, FitzGerald Papers. P80/1577/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1421</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-05-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0247">Bray, Co.Wicklow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Brigadier General, Richmond Barracks</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1421_img_832_1"  type="Letter"  url="9f7674e8aade394a21853016a9d6bb00.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1421_img_832_1"/>
                2 Loretto Villas,  Bray.    22.5.1916    The Brigadier General,  Richmond Barracks,  Dublin.   Sir,   In reply to yours of 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> (inst 109/A.) as my husban d <lb/> was a non-combatant and held no rank whatsoever in the Volunteers <lb/> and as I understand from him that Lieut. King who was a prisoner <lb/> in the G.P.O. made a deposition that he was a non combatant, I <lb/> think some grave blunder has been made in sentencing him to <seg type="del">two</seg><lb/>twenty years Penal Servitude, a blunder which is not by any <seg type="del">men</seg><lb/> means rectified by the remittance of ten years.  I understand from my husband that the only evidence <lb/> against him was his own statement, in which he voluntarily admitted <lb/> his presence in the G.P.O. and stated the part which he <lb/> took in non-combatant work, and that he was neither trained nor <lb/> equipped to fight. Had he been, he would not have been told <seg type="del">of</seg><lb/> off to take women and <seg type="del">children</seg> wounded  to a place of safety when the <seg type="del">G.</seg><lb/>G.P.O. was on fire.  It is obvious that when he was in Mountjoy Prison <sic>fr</sic><lb/>for a Speech from last October till within three weeks of the <lb/> Rebellion he had no share in planning it. As, therefore, he <lb/> was neither responsible for it, nor did he take a prominent or <sic>e</sic><lb/> even a belligerent part in it, the sentence of 20 years can on ly <lb/> only have been passed by error, and that it was confirmed with <lb/> remittance of only 10 years is evidence that the full facts of <lb/> the case could not have been familiar to the General Officer <lb/> Commanding in Chief. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Yours faithfully  Mabel W.Fitzgerald </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>