<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2018">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Mitchell Moubray to Robert Chalmers, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Mitchell Moubray</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from John Mitchell Moubray (b. 1856) to Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) under-secretary for Ireland. Chalmers became under-secretary for a brief period following the resignation of Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who relinquished his position following his political failure during the 1916 Easter Rising. The letter is an application by Moubray to acquire a permit for the travel of one of his Irish workers. In the enclosed letter he states that John Campbell, the Irish worker, and a boy. He goes on to state he requires them at once.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>National Archive of Ireland-Chief Secretary&#39;s Office-Registered Papers; NAI/CSO/RP/1916/5611/8173/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2018</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0577">John Mitchell Moubray</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0633">Sutton Farm, Lewes, East Sussex</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0858">Irish Office, Old Queen Street, Westminster, London.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2018_img_1466_1"  type="Letter"  url="62f3371e9cd9ff1f9ce6600d004b6b3f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2018_img_1466_1"/>
             SUTTON FARM, <lb/>LEWES.   13 May 1916   The Under Sec. <lb/>of the Irish Office <lb/>Old Queen Street <lb/>Westminster.   Dear Sir,   Please fwd a Licence to come to me <lb/> to John Campbell Faheens Swinford <lb/> County Mayo Ireland &amp; one for a boy <lb/> the Boy I am not quite sure about. I <lb/> require Campbell at once as he is my <lb/> Head Stockman. I expect 2 more <lb/>over
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>