<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3792">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Cahill to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Cahill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from solicitor Michael Frederick Cahill on the behalf of Dr Aimai Maneckji Cooper, a licentiate of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI), regarding the removal of the name &#39;Grace&#39; from Dr Cooper&#39;s certificates and records.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T68-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3792</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0813">Michael Cahill</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1478">16 Cleveland Road, Ilford, Essex, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0320">Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3792_img_3176_1"  type="Letter"  url="c47fb942c4ee0ccd79302fec5f81b27d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3792_img_3176_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="5f3da0051f385b4953f59b6fd73ccb58.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3792_img_3176_1"/>
             M. F. CAHILL, <lb/>Solicitor.   16, CLEVELAND ROAD, <lb/>ILFORD, ESSEX.   29. 5. 16   Dear Sir,   Miss Aimai M. Cooper   I lam much obliged by your courteous note to hand <lb/>on Saturday: and I enclose declaration of identity <lb/>with P. O. 21/. and am sending under separate <lb/>registered <seg type="unclear">way</seg> (1) the Physicians Diploma and (2) <lb/>License in Midwifery each dated 3 February 1899.   Kindly acknowledge safe receipt have the change of <lb/>name duly registered and return the diplomas to <lb/>me together with a letter from you (for the Medical <lb/>Register here) stating the change of name and <lb/>certifying that it has been duly made in your <lb/>books.   Yours faithfully   M. J. Cahill   R. Phelps Esq <lb/>R.C.P.I. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3792_img_3176_2"/>
             I Michael Frederick Cahill of 16 Cleveland Road <lb/>Ilford Essex, Solicitor solemnly and sincerely declare <lb/>as follows:   1. I am well acquainted with Miss Aimai Maneckji <lb/>Cooper of 15th High Road Ilford. She was formerly <lb/>known as Aimai Grace Maneckji Cooper but has <lb/>now discontinued the name "Grace."   2. She is the same person as Aimai Grace <lb/>Maneckji Cooper mentioned in the Certificates <lb/>issued by the Royal College of Physicians in <lb/>Ireland on the 3rd day of February 1899 to <lb/>Aimai Grace Maneckji Cooper being the one a <lb/>License in Midwifery and the other a Certificate <lb/>that she is a Physician and Licentiate in <lb/>Medicine of the said College. She is also the <lb/>same person to whom a Qualifying Cerficate <lb/>in Medicine Surgery and midwifery was issued <lb/>on the 2nd February 1899 by the Conjoint <seg type="unclear">Humanities</seg> <lb/>Board of the said Royal College of Physicians <lb/>and the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland <lb/>and she is the person described in all the <lb/>said Certificates as Aimai Grace Maneckji <lb/>Cooper.   M. J. Cahill   Declared by the said Michael <lb/>Frederick Cahill at 61 Moorgate <lb/>Street in the City of London <lb/>this 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day of May 1916 <lb/>Before me <lb/>H. I <seg type="unclear">Tiddlemen</seg> <lb/>A Commissioner for Oaths 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>