<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1518">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eithne A. Kelly to Nancy O'Rahilly, 14 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eithne A. Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter of condolence from Eithne A. Kelly to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). The letter is an expression of sympathy for Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly on the death of her husband, fighting in the Easter Rising. The writer says she prays for all those in the same situation.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Moore (Parnell) Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1518</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0748">Eithne A. Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-05-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1887">61 Anglesea Road, Donnybrook, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1518_img_978_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa02a53111738faa1f5f7537aa96445e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1518_img_978_2"  type="Letter"  url="8ec9028a233f7dce061ab799ca63e48a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1518_img_978_1"/>
                61, Anglesea Road  Donnybrook.    <hi rend="underline">May 14. 16</hi>   My dear Mrs O'Rahilly-   I should have <lb/> written before but that <lb/> I was afraid of dis <lb/>tressing you more . <lb/> God will give you <lb/>abundant reward for <lb/> your great sorrow &amp; <lb/>your love &amp; <seg type="unclear">fealty</seg> to him.  I pray for you &amp;  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1518_img_978_2"/>
              all afflicted so heavily, every <lb/>time I kneel down â  I wish I could do <lb/> anything for you. I <lb/> hope I may get the <lb/> opportunity some time, <seg type="closer"> Yrs. affy  <hi rend="underline">Eithne A Kelly</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>