<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1193">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr John Fitzgibbon to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, January 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Fitzgibbon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Fitzgibbon (1882-1918) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Fitzgibbon&#39;s financial issues, his health, and the experience of going through an offensive.Fr John &#39;Jack&#39; Fitzgibbon SJ was ordained a priest on 31st July 1915. His father, John Fitzgibbon, was a successful draper and Member of Parliament from 1910-1918. Fr Fitzgibbon served in the 6th Division of the British Army, having enlisted shortly after the death of his brother at Gallipoli. He was promoted to senior chaplain in 1917, and in the same year he was gassed at Loos on 5th September and awarded the military cross. Fr Fitzgibbon was killed in action by a shell on the 18th September 1918, and is buried at Trefcon, St. Quentin, Picardie.Father Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/17, IJA/CHPI/21/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1193</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0632">John Fitzgibbon</persName>
              <date>1918-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1022">France </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1193_img_3876_1"  type="Letter"  url="55833f357efbce03783ee1d9ee301af2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1193_img_3876_2"  type="Letter"  url="7888b2564f5f6c583b367f7726cad648.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1193_img_3876_1"/>
               Jan (1918)    Dear Fr Provincial — P.C.   I am enclosing <lb/>cheque for £30 as I think I have <lb/>at least that much to my credit. <lb/>This past six months has been <lb/>exceptionally expensive in the way <lb/>of donations of all kinds e.g. for <lb/>Xmas &amp; several officers &amp; men <lb/>in our unit got married to which <lb/>the officers subscribed rather lavishly <lb/>apart from the fact that I lost <lb/>the most valuable part of my <lb/>kit in the <seg type="del">&amp; col</seg> withdrawal before <lb/>Cambrai &amp; I shall get more of it <lb/>back except whatever is on Army <lb/>list, so I have had to purchase <lb/>all kinds of things out here and <lb/>at exorbitant prices. Being at <lb/>the advanced aid post at the <lb/>time I shall find it hard to prove <lb/>that my belongins were not left <lb/>behind through carelessness,so I <lb/>may be at a loss for all. Then even <lb/>what I had with myself at the <lb/>aid post I had not time to collect <lb/>so they are also gone. However I have  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1193_img_3876_2"/>
              to thank God that I am alive for <lb/>such a time I have never had <lb/>since I came out here. Twice <lb/>was I practically in the hands of <lb/>the Germans in fact on one <lb/>occasion we were certain <lb/>that we were prisoners but we <lb/>were fortunately released by a <lb/>counter attack.  At present we are having <lb/>nothing but mud to tread on <lb/>and yesterday I had to be pulled <lb/>out of it, as my knee rubber boots <lb/>got stuck &amp; I had to leave them <lb/>behind &amp; rescue them later.  My health is just fair at <lb/>present &amp; since that attack, <lb/>but we hope to get a little <lb/>rest soon &amp; I feel I shall quickly <lb/>recover.  With best wishes dear Father Provincial <lb/>&amp; hoping you are ever so well. <seg type="closer"> I remain <lb/>Your obedient child <seg type="unclear">in xt</seg>   J. Fitzgibbon <lb/>s.j. </seg> P.S. <lb/>Would you mind telling <lb/>Father Farley I said <hi rend="underline">18</hi> Masses <lb/>for him in December.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>