<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0442">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from 'Teresa' (Agnes Ryan) to her brother James Ryan, 4 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Agnes Ryan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Agnes (Teresa) Ryan (1888-1967) to her brother James Ryan (1891-1970) during his imprisonment. Teresa writes that she will send him &#39;griddle bread with inserted rashers&#39;, and provides him with news from home. James Ryan studied medicine in University College Dublin. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch, and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>James Ryan Papers, P88 12 001</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/442</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0286">Agnes Ryan</persName>
              <date>1916-06-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0882">Tomcoole</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0442_img_178_1"  type="Letter"  url="1043bbd81e3a50cf88afec8b8caed271.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0442_img_178_2"  type="Letter"  url="dd5feb7c1027d1fc70b44798ca005f0c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0442_img_178_1"/>
                Tomcoole.    4.6.1916.   My dear Jim,   I believe you have written since to No 19. That is good and perfect. <lb/> I had you sent all you asked for + cheese and cooked sausage.<lb/> This week I shall send you home made griddle bread with inserted <lb/> rashers. Bowâ wow! Things are much the same here. The turkeyâcock <lb/> strayed on the holiday â eve and was considered gone until next <lb/> day Mike discovered him tail less and tale-less in the <seg type="unclear">Coolteen</seg><lb/> meadow. Whitty's squealing mare, which we are working every day <lb/> now, strayed the same evening and returned to <seg type="unclear">Ahclaire</seg> â near <lb/> Ross â from which Jim Sinnott + Mike redeemed her last evening. <lb/> They sold small pigs on the 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> for fabulous prices. Jack bought <lb/> a cow for Mr M. Murphy Forest yesterday in Wexford. He is getting <lb/> on well in his new office. Your exiled sisters are still 'in' <lb/> Everyone is going   them out at once but nothing has come <lb/> of it yet. I believe most of the homes in Co. Wexford were<lb/> made happy yesterday. Dinny &amp; Sean t are gone further on <lb/> their holidays: also, Ginger etc. I suppose it is considered <lb/> better for their health on the whole. It was spilling rain here <lb/> today. We went in two cars to 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Mass. Maura Power is <lb/> staying with us now. Her house was burnt down in Dublin. <lb/> I wrote to P. Kehoe. I am sure he is great gas in the common <lb/> mess. We are papering the drawing-room, dining-room, breakfast <lb/> room, doing some painting &amp; titivating under the Breagh  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0442_img_178_2"/>
              We had 2 descriptions from Fr. Paul on his visit to you. We <lb/> considered it very satisfactory and Mother is now quite at <lb/> ease about you. She expects you home though any day. <lb/> I suppose you will do your exam in Autumn as intended. <lb/> I meant to be in Dublin this weekend to see our friends <lb/> but I got a warning not to endanger my throat by <lb/> going out! Happily too, the excuse for going at all was <lb/> removed by the men going away on holidays.  The garden is going to be in great style this year. <lb/>The grass is nearly all lawnâmown now and some <lb/> flowers are in bloom alright. Did you come across <lb/> Sean McEntee Belfast there â a good looking, whiteâ<lb/>toothed, dark waving haired youth, a great friend of <lb/> mine &amp; D's. Look him up.  The sweet pea is out on the ditch. You never saw such <lb/> a show. The big black prize bull always adorns the <lb/> Lawn. They sold Martin's mare for Â£38 ' 10.  Dick is very advanced in his ways now â never <lb/> never stops giving out on our side. We have young Mick <lb/> Harpur employed along to  . The turkey<lb/> s up to <seg type="del">45</seg> 50 are at the cross. They have happened on a <lb/> most unfortunate season.  Jem H O.C. comes over fairly often. I think our Jim <lb/> is coming. Kathleen Phelan &amp; Lily Grant are to send<lb/> you some novels. We earnestly hope you are<lb/> studying hard. You'd be surprised at the<lb/> way people think nowadays again. <lb/> Mother is grand. <seg type="closer"> With love from all.<lb/> Your fond sister  Teresa. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>