<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5793">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay 19 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

This letter continues about wedding arrangements. The  introduction of daylight savings time is also mentioned. He mentions a friend&#39;s relative who was in the volunteers but not called up.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5793</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5793_img_891_1"  type="Letter"  url="460d325ddc3d32f4d8168da5e5b99c3a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5793_img_891_2"  type="Letter"  url="b32a7a2e03c35228569f1bfbd07f36be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5793_img_891_3"  type="Letter"  url="b35192d97a786b5f90d9d5c06ecbd1ae.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5793_img_891_1"/>
             39, Belgrave Square,<lb/>Rathmines,<lb/>Dublin.   19th May, 1916. <lb/>   My dearest May,   I got your watch from<lb/>Hopkins all right yesterday on giving<lb/>your name care of Mr Finn. There was<lb/>nothing wrong with it they tell me<lb/>except that it required adjustment. I<lb/>don't know what that means but in<lb/>any case it is going all right now and<lb/>I hope it will continue to do so. Don't<lb/>forget to put it on an hour on<lb/>Sunday morning in accordance with the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5793_img_891_2"/>
             Daylight Saving. You'll have Mass in<lb/>Loughnavalley in future on alternate<lb/>Sundays at 7:30 (real time) so even<lb/>your mother will be put to the trim<lb/>of her collar to be in time unless she<lb/>makes the necessary changes in her<lb/>timepieces. I got a letter from Pat Moran<lb/>this morning to say that he will act as<lb/>best man for me with pleasure so I<lb/>have that much fixed up any how.<lb/>By the way I should like very much to<lb/>ask Father Willie Moran to the marriage<lb/>in addition to father Frank if your<lb/>mother would not mind. I am afraid  <lb/>that the accommodation may be somewhat<lb/>restricted and if it gives her any<lb/>inconvenience I'll not ask him but<lb/>would be glad to hear from you.<lb/>The guests from my side of the house would<lb/>then be four at the <hi rend="underline">most</hi> viz Father<lb/>Frank &amp; Willie Moran, Pat Moran and<lb/>Nora. Probably Nora may not be able<lb/>to go and perhaps Father Willie also but<lb/>in any case it won't be more than four.<lb/>If that number would be inconvenient<lb/>let me know when you are writing.<lb/>By the way about wedding presents for<lb/>Nano and yourself, I was thinking of 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5793_img_891_3"/>
             getting bangles or something of that sort<lb/>for both of you. What do you think<lb/>would Nano like also yourself. I'd<lb/>like to know that also soon.  No news at all. Dan Moran<lb/>called to see me yesterday evening. You<lb/>know he is Father Willie's brother. He was<lb/>in the Volunteers but was not called up.<lb/>Regards to all and fondest and<lb/>truest love to yourself.  <lb/> Always your loving and devoted <lb/> <hi rend="underline">James</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>