<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0899">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Peter Mooney (b.1886) to his sister, Katie (b.1884). Peter opens his letter concerning the Easter Rising, believing that Dublin must still be in a terrible state. Peter writes about his farm back home and how happy he is that the mane and foal are doing well. Peter asks about various people at home and closes the letter with a hope that peace is not far away.Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This letter part of a collection of over ninety surviving letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Mooney Family Papers, Mooney Family Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/899</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0342">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0899_img_2494_1"  type="Letter"  url="5325267cd7a0ff35bbb38e2f257b5cff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0899_img_2494_2"  type="Letter"  url="b22d31ba6f13293e524532f3602b5322.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0899_img_2494_3"  type="Envelope"  url="498e4231fce17f1a1c465ecd33802fac.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0899_img_2494_1"/>
                May 20 1916   Dear Katie   I received your very welcome letter alright <lb/> glad to see by it that all are so well. I feel quite well <lb/> &amp; happy nothing to complain of. The weather is lovely <lb/> &amp; fine in fact it is nearly too warm. Dublin must be <lb/> a greatly changed city since I saw it last it is terrible <lb/> to think of all the damage that has been done I <lb/> hope it is all over now. Tell the boys in Purcells <lb/> I was asking for them I was to write to them but <lb/> do not know the address will you please get it for <lb/> me. How is Paddy remember me to him also Mrs <lb/>&amp; family. I imagine he is shearing the sheep now <lb/> This little war will shortly start now clearing the <lb/> maggots out of the sheep. I am so glad to hear the <lb/> mare &amp; foal are doing so well. I am sure Charley <lb/> minds them well. I am writing this letter just <lb/> about when you are at the Rosary in old Dunboyne. <lb/> I know what it is to hear the whistle of a shell some <lb/> of them have burst quite close to me one evening they <lb/> shelled us out of our barn as we were having our tea. <lb/> I need not tell you how I felt at having to leave my tea <lb/> behind. Tell biddy I wish to be remembered to all her people. <lb/> I hope all are quite well. I did not lose anything in <lb/> weight since i came out here as we are well fed <lb/> &amp; the work is not out of the way hard.   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0899_img_2494_2"/>
              I will not be able to sleep in my nice soft bed when I <lb/> get home as i am now used to sleeping in all sorts of <lb/> places. I remember one night sleeping on sacks of oats in <lb/> a forage store boots spurs &amp; all on but still I slept well <lb/>as the saying is I could sleep on a harrow sometimes. <lb/>I had not a letter from the Paddock since I came out <lb/>I am sure the Governor would shoot some of the Sinn <lb/>Feiners if he caught them. I hope they are all well <lb/>tell him to write soon. Remember me to Miss Conlon <lb/>&amp; her sister tell them I am going on well. Tell Charley <lb/>&amp; Tommy to keep the place nice &amp; tidy as I hope to <lb/>return there some day &amp; I would like to see everything <lb/>well cared for. Still I know I need not fret on that <lb/>point as I know you are doing your best. Is old Barney <lb/>alive still &amp; little <seg type="unclear">Pat</seg> &amp; the greyhounds. It would be <lb/>if arrangements could be make to let the Grey <lb/>horse out anytime now &amp; couple of months grass would <lb/>do him a lot of good. I am glad to hear Father Brady <lb/>is going on well also Father Ford. I have <lb/>nothing more to say at present as I say a fond Good Bye <lb/> &amp; May God Bless &amp; keep you all &amp; I hope the day <lb/>is near when we shall live in peace one more Good-Bye <seg type="closer">  Peter Mooney  </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0899_img_2494_3"/>
                Miss. K. Mooney  Caulstown  Dunboyne  Co. Meath    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>