<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3887">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 4 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to his father, Hugh Doyle, regarding his activities before being sent to the front. Doyle, writes that the fears over a meningitis outbreak have now passed leading to a fresh crop of rumours surrounding their departure for the front which according to a ordinance officer should be very soon. While speculating on their destination Doyle reminisces about his previous time in Belgium and hopes that he will not be sent out as a spy because of it. Before signing off Doyle talks about the type of confessions he is hearing from the men and a fire that broke out in camp.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3887</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-02-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1503">Bordon Camp, Hampshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1210">Melrose, Dalkey, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_1"  type="Letter"  url="e12f77df860cba4dc88c1566842bf212.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_2"  type="Letter"  url="e162a3984d918c1347cd7baceb3d2799.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_3"  type="Letter"  url="eafe8b728bbbd2a55a79b67ef24b2d86.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_4"  type="Letter"  url="444ba2186d8ba4e8fd9d204a636156c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_5"  type="Letter"  url="e3ad74127b39057e8c59ea15cd71c526.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_6"  type="Letter"  url="87fa57b82ff984790bfa70282aacb440.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_7"  type="Letter"  url="efd31d565786284ad7eba1ea494c2e38.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3887_img_3266_8"  type="Letter"  url="9f049b033f7381ff40b7a43fe203bc82.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_1"/>
             J2/83 (22)<lb/> Borden Camp<lb/>Hants. <lb/> 4/2/'16. <lb/> My dear Father,   We have had no<lb/>fresh cases of meningitis<lb/>among the troops for some<lb/>weeks so all danger of a<lb/>serious outbreak is past,<lb/>the result has been a<lb/>fresh crop of rumours<lb/>about our immediate<lb/>depart for warmer climates.  In fact if half of these<lb/>had come true we should<lb/>now be keeping company 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_2"/>
             2  with the <sic>mumies</sic> and<lb/>crocodiles of Egypt, nubbing<lb/>up our forgotten Greek<lb/>grammar at Salonika,<lb/>with the prospect of<lb/>soon making the acquain-<lb/>tance of Kind Ferdy, or<lb/>digging ourselves, if not<lb/>into the mud of France,<lb/>at least out of it. However<lb/>they say there is no smoke<lb/>without a fire, and all<lb/>things are pointing in<lb/>the same direction. An<lb/>ordinance officer sent from<lb/>Aldershot yesterday to inspect<lb/>our rifles told us he had<lb/>got orders to do our<lb/>Brigade first as we<lb/>were leaving for the Front 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_3"/>
             3  very soon. A few days<lb/>before I had heard from<lb/>the Brigade Headquarters<lb/>that we leave on the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>,<lb/>which seems very likely<lb/>as our artillery for the<lb/>whole 16<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Division stationed<lb/>here, are leaving on that<lb/><seg type="del">h</seg>date, and to confirm<lb/>all the Colonel told me<lb/>just now that orders had<lb/>come to close all accounts<lb/>and return surplus stores<lb/>to Aldershot. This will<lb/>take some days and then<lb/>we have to stand by, ready<lb/>to move at an hour's<lb/>notice. Packing for<lb/>departure is a simple<lb/>affair since on service 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_4"/>
             4  every man carries what<lb/>he wants and any little<lb/>extras on his back, only<lb/>36 lbs per man being<lb/>allowed on the transport<lb/>waggons and in this<lb/>might you have to include<lb/>your blankets and sleeping<lb/>bag with a bucket for<lb/>washing in. The poor old<lb/>Mother's four poster bed<lb/>would <hi rend="underline">not</hi> do for active<lb/>service. We used to<lb/>sing long ago, Hard times<lb/>come again no more; it<lb/>seems to me they are<lb/>not far off at present,<lb/>but we are not downhearted!<lb/>Our destination is not known<lb/>even by the C.O. (Commanding<lb/>Officer) but as the 16<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Division  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_5"/>
             5  Headquarters are at Bethune,<lb/>France, I may say it is<lb/>certain we are going there.<lb/>The enclosed map may<lb/>interest you on this account. I<lb/>have marked Bethune near<lb/>La Bassée. On the right<lb/>of the map you will see<lb/>two towns Tourcoing and<lb/>Roubaix to which I often<lb/>walked across the frontier<lb/>when staying in Belgium<lb/>and then to Lille, so<lb/>that I am coming back<lb/>to familiar ground. I<lb/>hope the <seg type="unclear">Giniral</seg>won't<lb/>send me out as a spy,<lb/>but having three Iron<lb/>Crosses already on my<lb/>uniform I would be  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_6"/>
             6  quite a hero among<lb/>the Germans. By the way<lb/>I find that army con-<lb/>fessions have a humour of<lb/>their own: I said damn<lb/>his soul, Father, but he<lb/>was only a Hun, which<lb/>of course made it an<lb/>act of virtue in the<lb/>poor chap's eyes.  The calm monotony of<lb/>our usual life was enlivened<lb/>a few nights ago by an<lb/>outbreak of fire, when we<lb/>where snugly tucked up<lb/>in our blankets. It is<lb/>an iron law that the<lb/>moment the fire bugle<lb/>goes every man in<lb/>Camp must turn out  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_7"/>
             7  on parade instantly, doing<lb/>what dressing you can<lb/>while you run. You<lb/>may imagine the scene<lb/>in pitch darkness as all<lb/>external lights are now<lb/>extinguished, with 12,000<lb/>men rushing to their posts<lb/>for dear life, not for-<lb/>getting, you may be sure,<lb/>to consign the individual<lb/>who caused the fire &amp;<lb/>dragged them out of bed,<lb/>to a certain place of<lb/>warmth. The poor chaplain<lb/>of the 49<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Brigade, with<lb/>many groans, puffed up<lb/>the hill in the wind &amp;<lb/>rain only to find that  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3887_img_3266_8"/>
             8  a nervous sentry had<lb/>mistaken a burning<lb/>chimney for a passing<lb/>Zep: and that there were<lb/>no cor-n-nepses (as Bob.<lb/>calls them) to bury.<lb/><lb/>I don't think that I told<lb/>you about another of my<lb/>adventures during our<lb/>recent field manoeuvres.<lb/>Finding a platoon of<lb/>men wandering about <seg type="del">I</seg><lb/>without an officer I<lb/>thought I could not do<lb/>better than take com-<lb/>mand of them. Just<lb/>then a horseman was<lb/>seen in the distance<lb/>galloping from the<lb/>enemy's lines. With  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>