<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0333">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Brennan to John J. Farrell, 18 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Brennan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Joseph Brennan to John J. Farrell. In the letter Brennan states that he is writing on behalf of Chalmers in reference to a previous letter sent by Farrell and others regarding a theatre tax. Brennan states that an interview with Chalmers would serve no useful purpose in the matter.John J. Farrell (1876-1959) was the former lord mayor of Dublin and managing director of the Irish Kinematography Co. Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5611/8505/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/333</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0244">Joseph Brennan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John J. Farrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1559">62 Upper Sackville Street (O'Connell Street), Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0333_img_1561_1"  type="Letter"  url="bc0ce2452007193c321a30d370f640f0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0333_img_1561_1"/>
                DUBLIN CASTLE,    18th May, 1916.   Dear Sir,    I am desired by Sir Robert Chalmers to acknow- <lb/>ledge the receipt of the letter of the 18th instant <lb/> signed by you and others suggesting an interview with <lb/>him on the question of the Theatre Tax. Sir Robert <lb/>understands that you desire to advocate the temporary <lb/>postponement of this duty in Dublin, in which case he <lb/>is satisfied that an interview will serve no useful <lb/>purpose as the date from which takes <seg type="unclear">eg</seg><lb/>prescribed by Act of Parliament. <seg type="closer"> Yours <seg type="unclear">faithfully</seg>, <lb/> J.B.   Alderman J. J. Farrell,  Managing Director,  Irish Kinematograph Co., Ltd.,  62, Upper Sackville Street,  Dublin  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>