<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0223">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from V. Coffey to the Inspectors of Lunatics, 18 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>V. Coffey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from V. Coffey, resident medical superintendent at Maryborough (Portlaoise) Asylum, to the inspector of lunatics, discussing the case of Julia Conroy. Conroy was claiming compensation for an injury she received working at the asylum. Coffey claims, however, that the injury was not serious and healed within a few days. The letter includes a letter from the asylum&#39;s solicitor who also claims no compensation is warranted.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/8753/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/223</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1211">V. Coffey</persName>
              <date>1916-05-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1036">Maryborough Asylum, Maryborough (Portlaoise), Queen&#39;s County (Laois), Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Inspectors of Lunatics</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0223_img_1380_1"  type="Letter"  url="7659a2028938a5e8ca7f5964390fba12.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0223_img_1380_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="1fca0b1ac95861ec7706e2d7a0356bf7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0223_img_1380_1"/>
                District Asylum.  Maryborough    18th May 1916   Gentlemen,   In reply to your communication of 15th inst, I have <lb/> to inform you that Julia Conroy (nee Lodge) first entered the <lb/> service of this Asylum on June 1st 1890. She resigned on June <lb/> 30th 1898, was reappointed on 12th May 1900, and resigned to <lb/> get married on 30th October 1908.   The acident alluded to in her petition occurred through <lb/> falling off a stepladder some considerable time before her <lb/> resignation, and was not of a serious nature, nothing more than <lb/> a simple inflamation about the elbow Joint being apparent a <lb/> at the time. This passed away after a few days leaving no <seg type="del">phys</seg><lb/>physical signs of permanent injury. <sic>Nothign</sic> further was heard <lb/>by us about this case until last January, when an application <lb/> was made to the Committee for compensation respecting the <lb/>injury, before deciding which they referred the matter to <lb/>their Solicitor upon whose opinion (copy of which is enclosed) <lb/> they acted. Petition and medical certificate herewith returned.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Gentlemen, <lb/><lb/>Your Obt Servant   V Coffey <lb/> Resident Medical Superintendent.    To/  The Inspectors of Lunatics  Dublin Castle  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0223_img_1380_2"/>
               Re claim of Julia Conroy for injuries alleged to have been <lb/>sustained by her whilst in the service of the Asylum.    27th day of March 1916  Telephone No 15 <lb/>  Horace Turpin  Solicitor and Land Agent  Maryborough District Asylum  Maryborough  Queen's County   Dear Sir   I am in receipt of your letter of the 24th inst with <lb/> enclosures herein, all of which I return as requested.   In my opinion the Committee of Management are under no <lb/>obligation whatever to compensate the <sic>Claiment</sic> for alleged injuries <lb/>received, even if the facts stated by her in her application be correct. <lb/>It would be quite impossible for her legally to sustain such a claim <lb/>under the Workman's Compensation Act or any other act after such a <sic>lape</sic><lb/> lapse of time.   Apart from all other considerations your Committee would <lb/>indeed be establishing a very dangerous precedent in entertaining <lb/>such an application put forward for the first time more than seven <lb/> years after the Claimant had left the Asylum service.   Furthermore I am of opinion that the L.G. Auditor would be <lb/>almost certain to surcharge your committee if it ventured to <lb/>entertain such a Claim.  <seg type="closer"> Yours Faithfully  H. Turpin   Wm C Meechan Esq  D.L. Asylum  Maryborough.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>