<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2676">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael O'Riordan to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 23 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael O&#39;Riordan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Monsignor Michael O&#39;Riordan (1857-1919), rector at the Irish College in Rome, to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 until his death.

In this letter O’Riordan discusses a statement which he released. He claims to have written it for the Italian mind and has sent copies to those Bishops mentioned in it. In the letter O&#39;Riordan expresses a desire for the nations to give up fighting. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/I/239/2/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2676</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0177">Michael O&#39;Riordan</persName>
              <date>1916-10-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0191">Irish College, Rome, Italy</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2676_img_2099_1"  type="Letter"  url="7aaa7f464851cbed0b9c6f25e34f7f0e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2676_img_2099_2"  type="Letter"  url="eecf6768829a534b34e0e6d98d753e87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2676_img_2099_3"  type="Letter"  url="fd3e24eb919fbdbf5e350a61b7bdfeef.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2676_img_2099_1"/>
             Irish College <lb/>Rome   Oct 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    My Lord Bishop   Your letter, with enclosed, <lb/>has just come. I shall make <lb/>the presentation in due time; <lb/>and shall convey your message <lb/>also. I notice that the sum <lb/>is much larger than usual; <lb/>which also I shall bring under <lb/>his notice.   I am glad you liked <lb/>my statement. Of course I write <lb/>it for the Italian mind; &amp; therefore
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2676_img_2099_2"/>
            I omitted things which would <lb/>speak much to persons in <lb/>Ireland &amp; in England; but <lb/>which would mean nothing to <lb/>an Italian, or perhaps make <lb/>him misunderstand. I have <lb/>sent copies to the Bishops <lb/>whom I have mentioned in it; <lb/>also to a few who know Italian.   It is quite time the <lb/>nations gave up fighting. They <lb/>would be the laughing-stock <lb/>of Europe, if all Europe was <lb/>not engaged in the butchery; <lb/>— nobody is left out to laugh.   Is it not a great lesson in <lb/>fractional civilisation?   Experimental science has achieved <lb/>astonishing results for the benefit <lb/>of mankind; then comes the <lb/><hi rend="underline">un-civilised will</hi> (without religion) <lb/>and uses these results for <lb/>man's destruction   The late Fr Phelan, the famous <lb/>editor of the <hi rend="underline">Western Watchman</hi> <lb/>of Milwaukee, U.S.A., defined <lb/>modern civilisation as " the <lb/>improved methods of reciprocal <lb/>butchery". He was an exact <lb/>thinker.   We have just come back <lb/>from Tivili.<lb/> We begin our Retreat
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2676_img_2099_3"/>
            tomorrow and come ending it <lb/>on Nov 1<hi rend="superscript">st.</hi>. On Nov 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> I <lb/>will be here eleven years. How <lb/>fast time runs, when duties <lb/>multiply! —    I am yours obediently   M O'Riordan   P.S. <lb/>I have sent a full <lb/>report (un-censored) of your <lb/>reply to the Corporation. I asked <lb/>if there was such: and I have got <lb/>it. <seg type="unclear">Hoping</seg> be useful here.   I have had some strong letters from <lb/>some Cardinals in my Statement <lb/>Card. Maffi asked me for more <lb/>copies. I am glad I did it. Those <lb/><seg type="unclear">here</seg> will have known the <hi rend="underline">facts</hi>, before <lb/>Card. Gasquet, or Paul de Salis bring <seg type="unclear">fancies</seg>. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>