<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3461">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael J. O'Lehane to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 7 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael J. O&#39;Lehane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Michael J. O&#39;Lehane (1873–1920) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877 - 1946). O&#39;Lehane requests Skeffington&#39;s presence at a meeting he&#39;s holding for women to address women&#39;s economic difficulties and their position in industrial occupations. 

Michael J. O&#39;Lehane was a trade unionist, nationalist, and member of the Gaelic League and Sinn Féin. A draper by trade, he founded the Irish Drapers’ Assistants’ Benefit and Protective Association. He was elected president of the Dublin Trades Council in 1910. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/16-33</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3461</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1126">Michael J. O&#39;Lehane</persName>
              <date>1916-02-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0853">76 Grafton St., Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1920</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3461_img_2870_1"  type="Letter"  url="9c98d8115f5f00d2a83d0ca5082f1b0e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3461_img_2870_2"  type="Letter"  url="0c5ac9a87b224e18183c193b10734913.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3461_img_2870_1"/>
            <seg type="head">The Irish Drapers’ Assistants’ Benefit &amp; Protective Association <lb/>(ORDINARY SECTION.) <lb/>(Established to promote the welfare and protect the interests of those employed at the <lb/>DRAPERY and ALLIED TRADES in IRELAND).</seg> <lb/>Registered Head Offices —  76 GRAFTON STREET, <lb/>DUBLIN ,  7th Febry., 1916   General Secretary: <lb/>M. J. O'LEHANE.   Dear Mrs. Sheehy—Skeffington,   We are having an Organising Meeting for women <lb/>only, which will be held in the Large Concert Hall, Rotunda, <lb/>on Monday evening, 21st inst., at 8. o’clock.   Owing to the large influx of women into various Callings <lb/>and the fact that in many cases they are wretchedly, poorly, <lb/>paid, we think that a special effort should be made to organise <lb/>them into a militant Trades Union. As, no doubt, you are aware <lb/>we cater alike for men and women.   We sincerely hope that you will be able to attend this <lb/>meeting as, as I have said, it will be for women only and the <lb/>present economic difficulties, as well as the position of women <lb/>generally in industrial occupations, will be dealt with.   Yours sincerely,   M. J. O’Lehane   Mrs. Sheehy-Skeffington, <lb/>11, Grosvenor Place, Rathmines. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3461_img_2870_2"/>
            Reception  Jan 6<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>   : 52+ <lb/>Donors: <seg type="unclear">Crichton</seg>. <lb/>Officer <seg type="unclear">Wilkins <lb/>Jahmer</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Finance Teas</seg> <lb/>Rooms Teachers   <lb/>Tea Room. <lb/>Library <lb/>new members America <lb/>   May 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   general <lb/>Social function <lb/>2 Dances <lb/>whist Drives <lb/>Le Homes <lb/>meetings  <lb/> Feb 16 D. C.  <lb/>   <lb/>    Suffrage week <lb/>April: walker clempton <lb/>   <lb/>   <lb/>Harrison <lb/>Peace <lb/>Cat &amp; Mouse <lb/>Courts <lb/>Joint Com <lb/>Elections <lb/>Conference <lb/><hi rend="underline">Mis</hi>: cousins, Aeslam <seg type="unclear">celebration</seg> <lb/>Irish Citizen          
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>