<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2815">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Elizabeth Hackney to George Hackney, 1 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Elizabeth Hackney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney, a  Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;. In 1916 he was injured and spent some time a Hospital in Calais, France, and in Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield.


In this letter Liz expresses her hope that George is quickly recovering in  Wharncliffe War Hospital in Sheffield. She tells George that their ailing mother&#39;s cough has improved, but that her health would be much helped by a visit from George. &#39;Sis&#39; apologises for not being able to come see George herself, but expresses her gladness that some of his friends are able to make the journey.

The enclosed letter, addressed to a Mrs Gallagher from a Mr John A Ewing, appears to be completely unrelated to the main letter, and it is unclear how it ended up in the same envelope. In the letter, Ewing thanks Mrs Gallagher for a recent stay in &#39;Devenish House&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast; D3503/4/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2815</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1333">Elizabeth Hackney</persName>
              <date>1916-10-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1949">Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1546">31 Ward, 'D' Block, Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1977</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2815_img_2231_1"  type="Letter"  url="d5979393a92136b4b75d0f1e4c1d9f50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2815_img_2231_2"  type="Letter"  url="022ed2670abd843162621ef448c25b93.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2815_img_2231_3"  type="Letter"  url="d33530862f9691397013bccbfadf9109.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2815_img_2231_4"  type="Envelope"  url="6babba0b20e7359afc00fe6294d66b1b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2815_img_2231_5"  type="Envelope"  url="1a08b2b5ebe9bf813c829b69587998e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2815_img_2231_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="e05718516030c386cb2458f11c84586b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2815_img_2231_1"/>
             xxxx <lb/>from mother <lb/>in bed   1.10.16   My dear George   There is a drawback <lb/>in having so many of us to <lb/>write to you. I felt vexed that <lb/>you had never heard that we <lb/>received the money all right.    I put it in the Post Office on <lb/>the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Sept and the receipt <lb/>is in your book with the others <lb/>that is 21 here I believe, and then <lb/>those you sent yourself.   There is nothing I would like <lb/>better that just to go over and <lb/>see you for myself it seems so <lb/>hard that you are so near us <lb/> and yet we cannot see you <lb/> as there is not one of us could <lb/>get away. This is Mother's message —
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2815_img_2231_2"/>
            Mother  is longing  to see you home as <lb/> she is tired waiting, she wants you <lb/>to come as soon as you can to <lb/>see if it will do her any good.   Somehow George she cannot be <lb/>satisfied about you, - wonders <lb/>how you really are, and I don't <lb/>think she will be until she can <lb/>see you for herself. It is hard <lb/> for you George dear, as I know if <lb/>it was possible it is home You <lb/> would be, especially on Mother's <lb/> account, she finds the time so <lb/> long with so little variety, but <lb/> then she has not the strength <lb/>to be about yet, and we must <lb/>have patience until that time <lb/>comes. We hope you are feeling <lb/>better, but then you have not <lb/>had much time yet, as it may <lb/> be slow. We were glad to <lb/> hear about your excursion it <lb/> must have been very nice, and <lb/> such a long day too, it must <lb/> have been well arranged.   I was gathering the things up <lb/>this morning preparing to write <lb/>you, when the Doctor arrived <lb/> it was after one o'clock I think, <lb/> he said Mother's  pulse  was not bad <lb/> at all, seemed satisfied enough <lb/> and I told him she had slept <lb/> very well the last two nights, I <lb/> asked him about you, and he <lb/> thinks it would do Mother good <lb/> to see you, as she seems to be <lb/>fretting about you, so George <lb/> if you are able to come and can <lb/> get away, it will be the best <lb/> thing to do I expect, maybe you <lb/>will see Willie one of these days
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2815_img_2231_3"/>
            I hope you, I am sure he <lb/> will do his best anyhow, then <lb/> you will be telling us about <lb/> Berthas' visit, we are glad some <lb/> friends can go to see you. It was <lb/> very kind in M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Lynn asking <lb/>that clergyman to call and see <lb/>you, we said that you always <lb/> seemed to get friends everywhere.   L. J and I are struggling on as <lb/>usual, Lily's cough is not better yet <lb/> Father's is greatly improved, but best <lb/> of all Mother's is quite better, and <lb/> it is such a relief to us all, as <lb/> she seemed to cough all night <lb/> for I think four nights. I will <lb/> have to say goodbye dear George <lb/>hoping to have good news about <lb/> you soon love and kisses.   Your loving sister   Liz 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2815_img_2231_4"/>
             14815 <lb/>Lce. Cpl. George Hackney <lb/>14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Batt Royal Irish Rifles <lb/>Y.C.V <lb/>31 Ward 'D' Block <lb/>Wharncliffe War Hospital <lb/>Sheffield, Eng. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2815_img_2231_5"/>
            
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2815_img_2231_6"/>
             Mrs <sic>Jas</sic> Gallagher, <lb/>Devenish House, <lb/><hi rend="underline">Bundoran, Co. Donegal</hi>   Dear Mrs Gallagher,   Everybody knows that  even  the best of <seg type="del">Army</seg> <sic>Armies</sic> come to an end sometime <lb/> &amp; we are all very sorry that in our case this has now come true.    Nevertheless we <seg type="del">should</seg>  can  hardly grumble, as we did not expect our <lb/> good times to extend so long, It is hardly necessary to <lb/> state that the best part of all was the good times which we had <lb/>at "Devenish House", evenings which we will all cherish <lb/> while memory lasts.   We all feel very much indebted to your whole family for the trouble <lb/>which you took on our behalf at all times &amp; would especially <lb/> thank your own good self &amp; miss Mamie.   As a small token of our  esteem &amp;  thanks, we wish you to accept the enclosed <lb/> pair of Damask Table Cloths &amp; Miss Mamie the enclosed Blouse.   We do not wish you to measure the extent of our gratitude by the <lb/> apparent value of the enclosed gifts, as if you used that standard of comparison <lb/> the value of the gifts would fall far  indeed  below the amount of our gratitude <seg type="del">indeed</seg>    Trusting that we may all at some future time manage to meet again <lb/> under your hospitable roof.    We beg to remain <lb/>Very sincerely yours,   John A Ewing   <hi rend="underline">G.H.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>