<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5222">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charlie Daly to Kate Allman, 30 October 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charlie Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter written to family friend Katherine Allman who had previously announced her decision to become a nun. Katherine was later called St. Gertrude and gave her letters from Charlie to Charlie&#39;s sister in the 1960s.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/10/1/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5222</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date>1922-10-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2043">Tirconaill, Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0800">Kate Allman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1923</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5222_img_None_1"  url="2c97001759be33c3ac1a53e6dc1a61e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5222_img_None_2"  url="a1f491c09acf73f39bb0d04af1eb98da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5222_img_None_3"  url="4eb3468a2106af654e450f1bfd7ea645.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5222_img_None_4"  url="98415328cd82a7e78d8be5df8fe3b8b9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5222_img_None_5"  url="2b2c66a2535e6fa08ef59b310bb83b23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5222_img_None_6"  url="50f527435aa7da79ce6ac81760c38d5b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5222_img_0_1"/>
              Tirconaill    Oct 30th '22   <seg type="unclear"> A Chait A chara Dhílis  </seg>  Well wonders will surely never<lb/>cease! I got your letter of the 20th last nightThis<lb/>sudden announcement of yours took me completely<lb/>off my feet. for although 'tis quite natural that<lb/>you should make up your mind to become a<lb/>nun, the news has come so unexpectedly that<lb/>I couldn't help getting something like a shock.<lb/>I would indeed be far less surprised<lb/>if you had announced that you had just<lb/>got married. but of the two you are choosing<lb/>the wiser and I am sure, the happier course.<lb/>On account of its suddenness I cannot<lb/>rightly explain yet how I feel about it.<lb/>My first &amp; natural feeling was, of course, of<lb/>sadness. for the first thing I thought of was<lb/>that after Nov 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> I could no longer look<lb/>forward to any letters from you and I suppose<lb/>even if you do write, like May Allman, your<lb/>mind will be fixed so much on things eternal<lb/>that you <sic>wont</sic> bother about worldly affairs.<lb/>However, Katty, I can never imagine you like<lb/>that even if your were a nun a hundred<lb/>times over I rather think that you will 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5222_img_0_2"/>
             2  still be your same self who will always be<lb/>happy to see or hear from your old<lb/>friends. The saddest part of it is that we<lb/>can no longer look forward to the same<lb/>good old times at Rockfields. During<lb/>all the trouble I often looked forward<lb/>to the time when it would be all over, to<lb/>some of the same gay times when you<lb/>would be home on holidays. This of course<lb/>was but imagination but as you must<lb/>have <seg type="unclear">realised</seg> yourself one cant help<lb/>painting such pictures when away in a strange<lb/>place &amp; among strange people. Anyway God<lb/>only knows when all this trouble will be<lb/>over or if I ever see home again. Beside<lb/>in this life we can't have things as we<lb/>wish and sooner or later there has to<lb/>be a parting of the old friendships<seg type="unclear"> &amp;</seg><lb/>associations of our youth - this is one<lb/>of the inexonerable laws of this world.<lb/>You will probably smile at the way I have<lb/>put this &amp; will perhaps think that I am<lb/>setting myself up as a philosopher - or<lb/>perhaps a fool. The long &amp; short of it<lb/>anyway Katty is that I am glad for your 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5222_img_0_3"/>
             3<lb/>own sake that you are doing this. You are<lb/>choosing a course of life in which you<lb/>are sure to be happy and in which<lb/>you will not have much need for worry,<lb/>to tell the truth. I have often felt for the<lb/>past couple of years, especially for the past 12<lb/>months, when I have felt fed up with<lb/>things that I would be glad to be done with every<lb/>thing in some way like that. I'm afraid though<lb/>that I am not made for such a life &amp; I<lb/>suppose 'tis my lot to carry on as I am. It certainly<lb/>seems a big job remaining in the world &amp; saving<lb/>your soul these days when you follow the<lb/>dictates of your conscience &amp; try &amp; do what<lb/>you is right. You are told by the Bishops<lb/>&amp; priests that you are on the road to Hell<lb/>so far as I see 'tis only in a convent or<lb/>monastery where one has nothing to do<lb/>with government or wars that one has any<lb/>peace these days. You ask me to say a<lb/>prayer for you. I will &amp; be sure though<lb/>goodness knows if a person believes all<lb/>thats said these times it might be thought<lb/>that my prayers would be of very little<lb/>use. Here is our position at present: we 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5222_img_0_4"/>
                4  are denied the sacraments no mater how<lb/>much a priest is in sympathy with us he<lb/><sic>darent</sic> hear our confessions under penalty of<lb/>suspension. At least thats how tis in this diocese<lb/>Do you pray for me also Katty. Being denied<lb/>the other consolations of religion that is all<lb/>we have to fall back on. One thing they<lb/>cant do anyway is to stop us praying. On<lb/>account of the way the Church is getting on in this<lb/>country at present I fear that a good many<lb/>fellows will chuck up religion completely. It is<lb/>only our strong Catholic faith &amp; the conviction that<lb/>we are right that sustains us. Our pre<lb/>dicament is a pretty tough one but with Gods<lb/>help we will get over it.  I, too, would like to have a chat with<lb/>you before you enter but tis totally impossible<lb/>unless something unforseen happens within the<lb/>next couple of weeks. To get to Dublin<lb/>or anywhere else for that matter is out of<lb/>the question under present circumstances, but<lb/><seg type="unclear">le conghiamh Dé</seg> if I ever get out of here I<lb/>will pay you a visit without fail, and<lb/>I dont think that the fact of your being<lb/>behind convent walls will prevent us 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5222_img_0_5"/>
             5  having a good chat. I am glad that 'tis<lb/>a Mercy Convent you are entering. You will<lb/>have some liberty there &amp; it will be easier<lb/>getting to see you who knows but I<lb/>may be home in time for your profession.<lb/>Pray that I will anyway. I would like to<lb/>be there if possible. I hope that you<lb/>have got my last letter alright I think it<lb/>should have reached you about a week<lb/>ago. I explained in it why I didn't write<lb/>sooner. I hope you <seg type="unclear">took</seg> what I said<lb/>about the political situation in the way I meant<lb/>you would &amp; that you were not vexed with<lb/>me for putting things so plainly. Now that<lb/>I think of it you must have made up<lb/>your mind about leaving the world by<lb/>the way you wrote of things then. Is that<lb/>so? I'm glad that you found Míceál well.<lb/><seg type="unclear">Twasn't</seg> true then that he had left. Queer that<lb/>we should be in opposite camps but I<lb/>hope that the day is not far when we will<lb/>be all one again.  Write me a long letter soon <seg type="unclear">aga</seg><lb/>Katty. I will miss your letters very<lb/>much after our regular correspondence 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5222_img_0_6"/>
             for the past couple of years, but I do hope<lb/>that you will be able to drop a<lb/>line now &amp; again. I will know at<lb/>any rate that you are praying for<lb/>me no matter where I am alive or dead<lb/>and I will always remember you<lb/>as my best friend - if you like to<lb/>use a commoner term - my best<lb/>pal.<lb/>Wishing you every happiness and<lb/>the very best of luck   Mise<lb/>Do chara dílis go Buain<lb/>Cormac   P.S. I've had no letters from home<lb/>since. I will write you again<lb/>next week. I will give you another<lb/>add. next week so that I will<lb/>get your letter as soon as it arrives.<lb/>Slán / Beannacht leat arís<hi rend="underline"> C.</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>