<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6652">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Joyce to Herbert Thring</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Joyce</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>Joyce, J. Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6652</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0393">James Joyce</persName>
              <date>1919-09-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0136">Zurich, Switzerland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Herbert Thring</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6652_img_None_1"  url="phpWySBzL.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6652_img_0_1"/>
              Zurich    Herbert Thring Esq.,    Dear Sir,   My attention hase been drawn to a letter recently written<lb/>by your society to Mr. Curti, Silicitor, of Zurich. As the<lb/>partner of Mr. Sykes I should like to bring a few facts to your<lb/>notice.  Mr. Sykes and I founded the English Players cocmpany in<lb/>Zurich in April 1918 for the production of plays in the English<lb/>language. The company produced plays in English in spite of<lb/>difficulty, boycott and financial loss, and was the only enterprise<lb/>of the kind in Switzerland during the war. It was impossible for<lb/>Mr. Sykes to obtain in some cases the consent of the dramatists<lb/>owing to the postal delays, consorship and frequent and prolonged<lb/>closure of frontiers, although every effort was made to avoid what<lb/>might have seemed an infringement of literary courtesy. Mr.<lb/>Sykes was in direct communication with Mr. Edward Martyn, who<lb/>gave him permission to produce <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">The Heather Field</hi></hi>, with Mr. Meyer,<lb/>agent of the late Stanley Houghton, who gave him permission to<lb/>produce <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">Hindle Wakes</hi></hi>, and with Mr. Robert Ross (deceased) and Mr.<lb/>Samuel French with regard to the production of Wilde's <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">The<lb/>Importance of Being Earnest</hi>.</hi> He has asked Mr. Curti therefore to<lb/>let him know the names of the authors qwho are claiming fees. The<lb/>question<seg type="del">n</seg> of the production on the Continent of Europe of plays in<lb/>the English language seems, moreover, to be an exceptional case<lb/>not foreseen in the clauses of the Berne convention. Mr. Sykes<lb/>was legally advised on this subject at the outset that such<lb/>produtions were free.  The aims and achievements of the company are such, I<lb/>believe, as will be approved of by members of your Society,<lb/>and, owing to Mr. Sykes' energy and persistance, the prospects<lb/>financially and artistically are now much brighter.  My name as a writer will perhaps not be unknown to you,<lb/>and I am indebted to your Society for generous and timely aid in<lb/>the past. I trust that the proposal with Mr. Curti is forwarding<lb/>you on our behalf with meet with<seg type="del">o</seg> your approval and put an end to<lb/>any misunderstanding which ay have arisen.  <sic>I am, dear Sir,<lb/>Sincerely Yours<lb/>James Joyce.</sic>   21.9.19.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>