<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0019">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cis M. Coyle to James Ryan, 19 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cis M. Coyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Cis. M Coyle to James Ryan (1891-1970) on 19 July 1916. This letter was written while Ryan was a prisoner in Frongach in Wales. The writer refers to friends at home and some of Ryan&#39;s fellow prisoners.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P88/27(7)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/19</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0736">Cis M. Coyle</persName>
              <date>1916-07-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0473">58 Aughrim Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0981">Frongach, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0019_img_1048_1"  type="Letter"  url="53c1234db414e74f6c58a636f121714d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0019_img_1048_2"  type="Letter"  url="51d40d1258934a23187b9b6ddd4f2fb4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0019_img_1048_3"  type="Letter"  url="a1d4adc9b5969766bde4e708677fdbdd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0019_img_1048_4"  type="Letter"  url="bb5b3434827ac5bb39475ba920355468.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0019_img_1048_1"/>
                58 Aughrim St    July 19th. 1916   My dear Jim   I was so glad <lb/>to hear from your <lb/>sister this morning <lb/> that you were so well <lb/>and glad to know <lb/> that you got one <lb/> of my letters at all <lb/> events. I write to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0019_img_1048_2"/>
              you three but don't <lb/>know if you get them <lb/> Tell Michael I was <lb/>enquiring for him. Mrs <lb/>Kelly came to see me <lb/> yesterday evening &amp; <lb/>gave me all the news <lb/> as she had letters <lb/> from Jack &amp; Michael <lb/> I don't get any news <lb/> of Liam at all <lb/> I hope he is well but  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0019_img_1048_3"/>
              I believe he is not <lb/>in the same camps <lb/> with you. Numbers <lb/> are getting home now <lb/> so I am expecting <lb/>every day to see you <lb/> all walk in.   I hope you are well <lb/> off for everything <lb/> in Camp &amp; that <lb/> you like the change <lb/>from Stafford.   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0019_img_1048_4"/>
              Don't you know Vera <lb/>Bermingham? Well a <lb/>sister of hers is getting <lb/>married on Sep 6th.   Nothing else strange <lb/> at present I think   Remember me to Jack <lb/> &amp; Liam I am writing <lb/>to them also  <seg type="closer"> Kindest regards <lb/>Very Sincerely Yours   Cis M.Coyle </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>