<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0439">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 8 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (1866-1955). This letter seems to be incorrectly dated 8 July, but in it Marie refers to a letter she received from her mother dated 4 August. In the letter, Marie is responding to family news from her mother&#39;s last letter.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>France Letters, B/F/1/56</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/439</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-08-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1543">Hardelot, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1257">Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0439_img_1774_1"  type="Letter"  url="eeb1c09a32937f3a32fcb5e82a3e5c57.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0439_img_1774_2"  type="Letter"  url="3efcfc0363000ad353c9a0f556f3c1ed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0439_img_1774_3"  type="Letter"  url="187c2ff5ac93fc6f44c5ba1e1bc68902.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0439_img_1774_1"/>
                8-7-16   My very dearest Mother,   A thousand thanks <lb/> for your very nice long latter dated <lb/> Aug <seg type="del">1</seg>4 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which I received last <lb/> night, I was also delighted <lb/> to get the enclosed from <lb/> Tommy which I answer by <lb/> return post, I have been thinking <lb/> a great deal of him lately, <lb/> he must find the heat very <lb/> trying but I am so glad to <lb/> hear he is keeping so fit, it <lb/> is his only chance to escape <lb/> the fever — in a climate like <lb/> that— The heat has been <lb/> fair bad these last few <lb/> days but we are not very <lb/> busy just at present <lb/> I had such a nice long  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0439_img_1774_2"/>
              letter from Minnie Fitzgerald to-day <lb/> when she wrote last time she <lb/> had not received my letter it <lb/> is very sad about T <seg type="unclear">Waldron</seg><lb/> I hope he will turn up— his poor <lb/> young wife what an <seg type="unclear">anxious</seg><lb/> time she must be having <lb/> I am very sorry to hear about <lb/> Jack glands, it always rather <lb/> worries me to see them so bad <lb/> as it is very unnatural &amp; he gets <lb/> them so often— perhaps he ought <lb/> to go &amp; see a specialist if the <lb/> change does not do him any <lb/> good. It is really very hard <lb/> to know what to do about <lb/> Jack I suppose <seg type="unclear">Sr</seg> Ramsay <lb/> does not want to loose  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0439_img_1774_3"/>
              him.   Please give H. my very best <lb/> congratulation, he seems to <lb/> have done very well, how <lb/> I wish I were at home to <lb/> enjoy all the flowers, A Miss <lb/> Whitly come round very often <lb/> &amp; <seg type="unclear">brings us</seg> beautiful flowers <lb/> but is always reminds me <lb/> of home— Well I must close <lb/> this short note just to let <lb/> you know all is well with <lb/> me hoping you &amp; all at <lb/> home are the same— Will <lb/> write long letter tomorrow  <seg type="closer"> Fondest love to all— <lb/> yours ever  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>