<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3590">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Lansbury to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 8 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Lansbury</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from George Lansbury (1859-1940) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), George expresses his grief over the death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. He writes regarding the work of Francis&#39; life and laments the circumstances of his death. He finished by sending his love and with a comforting quotation.

George Lansbury was a British politician who held socialist views and advocated for social justice, disarmament, and women&#39;s suffrage. He held various elected offices and was the editor of the Daily Herald, which he helped to establish. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3590</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1474">George Lansbury</persName>
              <date>1916-05-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1951">21, Tudor street, London, E.C.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1940</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3590_img_2990_1"  type="Letter"  url="4db55d3eb1baffcc7110e210c0c7b11a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3590_img_2990_2"  type="Letter"  url="f83b2aafa64af9feff3fae1bd578ddc1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3590_img_2990_1"/>
            <!-- The following is a headed paper inscription in red lettering on top left hand side of page--> THE LIMIT PRINTING AND<lb/>PUBLISHING CO., LTD.  <!-- The following is part of a headed paper inscription in red letter on top right hand side of page --> TELEPHONE<lb/>CENTRAL 5991 <lb/><!-- The following is part of headed paper entered in red lettering naming the newspaper -->   The Herald<lb/>(The National Labour Weekly) <lb/><!-- The following is the actual address of the newspaper -->  21, TUDOR STREET, LONDON, E. C.  <lb/> 8.5.14 <lb/> My dear Mrs Sheehy Sheffington   Your card is just to hand, I can hardly<lb/>write to you so dreadful is the news, May God in His<lb/>infinite love &amp; Mercy comfort console &amp; cheer you &amp;<lb/>yours. I <sic>cannott</sic> imagine your dear devoted husband<lb/>as a rebel in areas, to me he was always the embodiment<lb/>of <sic>pacifisium</sic>, a passive   but never one to use<lb/>violence, now he is gone &amp; we are all poorer for his death,<lb/>but he is not dead, neither is the cause of which he<lb/>Toiled &amp; worked, out of the evils of to day a new &amp; better<lb/>day will come &amp; as Fanny Parnell says it herself <sic>wi</sic> her<lb/>beautiful poems. Your husband <sic>wi</sic> his   will hear<lb/>the <seg type="unclear">shouting</seg> &amp; his spirit join in the rejoicings, his has<lb/>been a   life for God &amp; the people.     All in this office send you love &amp; good wishes<lb/>&amp; and my wife whom you have never seen send you<lb/>with me our   &amp; our love again God bless     
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3590_img_2990_2"/>
             &amp; keep you<lb/> Always<lb/>JLansbury   God gives us love<lb/>Something to love He <seg type="unclear"></seg>   us<lb/>When love has grown to <seg type="unclear">ripeness</seg><lb/>That on which love <seg type="unclear">strove</seg><lb/>Drops off<lb/>and love is left alone     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>