<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0766">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 16 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter Spender writes of a row he has had with the General Officer Commanding following the GOC&#39;s discovery that one of Spender&#39;s letters had been published (without Spender&#39;s consent). Spender describes the fallout from this discovery in detail, relating it to his strained relationships with some of the other staff, and his growing anxiety about the future.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/348</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/766</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0766_img_2298_1"  type="Letter"  url="0840233c3cb0f03d71820ebd87d8e3a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0766_img_2298_2"  type="Letter"  url="ebfa92d44fb5e15ecf765f66a92ad58f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0766_img_2298_3"  type="Letter"  url="25c47415564cbdea04dee8b71806c723.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0766_img_2298_4"  type="Letter"  url="5ed251809c8c792ad2918ffaad8deadc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0766_img_2298_5"  type="Letter"  url="c8d17c043c22d6ea17c300875184f194.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0766_img_2298_6"  type="Letter"  url="bfc52d0f8af5c207aeafbb85a222a38c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0766_img_2298_1"/>
                16 July   My Pr    I have just had a <lb/> d of a row. Either Gen' P <lb/> or Sir G published the letter <lb/>I sent them, in which the <lb/>abbreviated version is 'the GOC <lb/>now confesses he has got <lb/>excellent troops'. He is perfect <lb/>-ly furious &amp; swears all <lb/>kind of threats. I can quite <lb/> see his point of view in <lb/>this as it makes an impli- <lb/>cation - not intended that he <lb/>did not appreciate them <lb/> before, &amp; he thinks I have <lb/>been criticising him behind <lb/>his back. I find it a little <lb/>hard to forgive Sir G who <lb/>I suspect is the culprit &amp; <lb/>who as a soldier ought <lb/>to have known better.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0766_img_2298_2"/>
              I have saved Farnham <lb/> &amp; Singleton by getting Henry <lb/>to suppress his paper in <lb/>which letters written by <lb/>them appear. It is rather <lb/>like the b w's luck &amp; <lb/>you will not even see my <lb/>name mentioned in conse- <lb/>quence â- in fact the fuss <lb/>is not yet over. The G never <lb/> forgives &amp; we at present <lb/> loathe the sight of each- <lb/>other, tho I do see his <lb/>point of view.  You may as well be very <lb/>careful in your dealings <lb/>with Mrs &amp; all who are <lb/>likely to pass on things to her. <lb/>I rather wish I was going <lb/> to the <seg type="unclear">24</seg> Div tomorrow to <lb/> get things over as the atmos  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0766_img_2298_3"/>
              phere is sultry &amp; P does <lb/> not help much- <seg type="foreign">au contraire</seg><lb/>he is coming by his own &amp; <lb/>will make the most of it.  Well thank goodness I <lb/>shan't be a soldier after <lb/>the war is over, &amp; tho I <lb/> suppose roses will be <lb/>forbidden the the state, <lb/>perhaps a cabbage rose <lb/>or 2 may be allowed.   As luck will have it <lb/> there is no letter today <lb/>from you, but I had 2 <lb/>yesterday, only today it <lb/> would just have been <lb/> extra appreciated.    17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I am out this morning <lb/>writing in the open which would be <lb/>rather jolly but for the flies, which <lb/>in the absence of flypaper , or p v <lb/>or other convenient substitutes are  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0766_img_2298_4"/>
              troublesome. I fancy I am now <lb/>on the <seg type="unclear">Gen's</seg> nerves like Russell <lb/> &amp;<sic>Graig</sic> in which case it may <lb/>be as well if I leave which is <lb/>what I think he has in mind. <lb/>In many ways I shall not <lb/>regret it as there are disad- <lb/>vantages in being with 'ones' <lb/>own children' in a battle &amp; <lb/>I quite see them. At the <lb/> same time it will be a bit <lb/>of a wrench &amp; will be one <lb/>of the other things which <lb/>one will not be able to <lb/>explain after the war, tho' <lb/> perhaps then - but not now - <lb/>I shall drop a hint to Craig <lb/>of how it has happened.   Poor old Sir G he would be <lb/>sorry if he knew, &amp; would proba- <lb/>bly do something even worse such <lb/> as write to the G or get Carson to <lb/>do so, which would be too awful.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0766_img_2298_5"/>
              You know the kind of feeling <lb/>of silent sorrow when one <lb/>little boy has been naughty, <lb/>the atmosphere is like that <lb/>now, &amp; I believe the culprit <lb/>is the only one who does not <lb/>'appear' to appreciate it. All the <lb/>others except Comyn <hi rend="superscript">&amp; the G</hi> are dining <lb/>out , &amp; hints have been given <lb/>by <seg type="unclear">Place</seg> which I'm <lb/>hanged if I will take. I've <lb/>had far too many smacks in <lb/>the past to run away from <lb/>another now &amp; can <seg type="unclear">devise</seg><lb/>quite a lot of fun out of <lb/>the complex situation.   Every one here seems fairly <lb/>comfortable &amp; Rex may I hope <lb/>settle in next week, but I can- <lb/>not tell you what an anxiety <lb/> his arrival is especially as one  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0766_img_2298_6"/>
              <lb/>is helpless to give him any aid, <lb/>&amp; I should only make a mess of <lb/>it if I tried - as has happened <lb/>before.   However there are great <lb/>advantages in all these unpleas- <lb/>antness, undoubtedly the b w <lb/>who would have miffed at any <lb/>ordinary b w law will now <lb/>be content with the most secluded <lb/>&amp; diminutive rabbit hutch, provided <lb/>the p v is satisfied to live in <lb/>it. Of the war news you know <lb/>more than I do. It begins to <lb/>bore me !   I hope this week will not be <lb/>too strenuous for a p v. Remember <lb/><seg type="unclear">bw</seg> it is her business to keep <lb/>fit not only for her work but <lb/>also for the sake of that very <lb/> unsatisfactory tho rather <lb/>affectionate animal <seg type="closer"> the  b w. <lb/> WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>