<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5789">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay 16 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
This letter is written after May has returned home after a week&#39;s visit to Dublin. James has confirmed his best man. He reports on colleagues who have been arrested and released</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5789</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5789_img_888_1"  type="Letter"  url="8158dd136c26170b47f5819a815c830f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5789_img_888_2"  type="Letter"  url="b8f0068ce3327e76e02c5d809ba7871c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5789_img_888_1"/>
             16th May, 1916.   My dearest May,   I have only time for a <lb/>line to say that I wrote to Pat Moran <lb/>to-day asking him to be my best man. I <lb/>haven't yet written to the brother, Father <lb/>Frank, to ask him to do the job for <lb/>me but I suppose it is the usual and <lb/>natural thing to do and I suppose people <lb/>would talk and say that there was a row <lb/>between us if I didn't ask him. What <lb/>does your mother and yourself think of it? <lb/>I suppose however that neither of you has any
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5789_img_888_2"/>
             particular opinion or preference one way or<lb/>the other about it.  I hope you both got home safe and<lb/>sound and found every one well and that<lb/>the cat didn't eat the kitchen <seg type="unclear">towels</seg><lb/>in the <seg type="unclear">interval</seg>. How does Gerald like his<lb/>new mirror? Has he started shaving yet?<lb/>When you see Mrs Seery (which will be<lb/>I presume within the <hi rend="underline">next week</hi> or so) will<lb/>you ask her whether Johnnie wants me<lb/>to call on those people in <seg type="unclear">Prison or</seg>she<lb/>was talking about and if so let<lb/>me have their names and addresses.<lb/>You'll be glad to hear that John FitzGerald<lb/> (one of our men here) who was arrested last<lb/>week has been released to-day and will<lb/>be back again on duty in a day or so.<lb/>I think I was telling you about him<lb/>having been arrested at his home in<lb/>Iona Road. One or two others of our<lb/>fellows have had their houses searched but<lb/>nothing incriminating was discovered. No<lb/>strange news in the papers this morning<lb/>beyond what you saw in last evening's papers.  Give my regards to all and with<lb/>warmest and fondest love to my very<lb/>dearest girl.  <lb/> Ever your loving and devoted <lb/> <hi rend="underline">James</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>