<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4394">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy Duffin to Ruth Duffin, 29 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4394</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1375">Ruth Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4394_img_3748_1"  type="Letter"  url="033c84944a26747abfd4aed858f743f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4394_img_3748_2"  type="Letter"  url="ff3657234d604407603a953ec786483c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4394_img_3748_3"  type="Letter"  url="f2a80dffc04644b44ffcb6433e821a78.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4394_img_3748_4"  type="Letter"  url="dd4c714cb1a72e55d772194869430d54.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4394_img_3748_5"  type="Letter"  url="242e9f47f3a12c08eeb0eac157561346.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4394_img_3748_6"  type="Letter"  url="1f5ecd767b1e3c7ddc48c01429a75b5a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4394_img_3748_1"/>
             Monday <lb/>29th Nov 1915   No. 16 General <lb/>Hospital <lb/>A.P.O.S. 13   Dearest Ruth,   This is a hopeless <lb/>Day &amp; we are sitting by the boiler <lb/>in the Hut Kitchen trying to keep <lb/>warm. Leslie  <seg type="unclear">Hurbough</seg> has got a bad <lb/>cold and has shut himself up <lb/>in the Lab to nurse it. His <lb/>note to me this morning on the <lb/>subject will amuse you - he is <lb/>the most <seg type="unclear">pedantic</seg> young man! <lb/>I have played a bit of golf with <lb/>him lately. I shall have a lot to <lb/>tell you when I get back. Miss <lb/>Bell has not yet said when she <lb/>means to return but whether she
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4394_img_3748_2"/>
            <lb/>comes back or not I or she intend <lb/>to stay later than the begining of <lb/>next week. Olive says Miss <lb/>Roberts will have me any time. <lb/>I am glad she thinks she'll get <lb/>home for Christmas. I wish Celia <lb/>could do the same. I had a <lb/>letter from Emma yesterday dated <lb/>Nov. 11th. She sounded very cheery &amp; <lb/>content &amp; was seeing a good deal <lb/>of Molly Carson. Her account of <lb/>poor <seg type="unclear">Butamal</seg> was pathetic. I wish <lb/>the poor boy could get home for <lb/>a bit. I feel I must see <lb/>Hilda before I get home but <lb/>I don't care for going to <seg type="unclear">Cien- <lb/>cester</seg> now - it is all so very <lb/>sad. Mr Swanwick so desolate.   I am dying to hear how you <lb/>are getting on in your new abode <lb/>&amp; do hope you will be happy <lb/>but I do wish there was another <lb/>life for your, but I'm so glad
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4394_img_3748_3"/>
            <lb/>you are at home and not far <lb/>away in a strange place.   We have had plenty of men in <lb/>the Hut lately owing to the awful <lb/>cold weather. We have had <lb/>another week of theatricals <lb/>which were very successful. The <lb/>local talent is quite wonderful- <lb/>most successful <seg type="unclear">Pierrotes</seg> &amp; "Box <lb/>&amp; Cox" quite professional. Capi <lb/>Shutte as Ms Bouncer was <lb/><seg type="unclear">really</seg> funny! It is hard to <lb/>realise one is only about 40-50 <lb/>miles from the firing line. I heard <lb/>the guns clearly on the golf
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4394_img_3748_4"/>
            <lb/>course the other day just as the <lb/>sun went down - it made me <lb/>think of all those who would <lb/>never see it again. There we <lb/>were playing golf as if nothing <lb/>was wrong. I hope A.J. <lb/>got home all right. I would <lb/>love to see him again.   Major Smith spent a week-end <lb/>here, he is not very far off <lb/>it seems The hospitals here <lb/>are very empty &amp; mostly sick <lb/>cases. Probably there will be <lb/>little fighting again till Spring.   Mr Horsburgh was lecturing in
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4394_img_3748_5"/>
            <lb/>Dorking the other day, where Ms <lb/>LeConas, D. Smith's sister lives, <lb/>&amp; was asking her about Leslie's <lb/>friend at <seg type="unclear">Treport</seg>. I saw her <lb/>here when we first came out. <lb/>He knows the Caldwells in the <lb/>Isle of Wight. She, I think, is <lb/>Ms Platt-Higgins niece.   I think I have grown very fat <lb/>out here so you may expect to <lb/>see me increased in size! I <lb/>hear <seg type="unclear">Matrone is determined</seg> to <lb/>Or something of this vain. It <lb/>is nice work but I have had <lb/>enough of it and will not be <lb/>sorry to leave. Miss Shercock <lb/>wrote me a nice letter saying <lb/>Helen was appointed in my <lb/>place. I hope she'll be happy <lb/>poor dear, but it is <seg type="unclear">Quasprells</seg> <lb/>coping &amp; <seg type="unclear">building</seg> but a good <lb/>job in it's way of course <lb/>&amp; now money means so much.
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4394_img_3748_6"/>
            <lb/>I feel ashamed of the little <lb/>French I have learnt here but <lb/>being at the Camp all day one <lb/>really hears very little of it. <lb/>Honor MacCormac is away at <lb/>present at a Rest Home as <lb/>she got a bad foot. She has <lb/>given me such a pretty Brittany <lb/>bowe but I don't know how <lb/>I am going to pack it safely.   No more now, it is possible <lb/>I may leave here at the end <lb/>of this week but <hi rend="underline">possibly</hi> <lb/>may stay till next Monday or <lb/>Tuesday.    With Love.   <hi rend="underline">Dorothy</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>