<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5090">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Madge Rodgers to Ellen Daly, 17 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Madge Rodgers</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/4/6/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5090</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1223">Madge Rodgers</persName>
              <date>1923-03-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2123">Central Girl&#39;s Model School, Marlborough Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5090_img_None_1"  url="115bdf87c6e4394e359214a7b01c5382.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5090_img_None_2"  url="4a773190dc2112e06581520c3a6f7dd6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5090_img_0_1"/>
              Central Girls' Model School,<lb/>Marlboro' St., Dublin    17/3/23    P41/4/6/7    My dear Mrs Daly,   I had the honour to know<lb/>your son, Charlie, in Donegal, so that though I am<lb/>a stranger to you, I take the liberty of writing to<lb/>sympathise with you in your great bereavement &amp; to<lb/>congratulate you too on having such a son. He<lb/>was a magnificent specimen of Irish manhood<lb/>in every respect and won the love of all those who knew<lb/>him in Donegal. Indeed contact with him changed<lb/>South Dongal to Hibernianism to Republicanism.<lb/>I could not describe to you how much he was<lb/>loved and honoured by us all and the men in his<lb/>column almost worshipped him. Our hearts go<lb/>out to you in sincere sympathy on the loss of<lb/>such a son. May God &amp; his holy Mother comfort<lb/>you in your great bereavement. Please God<lb/>his life sacrifice will not be in vain. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5090_img_0_2"/>
             We are all praying that God may give<lb/>you strength to bear your cross.  With love and sympathy.   Yours very sincerely,    Madge Rodgers.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>