<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3087">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 21 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Peter Mooney was born on 5th February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne. Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie (b. 1884) were brought up by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18th October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St.Omer and Passchendael, in Belgium.Peter was an avid correspondent with his sister Kate and this letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Mooney Family Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3087</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1915-11-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1180">Ballincollig, Co. Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0342">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3087_img_2491_1"  type="Letter"  url="d4826631909024efc988eeb01689f8b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3087_img_2491_2"  type="Letter"  url="12fa0049b7340763dc05f505d4b5c32e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3087_img_2491_3"  type="Letter"  url="6f4a6d3f0778a75d7165ab9d64832604.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3087_img_2491_1"/>
             Nov 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1915   Dear Katie,   I received your letter <lb/>this morning. I am glad to <lb/>see by it that you and all are <lb/>well. I must thank you <lb/>for sending me Christy <lb/>Meehans address. It would <lb/>be better to keep the Photo <lb/>as it would only get all <lb/>crushed here. I will write <lb/>to Mr. Martin &amp; tell him you <lb/>want five pounds. I see by <lb/>paper that the market <lb/>was good this week. We <lb/>got no drill yet, we are riding <lb/>the Horses now which you <lb/>may easily guess is for <lb/>me. Did the Hunt cross <lb/>any part of the places yet.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3087_img_2491_2"/>
            I was thinking of the hunt <lb/>today when I was grooming <lb/>my horse at two or it would <lb/>be about the time <seg type="del">I was</seg> <lb/>they were letting out the <lb/>deer. I wrote to Paddy <lb/>during the week I suppose <lb/>he was telling you I saw <lb/>the advertisement about the <lb/>letting of the land in <seg type="unclear">Holistown</seg> <lb/>in the papers. I hope it will <lb/>sit well. I do not <sic>no</sic> of any <lb/>chap of the name of O'Donnell <lb/>here yet but I might him <lb/>some day. To find any particular <lb/>man here is like looking <lb/>for a needle in a bundle of <lb/>straw. I suppose Charlie is <lb/>reading the Sport in the <lb/>Harness Room as I write <lb/> this it is now just half <lb/>past six I go to bed about <lb/>8.30 every night as the morning <lb/>is early here. I shave every <lb/>morning before I go out that <lb/>means getting up every morning <lb/>at 5.30. It came as no surprise <lb/>to me to hear that Dick <lb/>Farrell is bankrupt his lot <lb/>is indeed an unfortunate one <lb/>still he never put anything <lb/>before him. It was mean <lb/>of the Whithworth crowd <lb/>not to subscribe to your fund <lb/>but still they must have a <lb/>lot of calls nowadays. Tell <lb/>Miss Conlan I was asking <lb/>for her when you see her <lb/>again. I hope they are in <lb/>good health. Is there any
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3087_img_2491_3"/>
            of the Volunteers left now at <lb/>all. I had a letter from <lb/>James Reilly during the <lb/>week he told me he does <lb/>not go near them now. I <lb/>suppose Tommy is at the kitchen <lb/>by this time. Tell John and Mrs <lb/>McAuley &amp; the children I <lb/>was asking for them I must <lb/>write a letter to them shortly. <lb/>Tell Dick Manning &amp; Paddy <lb/>and to make it short all <lb/>the neighbours around that <lb/>I was asking for them both <lb/>men women &amp; children. Who <lb/>milks on Sunday mornings <lb/>now. I hope all the Doggies <lb/> &amp; Horses are well. I have <lb/>no more to say. Good Bye &amp; <lb/>May God Bless you all.   Peter Mooney 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>