<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2380">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from P. J. Mallon to the Secretary, Irish Government, 24 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>P. J. Mallon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from P. J. Mallon, solicitor, to the Chief Secretary&#39;s Office, Dublin Castle, asking to be considered for the position of Clerk of Crown and Peace for County Westmeath. He has practised as a solicitor in the counties of Longford and Westmeath for twelve years.  The letterhead also shows he has an office at 23 Suffolk Street, Dublin.  

Mallon names two persons who will give references in support of his candidacy - John Patrick Hayden (1863–1954), a nationalist MP for Roscommon South and proprietor and editor of the Westmeath Examiner, and Percy Philip O&#39;Reilly (1870-1942).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5615/10764</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2380</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0160">P. J. Mallon</persName>
              <date>1916-06-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0058">Coralana, Lissmacaffrey, County Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Secretary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2380_img_1824_1"  type="Letter"  url="d299d3673d4e4fc5b4e95280b553acc8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2380_img_1824_1"/>
             Coralana, Lissmacaffrey, <lb/>Co. Westmeath,   24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>June 1916   Sir,   I am a candidate for the vacant position of Clerk <lb/>of the Crown &amp; Peace for County Westmeath. I <lb/>practised as a solicitor for the last twelve years <lb/>in the Counties of Longford and Westmeath.   For reference I beg to refer you to Mr. J. P. Hayden. MP. <lb/>Mullingar. County Westmeath, &amp; Mr Percy O'Reilly <lb/>Colamber, County Westmeath.   I am <lb/>Sir<lb/>Your obedient servant   P. J. Mallon.   The Secretary <lb/>Irish Government <lb/>Dublin Castle 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>