<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3713">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Benson to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 22 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Molyneux Benson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles Molyneux Benson (1877-1919) to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) regarding proposed changes to the Constitution of the Conjoint Board. While the Royal College of Surgeons of Ireland (RSCI) with all of the amendments advocated by the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) they agree these to move ahead with the agreed changes and review any problems that arise over time.

From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T59</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3713</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1084">Charles Molyneux Benson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1615">Royal College of Surgeons, Stephen&#39;s Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0168">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3713_img_3103_1"  type="Letter"  url="59070a9a93c444bf8661fe6183042766.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3713_img_3103_1"/>
             Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland.   Dublin    Jan. 22<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">nd</hi></hi> 1916   To T.P.C. Kirkpatrick Esq FRCP <lb/>Registrar <lb/>Royal College of Physicians   Dear Sir,   I am directed by the President, Vice President &amp; <lb/>Council to thank the Royal College of Physicians for the <lb/>sympathetic consideration which they have given to proposals <lb/>which, while they materially affect the interests of both <lb/>Colleges, also benefit the College School.    While the President, Vice President &amp; Council accept the <lb/>Amendments proposed by the College of Physicians to the <lb/>"Report of the <seg type="del">Report</seg> Committee to Consider the Constitution <lb/>of the Conjoint Examining Boards", they desire to point <lb/>out that the omission of the financial clause makes <lb/>temporary rearrangements of the Examining Board difficult, <lb/>and places an annual charge on the College of Surgeons, <lb/>which, although not large, is still inequitable; and that <lb/>the Amendment dealing with the Examiners in Medicine <lb/>makes it necessary to declare the Chair of Medicine in <lb/>the College School vacant next May.   This course is very distasteful to the Council, in spite <lb/>of the knowledge that the claims of the present Professor <lb/>to re-election will be fully considered by your College. <lb/>But the necessity of their Professor of Medicine being an <lb/>Examiner in that important subject must override <lb/>all other considerations.   The President, Vice President &amp; Council recognise, however, <lb/>that the Amendments criticised by them deal only with <lb/>matters secondary to the main object of the report: and <lb/>they are satisfied to wait until the scheme, as amended, <lb/>has been in force long enough to develop its weak points, <lb/>before submitting to your College proposals for its <lb/>improvement   I am, Sir, <lb/>Yours faithfully   C. M. Benson. F.R.C.S.I  <lb/>Secretary to Council.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>