<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1781">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir John Robert O'Connell to Sir Matthew Nathan, 27 March 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Robert O&#39;Connell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir John Robert O&#39;Connell (1868-1943), a solicitor, to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939).  O&#39;Connell writes to apply for the vacant position of chief crown solicitor for Ireland following the death of it&#39;s previous holder, Sir Malachy Kelly (1851-1916). O&#39;Connell mentions that he has practised law in Dublin for over twenty-five years and that he is a member of the Senate of the University of Dublin. O&#39;Connell had also acted as solicitor to Sir Jonathan Pim during his time as attorney general for Ireland. He continues to mention the various experiences he has attained through his legal work and hopes that the public experience he has gained will be taken into consideration.

Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1781</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0595">John Robert O&#39;Connell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1781_img_1236_1"  type="Letter"  url="0b01ab1f284d67103cf7f9d58fe8f123.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1781_img_1236_2"  type="Letter"  url="55f00b3dfee09826436de91975b763d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1781_img_1236_3"  type="Letter"  url="19344a1893c4ba4817cc7dcfcce70d67.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1781_img_1236_1"/>
             Telegrams Lawyers Dublin<lb/>Telephone No. 1462  34, Kildare Street,<lb/>Dublin.   27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1916.     Dear Sir Matthew Nathan,   Owing to the death<lb/>of my friend the late Sir<lb/>Malachy Kelly a vacancy<lb/>occurs in the office of Chief<lb/>Crown Solicitor for Ireland<lb/>and I venture to ask<lb/>you to bear in mind<lb/>my claims in any<lb/>influence you may exercise<lb/>in the appointment to that<lb/>office. I have now been  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1781_img_1236_2"/>
             for over twenty five years<lb/>in very extensive practice<lb/>in the City of Dublin. I<lb/>am a Graduate both in<lb/>Arts and in Law and a<lb/>Member of the Senate of the<lb/>University of Dublin. I<lb/>have had a great deal<lb/>of official experience as<lb/>the Chairman of the Loan<lb/>Fund Board for many<lb/>years until its dissolution<lb/>and, I acted as Solicitor<lb/>for the Rt. Honourable Jonathan<lb/>Pine during the period  <lb/>of his Attorney Generalship<lb/>I have written a good<lb/>deal on the Housing<lb/>Problem in Ireland and<lb/>on the various subjects<lb/>such as Infant Mortality<lb/>Street trading of children<lb/>re connected with it and<lb/>have given practical service<lb/>to this cause as a Director<lb/>of the Association for the<lb/>Housing of the very poor  <lb/>and I think I may claim<lb/>that it was I who rendered<lb/>the holding of the Civics<lb/>Exhibition — subsequently<lb/>closed as the result of the<lb/>  Hall barricade being    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1781_img_1236_3"/>
             required for Military purposes<lb/>at the outbreak of the War —<lb/>in 1914, possible.     Pray forgive these<lb/>somewhat personal<lb/>details but I venture<lb/>to hope that the public<lb/>service, I have been so<lb/>fortunate as to be able to<lb/>render are an element<lb/>which ought to be taken<lb/>into consideration  Believe me<lb/>Yours Sincerely   <hi rend="underline">John Robert O' Connell</hi>    The Rt. Honble Sir Matthew Nathan<lb/>G.C.M.G.  <lb/>Under Secretary Lodge<lb/>Phoenix Park Dublin   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>