<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0411">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Julia Taylor to Maire Elizabeth Savage Armstrong, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Julia Taylor</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Julia Taylor to Marie Elizabeth Savage Armstrong (b. 1854). Marie was the wife of poet George Francis Savage Armstrong (1845-1906).The letter concerns the Easter Rising. Taylor describes the noise of fighting and laments over the loss of life. She states that the soldiers were nearly dead for want of food and that all they had received were some biscuits and tea. Taylor also writes about how the military came and searched the village with machine guns on the top of streets and armoured cars. Julia mentions that Mrs. Pearse and her daughter, the mother and sister of Patrick Pearse, remain in the Hermitage, the site of Pearse&#39;s school in Rathfarnham.The rest of the letter concerns personal affairs, such as the letters Miss Taylor has recently sent and received.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Savage Armstrong Collection, D/618/166</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/411</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1552">Julia Taylor</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1891">The Priory, Rathfarnham, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Marie Elizabeth Savage Armstrong</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1536">Strangford House, Strangford, Co. Down, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_1"  type="Letter"  url="a12f3b1743f54d06bb401e52156e2329.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_2"  type="Letter"  url="01576cb4b2ebf650c26193900a12d1b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_3"  type="Letter"  url="27527fda0777a2395b01dad6e0c5eb06.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_4"  type="Letter"  url="92fd268722f1accc1e520bbadbcc39ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_5"  type="Letter"  url="27e1145dbed48cf3943202899c06e2d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_6"  type="Letter"  url="1d7e07caacd92d43d71100e1611d4f4d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_7"  type="Letter"  url="b758a4ba1448896099c0a77ee77351a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_8"  type="Letter"  url="dfff05ca1d2503bee9da8d4f01e7f0e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_9"  type="Letter"  url="df0289ba730207e3ca0f10f61fc85be2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_10"  type="Envelope"  url="d9a1602b7b55cf5d6259f8795fffe732.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0411_img_1679_11"  type="Envelope"  url="d4a73a52bf6243b29dc7a0b71558a2f4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_1"/>
                The Priory  Rathfarnham    May 14th 16   Dearest Dammie   I don't think I <lb/> answered a nice long <lb/> letter I had from you <lb/> just before the rebellion. <lb/> What a time we have <lb/> had. Here the roar of  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_2"/>
              <lb/>of Cannon of Rebel &amp; <lb/> machine guns never <lb/> ceased night or day, <lb/> only some times the <lb/><hi rend="underline">Fleet</hi><hi rend="underline">spoke</hi><hi rend="underline">up</hi> &amp; then <lb/> we heard nothing else <lb/> &amp; our windows rattled, <lb/> it was awful. The house <lb/> lighted by night by <lb/> fires, &amp; by day we looked <lb/> into a lurid cloud, <lb/> in the night there <lb/> seemed to be a sea <lb/> of fire — Soldiers home <lb/> from the Front, say <lb/> what <hi rend="underline">was</hi> Sackville St, <lb/> is now like Ypres.   Is it not wicked to say <lb/> say that lazyness <lb/> &amp; 'wait &amp; see' policies brought  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_3"/>
              such terrible loss of life <lb/>&amp; destruction of property. <lb/> The soldiers were nearly <lb/> dead from want of <lb/> food. From Monday <lb/> till Friday only a <lb/> little biscuit &amp; some tea. <lb/> We were better off than <lb/>those in Dublin as we <lb/> helped each other. The <lb/> first flour for Rath<lb/>farnham.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_4"/>
              <lb/>came in armoured <lb/> cars with escort of troops, <lb/> &amp; last Tuesday the <lb/> military came to <lb/> search the village with <lb/> machine guns at top <lb/> of street &amp; armoured <lb/> cars in it too. I think <lb/> 3 of those in. Hermitage <lb/> straight op p osite is the  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_5"/>
              <lb/>'St Enda' the Pearce's <lb/> &amp; the mother &amp; sister <lb/> are still there.   Where you stand on <lb/> Carlisle Bridge beyond <lb/> the Pillar there is <lb/> only a black, smoking, <lb/><hi rend="underline">stinking</hi> mass. The <lb/> wall or front of a house <lb/> standing like a skeleton <lb/>&amp; also down to Custom <lb/> House. Dr. <seg type="unclear">Lent</seg> biked <lb/> in to see Bank was safe <lb/> 3 or 4 days. He said bullets <lb/> were falling like a <lb/> hail shower - &amp; on <sic>Tuesday</sic><lb/>&amp; Wed there was still a <lb/> little sniping. Clyde <lb/> Rd round St Bartholemews <lb/> was very bad. There are  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_6"/>
              <lb/>some of the soliders <lb/> buried in the Church <lb/> grounds. There are <lb/> many other things <lb/> I heard but dont care <lb/> to write.    I had a nice <lb/> letter from Staff he <lb/> is very busy at his <lb/> garden. I also had  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_7"/>
              <lb/>from Cecil 2 lines, <lb/> and another short one <lb/> from D. I wrote to <lb/> her a civil letter <lb/> Easter Eve - but did <lb/> not hear since- &amp; just wrote <lb/> a P. S. to Cecil <lb/> to say we were safe <lb/> but neither wrote. <lb/> but Dammie dear  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_8"/>
              <lb/>I simply could not <lb/> respond to all her <lb/><seg type="unclear">gush</seg> — I was just friendly <lb/> &amp; hoped she would <lb/> write &amp; tell me how <lb/> they got on 'I was always <lb/> glad to hear' It is a <lb/> most painful photo <lb/> to me. She <seg type="unclear">swears</seg> so to <lb/>dominate poor Cecil <lb/> &amp; it is a horrid face <lb/> tho' handsome. He <lb/> is not likely to get more <lb/> work afloat. One's <lb/> age - she &amp; he say - <lb/> &amp; they are giving up <lb/> the flat &amp; going to the <lb/> country to start a food <lb/> farm. I don't under <lb/>stand  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_9"/>
              <lb/>it at all. A letter from <lb/>Wm Read. love to you- <lb/>I do hope Frank &amp; <lb/>Raymond are both <lb/> better — <seg type="closer">  With much love <lb/> Your dearest <seg type="unclear">Granny</seg><lb/> For my <seg type="unclear">affec.</seg> <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Julia</hi> <lb/> I here <seg type="unclear">a Ply. Lady Garden's</seg><lb/>Pupil—</seg> 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_10"/>
              Letter from Julia Taylor, about the Rebellion. 1916    Ms Savage-Armstrong  Strangford House  Strangford  Co. Down    
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0411_img_1679_11"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>