<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2649">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin  to her mother Maria Duffin, 14 February, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

This letter was written by Celia Duffin (b. 1888) to her mother Maria (1854 – 1954). According to Celia’s letter the cold water has interfered with the availability of running water for washing and other such ‘luxuries’. Celia enquires after her sister Emma, (1883 – 1979), who was serving as VAD in Egypt initially and then France (1915 – 1919).  Celia writes that she will be giving her name for foreign service soon since she expects a lot of people will be wanted abroad soon and a year at Stockport would seem very dull and monotonous. 

According to Celia nearly all the cases coming in to the nurses were men with trench feet due to the cold and wet conditions. Before signing off Celia asks her mother about news concerning friends and family and tells her the news that she has heard.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2649</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1315">St.Geroge&#39;s Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0784">Dunowen Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2649_img_2074_1"  type="Letter"  url="b957ce0937c13764e7ad9b1aa78e6999.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2649_img_2074_2"  type="Letter"  url="820a142b17423df35950f0991376f1ab.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2649_img_2074_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/B   St.George's Hospital    Feb. 14.    Dearest Mamma,   I hope the family have recovered and all coughs and chills<lb/>are gone. It has been awfully cold here, and last week we<lb/>were quite frozen up at our billets, not a drop of water to be<lb/>got, so no baths or any luxuries of that sort. We are<lb/>looked after by Mrs <seg type="unclear">Tirrewell</seg>, the matron's sister whom we<lb/>all dislike. She said she had got enough water for everybody<lb/>to have a wash one night, she had collected the<lb/>drippings off the roof and when I saw it I thought I preferred<lb/>going to bed dirty. You would have laughed if you had<lb/>seen us starting for hospital in the morning, everybody<lb/>carrying their hot bottles to fill at St. Georges. We<lb/>brought them back full and emptied them for a wash<lb/>in the mornings. The pipes have thawed at last, and I<lb/>managed to get my first bath last night.  I haven't heard from Emma for some time, what<lb/>news have you had of her. I am going to give in my<lb/>name for foreign service as I expect a lot of people will<lb/>be wanted abroad soon, and I think a year of Stockport<lb/>will be very dull and monotonous.  I wonder if there is any skating at home, all the ponds<lb/>and rivers are frozen here. Nearly all the last cases<lb/>that came in were men with trench feet, some of them 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2649_img_2074_2"/>
             D2109/10/1/B  <lb/>quite black.; they are talking of putting up marquees in the<lb/>school yard here to hold more beds for the spring—  I have just finished the Broad Highway, and liked it<lb/>very much, especially the 2<hi rend="nd"></hi> part about Charmain, I<lb/>expect you have read it.  I suppose <seg type="unclear">Molly</seg> will be home at the end of next month. I<lb/>may see her on her way back. How far is Pleasley from<lb/>here I wonder, if it is any place near I would ask<lb/>Annie to put me up my next day off, it would be<lb/>nice to go there for a change. I am glad Emmie<lb/>got home safely. I am sure Aunt Fanny must have<lb/>been anxious about her, it is dangerous work travelling<lb/>these days. Its awful how many ships have been sunk lately.  There is nothing to do here at present, and I am too lazy<lb/>to go into Manchester, it will be better when the summer<lb/>comes and we can go some expeditions again.  Is Dorothy going back to her old job again. I suppose<lb/>her leave must be nearly up now. I see Lord Norfolk,<lb/>Colonel Donnet's friend is dead. I wonder what the old Colonel<lb/>is doing now and if he is well again.  I have no news, everything here is the same as usual.  With much love<lb/>Ever your own   Celia.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>