<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2659">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Duffin to her mother, Maria Duffin, 5 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Emma Duffin (1883 - 1979) to her mother, Maria. Although the letter is dated 5 March it is written over several days up to and including 10 March. Emma is a VAD based in Alexandria, Egypt. Here she writes about the impending prospect that she will soon be home as there isn&#39;t enough work in her hospital. She has enjoyed her time there and hopes to get to Cairo to see some of the sights before she leaves for home. After some time at home she might consider working again as a VAD in England or France. Finally, she tells how she is looking forward to going home and seeing everybody again.

Emma was the fourth daughter and fifth child of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She was educated at Cheltenham Ladies College. Emma served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. She served initially in Egypt and was transferred to northern France just before the Battle of Somme, where she remained to the Armistice in 1918. On her return to Belfast, Emma worked as an illustrator of cards and books, including children’s stories written by her sister Ruth. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2659</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1134">Emma Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1678">Alexandria, Egypt</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2659_img_2083_1"  type="Letter"  url="f5d82e2f44f1dd5977dd09208784be71.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2659_img_2083_2"  type="Letter"  url="65e75192ce36405f458efa1ac48f59e9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2659_img_2083_3"  type="Letter"  url="7f438016c7d53a41ae1ab0fc06c486e4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2659_img_2083_1"/>
              D2109/10/1/C    ALEXANDRIA<lb/>(EGYPT)    March 5—/16. <lb/><lb/> My dearest Mamma   You say at the end of your letter which I got<lb/>today, that you sometimes long to see me &amp; you may be sure I<lb/>do the same for you, but perhaps you will be astonished to<lb/>hear that you may see me quite soon after you get this letter<lb/>if not before. I cannot tell you when exactly. Matron says<lb/>she does not know herself, it might be this month and it might<lb/>not be till next. I suppose it depends when they have a hospital<lb/>ship free to take us but i think we are all going home. When<lb/>I was asked whether I would sign in again I said yes as I have been<lb/>very well all the time and they were being very strict about medically<lb/>examining everybody before the bad weather came on, but later the<lb/>Matron of our hospital came to the conclusion that she would<lb/>rather we did not sign in again. There is not enough work for us to<lb/>do at present. She does not think there is going to be and thinks<lb/>a lot of us would <seg type="unclear">break</seg> up with the heat. All the Matrons are<lb/>not of the same opinion &amp; some are keeping theirs V.G. D's on<lb/>&amp; some of our girlsare rather indignant at our Matron for not<lb/>doing the same but I think she is right. She said to me that she<lb/>felt that there was not enough work to justify her keeping us on<lb/>&amp; she felt it would not be honest to to do so though she would like to but<lb/>it was waste of Govt. money, she said she hoped no one would feel<lb/>hurt or think they had not been wanted, for she felt we had all<lb/>worked well &amp; had been of great use &amp; could be if we would join again<lb/>for home service or in France. She could not have been nicer about 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2659_img_2083_2"/>
              D2109/10/1/C.    ALEXANDRIA<lb/>(EGYPT)   than she was to me personally but she has made a great mistake<lb/>in not having us all together and saying so, instead of speaking to individuals<lb/>but she is very shy &amp; I believe could not face it &amp; was afraid we<lb/>would all take it badly &amp; be offended because she did not want us,<lb/>as it is we have all felt rather low for the last fortnight because<lb/>the girls at the other hospitals were asked to stay by their Matrons &amp;<lb/>ours made us move. I think she hoped we would most of us<lb/>refuse to sign &amp; save her the <seg type="unclear">uncon</seg> task of telling us we were not<lb/>wanted, as it was I believe the majority said they would stay.   March 7  We are having perfect weather at present, just nice<lb/>heat &amp; the almond blossoms are all out. It is so funny here,<lb/>you see nasturtiums, sweet peas &amp; all sortsof spring flowers<lb/>flowering at will. I am in an awfully jolly ward, or<lb/>rather wards, for there are four small wards with 12 beds in each<lb/>there are 3 sisters another V.A.D &amp; myself, &amp; the only<lb/>trouble is we have not enough to do. Sister Rice Oxley. A.J's<lb/>friend is my sister &amp; she &amp; I have great fun together.   March 10th  This is a very scrappy letter I am afraid, I am writing<lb/>this in bed on my half day, which I spent at teh Sporting Club<lb/>playing tennis with Capt Boyle, a Capt. <seg type="unclear">Dibden</seg> &amp; Rhoda Whyle.<lb/>I saw Molly &amp; John Cannon there and she told me he was off to<lb/><seg type="unclear">M...</seg>probably on Wednesday, but she intends to stay on here<lb/>for thew present. We have heard no further news about<lb/>going home but I do not expect we shall get much notice before<lb/>hand, probably a line from me when I reach England will<lb/>be the first indication you will have. I shall be very sorry to  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2659_img_2083_3"/>
             leave in many ways, but it will be <hi rend="underline">very</hi> nice to be home and<lb/>seen you all again, and so nice to have a holiday! What my<lb/>next movements will be depends on the war I suppose like every<lb/>thing else. I should not mind going to France but I would hate<lb/>to be a V.A.D. in some English town where I didn't know anyone<lb/>I am sure Celia has a rotten time compered to what I have had<lb/>I have really been very happy here &amp; have met with no disagree<lb/>ableness from sister or anyone else, &amp; a lot of kindness from a<lb/>great many people. Matron told me she would try &amp;<lb/>let us all go to Cairo for a day or two before we went home so I,<lb/>hope she will, I should hate to leave Egypt without seeing it and<lb/>the old Sphinx.  They have opened sch a nice club for Sisters &amp; V.A.D's here, very<lb/>nice tea room, writing room &amp; sitting room, with nice chintz curtains<lb/>big settees and cushins, really very comfortable!. It would have<lb/>been more of a look in the colder weather &amp; the dark evenings<lb/>The subscription is only 2/- a month, &amp; tea costs 4 piastres<lb/>It is funny to think how soon I may see you all! What talks<lb/>we will have.  Best love to you all dearest<lb/>Ever your own   Emma  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>