<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3456">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maria Coyle to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 20 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Coyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Maria Coyle (b.1843) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946). Coyle writes to Skeffington in order to return tickets for the fundraising concert in aid of the &#34;Irish Citizen&#34;. While unhappy to hear that the paper is struggling Coyle does not believe it will make much difference with the passing of the Home Rule Bill. Coyle argues that women&#39;s rights will not have a hope in Ireland as Irishmen will never tolerate freedom of their women. Coyle goes on to congratulate Skeffington on her achievements and while she disagrees with certain methods expresses a continued fondness for those involved in the struggle for suffrage.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/16-25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3456</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0835">Maria Coyle</persName>
              <date>1916-02-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3456_img_2866_1"  type="Letter"  url="cf8522a17af91b64e8fdad9d784a4503.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3456_img_2866_2"  type="Letter"  url="0bf46df534bc681fea7cf3c175eb8d1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3456_img_2866_3"  type="Letter"  url="3a6db22e8c9e483b327a7badc76a1476.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3456_img_2866_4"  type="Letter"  url="795568bf7154a7315fb49d484a9fdb18.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3456_img_2866_1"/>
             24 Charleston Road   20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb 1916   My dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington   I was glad to receive <lb/>your memo, as it gave <lb/>me an opportunity <lb/>of apologizing for my <lb/>neglect in not writing <lb/>in reply to former com- <lb/>munications, one of which <lb/>was an application <lb/>for my annual subscription. <lb/>No doubt that was sent <lb/>by mistake &amp; probably <lb/>you then remembered <lb/>that in May 1913 I had <lb/>resigned my membership.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3456_img_2866_2"/>
            &amp; had not since exercised <lb/>any privilege in con <lb/>nection with it.   I return the tickets which <lb/>only reached this morning <lb/>in any  case  would not <lb/>have gone myself and <lb/>the time was too short <lb/>to find any one to take <lb/>there. I am sorry to hear <lb/>of the non-success of the <lb/>paper, but I really feel <lb/>that it does not now <lb/>much matter, as since <lb/>the "Home Rule Bill" <lb/>has passed, the women's <lb/>movement has no hope <lb/>in Ireland. Irishmen <lb/>will never tolerate the
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3456_img_2866_3"/>
            Freedom of their women. <lb/>I will however  send on  a very <lb/>small trifle, <seg type="unclear">it</seg> is all <lb/>I can afford towards <lb/>your deliverance and <lb/>indeed you all have <lb/>mt sincere sympathy <lb/>&amp; good wishes in the <lb/>struggle &amp; self denial <lb/>you have made <lb/>for a worthy object. <lb/>I believe that the <lb/>splendid conduct <lb/>of the women during <lb/>this terrible crisis <lb/>is entirely due to the <lb/>disciplinary educational <lb/>struggle which you, and <lb/>your sisters have <lb/>reiterated and carried
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3456_img_2866_4"/>
            on during these years <lb/>passed and although <lb/>I do not approve of <lb/>some methods adopted, <lb/>I will always entertain <lb/>a deep regard for my <lb/>former friends in our <lb/>suffrage movement &amp; <lb/>now thank them for <lb/>their kindness and <lb/>consideration during <lb/>the pleasant evenings <lb/>we have passed together <lb/>&amp; for their toleration <lb/>for one who only now <lb/>"cumbereth the ground."   Very Sincerely <lb/>yours   M Coyle 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>