<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2107">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Margaret Ruth Leslie to her brother Cecil George Leslie, 29 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Margaret Ruth Leslie</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Margaret Ruth Leslie and Cecil George Leslie come from the wealthy south Ulster family known as the Leslies of  Corravahan outside Cavan. Margaret had been living in Wilton place since at least 1911. Her brother Cecil George Leslie was wounded in the opening stages of the Great War losing an eye as a result and at the time of this letter was stationed at the Seine divisional HQ for the duration of the war. 
This letter from Margaret Ruth Leslie (1886-1972) to Cecil George Leslie (1879-1919) gives an eye witness account of the impact of the Easter Rising in the wealthy area of Wilton Place in south Dublin. Areas which she has covered in the letter include the rebel garrisons occupation of St Stephens Green, heavy fighting in the city centre, well hidden snipers, lack of popular support for the rebels fro the Dublin population, having to forage for food supplies and rumors surrounding a body of Sinn Feiners marching on Dublin from Wexford. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>McKeown Private Collection </repository>
                  <collection>McKeown-1916-04-29</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2107</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1141">Margaret Ruth Leslie</persName>
              <date>1916-04-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0543">1 Wilton Place, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Cecil George Leslie</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_1"  type="NULL"  url="8210ead8d6b9349f5d4af97842c4b6c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_2"  type="NULL"  url="b2d59d67369906edff9ecb5c0bfad392.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_3"  type="NULL"  url="79c548bf9184e89705c8a085b7fca7f9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_4"  type="NULL"  url="efe5e9f9816ba0ea1ff8af28962c2216.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_5"  type="NULL"  url="31a8ef26ba140f519c3ed66098546f25.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_6"  type="NULL"  url="924031fc5871119a1e8e0fbe45fdaf86.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2107_img_1558_7"  type="NULL"  url="daa5d8f50bc3ea9f2a1da7f2308553ed.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_1"/>
              1 Wilton Place <lb/>Dublin  <lb/> 29 - IV- 16     Dear Choppy,   I don't know if you will ever get this but <lb/>Bergy Tombe has motored up from Wicklow <lb/>to—day &amp; says he'll get some letters posted <lb/>on his way home. There's no post in Dublin <lb/> &amp; we haven't seen a paper since Monday <lb/> except a Daily Sketch which we saw <lb/> yesterday. It was going the round of <lb/>Dublin and we got "a read of it".    It's extremely hard to know where to <lb/>begin especially as we know practically <lb/>nothing though we hear hundreds of <lb/>rumours. We can hear fierce battling <lb/>going on constantly. I see fearful <lb/>fires down in the city. We can hear machine <lb/>— guns, bombs, some kind of bigger gun <lb/> and of course incessant rifle-fire. There <lb/> are snipers everywhere &amp; it's next to im <lb/>-possible to locate them. To begin with we
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_2"/>
            <lb/>were much cooped up &amp; only allowed out <lb/>into the square etc. except that some of <lb/>us had to go &amp; see Dina <seg type="unclear">Hensworth</seg> twice <lb/>a day. She is all by herself in a house in <lb/>Pembroke Road just across Baggot <lb/>St Bridge &amp; has just perpetrated an infant <lb/>&amp; as the fighting was very hot in <lb/> that district someone has to call constant- <lb/>ly &amp; distract her maid with prattle. As a <lb/>matter of fact she is merely <sic>pleasureably</sic> <lb/>excited — in fact, dreadful to relate we <lb/> are all enjoying it enormously. There <lb/> must be masses of troops in Dublin now <lb/>They hold all the bridges this side of <lb/>the town now, which the Sinn Feiners <lb/>did on Monday &amp; Tuesday of course they had odious <lb/> fighting to get them back &amp; the hospitals <lb/>are crammed. I believe two trains of <lb/>wounded have gone to Belfast &amp; a lot to <lb/>England. Of course the S. F.'s tried to cut
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_3"/>
             the railway to the north but I believe they<lb/>only half blew up a bridge &amp; there is a single<lb/>line still. Of course all this information<lb/>is quite unreliable. It's a loathsome job<lb/>for the troops as they haven't even decent<lb/>maps &amp; of course they can't trust anyone<lb/>&amp; have no guides &amp; being English know<lb/>nothing, &amp; except at rare intervals they<lb/>never see the enemy. It's house to house<lb/>fighting &amp; they are sniped from everywhere.<lb/>Thank goodness Jane &amp; Ira are getting<lb/>so used to it all that they have ceased<lb/>to fuss about us &amp; we were allowed<lb/>down to Ballsbridge this morning to<lb/>see the troops coming in. It's perfectly<lb/>safe as we hold the whole road from<lb/>Baggot St out to Kingstown now &amp;<lb/>the snipers don't want to shoot us in<lb/>the least. I can hear them going all round<lb/>now. Half the time I don't think they<lb/>can be firing at anything in particular.<lb/>The police are all cooped up somewhere. They<lb/>can't let them out as they aren't armed<lb/>&amp; in even in plain clothes, directing the troops  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_4"/>
             would be quite unmistakable &amp; a plain<lb/>mark for snipers. There is very likely nothing<lb/>going on in Merrion Square now &amp; I hear<lb/>they fired on the Red + nurses there<lb/>yesterday but on the whole they seem to have<lb/>behaved very decently. <seg type="del">We</seg> We have heard of<lb/>several people whose houses they occupied<lb/>&amp; they weree quite <seg type="unclear"></seg>I didn't even loot<lb/>if they were not resisted. There strikes one<lb/>as being curiously little popular sympathy<lb/>with the movement &amp; it seems Redmond's<lb/>lot — the National Volunteers (who he said<lb/>were to keep the peace at home!) are lying<lb/>very low &amp; are not in with the S. F's at<lb/>all. Of course they must be feeling sick<lb/>as at any rate this must do for Home Rule.<lb/>We were allowed down to Nassau St one<lb/>day to pack parcels for the Dublin Fusilier<lb/>Prisoners as they depend on the food that is<lb/>sent there &amp; it would be dreadful if they<lb/>didn't get it. So the   were to get a pass<lb/>for a motor to take this week's consignment<lb/>down to Kingstown &amp; dump it on one of the<lb/>returning transports. We strolled down in<lb/>great hopes of seeing strange sights &amp; per -   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_5"/>
             haps being shot at but saw very<lb/>little except a dead horse in Stephens Green<lb/>(where we weren't supposed to go) &amp; a lot of motors<lb/>&amp; trams across the road &amp; bullet holes<lb/>in the windows, of course this was after<lb/>the S F's had evacuated Stephen's Green<lb/>which they did on Tuesday night. I don't know<lb/>why they were let as they could simply<lb/>have been starved out there. However I<lb/>believe we were desperately short of troops<lb/>&amp; everything else till Wed. One of the great<lb/>difficulties is to bury the dead as of course<lb/>they can't always get them to the cemeteries.<lb/>They are going to use the field at the back<lb/>here I think. You should see us foraging<lb/>in the morning - Jane , Nelly, Margery, &amp; me<lb/>I don't know what will happen if it goes on<lb/>much longer &amp; the food begins to give out.<lb/>I believe a lot of Sackville St is burnt out<lb/>&amp; <seg type="del">they</seg> we have blown up Jacob's factory &amp; <seg type="unclear">burnt</seg><lb/>a lot of S F's in it. I don't know if we have<lb/>got the <seg type="del">Post</seg> GPO back yet but I doubt  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_6"/>
             it. The Sinn Feiners seized that &amp; Stephen's<lb/>Green first thing &amp; report says they bagged<lb/>some young officers &amp; a parson or so &amp; several<lb/>other people &amp; kept them with them so<lb/>those poor devils will have to be blown up<lb/>with the S. F. 's. We have just heard a<lb/>report that the Sinn Feiners are at Slane<lb/>which we must keep carefully from Dina.<lb/>It's possible I'm afraid as otherwise I<lb/>think Lady Connyham would have got to<lb/>her somehow.  There are supposed to be a big Body of S F 's<lb/>marching up from Wexford but <seg type="unclear">Bergy Tombe</seg><lb/>says he doesn't believe it as he has seen no<lb/>sign of them &amp; anyhow there are troops<lb/>lying in wait for them.  From the paper yesterday Asquith seems<lb/>to be minimizing the affair as much<lb/>as he can but it's bound to come out. I  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2107_img_1558_7"/>
             hope all's quiet in the country but there<lb/>but there are rumours of trouble in the west.<lb/>Gen French was away when the<lb/>outbreak occurred (1 p.m. on Monday) Of course<lb/>the government has been warned over &amp;<lb/>over again that this was imminent<lb/>They say French had gone over to hand<lb/>in his resignation as they wouldn't give<lb/>him men. Must stop as this has<lb/>got to go. I'm afraid it's a very<lb/>garbled account, but my information<lb/>is profuse but scanty if you know<lb/>what that means. I wish we could<lb/>get some war news .Best love.  Yours ever  M.R.L.<lb/><lb/>I don't know if they have heard anything<lb/>of me at home 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>