<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0405">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfred Short, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfred Short</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Wilfred Short (1870-1947) to the Chief Secretary&#39;s Office. Short is writing to enclose an anonymous letter addressed to Arthur James Balfour. The enclosed letter claims that the Irish are planning another Rising, and warns that the British should prepare the military and navy. The writer says that millions of Irish American Fenians plan to take over not only Ireland but England.&#39;These traitors will eat the heart out of the Empire&#39;.Wilfred Short was a British civil servant. In 1916 he was serving as private secretary to the statesman Arthur James Balfour (1848-1930), a British Conservative politician who was the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from July 1902 to December 1905. The letter is addressed to the Chief Secretary for Ireland. At this time there is no official Chief Secretary for Ireland following the resignation of Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) on 3 May 1916. Birrell&#39;s resignation was a consequence of the 1916 Rising for which he accepted responsibility. His successor, Henry Edward Duke (1855-1939), was not officially appointed until 31 July 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9864/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/405</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0341">Wilfred Short</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr (A.J.) Balfour</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0405_img_1667_1"  type="Letter"  url="a7bd8ea9a2d1c5ea4ebf93aca94bdd91.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0405_img_1667_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="be3b9b3c561ec94dce3237b741ad78ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0405_img_1667_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="a3958ad0c94aa2e28fabdf8157239f28.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0405_img_1667_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="0394a1960574bdae42f0ebbef0a12c3f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0405_img_1667_1"/>
                9 June 1916   Dear Sir,   The enclosed anony- <lb/> mous communication<lb/> has been addressed to<lb/> Mr Balfour. For<lb/> what it may be<lb/> worth I send it to<lb/> you. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Wilfrid Short</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0405_img_1667_2"/>
                Dublin    7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916   Sir   I wish to let you<lb/> know that the Irish are <lb/> rising again on White <lb/> Monday or so, and<lb/> your Government would<lb/> want to take precautions<lb/> This is why they want<lb/> Home Rule in order  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0405_img_1667_3"/>
              to get the military and<lb/> ships that guards the<lb/> coast of Ireland with-<lb/> drawn until they get<lb/> in the 3 millions of<lb/> Irish American Fenians<lb/> who are coming over to<lb/> take not only Ireland<lb/> but England. the way<lb/> Asquith has acted in<lb/> letting out the rebels<lb/> has demonstrated to<cb/> them that they can kill<lb/> police etc. with impunity<lb/> and so they are re-forming<lb/> and are rising again.  You must see that<lb/> the Liberals are not let<lb/> wipe out the whole <lb/> Constitution and it is<lb/> time they were put out<lb/> before they trail England<lb/> in the dust any more.<lb/> and you should see that<lb/> a good Conservative  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0405_img_1667_4"/>
              General is appointed<lb/> in Lord Kitchiner's<lb/> place.  England's difficulty<lb/> is Ireland's opportunity<lb/> has long been the rebels<lb/> motto, and this rising<lb/> in Ireland is made<lb/> whilst the men are in<lb/> France, and unless this<lb/> war is stopped these traitors<lb/> will eat the heart out <lb/> of this Empire  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>