<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0633">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael O'Riordan to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 12 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael O&#39;Riordan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Monsignor Michael O&#39;Riordan (1857-1919), rector at the Irish College in Rome, to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 until his death. This letter concerns O’Riordan’s reaction to the Easter Rising. O’Riordan is critical of the excessive British response to the Rising. Had the executive shown greater leniency the insurgents, who were to become immortal heroes, would probably have been instead regarded as thoughtless youths. He also refers to the death of Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 – 1916), an Irish, pacifist, writer and feminist who had adopted his wife Hanna Sheehy&#39;s surname. Skeffington was executed on the morning of 26 April 1916, along with two other civilians who were shot by firing squad on the orders of Captain John Bowen-Colthurst, an experienced officer of the Royal Irish Rifles. Colthurst would later be court-martialed by the British authorities for his actions. O&#39; Riordan states that the execution was lawless and stupid.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/I/1, LDA/BI/ET/I/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/633</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0177">Michael O&#39;Riordan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0191">Irish College, Rome, Italy</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0633_img_2096_1"  type="Letter"  url="b3c067eab838da8df96ffd136984c83b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0633_img_2096_2"  type="Letter"  url="fb732682e6d4b66d32fef46b8da1c120.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0633_img_2096_3"  type="Letter"  url="7cd58e08e7b19b6700c2adbf54524403.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0633_img_2096_1"/>
                Irish College  Rome    12 May 1916   My Lord Bishop   I enclose a <seg type="unclear">receipt</seg>. I<lb/> suppose the Censor is at work<lb/> again. If he opens this letter he<lb/> will have an opportunity of<lb/> revising his Latin â if he ever<lb/> knew any.  The Government Executive<lb/> seems to be as foolish as the<lb/> insurgents. Mr Skeffington never  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0633_img_2096_2"/>
              had any sense. But he should<lb/> have had a trial; to shoot<lb/> him without one was  <lb/> lawless and stupid. It will<lb/> probably be sought now to impress<lb/> on the public conviction that<lb/> all were executed without trial.<lb/> If the  (executive)  showed living under<lb/> their natural provocation the<lb/> the insurgents who are now likely to<lb/> become immortal heroes could<lb/> probably have lived in the<lb/> public memory of Ireland as<lb/> impulsive thoughtless youths <cb/><seg type="del">the</seg> the <seg type="unclear">scorn</seg> of <hi rend="underline">wisdom</hi> there is<lb/> not a pin to choose between<lb/> the executive and the insurgents.  We are still in the dark <lb/> here as to what directly led up<lb/> to the trouble. I take no notice<lb/> of what politicians &amp; journalists<lb/> say on any side since the war<lb/> began. They have made lying an<lb/> art and a <hi rend="underline">virtue</hi> â it is a<lb/><hi rend="underline">moral duty</hi> to lie if it pays<lb/> It is a <hi rend="underline">literal</hi> truth that I have<lb/> not read <hi rend="underline">one sentence</hi> about the<lb/> battle of Verdun and I seem to<lb/> know as much about it as those  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0633_img_2096_3"/>
              who study it with maps â more<lb/> because I am aware of my<lb/> ignorance.  I have heard that some persons<lb/> here have sent a telegram to Mr Redmond<lb/> on the trouble in Dublin as from<lb/> 'the Irish in Rome'. I know nothing of it<lb/> and the Augustinians &amp; Franciscans know<lb/> nothing of it. I am told that the <lb/> sender of it (who the   were I<lb/> cannot say) was born in Scotland. So<lb/> we have a <seg type="unclear">Foaley</seg> St in Rome as in<lb/> London and there are <seg type="unclear">traitors</seg> in it<lb/> too. It is a foolish thing for nearly<lb/> all the Irish in Rome are students or <lb/> nuns. <seg type="closer"> I am <seg type="unclear">My Lord</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">yours obediently</seg> <lb/> M O'Riordan </seg><seg type="postscript"> P S As I have these remarks on the troubles in Dublin I have<lb/><seg type="unclear">not put 'a priest sends sermon' on the envelope</seg> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>