<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1273">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Connolly to Lady Clonbrock, 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Connolly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Postcard from a prisoner of war, Joseph Connolly, to Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Connolly writes an acknowledgement of food parcels and change of address information.Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Papers, Ms 35796-14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1273</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0348">Joseph Connolly</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1273_img_47_1"  type="Letter"  url="236eb98b3ab61bb13722647526b67d37.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1273_img_47_2"  type="Letter"  url="3d240405565096c9280e6d2eeeedc839.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1273_img_47_1"/>
                 Bureau de secours  aux  prisonniers de guerre  SECTION ANGLAISE  BERNE      29/5/16   Madam,   I wish to <lb/>inform you that I have <lb/>two <sic>Pracils</sic> of Bread, <lb/>I wish to inform you that <lb/>I have <sic>change</sic> my address <lb/>to Limburg, Thanking you <lb/>very much for Parcels, <seg type="closer"> <sic>your turly</sic>  J Connolly<lb/>Connaugh Rangers </seg> <hi rend="underline">Please always give your Regiment and <lb/>Regimental No.</hi>   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1273_img_47_2"/>
                 Kriegsgefangenenlager   <hi rend="underline">Limburg Lahn</hi>  Pte Joseph Connolly  Connaught Rangers  Regt No 10760  11â Batl 4 Comp 747  <sic>Prisonnres</sic> of war camp  Limburg Lahn  Germany    Right side    Bureau de Secours   aux Prisonniers de Guerre  Section Anglaise  Thunstrasse 50  <hi rend="underline">BERNE</hi>  (Suisse)     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>