<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4908">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Devoy to Daniel Cohalan, 20 July 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Devoy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>American Irish Historical Society</repository>
                  <collection>Friends of Irish Freedom, Office of the National Secretary, 1918-1939</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4908</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0598">John Devoy</persName>
              <date>1920-07-20</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Daniel Cohalan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1928</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4908_img_None_1"  url="f3cc00f564dfc7383af3144112064d6e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4908_img_None_2"  url="b8129ca0d5b9d81370d11b11b31ddf09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4908_img_None_3"  url="cb14afbf947db65d40805c36db0d4c20.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4908_img_0_1"/>
             <hi rend="superscript">M.J. O'Brien says he<lb/>finds all the people he meets<lb/>on our side</hi>   July 20/20    Dear C:,   If Murphy is still with you show him enclosed type-<lb/>written letters. If he has gone home please forward to him. His<lb/>business address is (if you don't already know it) 304 People's<lb/>Bank Bldg.  James K. called to-day, but only stayed about half<lb/>an hour. Harry showed him the letters, and they don't bear out<lb/>the description of the proposition he gave the man to whom<lb/>he talked, <hi rend="underline">but he knows what they intend by it.</hi> The organization<lb/>has changed its Constitution and made itself part of the Re-<lb/>public. They want us to do the same, and the implication is<lb/>that if we don't do so they will cut us off. Of course, it would<lb/>be suicidal, <hi rend="underline">for us and them</hi>, to do so. I think by the time it<lb/>comes round to the settlement of that question we'll be so<lb/>strong that there will be no difficulty about that.  We won, hands down, last night at the Local Council and elected<lb/>Mulcahy to succeed Gargan. The others had made great preparations<lb/>to elect Tom. Rock, but they did not even mention his name and put<lb/>up no candidate. The drubbing they got last Sunday week at the<lb/>Clarke Branch put the fear of God in them. They were all there<lb/>and were told plainly<hi rend="superscript"> <hi rend="superscript"> by Sheahan </hi> </hi>they would get the same again if they raised       
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4908_img_0_2"/>
             a disturbance anywhere. He invited them to try it in his branch, but<lb/>told them they would be welcome if they conducted themselves properly.<lb/><hi rend="superscript"> Col. Anderson presided  </hi>Mc Mahon says there is a strong reaction in Philadelphia. Two<lb/>S.G's told him they were sorry for voting against the G.A., and he<lb/>met lots of members who are all right. But they don't express<lb/>themselves at meetings. He says Joe's campaign is getting nowhere and<lb/>there is a growing feeling against <seg type="unclear">Mc Cartan</seg> In Atlantic City he<lb/>was afraid of a Father Moran, a pastor, who was a little wrong a<lb/>few weeks ago, but when he went to see him a few days ago he<lb/>said he had read up the trouble in the I.W., the Press and the<lb/>G.A. and had made up his mind that you and the G.A. are<lb/>right. They have three branches and he found officers and members<lb/>all right. In Phil. he told Mc Carney he was greatly mistaken about<lb/>the feeling of the Country and that if there was a Split Joe's crowd would<lb/>be overwhelmingly beaten. Mc C wants no fight, but through old friendship<lb/>sticks to Joe. But his brother, who is a more intelligent man, is all right.<lb/>Mc M. spoke at one club and one branch meeting. He did not refer to the<lb/>fight, but told of the great work done by the Friends and yours in Wash-<lb/>ington and it was vigorously applauded. He is very <seg type="unclear">sanguine</seg> that we'll<lb/>win.  Harry showed James K. a lot of captured documents <hi rend="superscript"> some of them  </hi>about crooks<lb/>among us. The whole lot, he says, are very interesting. They have the<lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/> <hi rend="superscript"></hi><lb/><hi rend="superscript"></hi>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4908_img_0_3"/>
             3  fellows' reports, but they are all about proceedings at ordinary meetings.<lb/>Mick is Minister of Defence and doing all the work.<lb/>The Visitor and Harry went to see James last night. The Visitor did<lb/>not attack anybody; said he was done speaking and was going to<lb/>go home. <hi rend="superscript">James</hi><seg type="del">He</seg> sent him out in an auto with his wife while he talked<lb/>to Harry. Harry seemed anxious to settle things peaceably,<lb/>He has a craze about <hi rend="underline">control of things from home</hi> , like all<lb/>little men, but seems to want no fight.  James showed the Visitor a scrap book about the Split<lb/>from 1888 to 1892 and told him a lot about his own experience.<lb/>He said if there was a Split now he would get out. He didn't say<lb/>whether he made any impression or not and I think he doesn't<lb/>know.  I saw a letter from Fr. Magennis to-day. He says he is out for good.<lb/>He gives the Old Man credit for honesty, but wonders how he can't see<lb/>that telling all those things in public is not helping the enemy. He also<lb/>says something about cheap politics.  I have a letter from a priest (can't lay my hands on it just now)<lb/>asking how the Commission on Ireland. came to be formed and why it butted in.<lb/>He is apparently all right. I will answer him to-morrow.<lb/>This is my whole budget of news.   Yours truly<lb/>J.D. <lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>