<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3684">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell  to The Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 31 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926), assistant under secretary of Ireland, asking the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) for their opinion on a proposed change to the Orders governing the sale of &#39;carbolic preparations for agricultural and horticultural purposes&#39;. Enclosed  is a copy of a letter from William Cooper &amp; Nephews Chemical Works requesting that these changes be made.  

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T56-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3684</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-01-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3684_img_3077_1"  type="Letter"  url="1f73c2414b31fe69e409f989532cfa48.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3684_img_3077_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="405e5c18cfee3ad140f0bf1acc758490.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3684_img_3077_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="afcb9d8e2b2e3ab09568171c5b1166ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3684_img_3077_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="ce1d8e0f3bd8508e6e71d73e176b75ba.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3684_img_3077_1"/>
             DUBLIN CASTLE,   31st. January, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Lord Lieutenant to transmit to you, <lb/>to be laid before the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, <lb/>copies of letters which have been received from Messrs William <lb/>Cooper and Nephews of Berkhamsted and the Department of <lb/>Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland on the <lb/>subject of the sale of carbolic preparations for agricultural <lb/>and horticultural purposes.   His Excellency is advised that there is no power to <lb/>alter the Order in Council of the 17th June, 1897, approving <lb/>the resolution of the Royal College of Physicians adding, <lb/>amongst other substances, Phenol, commonly called Carbolic <lb/>Acid, to Part II. of Schedule A of the Sale of Poisons (Ireland) <lb/>Act, 1870, but that the object desired by Messrs Cooper and <lb/>Nephews may be attained by making an Order in Council under <lb/>Section 2(1) of the Poisons and Pharmacy Act, 1908, adding <lb/>to the poisonous substances mentioned therein any liquid <lb/>preparation of carbolic acid and its homologues, provided <lb/>that such poisonous substances shall be contained in a closed <lb/>vessel, distinctly labelled with the word "Poisonous," the <lb/>name and address of the seller and a notice of the special <lb/>purposes for which the preparations are intended.   Before giving directions for the issue of such an Order <lb/>in Council His Excellency would be glad to receive and con- <lb/>sider any criticisms or suggestions which the Royal College <lb/>of Physicians may desire to offer in the matter.   I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   E O'Farrell   Macd.C <lb/>4.II.18   The Registrar, <lb/>Royal College of Physicians, <lb/>Kildare Street. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3684_img_3077_2"/>
             (Copy) 13832   Chemical Works, <lb/>Berkhamsted.   17th August, 1915.   CJG/EC. <lb/>The Secretary of the Privy Council, <lb/>Dublin Castle, Dublin.   Dear Sir,   Will you be so kind as to inform us whether there <lb/>is any difference between the English and the Irish Law in <lb/>regard to the sale of Carbolic Preparations for Agricultural <lb/>and Horticultural purposes (1) by persons holding a license <lb/>for the sale of Agricultural and Horticultural poisons, <lb/>(2) by persons who do not hold such a license.   The facts which immediately suggest this enquiry <lb/>are as follows:- We manufacture a fluid for the spraying <lb/>of fruit trees, containing a fairly high percentage of <lb/>phenols. This has beeen sold in Ireland by our Agents, <lb/>some of whom hold a Poisons License and others who do not.   Some of these Agents have been told that they <lb/>being neither Pharmaceutical Chemists nor Druggists, the <lb/>selling of this fluid is a breach of the law.   As far as we can gather the reason given why they <lb/>are supposed to be breaking the law is that under an Irish <lb/>Order in Council dated 18th June, 1897, Phenol, commonly <lb/>called "Carbolic Acid" was declared to be a poison and <lb/>directed to be added to Part 2 of Schedule A of the Poisons <lb/>Act, 1870, and apparently it is contended that, even with the <lb/>aid of a license under the Poisions Act, 1908, unqualified <lb/>persons cannot sell these preparations.   As you are perhaps aware the English Order in <lb/>Council dealing with this subject is as follows:-   "Carbolic Acid, and liquid preparations of <lb/>carbolic acid and its homologues, containing more than 3 % <lb/>of those substances, except preparations for use as sheep <lb/>wash or for any other purpose in connection with agriculture <lb/>or horticulture, contained in a closed vessel distinctly <lb/>labelled
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3684_img_3077_3"/>
            the length and breadth of Ireland.   In view of this position, which is obviously opposed <lb/>to the avowed intentions of Parliament in passing the <lb/>Posions Act, 1908, and the English Law upon the same subject <lb/>under which any person can sell Carbolic Preparations for <lb/>Horticultural and Agricultural purposes, we shall be glad <lb/>to know whether your Council will modify the Irish Order <lb/>in Council, 18th June, 1897, so as to bring it into accord <lb/>with the English law and with the intentions of Parliament.   In the meantime as the season for the sale of Carbolic <lb/>Horticultural Preparations is now upon us, will you kindly <lb/>inform us, in the event of any prosecution taking place for <lb/>the sale of such preparations, whether you will advise the <lb/>Lord Lieutenant to remit any penalties which may be inflicted.   Practically the whole of the sheep in the north of <lb/>Ireland, and many of those in other parts of the country are <lb/>in the autum dipped with Carbolic Preparations, 95 % of <lb/>which are sold by persons other than Chemists and Druggists <lb/>everyone of whom will apparently become liable to heavy <lb/>penalties on account of this violent change of policy by <lb/>the Pharmaceutical Society.   Yours faithfully,   William Cooper &amp; Nephews.   Macd.C <lb/>4.II.16 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3684_img_3077_4"/>
             (Copy) <lb/>No. G. 4023-15.   17929.   Department of Agriculture <lb/>and Technical Instruction <lb/>for Ireland, <lb/>Upper Merrion Street.   26th October, 1916.   Sir,   Adverting to your letter of the 22nd ultimo, 15342, and <lb/>enclosures, on the question of the sale of carbolic prepara- <lb/>tions in Ireland for agricultural and horticultural purposes, <lb/>I have to state, for the information of His Excellency the <lb/>Lord Lieutenant, that in the view of the Department, it <lb/>would be a considerable benefit to the Irish agricultural <lb/>industry that preparations of Phenol (carbolic acid) should <lb/>be sold for these purposes by persons licensed by the Country <lb/>Councils, as well as by pharmaceutical chemists and druggists <lb/>as is the case in Great Britain. Difficulties are often <lb/>experienced in Ireland in having sheep properly dipped, and <lb/>it would be extremely desirable that no unnecessary obstacle <lb/>should be placed in the way of the sale of carbolic preara— <lb/>tions for sheep dipping, and for horticultural purposes <lb/>generally.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   T. P. GILL,  <lb/>Secretary.  The Under Secretary, <lb/>DUBLIN CASTLE. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>