<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0967">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Carson to Sir David Harrell, 20 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Carson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Carson to Sir David Harrell (1841-1939) concerning sedition in Ireland. Carson writes that the government is not being firm enough with sedition in Ireland and that if British law is enough for England, Wales, Scotland and Ulster it should be enough for southern Ireland. Additionally, Carson writes about the weapon he designed at the outbreak of the war which was deemed to severe by Asquith for military use. This rejection has convinced Carson that Asquith does not want to win the war and is complicit with the Germans.Sir David Harrell was a member of the Privy Council of Ireland. A former constable of the Royal Irish Constabulary, Harrell worked with several bodies to improve relations between Catholics and Protestants and relieve the poverty of the Irish peasantry.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papaers, 1916-10679</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/967</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0928">Robert Carson</persName>
              <date>1916-06-20</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir David Harrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1179">Royal Societies Club, James Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0967_img_2797_1"  type="Letter"  url="eb8d6c21c24046ce38a89e9a29c360fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0967_img_2797_2"  type="Letter"  url="533545aeb505f2cb3378fa263706ec4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0967_img_2797_3"  type="Letter"  url="7cfd60c2c30dff5038f33dfa59615475.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0967_img_2797_1"/>
                7 Waring street  Belfast    June 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    Sir David Harrel  Dublin Castle   Dear Sir   I enclose copies of letters to <lb/>Mr. Asquith and Mr. Lloyd George.  These may interest the 'Lord <lb/>Justices' and the misgovernment of <lb/>Ireland council. Why not put a <lb/>firm man in charge of the country. <lb/>A man who will honestly administer <lb/>the British Law without fear or favour.  Give General Maxwell a free hand <lb/>and let him at once crush out sedition <lb/>and rebellion whether in North or South.  If the British Law is good for England, <lb/>Wales &amp; Scotland and <hi rend="underline">Ulster</hi> it would <lb/>also be good for the South &amp; West. Law <lb/>abiding citizens do not whine at Martial <lb/>Law being in force. it is only the rebel gang <lb/>who whine. The country has been ruined <lb/>by the Agitators and the Priests and the people <lb/>bled white by both. I will be glad to have <lb/>your views on these letters. I am dear Sir <seg type="closer"> yours truly  Robert Carson </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0967_img_2797_2"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> If it comes a question of fighting <lb/>between the <hi rend="underline">rebels</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">Loyalists</hi><hi rend="underline">of</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">Ulster</hi> the rebels would be wiped out <lb/>in quick time.  At the outbreak of the War I offered my <lb/>services to the crown, and also offered <lb/>to bring a new weapon of death with me <lb/>(an Ulster invention) I gave the War office <lb/>a few particulars of this invention, it is <lb/>an Electrical invention, electricity under <lb/>control, with from one to four miles <seg type="del">rage</seg><lb/>range according to the Voltage, the higher <lb/>the voltage the greater the range. One of these <lb/>machines mounted on an armoured car could <lb/>mow down an army in a minute, a smaller <lb/>size can be carried by a man on his back and <lb/>when his battery is <hi rend="superscript">fully</hi> charged he could stop <lb/>a rush of 500 men without having to expose <lb/>himself. The War office considered <lb/>this machine too drastic a way of killing <lb/>the Germans, a proof that Mr Asquith <lb/>does not want England to win the war if he <lb/>can help it. instance the loose blockade &amp; <lb/>information is being passed from our War office <lb/>to the Germans constantly. Asquith has been <lb/>playing the German game since he came into <lb/>office. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0967_img_2797_3"/>
                Sir David Harrel  Royal Societies Club  <seg type="del">Dublin Castle</seg>  <seg type="del">Shankill</seg> St James's Street  <seg type="del">Co Dublin</seg><seg type="del">Dublin</seg> London    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>