<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2249">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to George Francis Stewart, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to George Francis Stewart (1851-1928). Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland. 
Stewart was a land agent and unionist. He became vice-president of the Land Owners&#39; Association and became heavily involved in southern unionist campaigns against partition and Home Rule. His willingness, with other southern unionists, to strike a deal with John Redmond (1856-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, regarding partition resulted in a dispute within the Irish Unionist Alliance.
This letter concerns Unionist politics and the leadership of Edward Carson (1854-1935). In the letter Montgomery seems satisfied with the decision that have been made and rejects the notion that they have abandoned anyone. He refers to Edward Carson as the only leader who has not been &#39;Asquixiated&#39; - or fallen under the influence of British Prime Minister Herbert Asquith (1852-1928). He acknowledges that Carson is not an Ulster man but believes that he come to the &#39;best possible arrangement under the circumstances&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/42</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2249</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Francis Stewart</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2249_img_1692_1"  type="Letter"  url="092d9b4945916af3f8ea0ad1fe1b2237.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2249_img_1692_1"/>
            Copy  18th June, 1916.   My dear Stewart   Many thanks for your letter.   I will take your advice as regards next Wednesday's <lb/> meeting. At the same time I must say that I still regard <lb/> what has been done as strategic, and do not admit that it <lb/> amounts to an abandoning of anybody. We have not abandoned <lb/> our friends any more than France and England have abandoned <lb/> Belgium because we did not allow our armies to be annihilated <lb/> on Belgian soil. Carson seems to be the only leader of <lb/> imminent ability who has not been <sic>"Asquixiated."</sic> He is <lb/> not an Ulster man, but a representative of T.C.D. I am <lb/> sure he believes that he has done and advised to be the best <lb/> possible arrangement under the circumstances for you and <lb/> for the United Kingdom. If you take the line that he has <lb/> abandoned you, where do you look for a leader that you can <lb/> trust, and without a leader what can you do.   I suppose there is not much use in arguing at the <lb/> present moment; but I must make my position clear.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>