<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0699">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Seamus Fitzgerald to his mother Alice Fitzgerald, 26 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Seamus Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Seamus Fitzgerald (1896-1972) to his mother, Alice. Seamus writes that his new privileges allow him to write more often. Prisoners are allowed to walk and talk in pairs for nearly an hour &#39;a blessing after such isolation&#39;. He requests a pencil and a stamped addressed envelope (to write home), as well as &#39;about 1/2 lb butter every week, a large cake, home made preferable, twice a week, a piece of cooked bacon or pork, some hard sweets like bullseyes etc., and such like&#39;. He cautions no tins are allowed and requests the food as soon as possible. He would also like some volumes of Cassell&#39;s Educator to be sent on so he can use the time profitably, as well as his prayerbook and rosary beads. He closes the letter with a warning not to put letters in parcels and sends love to all at home.Séamus Fitzgerald was an Irish business man and politician. Apprenticing at a dock yard, Fitzgerald joined the Irish Volunteers and Sinn Féin after Easter week and was subsequently arrested and interned in Frongoch camp. He would enter politics upon his release.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork City and County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>PR/6/8, PR/6/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/699</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1323">Seamus Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-05-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1691">Wakefield Prison, West Yorkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1349">Alice Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0055">3 East Hill, Queenstown, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0699_img_2190_1"  type="Letter"  url="fe969908f545c7dcd0ab87908af390d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0699_img_2190_2"  type="Letter"  url="04e91bd3d1016ab9f3464fa06781d094.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0699_img_2190_3"  type="Envelope"  url="b052b3b0f5f77a91f03265a310a16b79.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0699_img_2190_4"  type="Envelope"  url="03e6dcd888d5ee7366ad5f295bb08e8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0699_img_2190_1"/>
              Address Reply   C1036 James Fitzgerald   Irish prisoner  (Wakefield)  C/O Chief Postal Censors   London    P.S. Don't forget the number C1036 in the address: Jim    Frid. 26th May 1916   Dear Mother,   <lb/>Certain privileges just granted to us <lb/>explains this, my second letter this week. We were <lb/>allowed talk and walk in pairs at exercise today for <lb/>nearly an hour; a blessing after such isolation. <lb/>We are allowed write home as after as we wish, provided <lb/>we have stamped addressed envelopes, so I just want you to <lb/>send me some note-papers, envelopes &amp; about 12 stamps  &amp; a puce pencil. <lb/>I'm sure you will know what to send me, for instance <lb/>about 1/2 lb butter every week; a large cake, home-made <lb/>preferably, twice a week; a piece of cooked bacon or  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0699_img_2190_2"/>
              <lb/>pork; some hard sweets like bullseyes; and such <lb/> like; but tinned stuff of any sort are not allowed. <lb/>If you send these as soon as possible, Mother, <lb/>it would please me greatly, for as you can <lb/>imagine, we don't get too much here.  I would also like you to send one or two <lb/>volumes of Cassell's Educator, so that I can <lb/>make some use of my time here, also my prayer <lb/>book and rosary beads. I hope you sent the <lb/>Bible, for I have got nothing yet from home. <lb/>As for the clothes and boots, I have already <lb/>got a new suit and pair of boots from the <lb/>authorities, who served them out to all those in <lb/>need of them, but if you have sent them, it <lb/>doesn't matter as these ones are not as good <lb/>a fit, as my own, of course.  If the censor doesn't say otherwise here, <lb/>you need not send the parcels thro' London; only <lb/>the letters need be sent thro' London, <lb/>and don't out letters in the parcels. Tell <lb/>Bob &amp; Lil to write, and Patrick, as it is a joy <lb/>to get a letter. <seg type="unclear">Mind</seg> you address them properly.  Again, hoping you won't forget <seg type="del">the</seg> to send <lb/>the parcels immediately, I will say goodbye,<lb/><lb/>with love to all at home, Lil, <seg type="unclear">me,</seg>Bob &amp; rest, <lb/>hoping and trusting God will soon bring home, <lb/>safe, to you, your  <seg type="closer"> Affectionate son  Jim xxx <lb/>xxx </seg> P.S. Hope Tom &amp; Michael &amp; Eddie <lb/>Pray for me. Jim.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0699_img_2190_3"/>
                M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> J. Fitzgerald  3 East Hill  Queenstown  <seg type="del">E</seg>Ireland    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0699_img_2190_4"/>
               OPENED BY CENSOR <lb/>GRESHAM HOTEL DUBLIN <lb/> imprinted on the envelope <lb/>Saint <seg type="unclear">Aust. Guide</seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>