<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6659">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Cyrillus Walsh to John N. Milholland, 13 June 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter Joseph Cyrillus Walsh informs John N. Milholland about the growing support for Irish independence within the USA. He also describes his efforts to generate more support by distributing literature, circulating petitions and writing letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Folder: Box 2. f.2 Joseph C. Walsh Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6659</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date>1921-06-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0394">Chicago, Illinois, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John N. Milholland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0545">Layfaette Hotel, Washington, D. C., USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6659_img_None_1"  url="phpm98YNS.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6659_img_None_2"  url="phpmTf2vE.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6659_img_None_3"  url="php3aYteq.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6659_img_0_1"/>
              Chicago, Ill.,   June 13, 1921.    Mr. John N. Milholland <lb/> Lafayette Hotel, <lb/> Washington, D.C.    Dear Mr. Milholland:   Many Thanks for your kind note. I had the pleasure of meeting<lb/> you  when we were all here for the Republican Convention last year,<lb/>but  it  is not surprising if you miss remembering an odd one of the<lb/> multitude  whom you saw.  It is quite true that we have gone pretty far since last<lb/>November. Let me see if I can give you an idea.  We began work on the new organization about December 1, and then<lb/> there  were some delays occasioned by a state of uncertainty about<lb/> President  De Valera, who had made some engagements in states where<lb/> they  naturally waited for him, so that we did not get properly going<lb/> until  January. Nevertheless, when the National Convention came along<lb/> on  April 18, there were people here from thirty-three states and they<lb/> had  paid in to the national treasury for their credentials $78,792,<lb/> which , at 25 cents each, (headquarters' share of the membership fee),<lb/> represented  320,000 members. Delayed returns brought the membership<lb/> total  reported to May 1 to nearly 400,000. And there is a determined<lb/> effort  being made, weather permitting, to reach a million by July 4<lb/> on  our second wind. We shall certainly much exceed that number when<lb/> cool  weather comes again.  Meantime, and probably to the prejudice, temporarily, of the<lb/> membership  campaign, our people are busy getting petitions signed<lb/> in  the congressional districts. The flow to Washington has commenced,<lb/> and  presently it will be a flood.  I need not tell you that Massachusetts and New York are going<lb/> strong , but what will you say to 20,000 members in Minnesota, 15, 000<lb/> in  North Dakota, 15,000 in Iowa, 5000 in Tennessee, 20,000 in Ohio,<lb/>20,000 in the Pittsburgh district  of  Pennsylvania, 60,000 in Chicago?  Miss Mary Mac Swiney has just spent eight days in Illinois,<lb/> addressing  splendid meetings in Rockford, Joliet, Princeton, La Salle,<lb/>Galesburg, Quincy, Peoria, Decatur and Danville. Overflows in several<lb/> places . In a fortnight she will be in Ohio, which has already given<lb/> great  meetings to Lord Mayor O' Callaghan, and will speak at Sandueky,<lb/>Lima, Canton, Marion, Dayton, Youngstown and other places. Ohio has<lb/> heard  more about Ireland than about any wholly American subject  what   - <lb/> soever  these past few months.  We shall have an intensive campaign along the Atlantic beaches<lb/> in  July and August.  Here are two items that will give you an idea of the strength<lb/> of  the  currents :     ×    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6659_img_0_2"/>
             1. I had Senator Norris' resolution printed as a poster and<lb/>sent out samples. We got orders for 20,000 from this office<lb/>from little places all over the country, and in the big places<lb/>they printed their own, e. g. Cleveland 2500, Philadelphia<lb/>will be placarded within this week.  2. About June 1 I sent out a letter calling attention to Senator<lb/>La Follette's speech. Already I have had to order 50,000<lb/>from the senator; Ohio ordered another 25,000, and we are<lb/>sending to Washington every day from 2000 to 5000 names. We<lb/>shall reach 100,000 by July 1. These names come to us with a<lb/>dollar for every hundred, which shows the keenness of our<lb/>people, and go out to people not in the Irish circle. A man<lb/>will spend a dollar to reform 100 of his non-Irish neighbors,<lb/>and we are nearing the 100,000 in three weeks'.  As I dare say you know, both houses in Wisconsin and Illinois have<lb/>passed resolutions committing the people of their states to recognition,<lb/>and there have been single chamber pronouncements in Pennsylvania,<lb/>Minnesota, Montana, New Jersey- with more to come. Many cities are also<lb/>passing these resolutions. We got word of a couple of new ones almost<lb/>every day.  You may believe, and you can confidently affirm, that the work of<lb/>making friends for Ireland is going on in nearly every congressional<lb/>district of importance. We have a newspaper service, backed up by<lb/>local publicity committees, reaching 800 newspapers in the twenty-one<lb/>states from which come the members of the Foreign Affairs and Foreign<lb/>Relations Committees.  Led by Massachusetts, where our members will be at least 250,000<lb/>by the end of the year, our friends have decided to give the legal<lb/>notice of retirement from their primary affiliations in national and<lb/>state policies, holding themselves free to register later on as they<lb/>think best.  You can see what this outpouring of activity means.  We are<lb/>creating a state of mind,  and this state of mind will be translated<lb/>into action, quickly, spontaneously, at a given time. It is not a<lb/>thing that can be mnchined or controlled, but will follow to instinct.<lb/>A friend was telling me the other day of how, when Mr. Harding was<lb/>teased into making a direct statement against the League at an Iowa<lb/>meeting, next morning everyone in our town was for Harding. Some-<lb/>thing like that is what will happen next November.  Do not let anyone mislead you with the story that this work of ours<lb/>is aimed at the destruction of Judge Colyalan's organization, and that<lb/>we are only a faction, his friends another. Away from the seaboard, even<lb/>his name is not known, and our hundreds of thousands, a surprisingly large<lb/>percentage of whom are not Irish at all, have never heard his name. When<lb/>the Congressmen ask questions of their friends back home, they will learn<lb/>the truth. The people are for justice to Ireland and care nothing for<lb/>personalities. If they are wise, they will start their inquiries, for 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6659_img_0_3"/>
             this movement is already too strong in forty states to be controlled<lb/>or manipulated by any old line political experts. And, believe me,<lb/>it will be many times stronger if the military pressure against the<lb/>exercise in Ireland of freedom as Americans understand it becomes in-<lb/>creasingly more oppreseive and therefore more odious.  We are proceeding through the holding of meetings, the distribution<lb/>of literature, the circulation of petitionss, the writing of letters and<lb/>the enlistment of members. Our friends are clamouring for a lead, and not<lb/>always waiting for it, in the matter of conscious preferment for American<lb/>as against English articles of commerce. The whole movement is amply<lb/>sustained by the individually trifling offerings of those who engage in<lb/>it. In short, I venture to say that outside the time America was actually<lb/>at war, there has been no other effort of the kind that has had anything<lb/>like the success of this one.  I am going East tomorrow on a survey of one branch of the work. Our<lb/>mutual friend will know where to reach me in case you happen to be in<lb/>New York and care to waste a half hour.  Hoping for the success of the personal efforts I know you are al-<lb/>ways making, and with all best wishes,  Faithfully yours,     JCW 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>