<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1004">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John MacDonagh to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John MacDonagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John MacDonagh (1880-1961) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding an upcoming performance that she is putting on, and whether he could come and watch a rehearsal, due to his experience in theatre. John MacDonagh was an Irish film director, playwright, and a participant in the Rising of 1916. His brother was Thomas MacDonagh (1878-1916), one of the seven main leaders of the Rising, who was executed 3 May 1916. John MacDonagh was sentenced to life imprisonment, but was released August 1916. After the Rising, he turned to political film and media, even filming the Issuing of Republican Loan bonds by Michael Collins (1890-1922).Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47, MS 33,604/15-17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1004</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0163">John MacDonagh</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1467">Hardwicke Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1980">34 Westmoreland Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1004_img_2850_1"  type="Letter"  url="719d518a7571a1df1d8b7def75227d4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1004_img_2850_2"  type="Envelope"  url="bc67cae4f4ba90f515068daab5151946.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1004_img_2850_1"/>
                Hardwicke St 5216    1916   D— Mrs. Skeffington   Tomorrow is impossible for me. <lb/>I'm out with the Volunteers in the county. Then have <lb/>an appointment with my brother for the county <lb/>for the rest of the time. I find we must play <lb/>a performance before Lent, probably a Strindberg <lb/>play. ('Easter') This as you can imagine is a <lb/>tremendous lot of work for me. And is of course <lb/>my head &amp; butt. However as I told you I'd like <lb/>to help by seeing some of your rehearsals &amp; <lb/>giving as you call it the benefit of my experience <lb/>Reddin is oft in want of some speech. <lb/>I know no one else I think who would suit. <lb/>Wouldn't Mr Harford do all that part <lb/>being in the business? I'll call in some <lb/>day next week &amp; see how things stand  <seg type="closer"> Yrs  John MacDonagh </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1004_img_2850_2"/>
                Mrs. Skeffington  34 Westmoreland St.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>