<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5284">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to Victoria Mary Tyrrell, 6 November 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

Summary of the present letter:

Miss Ball sent Willie an Irish Life magazine with a cartoon of two cats marked. One cat was an R.A.M.C. doctor and the other a soldier asking for sick leave. A young American officer is staying with William&#39;s regiment. The American is amazed they are sleeping in beds and eating five-course meals. Leave has been extended.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5284</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-11-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5284_img_None_1"  url="78af425dd94e632004d2af33ed35703f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5284_img_None_2"  url="15bf91b6d96fe8c7d623e0b0686f1a53.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5284_img_None_3"  url="baef9cc593b67bc3dacd1f75b5adf984.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5284_img_None_4"  url="55ac6eac71c00ff9a51fd1798fb2120a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5284_img_0_1"/>
              Tuesday 6/11/17    My dear Minnie   Thank you very much<lb/>indeed for your letter of 1st which<lb/>came yesterday - I really must<lb/>start writing to you in French but<lb/>I have not enough to say today<lb/>to make it worth while!!  I am terribly shocked at Miss<lb/>Bells conduct. She sent me an<lb/>Irish Life and in it marked in<lb/>red pencil a horrid cartoon<lb/>about two cats. One cat doing<lb/>R A M C doctor and the other cat<lb/>asking for sick leave.  I will have to get some<lb/>horrid post card to send her. That<lb/>will settle her perhaps.  I don't know if I mentioned<lb/>yesterday that the new writing pad<lb/>arrived at a most <sic>oppertune</sic> moment 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5284_img_0_2"/>
             We have a young American officer<lb/>attached to us here just to see<lb/>what things are like. He seems<lb/>a very nice fellow. He lives with<lb/>me in my dug out. He came up<lb/>with ideas which were all wrong<lb/>He had an idea that he was<lb/>going to somewhere where there was<lb/>a war on. So he was rather<lb/>astonished when he saw me<lb/>putting on pyjamas and getting in<lb/>to my bed comfortably at ten<lb/>o clock last night. Of course this<lb/>is not in the front line which<lb/>makes a considerale difference.<lb/>Also he expected I think to live<lb/>on bully <seg type="del">I</seg> beef and dog<lb/>biscuits so a 5 course dinner<lb/>rather astonished him.  There is no doubt I struck luck<lb/>when I was put on signalling officer<lb/>for this tour. Of course I will go 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5284_img_0_3"/>
             back to my company as soon as<lb/>ever we go out.  Young the proper<lb/>sigs officer is just having a<lb/>rest.  No one knows why as<lb/>he has just come back off<lb/>leave but I am jolly glad he<lb/>is getting a rest.  Leave by the way now is <lb/>14 days instead of 10 but as<lb/>we always got 12 days for<lb/>Ireland it wont make so<lb/>very much difference.  I see by yesterdays papers that<lb/>there has been some<lb/>excitement at Newbridge over<lb/>a meeting The Times had a long<lb/>story about it.  I wrote Bobby a decent letter last<lb/>night as I see he says he<lb/>has not heard from me for<lb/>a long time.  I write to him at       
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5284_img_0_4"/>
             least twice a week  Weather still warm but dark<lb/>The evenings are getting awfully<lb/>short.  It is pitch dark about<lb/>five oclock.  No news, I will write again<lb/>tomorrow.  Very best love to all from<lb/> Your most affec brother<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>