<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2615">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to James Ryan from Margaret</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Margaret [?]</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to James Ryan from Margaret [?]. She&#39;s not supposed to be writing to him. She discusses the lack of young men in Ireland at the time, the cruel treatment of the Dublin women who were imprisoned and the attempts to raise money for Irish relief - including a picnic the following Saturday.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>P88/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2615</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0733">Margaret [?]</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1930">Train to Carlow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2615_img_204_1"  type="Letter"  url="fc9f14e931d83a8eb5684b69e2a4a336.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2615_img_204_2"  type="Letter"  url="f05e021a1d467dd5728fa97b0037b05f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2615_img_204_3"  type="Letter"  url="543b3622de7638f1f05ff4667cf1faa7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2615_img_204_4"  type="Letter"  url="1f78ac05c5db10cb1798fc452c4f6a76.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2615_img_204_5"  type="Letter"  url="f74e7dd11bb4a4fa20a1e11c6a3fbee1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2615_img_204_1"/>
             in Bagenalstown <lb/>is always asking <lb/>me about him. <lb/>Sr. Aloysuis. <lb/>Tell him that <lb/>won't you. Nell <lb/>has written a great <lb/> ballad on Mountjoy <lb/>jail.Oscar Wilde's <lb/> is nothing to it. The <lb/>poor Commandant — <lb/> we are often reminded <lb/>of him. Best love to <lb/>yourself Jim — &amp; if you <lb/>can spare a few <lb/>minutes I would love to get a <lb/>line from you.  Yours! Margaret    Train to Carlow   My dear Jim   You know I'm running a <lb/>great risk by writing to you. K. <lb/>was a long time before she could <lb/>make up her mind to ask permission <lb/>and it was given so reluctantly <lb/>that I thought it better to take <lb/>the law into my own hands once <lb/>I got off '52' premises. Of course <lb/>you mustn't be telling on me when <lb/>next you write to 'herself' — after
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2615_img_204_2"/>
             2  all, she who brought ye together <lb/>deserves some little consideration <lb/>I'd say I'm about the only one <lb/>existing at present who isn't a <lb/>sort of grass widow. Its well in <lb/>a way because I can devote <lb/>my time to keeping others <lb/>faithful — though to tell the <lb/>truth that is not very hard. <lb/>The very least of us wouldn't <lb/>be bothered with those that <lb/>are left. An ordinary <lb/>'beardless boy' has no attractions <lb/>for us now. Bergin is the
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2615_img_204_3"/>
            <seg type="unclear">dearest</seg> approach —his heart is with me <lb/>of course but 'the Lord knows who he'll <lb/>marry' (does this remind you of the curls wagging) <lb/>Now that he has the fractured skull or <lb/>whatever it developed into in the end. <lb/>Of course my one consolation in life is <lb/> that 'Art' has been spared to me. <lb/> Unfortunately though one does not feel <lb/>in humour for a 2 step — nor even <lb/>as he said to me of yore 'for the <lb/>melancholy waddle of the waltz.' K. <lb/>Brady is trying to do me out with <lb/>that triangular glance she has — but <lb/>thus far her wiles have proved <lb/>fruitless and of no avail. Does <lb/>that last part sound biblical — now <lb/>that you are so well up in the <lb/>bible. Which of Lot's daughters would <lb/>you rather have — or does Susanna <lb/>remind you more of the Sinn Fein <lb/>Prima Donna — This damn train is shaking horribly
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2615_img_204_4"/>
            We had a great letter from <seg type="unclear">Fionn</seg> at Wandsworth.<lb/>He told us he made a strong plea for <lb/>us to his colonel at Wandsworth — representing <lb/>to him that the British atrocities on the <lb/>Dublin girls were even on a more refined <lb/>plane of cruelty than the Belgian ones — <lb/>but he added — the heartless wretch only <lb/>laughed. Right enough Jim — our gatherings <lb/>are a problem. All women &amp; an <hi rend="underline">odd</hi> <lb/>priest. I feel that this picture has already <lb/>been vividly put before you, so I won't give <lb/>further details. We are absolutely run to <lb/>death trying to get funds for the relief. <lb/>Many and varied are our projects — <lb/>amongst others — a picnic — which we <lb/>are having on Sat week. — We will take any <lb/>money we get but I'm afraid we'll only<lb/> give a very meagre tea — I am to act as <lb/>a sort of vigilance committee. Picnic <hi rend="superscript">2</hi>/6 <lb/>and there is a graduated scale of extras. <lb/>For instance holding hands 2 <hi rend="superscript">d</hi> and so on <lb/>ad infinitum. We will be awfully busy
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2615_img_204_5"/>
            though as in '82' is in complete control — and <lb/>we may be able to procure some frivolous <lb/>females content to amuse themselves with <lb/>the men that are left. We all went <lb/>up to meet Kit coming out — a tremendous <lb/>reception — 2 or 3 hundred.They were <lb/>to have let her out at 8.30 but she <lb/>actually did not get till 11o'clock — <lb/>nearly everybody waited — &amp; I felt <lb/>like 'the queen going to the races' <lb/>going off in a taxi with her. I am <lb/>getting absolutely no work done at all — <lb/>Poor Osbie will be sad when he finds <lb/>another of his idols smashed. I had a <lb/>letter from F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Paul. He had been to see <lb/>you and thought yourself &amp; Michael <lb/>O'Kelly very picturesque. You should have <lb/>seen Shaun go away with the <seg type="unclear">Srg mjr</seg> &amp; <lb/>gloves &amp; the 'late buff mail' sticking out <lb/>of his pocket. They got a great send off.  <lb/>Love to Michael Kelly, Doer (if he remembers me) <lb/>C.B O' Higgins (who doesn't know me at all. A man
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>