<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5726">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, [November'] 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Marie begins this letter to her mother by explaining that she had written her previous letter in a hurry and describes it as the &#34;madest (sic) letter&#34; she had ever written.  She mentions that they had experienced a terrible storm which meant that she could not go out on her day off and their accommodation had flooded.  The Canadian soldier whose mother Marie had mentioned writing to in her previous is improving and she is happy about this.  She describes a number of her patients and mentions a Wexford sailor called Richard who may call to her family once he has returned to Ireland.  She also mentions a trip to Valletta in a rowing boat.  Overall, her mood seems upbeat.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Malta Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5726</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1540">Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_1"  type="Letter"  url="fda76b1a35d1d1edbc91252d3c91e9d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_2"  type="Letter"  url="538ea19b03ceb0188107807d3456c688.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_3"  type="Letter"  url="2839a411539e78203f65c392a3280c5d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_4"  type="Letter"  url="a8a6b2c1d0a56ea5dcbca6256660ff45.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_5"  type="Letter"  url="acfacdf642b134e943bcd8c70cffb141.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_6"  type="Letter"  url="1081023736e3ab07921f3497990381cf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_7"  type="Letter"  url="24ab98a749247bda2a9508126bef27b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_8"  type="Letter"  url="35377ad4ee94fd0e71ff2d580e0e3e6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_9"  type="Letter"  url="9c5fbd1b8e534ddb98059a9ad0c0ba75.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_10"  type="Letter"  url="b50d4b22a4f8fdf5ebc970504dd261c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5726_img_827_11"  type="Envelope"  url="d0b014fcc86dc6a0e3268e63afaf362a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_1"/>
             My own dearest Mother,   My last letter was the maddest <lb/> letter I have ever written. I <lb/> started it so often and now in the <lb/> hurry discover I have left out <lb/> 1 <sic>pages</sic> so you will have some <lb/> fun making it out. I have my <lb/> whole day to-day so am starting <lb/> off by taking a quiet morning <lb/> in bed, this afternoon we hope to <lb/> go to <sic>Citioicchica</sic> St Pauls Bay but <lb/> there has been such a terrible <lb/> storm during the night, we were <lb/> nearly flooded out of our room <lb/> the little Kitchen or Bathroom off <lb/> ours is ankle deep in water, the <lb/> thunder &amp; lightning was something <lb/>too awful for words — however things <lb/> look brighter now &amp; we are hoping <lb/> it will clear up—
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_2"/>
            Ever so many thanks for all your <lb/> letters dated Nov: 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. also for <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Terneys</seg> Court Bills but I got £3.10.0 <lb/> expenses which is not really bad &amp; <lb/> I am keeping it for the present till <lb/> I see how things are going— <lb/> as I have had to spend a good <lb/> deal of money one way &amp; another, we <lb/> spend a perfect fortune on food <lb/> but as we say it is better to eat <lb/> well &amp; keep well— I am glad to be <lb/> able to say the patient whose Mother <lb/>I wrote to in Canada &amp; who I <lb/> bought the Burgundy is improving <lb/> every day since we started giving <lb/> it to him &amp; hope in a day or <lb/> two if all goes well to be able <lb/> to write he is out of danger — <lb/> Really one does not mind what <lb/> trouble &amp; expense one goes <sic>too</sic> when
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_3"/>
            (2) <lb/>it is the saving of life. I <lb/> am not actually nursing him <lb/> now as I have been moved but <lb/> there is a charming Irish Sister <lb/> (Flynn) who nursed Morrogh at <lb/> Torquay looking after him &amp; certainly <lb/> she deserves the greatest praise &amp; <lb/> award if she gets him through <lb/> imagine he has had Hemorrhage <lb/> for over a month &amp; is absolutely <lb/> nothing but skin &amp; bones— but <lb/> such a plucky boy—     Well my favorite patient went <lb/> off yesterday with a lot of very <lb/> nice other boys, they went on <lb/> Hospital Ship "Egypt" so if by <lb/> any chance they are sent to <lb/> Ireland, will you get the Girls <lb/> to <sic>took</sic> up the following <lb/> &amp; give them as good a time as
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_4"/>
            possible <hi rend="underline">especially</hi> G. Boase <lb/> City of London Yeomanry, &amp; don't <lb/> be a bit surprized if a Sailor <lb/> Man called Richard Layne of <lb/> Wexford turns up as he said <lb/> he would go &amp; see you all &amp; <lb/> tell them how I was, so give <lb/> him a good welcome as they <lb/> have all had a very rough <lb/> time of it out here poor <lb/> men —   We had a very nice day yesterday <lb/> I stayed in bed till about <lb/> 9.30 &amp; went into Valetta about <lb/> 11.30 but as the ferry was not <lb/> running owing to the storm we <lb/> had to go over in a rowing <lb/> boat so got rather a tossing &amp; <lb/> found a great number of the <lb/> roads round Valetta swept away
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_5"/>
            3 <lb/> with the foods, we had lunch at <lb/> Blackeys (the only safe tea shop) <lb/> consisting of <sic>sauges</sic> &amp; eggs which <lb/> I need not tell you we all <lb/> enjoyed immensely it is such <lb/> a change &amp; tastes so good <lb/> in fact every time we are off <lb/> for a meal I think we over <lb/> eat ourselves, after that excellent <lb/> lunch we took the train on <lb/> to Citto Vichia &amp; saw all the Catacombs <lb/> of St Paul &amp; the magnificent <lb/> cathedral of St Pauls after that <lb/> we went on &amp; paid Nellie a <lb/> visit at Imtapha it is a beautiful <lb/> hospital &amp; they have such nice <lb/> quarters, we have of course only a <lb/> Tent for our meals &amp; in this <lb/> raining &amp; cold weather we are <lb/> nearly blown away &amp; flooded.
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_6"/>
            out. Is there any news of Gerald <lb/> G. lately. I hope all is well with <lb/> them all. I had a sweet letter <lb/> from M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> Garttan about a week <lb/> ago but have not had time <lb/> to answer it yet also U. Charlie <lb/> but hope to write to-night if <lb/> not too tired we are not quite <lb/> so busy to-day as we have 15 <lb/> beds empty but expect new <lb/> ones today— the patients were <lb/> greatly amused with me to-day <lb/> I had to carbonize <lb/> the bed which meant getting down <lb/> on my knees &amp; scrubbing them <lb/> which I thought I was doing <lb/> most gracefully when I heard <lb/> a titter all round &amp; they all said
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_7"/>
            4 <lb/> "it is easily seen you are not <lb/> used to this sort of work &amp; the <lb/> handling of a scrubbing brush— <lb/> I am feeling A.1. now &amp; really <lb/> like being here very well I love <lb/> the work &amp; seem to be getting <lb/> on all right, my Sister in Charge <lb/> is very nice &amp; seems fond of <lb/> me &amp; the other is very easy to <lb/> work with. I am called a ray of <lb/> Sunshine in our ward when I enter <lb/> to say good-morning, another <lb/> Always Smiling, another the <lb/> Dairy-maid as they say the <lb/> milk I give them is Milk &amp; that <lb/> I don't forget to turn of the W. <lb/> tap. Of course Surgical cases <lb/> would be more interesting but <lb/>there is something very fascinating
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_8"/>
            about medical work &amp; the delight <lb/> in seeing them get well &amp; bright<lb/>again quite repays you— <lb/>Thursday 25<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> I cannot tell you <lb/> when I really started this Letter <lb/> but as you will see have never <lb/> had time to finish it till now <lb/> I was hoping to get off duty at <lb/> 4.30 to-day &amp; come up to my <lb/> room have a quiet evening &amp; <lb/> write letters but Man proposes <lb/> God dispose instead I went on <lb/> duty all day as several of our <lb/> men are very poorly &amp; there <lb/> was only one Sister on so I <lb/> went back till 7 O'ck when <lb/> I came off duty &amp; came up <lb/> here straight to bed &amp; have <lb/> been writing letters to fond mamas
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_9"/>
            5 <lb/> for some of the men who are too <lb/> bad to write— I am just as <lb/> happy as I can be on duty &amp; <lb/> only wish I had two pr of <lb/> arms &amp; legs to be able to do <lb/> twice as much. I am feeling <lb/> splendid now &amp; hope soon <lb/> to be able to send you a photo <lb/> so that you will be able to <lb/> see for yourself— M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Kay <lb/> the Burgundy man I am <lb/> glad to say is going on top <lb/> job, he is so grateful, really <lb/> he is a wonderful man <lb/> all he has gone through— <lb/> I want to thank you a <lb/> thousand times for your <lb/> sweet letter also the papers
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_10"/>
            especially Irish Life with the <lb/> photo which I <sic>look</sic> great pride <lb/> in showing to all the men <lb/> they picked Violet out immediately <lb/> they think her so like me— <lb/> Well I shall end this now <lb/> as it is getting late &amp; I am <lb/> very tired. One of the men <lb/> is taking it tomorrow, he <lb/> is going to England— <lb/> Very best love to all at <lb/> home, will write to-morrow <lb/> with luck— <lb/>Take care of yourself— <lb/>  Your ever loving &amp; <lb/> grateful - Marie—   The parcel has not arrived <lb/> ye t— 
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_5726_img_827_11"/>
             M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> Martin<lb/> Greenbank<lb/> Monkstown<lb/> Co Dublin<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>