<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4399">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to Maria Duffin, 1 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers; D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4399</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1885">7 Westcliff, Eastbrough, Sussex, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4399_img_3752_1"  type="Letter"  url="c9374de6c7499b7a62f8f4892cfea8c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4399_img_3752_2"  type="Letter"  url="bdcc003f70b0b894e2b730e1f8dee494.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4399_img_3752_3"  type="Letter"  url="a11cfb79d521c788ba620c7d4e9d2b01.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4399_img_3752_1"/>
             7 West-Cliff.   1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>Nov. 1915   Dearest Mamma,   I was glad to get your letter &amp; all <lb/>the enclosures sent in this week from Terry, Emma, <lb/>etc. were so nice to get. I have forwarded them on <lb/>to Celia. I send Helen's back.   We have had awful weather this week, blowing &amp; raining <lb/>cats &amp; dogs, it is very difficult &amp; these conditions to <lb/>grope one's way about after dark especially where <lb/>we are on the sea front where <hi rend="underline">no</hi> lights are allowed. <lb/>Fortunately a Miss Need is here &amp; occupies Miss <lb/>Roberts. She is a great talker, &amp; full of information <lb/>about people especially 'country people &amp; royalties'. <lb/>She was terribly upset about the King's 'accident' &amp; <lb/>makes remarks like "Ah, I see Queen Alexandra <hi rend="underline">has</hi> <lb/>been to such &amp; such a place, I was sure <hi rend="underline">she</hi>would <lb/>be there!" but she is a decent soul &amp; quite nice <lb/>to me &amp; I welcome any visitors.   Who did I meet in the town one day but M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> <seg type="unclear">Linda</seg> <lb/>Johns, quite sane looking &amp; nicely dressed. Her <lb/>brother lives here &amp; she has taken a cottage somewhere <lb/>not far off. She had had all her front teeth removed <lb/>&amp; was having others in the day after!
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4399_img_3752_2"/>
             I met Mrs Bayford again yesterday &amp; she asked <lb/>me to go &amp; see her in a farm house at a village <lb/>just outside Eastbourne where she has taken refuge <lb/>now, her caravan being no longer comfortable. <lb/>Everyone is very kind &amp; I feel I have a few friends <lb/>now. I go to the Red <sic>X</sic> Depot most days. Today <lb/>there was a funny coincidence two ladies at my <lb/>table were talking &amp; one said, "a friend of mine <lb/>read me a letter from a man in the Notts &amp; <lb/>Derby Yeomanry saying they were so badly equipped <lb/>&amp; went into action with the officers in mufti <lb/>carrying little canes" etc. etc. I said I had a <lb/>cousin with them &amp; I thought it could not be true <lb/>as they had been in Egypt for some time &amp; were <lb/>fully trained &amp; ready. It then turned out the <lb/>letter she quoted was from Bertrand Swanwick <lb/>written to her friend - M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Harker. so we were <lb/>speaking of the same man!   Miss Bruce asks me to go up for a night or <lb/>two to meet Hilda this week. I am just waiting <lb/>to hear from Celia. I may go up Thursday or <lb/>Friday.   I am glad you are getting something to send out <lb/>to Emma, it makes me long to help. Do you get
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4399_img_3752_3"/>
            <lb/>the things by post or through some agency?   I have got about £20 now for the Y.M.C.A. Hut &amp; <lb/>don't know what D. may have got.   E's letters are very interesting &amp; very pathetic about the <lb/>men. I am sure she is splendid. I am glad she <lb/>has a little outing too. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Donnet says she <lb/>will tell M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Dickie Dixon to look her up. She is <lb/>going out to join her husband.   I had a note from poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Eastwood asking me to <lb/>stay a weekend with her, at Brighton but I can't <lb/>do so at present, she goes to Hampton Court for <lb/>the arrival. We had a Miss Patterson for lunch on <lb/>Sunday, her job is massaging the soldiers, at the <lb/>Convalescent Camp here, she belongs to the Pager Corps. <lb/>run by Miss French. They are badly paid &amp; hard <lb/>worked of course! they can qualify after 6 months' <lb/>training. Miss P. has worked at it for several <lb/>years &amp; says one can make £50 &amp; one's keep at <lb/>ordinary times; but the W.O. does not give so much <lb/>of course. I think I have no further news. I <lb/>am sure you are busy writing letters to everyone &amp; <lb/>other things. I hope you are not worrying. Love to all.   Ever your loving   Olive. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>