<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6673">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from WB Yeats to George Russell, 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.B. Yeats</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 7. Folder: Letters 43 TL/copies to Russell, George William (7.8)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6673</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date>1922</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1918">Cuttle-brook House Thame, Oxford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0970">George Russell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6673_img_None_1"  url="phpJDEq7l.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6673_img_0_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">1922.</hi>   at<lb/>Cuttle-brook House<lb/>Thame<lb/>Oxon.    My dear Russell   My sisters can publish anything from ten to say thirty<lb/>thousand words. My Four Years which they publish in October is about<lb/>twenty thousand and my Reveries was over thirty thousand. I think it<lb/>would be best if you could let them have a whole section, <sic>rether</sic> than<lb/>selections. Their subscribers will pay a higher price than the readers<lb/>of the ordinary editions. I like I think to feel that they have the<lb/>first edition of something. For instance though my Four Years will<lb/>be trebled in size and extended to ten or fifteen years instead of four<lb/>that little work will still be the first edition. Perhaps it would still<lb/>be the first edition of your selection but I am not quite clear on the<lb/>point. Perhaps you might let them have what you have written up to date,<lb/>and call it part 1. You would find a stimulus in the doing of the rest<lb/>to have so much published &amp; talked of.  Now a matter of immediate interest to myself. Have you<lb/>republished those old pamphlets--The Hero in Man, &amp; some pamphlets<lb/>in which you speak of the Bible stories having taken away the sacredness<lb/>of the soil? Do you remember the dates of their publication? I have<lb/>your books but they are in Oxford &amp; I dont want to make an expedition<lb/>there till I know whether these pamphlets are in your book of essays.<lb/>If they are not I can get them in the Bodleian probably though not<lb/>certainly. I shall probably contrast them with Eglinton's Essays on<lb/>the Remnant , &amp; between the two get an exposition of Unity &amp; Culture, as<lb/>against Unity of Opinion which Nationalist Ireland preferred   <sic>Yrs</sic> ever<lb/>W.B. Yeats  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>