<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3930">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Stanley Unwin to Francis Sheehy Skeffington, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Stanley Unwin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916),  journalist, was a prominent feminist, activist and co-founder of the Irish Women&#39;s Franchise league in 1908. In 1912, he and his wife, Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), founded the suffragist newspaper The Irish Citizen. A staunch pacifist and nationalist, Sheehy Skeffington opposed Irish involvement in the Great War. During the Easter Rising, he attempted to organise a civilian defence force to prevent looting and saved the life of a British officer under fire. Arrested on the evening of Tuesday 25 April 1916, Sheehy Skeffington and two other civilians were shot by firing squad on the morning of Wednesday 26 April.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,604/13-36</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3930</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0756">Stanley Unwin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0059">Ruskin House,40 Museum Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1861">12 D'Olier Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1968</item>
               <item n="tag">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3930_img_3306_1"  type="Letter"  url="453011725549159800ee81f7c8340922.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3930_img_3306_1"/>
             Telegrams, "Deucalion, Westcent, London."   Telephone: Museum 1470  <seg type="head">George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd. <lb/>PUBLISHERS &amp; EXPORTERS</seg>  Ruskin House, <lb/>40, Museum Street, LONDON, W.C.   All communications to be <lb/>addressed to the Company.   November 22nd, 1915   The Editor of <lb/>"The Irish Citizen" <lb/>12 D'Olier Street, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   We are in receipt of your note of the 17th November asking <lb/>for a review copy of "Oblomov" by Ivan Goncharov, but regret we <lb/>are unable to comply with your request, as we have had so many <lb/>applications for free copies of this book that we have been compelled <lb/>to close our list. If, however, it would be of any service to you, <lb/>we shall be pleased to let you have a copy, for the particular purpose <lb/>for which you require it, on receipt of half the published price, plus <lb/>postage, viz 3/5.    Yours faithfully, <lb/>GEORGE ALLEN &amp; UNWIN, Limited   Stanley Walsh <lb/>Managing Director  <lb/>Managing Director.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>