<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0181">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major W. Kinsman to Robert Chalmers, 27 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W. Kinsman</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from W. Kinsman, on behalf of the major-general in charge of administration, to Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), under-secretary for Ireland. The letter refers a Mr John Loughrin (b. 1900) for whom an application to be discharged from the army has been filed. The letter states that a birth certificate must be forwarded to prove that Loughrin is under 17, and therefore may be discharged.Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9050</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/181</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1125">W. Kinsman</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0890">Dublin Castle</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0181_img_1318_1"  type="Letter"  url="e858c47ca7e800bd6fd660fe2d668daf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0181_img_1318_1"/>
                Headquarters, Irish Command,  Parkgate, DUBLIN.    27th May, 1916.   Sir,   With reference to the attached application <lb/>for the discharge of John Loughrin.  It is necessary for his father or legal <lb/>guardian to forward an application for his discharge, and <lb/>enclose a birth certificate, to the Officer Commanding, <lb/>Royal Field Artillery Depot, Athlone, who, if the lad is <lb/>found to be under 17 years of age, has power to discharge <lb/>him forthwith. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant,  W. Kinsman Major. <lb/>for <lb/>Major-General i/c Administration, <lb/>Irish Command.   The Under Secretary for Ireland,  DUBLIN CASTLE.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>