<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2054">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jasper Travers Wolfe to Sir Robert Chalmers, 15 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jasper Travers Wolfe</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Jasper Travers Wolfe (1872-1952), a solicitor from Cork. The letter  was addressed to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858–1938), under-secretary for Ireland. Chalmers  was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary following the Easter Rising in 1916.
In the letter Wolfe is applying for is applying for the vacant crown solicitor of Cork position. The position had been left vacant due to the promotion of Dr Henry Arthur Wynne (1867-1943) to chief crown solicitor for Ireland. Wolfe states that he has been a solicitor since 1893 and has practised in the West Riding of County Cork since. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/8264/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2054</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0660">Jasper Travers Wolfe</persName>
              <date>1916-05-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2096">Skibbereen, Co. Cork, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1952</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2054_img_1501_1"  type="Letter"  url="4113ce7221f3a4b2677d3db04a89b0a4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2054_img_1501_1"/>
             Offices—Skibbereen, <lb/>Co.Cork.   15th day of May 1916.   Sir,   I beg to apply for the Office of Crown Solicitor <lb/>for the City of Cork and West Riding vacated by appointment of <lb/>the Chief Crown Solicitor. I was admitted a Solicitor <lb/>in 1893, obtaining at my final examination the Incorporated <lb/>Law Society's Gold Medal (first place), and subsequently the <lb/>Findlater Scholarship. Since then I have practiced in <lb/>the West Riding of the the County of Cork, and enquiry will show that <lb/>I have a larger experience of criminal and  general  Court advocacy, than <lb/>any other Solicitor in the City of Cork or West Riding, save the <lb/>newly appointed Chief Crown Solicitor.   As to the manner in which I have performed my work <lb/>and my professional character, I respectfully refer to the Judges <lb/>before whom I have practised, and the Officials of the West and <lb/>East Ridings of the County of Cork.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your Obedient Servant,   Jasper Travers Wolfe.   The Under Secretary for Ireland. <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>