<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5396">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Douglas Campbell (later Major General Sir Douglas Campbell) to his sister Catherine Agnes Meta Campbell (later Wetherall), 28 October 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Douglas Campbell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Eileen Wetherall</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5396</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0026">Douglas Campbell</persName>
              <date>1917-10-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1417">R. E. Mess (The Royal Engineers&#39; mess), Brompton Barracks, Chatham, North Kent, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Catherine Agnes Meta Campbell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_1"  type="Letter"  url="d273f4e5e4dfefa6a65d731fcc0613d2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_2"  type="Letter"  url="327e4f27a5c8e751e6e02d783e1fcb3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_3"  type="Letter"  url="f1672d39ed86a69b07739a9b4008e96b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_4"  type="Letter"  url="a9f0a6f9aeffca61f9faf3fbf3d2ef91.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_5"  type="Letter"  url="8cb22a55d9d631eb1fd0e81f42895d3b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_6"  type="Letter"  url="6d086b3038e0c89285f571bdd1c3d2ee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_7"  type="Letter"  url="1d571a98b00997ce2a9a5c866b9e47ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5396_img_4680_8"  type="Letter"  url="115e92bd6b78fffb202d2beba260cd5b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_1"/>
             R.E. Mess.<lb/>Brompton Barracks,<lb/>Chatham.   28.10.17.transcription-editor    Dear old Twin,   How's the world treating you in Ireland?<lb/>Do write &amp; tell me all about everything. I don't know your<lb/>address so I'm sending this home to be forwarded on.<lb/>It's most frightfully cold here, even a new pair of fur lined gloves don't 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_2"/>
             <lb/>keep the cold out. What it's like in the trenches, Lord only knows.<lb/>Poor old Roy will be having an awful time. Imagine existing for days<lb/>in a semi frozen porridge of Flanders mud, &amp; then being expected to feel<lb/>really cheery, &amp; fit for a real good bit of Hun bombardment.  And the advances too, I see they have to go through water up to their necks,<lb/>— cheery job for this weather, isn't it? 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_3"/>
             You should have seen us this morning, I had to take a Company of about 70 <lb/>or 100 men to Church. There was a whole battalion of us, about eight Coys.. <lb/>And we marched off to Church, you can imagine me strutt<hi rend="superscript">ing</hi> along on my <lb/>own —- three paces ahead of the Company feeling an impossible blood. Of course <lb/>the band played us all the way there, &amp; when I'd got my men in, I wandered up
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_4"/>
             <lb/>to the Colonel, gave him a crashing salute &amp; said ''E Company all correct ,Sir''.<lb/>Then we went in, &amp; the R.E. violin (string) band played us through the service<lb/>starting with the ripping Intermezzo Ave Maria, out of <seg type="foreign">Cavaliera Rusticana,</seg><lb/>&amp; ending up with the Marseillaise. I got one or two real good bellows on in<lb/>the hymns. Then we marched back saluting the General on the way, &amp; also<lb/>the guard, &amp; formed up in a hollow square, I actually found my way all right,<lb/>&amp; about 7 or 8 medals were presented by the General followed by a real Irish 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_5"/>
             <lb/>'' Handshake ''. Then we broke off. That's what happens every Sunday<lb/>morning, except for the medals, only of course I'm not always on parade.<lb/>Often I go to the Hagues for the weekend, at least not frightfully often,<lb/>but just often <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> enough not to tire them out. Nice girls, both of them,<lb/>have you ever met them? Of course you knew May in Killybegs years<lb/>ago, but doubtless you've forgotten her.  I heard from Dad this morning, very fit &amp; awfully happy building huts<lb/>by starting on the roof &amp; putting in the foundations afterwards. 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_6"/>
             Dug ( First World War)  <lb/>Delightfully original, &amp; apparently successful.  Poor old Italy is getting it in the neck, they are clever devils those Germans,<lb/>I daresay you noticed about 10 days ago a mysterious retirement on the<lb/>Russian front, quickly followed by the deuce of a push against<lb/>poor old Cadoma. Obvious they've shifted practically every man<lb/>across, but think of the staff work; a push like that worked out &amp;<lb/>prepared in 10 days. It really is marvellous, but the poor Engineers, it gave<lb/>them absolutely no time to do their bit. 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_7"/>
             Here's a dirty piece of paper but you won't mind. As you've gathered I'm <lb/>merely writing this as I've nothing to do, as I thought you might as well <lb/>be bored too. Tear it up when you're tired.   Brother Hun's got the wind right up this time, the moon's full on Tuesday, <lb/>&amp; only one raid, in which he came off distinctly second best. <lb/>Swan &amp; Edgar's are pretty well done in in Piccadilly.
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5396_img_4680_8"/>
             It's quite a common thing to all motor cars &amp; buses &amp; I believe motor cycles<lb/>drifting about the place with semi-inflated gas bags on top. Petrol is<lb/>impossible to get, so they're using gas-engines. I mean people don't<lb/>even stare at them now they're so used to them. And it was only a<lb/>few weeks ago that one of the pages in Punch was devoted to the new<lb/>methods of car driving, &amp; gasbags were put as the principal ways, &amp;<lb/>certainly the most amusing. Have come to an end of paper, so you're released.  Dug. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>