<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0316">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Stanley Owen Buckmaster to John Redmond, 15 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Stanley Owen Buckmaster</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Copy of a letter from Stanley Owen Buckmaster, Viscount Buckmaster (1861-1934) to John Redmond (1856-1918), nationalist MP. In the letter, Buckmaster states that there is a body of Irish operatives in the town of Keighley of strongly Nationalist persuasion who have formed a body by themselves. He writes that at the outbreak of war, these men offered themselves up for military service as a body, and that he doubts there are many left who have not signed up. Buckmaster goes on to say that his statement should be verified but that he hopes it will offer Redmond encouragement on his difficult task of Irish recruitment. Buckamster was a politician and lord chancellor in 1916. John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers, Collection List No. 118, Ms. 15,175/1/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/316</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0937">Stanley Owen Buckmaster</persName>
              <date>1916-02-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0316_img_1540_1"  type="Letter"  url="bb5d246026fffe93ee4504d5c4907057.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0316_img_1540_1"/>
                Feb 15 1916   Lord Buckmaster to R   There have always been as you know well a very <sic>considerabl</sic><lb/>body of Irish operatives in the town of Keighley They are stro <lb/>gly Nationalist and have always formed a body by themselves... I <lb/>Believe that I <sic>oce</sic> enjoyed their confidence and <sic>thei</sic> support  What I thought right to tell you was this: that as soon as <lb/>the War was declared all of these men available for military service <lb/>enlisted in a body, and it may be doubted if there are even a <lb/>handful left who are fit to fight <sic>andhave</sic><sic>notoffered</sic> their <sic>sevue</sic><lb/>ice I want you to know this as the Irish position is as no one knows <lb/>better than yourself often but imperfectly understood You <sic>cd</sic><sic>probabl</sic><lb/>verify this statement of mine by enquiry in the district At any rate <lb/>I <sic>knowit</sic><sic>willgive</sic> you encouragemnet in the difficult work at which Y <lb/>you have laboured so hard <seg type="closer"> <sic>Yrs</sic> Very sincerely Buckmaster </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>