<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1769">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eoin Mangan to Mary Ellen O’Rahilly, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eoin Mangan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Eoin Mangan to Mary Ellen (‘Nell’) O’Rahilly. In this letter Eoin and Nell discuss the distribution of medals for &#39;real Volunteers&#39;. Mangan continues on praise the Volunteers and describes how the &#39;Brave blood of our heroes is redeeming Ireland&#39;.

Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated. 

Nell was also involved in the Nationalist movement as a member of Cumann na mBan and was imprisoned after the Rising for her role.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers; P106/121/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1769</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0448">Eoin Mangan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1904">Ballycastle, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Ellen O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1769_img_1225_1"  type="Letter"  url="7f4daea45b70996f50f7d63e16a88399.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1769_img_1225_2"  type="Letter"  url="01d05885c592e2ac2d5d53106b21c645.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1769_img_1225_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Clonard Monastery, Belfast.</seg> Bally Castle -  Saturday. <lb/> (Co. Antrim)   A Nell a Chara Dhílis,   Pardon me for my horrid delay.<lb/> Your letter was most welcome. God bless<lb/> you for it. You are wonderful in<lb/> your Charity and in your devotion to<lb/> Our Lady of P. Succour. I really did<lb/> not know what what to answer you in re-<lb/> -gard to distribution of medals - as <lb/> Anna said it is not an easy thing<lb/> to do and do it right. I would suggest<lb/> when you come in contact, directly or <lb/> indirectly, with <hi rend="underline">real Volunteers </hi>to give<lb/> a supply to one person for distribution<lb/> amongst his lot &amp; so on. Some priests  Mr Quinn - Church St.<lb/> Belfast - has wonder-<lb/> ful 3 colour badges - Our Lady of <lb/> Perp. Succour; Armagh<lb/> &amp; others!!! <lb/> Write to him<lb/> for specimen 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1769_img_1225_2"/>
            would give them all right, but most <lb/> would give them out at random.   I congratulate you, a Chara &amp; Anna<lb/> on S. Longford. Now, don't we see<lb/> how the holy, Brave blood of our heroes<lb/> is redeeming Ireland. Oh tis well<lb/> these days to be able to say that the<lb/> blood of our blood has been spilt out<lb/> for Éire to the last drop. These victorious<lb/> days give joy to our blessed ones<lb/> in Glory. But we are only at the<lb/> beginning. Let us keep on praying<lb/> &amp; living for a little longer. Freedom <lb/> is coming from God's Right Hand in<lb/> every truth. All honour to the dead!   I am here for 2 weeks till the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<lb/> Unfortunately I am <hi rend="underline">not</hi>going to mission<lb/> near Loch Derg. Tell Anna Fr. Con<lb/> is going to <hi rend="underline">Cathedral of Armagh tomorrow</hi>. God have mercy on Sean Mac Diarmada &amp; Com-<lb/> mandant Michael. Love to Madam, self, All    Do Cara  Eóín C. Mac
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>