<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6670">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J. B. Fitzpatrick to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 7 March 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J. B. Fitzpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, J. B. Fitzpatrick lets Joseph Cyrillus Walsh know about his regret that Walsh will no longer be able to edit the daily newspaper &#34;Ireland&#34;. He stresses that the Irish need such a paper in order to properly express their demand for representative government.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph C. Walsh Papers. Letters Earls - Foy</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6670</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0681">J. B. Fitzpatrick</persName>
              <date>1917-03-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0015">104 Kingston Street, Boston, Massachusetts, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6670_img_None_1"  url="phpIXsgUq.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6670_img_0_1"/>
             BROWN DURRELL CO  IMPORTERS AND MANUFACTURERS  HOSIERY, UNDERWEAR, HEANDKERCHIEFS &amp; FURNISHINGS   BOSTON<lb/>104 Kingston Street    NEW YORK<lb/>11 West 19th Street    CHICAGO<lb/>506 Textile bldg. Adams &amp; 5th Ave.   Officers and Directors  Thomas B. Fitzpatrick, Prest. and Treas<lb/>Hugh Mullen Vice Prest. and Asst Treas<lb/>William H. Stalker<lb/>Paul E. Fitzpatrick<lb/>James P Lynch<lb/>Frank S. Adams<lb/>Thomas M Fitzpatrick   Mar. 7, 1917   Cable Address DURRELL Liebers Code Used   Dear Mr Walsh:   I have been home sick for some days, and<lb/>therefore my correspondence, and other obligations, have<lb/>been neglected. I have recovered enough, however, to be<lb/>in a few hours today, and tomorrow I am going away to<lb/>take a rest for two or three weeks.  It is needless to say that I regret<lb/>extremely to learn that conditions are such that you<lb/>cannon continue the good work you have been doing in<lb/>conducting and editing Ireland. You will recall<lb/>that when the proposition was originally made, I was<lb/>not free to recommend it on account of what I believed<lb/>might be the financial difficulties, for I appreciated<lb/>the fact, and gave utterance to it at the time, that I<lb/>belived it was no trifling matter to establish a news-<lb/>paper. I felt sure that it required moneyed backing that<lb/>I could see no guarantee of at the time, but still, if<lb/>others thought it wise, I would do my humble share in<lb/>contributing at the outset.  I feel sure you have done your share to<lb/>make the paper a success, and if you had the necessary<lb/>support I am confident it would become a great power for<lb/>good in the land. We need such a paper, not only to give<lb/>proper representation to the best claims of Ireland for<lb/>representative government, but for the vital interests<lb/>of the Irish race in the United States. To do this,<lb/>however, will require adequate means in the way of money<lb/>and equipment, and I would be glad to see a disposition on<lb/>the part of our well-to-do men of the Irish race to furnish<lb/>aid for such an enterprise. It certainly would be too much<lb/>to ask of you, or of any single individual, to bear the<lb/>burden alone. I feel confident that you have done more<lb/>of this already than most men would be willing to do, and<lb/>while the readers of Ireland will regret any interruption<lb/>in its publication, no one can blame your good self for<lb/>taking the position outlined in your letter.  I remain,   Respectfully yours    J B Fitzpatrick                    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>