<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2565">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Fogarty to his mother, 8 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Fogarty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Patrick Fogarty (1895 – 1920) to his mother Margaret (b.1879) while Patrick was detained in Portland Prison. Patrick served during Easter Week and was subsequently sentenced to death. The sentence was commuted to three years penal servitude and he was released in 1917. Fogarty continued to serve until his death which was due to pneumonia contracted while on duty with the IRA outside Mountjoy Prison in April 1920. 

In this letter Patrick reassures his mother he is in the best of health and mentions his brothers John and Thomas (1898 – 1962) who also served during Easter Week. Patrick informs his mother that he left his watch at Arbour Hill Barracks and his overcoat in a house in Cabra and that he has filled in a form for the return of both. He does note that the coat may be more difficult to return as their uniforms were not sent home. Before signing off Patrick informs his mother of her rights to write back to him.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Brother Allen Collection, IE/AL/PF/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2565</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1183">Patrick Fogarty</persName>
              <date>1916-09-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0988">Portland Prison, Portland, Dorset, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs Fogarty</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2565_img_1993_1"  type="Letter"  url="126bc31253310a7ce84225b74455ff66.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2565_img_1993_2"  type="Letter"  url="390f0da8cd46e16ccdc61527257b61a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2565_img_1993_3"  type="Letter"  url="a0b79cf880d695f992c309693df2e299.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2565_img_1993_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September</hi> 1916.   My dear Mother   My time has come round again to<lb/>write home, and it gives me great pleasure, as I am<lb/>sure you are expecting one every morning.  I hope you are all in the best of health and going<lb/>on well. I am very glad to see by your letter that<lb/>John has taken over Mr Doyle workshop and hope he<lb/>is going on well and has plenty of work. I suppose<lb/>trade is a bit dull at present.  Dear Mother I hope you are not worrying about me<lb/>as I am in the best of health Thank God.  Tell Father I am very sorry to hear about Robin and<lb/>hope he is quite well now. I hope Tom will be home<lb/>soon and is in the best of health. It was very <sic>thoughtfull</sic><lb/>of him to send home his card, for you to get what money<lb/>he had saved. Remind him in your next letter to tell<lb/>Mockay I was asking for him.  I will be very glad to have the Photo's of you all as<lb/>you mentioned in your last letter. if you have not<lb/>them taken yet or are waiting for news from Tom<lb/>dont be in a hurry to <sic>answered</sic> my letter. Tell<lb/>Grandmother and Shames and all at home I was<lb/>asking for them. also if you ever see Mrs P Fogarty<lb/>or Frank <seg type="del">the</seg> tell them I was asking for them all  I left my watch at Arbour Hill Barracks. I am <seg type="del">get</seg><lb/>sure any day you could call up there you could get<lb/>it you could give it tp John. I left my overcoat in<lb/>the house on Cabra Road but I suppose it was<lb/>taken away by the military. I filled up a form 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2565_img_1993_2"/>
             about my coat and watch. so I hope you will be able<lb/>to get them. You will have no trouble as <sic>regeard</sic> the<lb/>watch, but if you think best don't bother about coat<lb/>our uniforms were not sent home. Your letter can be as large as a full sheet of fools cap<lb/>but if you are sending any small notes from<lb/>any friends, <sic>you</sic> letter and note's must be no longer<lb/>than a full sheet of fools cap. I hope John is able to<lb/>make <sic>soom</sic> use of the bike. no use letting it hang<lb/>there to rust. My next letter will be in about two<lb/>months.   I Remain dear Mother<lb/>Your affectionate son<lb/>Patrick Fogarty 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2565_img_1993_3"/>
             In replying to this letter, please write on the envelope:<lb/>NUMBER <hi rend="underline">9.169</hi> NAME <hi rend="underline">P.Fogarty</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">PORTLAND.</hi> PRISON  The following regulations as to communications, by Visit or Letter, between prisoners<lb/>and their families are <hi rend="underline">notified for the information</hi> of their correspondents.  The permission to write and receive Letters, is given to prisoners for the<lb/>purpose of enabling them to keep up a connection with their respectable friends and<lb/>not that they may be kept informed of public events.  All Letters are read by Prison Authorities. They must be legibly<lb/>written and not crossed. Any which are of an objectionable tendency, either to or<lb/>from prisoners, or containing slang, or improper expressions, will be suppressed.  Prisoner are permitted to receive and to write a letter at intervals, which<lb/>depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry and good conduct; but matters<lb/>of special importance to a prisoner may be communicated at any time by Letter (prepaid)<lb/>to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof, if expedient.  In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving and writing a Letter may<lb/>be forfeited for a time.  Money, Books, Postage Stamps, Food, Tobacco, Clothes &amp;c, should not be<lb/>sent to Prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received at the<lb/>Prison for that purpose.  Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce any<lb/>article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine and imprisonment, and any prisoner<lb/>concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.  Prisoners' friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorised persons, to send<lb/>Money &amp;c, to them privately, under pretence that they can apply it for the benefit<lb/>of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such application, received by the friends<lb/>of a prisoner should be, at once, forwarded by them to the Governor.  Prisoners are allowed to receive Visits from their friends, according to<lb/>rules, at intervals which depend on their stage.  When visits are due to prisoners notification will be sent to the friends<lb/>whom they desire to visit them.  <lb/>No. 243.<lb/>(8254) 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>