<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4267">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 2 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/204</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4267</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4267_img_3632_1"  type="Letter"  url="6fe0b32379cb12ef57b6eda3a0c431ee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4267_img_3632_2"  type="Letter"  url="7a3d078cd3960f0e3ce92182393e4783.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4267_img_3632_3"  type="Letter"  url="f4ff000e5145360d59f7b60b41b3204a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4267_img_3632_4"  type="Letter"  url="a43006b3be193bf1a058d7ced4dbd7a4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4267_img_3632_1"/>
             2 April   My p r    a very bright day outside, but a good deal <lb/> of worry in . R I believe is being trans- <lb/>ferred to London at an early date &amp; I believe <lb/> the London man is coming here. Not <lb/> very hopeful, &amp; he probably knows less of <lb/> the war than I do now. Really it is <lb/> a thin farce, but no doubt it is part of <lb/> the day's work. Yet when I see those <lb/> who are getting <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">of</seg></seg>  on  — men I know — it <lb/> makes one a lttle disheartened. However <lb/> Ulster — with a — — thrown in ! ! ! — is worth it <lb/> jolly well. Boylan Smith has just bet £10 <lb/> to £1 with me that Carson won't be premier in
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4267_img_3632_2"/>
            the year. I should like to get his subscription <lb/> to your fund !    When the new man comes  &amp; is settled in  I shall <lb/> really try to get away on leave, but it is <lb/> extremely unlikely I shall get it, tho' <lb/> there does not seem the same mad haste <lb/> <seg type="del">as</seg> about things that  there was lately. This is what I <lb/><seg type="del"> </seg>wrote about, &amp; it is a great relief <lb/> to find that sounder counsels prevail now <lb/> that we have a real good C in C.    I was a little disappointed in Carson's <lb/> speech. It appears to me that Bonar <lb/> Law, that man of supremely honest <lb/> Convictions has persuaded him to hold his
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4267_img_3632_3"/>
            hand , &amp; tho' I know he is absolutely loyal <lb/> I do not think his judgement is as sound as <lb/> Carson's.   The loathing for Squiffy out here is <lb/> intense; to men in action an inactive man <lb/> is like water to fire, it makes it hiss &amp; <lb/> often puts it out if brought into touch with  it .    I think I could find a good simile <lb/> to the Irish situation in the anatomy <lb/> of a man:— the entrails the <seg type="unclear">Sinn feiners</seg> <lb/> who suck in all they can &amp; squeeze;    the heart the sentimental Home rulers, <lb/> &amp; their joint conspiracy to leave the head <lb/> with its balance (bank &amp; judicial).   I'm afraid the Division that took <lb/> over from us were too much rushed, but <lb/> luckily the Huns did not take advantage of
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4267_img_3632_4"/>
            it, though <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">thoug</seg></seg> it is bad for young troops <lb/> sometimes.   The man who is coming is a youngster <lb/> a protégé of the <seg type="del">AC</seg>Army Commander. I <lb/> could get it altered if I wished by going <lb/> to R who is a time-server &amp; telling him <lb/> of my intimacy with Sir E, but I'm <lb/> hanged if I put forward a finger — much <lb/> less a dirty finger — in the matter.   No letter today &amp; no papers, but <lb/> I don't mind so much on Sundays.    Yes the b w does want his p r <lb/> extra bad   ever your b w    W.BSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>