<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0204">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Margaret May Loughren to Augustine Birrell, 26 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Margaret May Loughren</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Margaret May Loughren (b. 1889) to the Chief Crown Secretary Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Margaret is a native of Co. Roscommon but writing from America. Margaret writes to Birrell in light of her brother&#39;s enlistment in the British Army. John J. Loughren (b. 1900) enlisted a month before the letter was sent and was only sixteen. Margaret pleads for Birrell to send him home as she says the army &#39;does not need the boy as much as he needs his home.&#39;Birrell served as the chief secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish education system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares and, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Birrell offered his resignation on 1 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/6833/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/204</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0978">Margaret May Loughren</persName>
              <date>1916-03-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1537">Lenox Dale, Massachusetts, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0204_img_1350_1"  type="Letter"  url="24b79afe30740c3136270aa4a37496a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0204_img_1350_2"  type="Letter"  url="dc6b62040ff2d2a6fc30ee904aefd7f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0204_img_1350_3"  type="Letter"  url="a430bf4c82dc112e1045829f6df7e4a5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0204_img_1350_4"  type="Letter"  url="b09a893c31a184f646aeb3025b67ec5a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0204_img_1350_5"  type="Envelope"  url="04b8dcbd9cdc8756a502432060f4cb7e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0204_img_1350_6"  type="Envelope"  url="356d3c089940061fac752f6a9b3aac30.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0204_img_1350_1"/>
              U.S <lb/> This is a War Office matter <lb/> but perhaps the Police can say in <lb/>what Rgt. Longhren enlisted <lb/>A.P.M. <lb/> 15/4/16   I G. <lb/> Please ascertain. <lb/>17/4    Lennox Dale,  Mass. U.S.A.    March 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916     I do not know how to <lb/> address you so shall not <lb/> make a mistake. My brother <lb/> John J. Loughren of <lb/> Kilglass Strokestown Co <lb/> Roscommon enlisted about <lb/> a month ago and as he <lb/> was <hi rend="underline">only seventeen</hi> last <lb/> October 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I thought I <lb/> would let you know the <lb/> facts as surely his <lb/> country does not need  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0204_img_1350_2"/>
              that boy as much as he <lb/> needs his home, he did <lb/> not have a mother since <lb/> he was 9 and <seg type="unclear">poor chap</seg><lb/>and I'm sure he can <lb/> be of no use to the Gov- <lb/> ernment. I am sure you <lb/> do not know the cir- <lb/> cumstances and neither <lb/> does the Government as <lb/> it surely must be un- <lb/> lawful to take a boy <lb/> scarcely seventeen. I beg <lb/> of you to let him go  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0204_img_1350_3"/>
              home to his father <lb/> as he is alone but for <lb/> him. I know England <lb/> does not want her children <lb/> so bad as that. Give <lb/> him please your attention <lb/> as I am sure he needs <lb/> it <seg type="del">for</seg>though his spirit <lb/> was willing to do his best <lb/> for his Country by this <lb/> time his flesh must have <lb/> weakened. If you do this <lb/> as I know you will <lb/> for me I shall be glad  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0204_img_1350_4"/>
              to pay what it may cost <lb/> and remember I shall <lb/> always pray for those who <lb/> helped me. I feel responsible <lb/> for him as three years <lb/> he begged to come here <lb/> and I would not take <lb/> him. <seg type="closer"> I remain Sincerely <lb/>a British Subject  Margaret May <lb/> Loughren </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0204_img_1350_5"/>
                Chief Sec. Birrell of Ireland   Office of the Chief Sec.  Dublin   Ireland    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0204_img_1350_6"/>
               Back of envelope. No text.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>