<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4162">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Terence Duffin to his mother Maria Duffin, 26 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terence Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by Major Terence (Terry) Duffin (1886 - 1936), to his mother Maria Duffin (1854 - 1954). 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4162</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0305">Terence Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1936</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4162_img_3535_1"  type="Letter"  url="a080d03669d89f6ae1afc225c4b40261.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4162_img_3535_2"  type="Letter"  url="e61b0dfca321d9241963a3a87d03c51c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4162_img_3535_3"  type="Letter"  url="3c95fd1e47b9592f06d1afa9589a0455.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4162_img_3535_4"  type="Letter"  url="4007ee4daf18ab13da4dc7acab8323ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4162_img_3535_5"  type="Letter"  url="e6c3fcc2f7240bb3730c3fa5ff8de9fd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4162_img_3535_6"  type="Letter"  url="bf9188843598e7e578fdf13721c9bfb6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4162_img_3535_1"/>
             Dearest mamma   Many thanks for your letter <lb/>also the woolen flannels which were <lb/>most welcome - I really should <lb/>have written for them earlier but <lb/>the cold snap came on suddently <lb/>and I was taken by surprise - <lb/>it is bitterly cold out here. Most <lb/>of the snow is gone but we are <lb/>having sleet showers and very <lb/>heavy frosts at night.   We are just back from <lb/>our week up in the trenches, where <lb/>we came in for a fairly rotten <lb/>time for this part of the line - <lb/>mostly on account of the weather <lb/>but the <seg type="unclear">"Bolch"</seg>was inclined to <lb/>be rather uppish also and we <lb/>had a few casualties in consequ- <lb/>ence.   I don't get many <lb/>chances of getting about and
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4162_img_3535_2"/>
            seeing what is doing in the <lb/>trenches but had one most inter- <lb/>esting morning.   Our guns <lb/>had prepared a bombardment <lb/>and I went out to watch it, <lb/>with a gunner colonel from one <lb/>of their advanced observation <lb/>posts.   It is rather a curious <lb/>part of the line at this particular <lb/>spot - the Germans have a <seg type="unclear">lookout</seg> <lb/>and so have we, the conseuence <lb/>is that the trenches are practically <lb/>side by side.   Where I was, <lb/>we were only 200 yards away <lb/>from them and looking into <lb/>the back of their trenches so to <lb/>speak! —Till our guns started <lb/>we had to lie low but once they <lb/>got busy we stood up and <lb/>looked over the parapet in <lb/>comfort, as the Germans naturally <lb/>go to ground when the bombard— <lb/>ment starts.   It is a magnificent sight
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4162_img_3535_3"/>
            to see a big bombardment like <lb/>this at close quarters and I was <lb/>lucky to have the opportunity—   Our shells were passing <lb/>over our heads and <seg type="unclear">bursting</seg> <lb/>on the German lines within 200 <lb/>yards of us —all sizes of shells <lb/>and the greatest satisfaction to <lb/>see them plumping on th "Bosch" <lb/>trenches and tearing up yards <lb/>of ground.   It gives one an <lb/>idea what it must be like when <lb/>the reverse happens — What <lb/>surprises me is the extraordinary <lb/>small casualties which result.   We had about 300 <lb/>German shells fired on to quite <lb/>a small frontage if you like one <lb/>morning and yet had only 15 <lb/>killed &amp; six wounded as a <lb/>result.   Apparantly our gunners <lb/>are getting out a much bigger <lb/>supply of shells now though
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4162_img_3535_4"/>
            I daresay they can still do <lb/>with more!   I am amused at our <lb/>Brigades composition now — We <lb/><seg type="del">deleted text</seg><hi rend="superscript">have a</hi>nationalist and an <lb/>Ulster Division battalion side <lb/>by side in the trenches and appar— <lb/>antly quite fond of one another.   Redmond was up here <lb/>last week and inspected some <lb/>of our men —he is a fat com— <lb/>fortable old gentleman but his <lb/>son who was with him looked <lb/>a horrible bounder!   I don't know of any comforts <lb/>you can send me at present as <lb/>all one can make use of is <lb/><seg type="unclear">deliveries</seg> in the way of food and <lb/>they would hardly have safely <lb/>from Ireland to here and <lb/>now I hear all parcels are <lb/>confined to 7lb weight and <lb/>must be wrapped up in water
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4162_img_3535_5"/>
            proof cloth.   I shall try and <lb/>order some stuff out direct from <lb/>London which will have a better <lb/>chance of reaching safely.   I had a nice letter and a <lb/>pair of mits from Auntie B <lb/>which I will acknowledge when <lb/>I get a chance.   Nixon has left to take over <lb/>command of his regiment and <lb/>his successor a Capt Day from <lb/>the South of Ireland has just <lb/>arrived — He seems an excellent <lb/>fellow.   Glad to hear of Sam's decoration. <lb/>I am sure he has well earned it —   I wish I could come across <lb/>him or Charlie.   I must end up now as <lb/>it is nearing midnight.   Best love to all, I am in
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4162_img_3535_6"/>
            the best of health and as safe <lb/>as possible so you need not worry <lb/>about me. <lb/> Ever your own   Terry   26/11/15 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>