<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1163">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A.C.C. Fraser, 8 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A.C.C. Fraser </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from A.C.C. Fraser, received in the office of the chief secretary of Ireland. Fraser was a member of the 9th (Scottish) Divisions &#39;Divisional Train&#39; and part of the British Expeditionary Force, originally sent to France at the outbreak of the war in 1914. The Divisional Train was responsible for transporting supplies and soldiers. He requests the results of the examination for cadetship in the Royal Irish Constabulary, the police force for the island of Ireland (excluding Dublin city), as he intended to gain a commission as an officer and felt it would be advantageous to his application.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office, CSO RP/1916/594/1/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1163</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0119">A.C.C. Fraser </persName>
              <date>1916-01-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1163_img_384_1"  type="Letter"  url="55a29979f17b09a4fb83ef83931c3408.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1163_img_384_1"/>
                107 Company A.S.C.  9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Divisional Train  B.E.F.  <hi rend="underline">France</hi>   Sir,   I take the liberty to write and ask if you <lb/>would be so kind as to send me a copy of the <lb/>result of the last competitive examination for <lb/>cadetship in the Royal Irish Constabulary <lb/>at which I qualified with 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> place.  I am desirous of obtaining a commission <lb/>in the Regular army and think it would <lb/>be of advantage to me if I could produce a <lb/>certificate of having qualified for the <lb/>R.I.C. <seg type="closer"> Thanking you in anticipation <lb/>I remain <lb/>your obedient servant.  A.C.C. Fraser <lb/>Lieut A.S.C.   8/1/16  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>