<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3552">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eva Gore-Booth to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, circa May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eva Gore-Booth</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Eva Gore-Booth (1870-1926) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding the death of Hanna&#39;s Husband, Francis. Eva expresses a desire to visit Markievicz, if she is able to get permission, adding that she hopes she will be able to see Hanna during this visit.

Eva Gore-Booth was a poet, trade unionist, suffragist, and an active social campaigner, mostly on women&#39;s issues, and contributor to the Irish literary revival from the late 1890s. A sister of Constance Markievicz, she was active in the campaign for a reprieve of Markievicz&#39;s death sentence for her participation in the Easter Rising and for the improvement of her prison conditions.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3552</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0250">Eva Gore-Booth</persName>
              <date>1916-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0156">33 Fitzroy Square, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3552_img_2956_1"  type="Letter"  url="26013194244217ee52068ccec277d1a7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3552_img_2956_2"  type="Letter"  url="84a0e1adaa747cab12eb7091ebfad04b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3552_img_2956_1"/>
              May 1916    33, FITZROY SQUARE,<lb/>W.    Dear Mrs Sheehy Skeffington <lb/>I don't like to bother<lb/>you with a letter but I<lb/>feel I must write I am so<lb/>appalled and miserable about<lb/>Mr Sheehy Skeffington. Your<lb/>suffering is too dreadful. The<lb/>story is shocking and horrifying<lb/>everyone here is <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>great in <seg type="unclear"></seg>. I hope<lb/>to come over to see you<lb/>if I can get permission 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3552_img_2956_2"/>
             I shall hope to see you then if<lb/>you will let me. It is all<lb/>quite heart breaking   With all my sympathy<lb/>Yours v sincerely<lb/>Eva Gore Booth  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>