<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3540">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B.J. Goff and J.E. Lyons to the editor, 6 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>B.J. Goff and J.E. Lyons</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>B.J. Goff and J.E. Lyons write to the editor the 6th of March 1916 regarding the historical annual overtaxation of Ireland and the response by the Irish people. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; ms 33,604/17-17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3540</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1271">B.J. Goff and J.E. Lyons</persName>
              <date>1916-03-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3540_img_2943_1"  type="Letter"  url="c643119bee6089140459f71824e0a160.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3540_img_2943_1"/>
             Irish Financial Relations Committee, <lb/>Mansion House, <lb/>Dublin.   6th March 1916.   Dear Sir,   In the year 1896 the admitted annual overtaxation of <lb/>Ireland amounted to two and three quarter million pounds. In <lb/>the twenty years that have since elapsed the annual taxation <lb/>has steadily increased, and the annual amount now levied on <lb/>on Ireland is £9,400,000 in excess of the amount levied in 1896. <lb/>All this time the population and real wealth of the country <lb/>has decreased each year.   The people of the country were so much occupied with <lb/>other important problems, that no concerted action was taken <lb/>to call attention to the desperate financial position of Ireland. <lb/>Within the last few weeks however, a provisional committee came <lb/>together in Dublin with the object of endeavouring to do something <lb/>to stop the fatal drain on the resources of the country.   It was determined to start a campaign against the over- <lb/>taxation of Ireland by calling a mass meeting of the citizens of <lb/>Dublin at the Mansion House. The meeting was held on Tuesday, <lb/>29th February, and a crowded audience unanimously approved of <lb/>the action of the committee, and resolutions were passed demanding <lb/>the exemption of Ireland from the taxes imposed last year and <lb/>foreshadowed for the present year, and authorised the formation <lb/>of a committee to conduct an agitation to secure such exemption.    A condensed report of the meeting is enclosed, as well <lb/>as a leaflet prepared by the committee setting forth the financial <lb/>grievances of Ireland.   The committee hope that you will see your way to publish <lb/>the report. The subject is one of vital importance to the <lb/>interests of the country, and it is generally admitted that, if <lb/>the present rate of taxation continues, it will lead to the ruin <lb/>of Irish trade and industries, and make life almost unbearable <lb/>for the vast majority of the people. A determined agitation, <lb/>even if not entirely successful, will be bound to produce good <lb/>results. The committee trust that they will be favoured by <lb/>your co-operation in a matter which so vitally concerns the <lb/>interests of everybody.   The committee would be glad to be favoured with a copy <lb/>of the issue of your paper containing this report.   Yours faithfully,   B.J. Goff, M.A. <lb/>J.E. Lyons <lb/>Hon. Secs.    To/ The Editor. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>