<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4168">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 11  November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/54</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4168</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4168_img_3540_1"  type="Letter"  url="edecadf4d2a5b5693eee409adba87ab0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4168_img_3540_2"  type="Letter"  url="ca15a2aef0308bce7ca7af9d5ef9c068.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4168_img_3540_3"  type="Letter"  url="a40c1a29e26ed47e60224aea303a2d5a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4168_img_3540_4"  type="Letter"  url="ed4a3a21cabd7210b776bb1acc5f7f3c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4168_img_3540_1"/>
              D1633/1/1/54    Nov 4 . 15    My   I don't know whether you had better get<lb/>a daily letter  from  now on, however perhaps I'll chance<lb/>it <hi rend="underline">if</hi> there is nothing to prevent my writing.  Today I was tied to the office all day as Richardson<lb/>was doing an  intelligence  investigation but got out after dark for<lb/>a smart walk which I hope gave my <seg type="unclear">liver</seg> a little<lb/>chance, but I really miss the cooking of our cooks<lb/>—excluding one I think- or is it the housekeeping of<lb/>a funny little creature which I really want, I wonder.  This part of my anatomy misses the p r at<lb/>any rate still &amp; perhaps then <sic>an other</sic> odd bits<lb/>inside which do also strange to say. <seg type="del">I</seg>  I wish am could get how alone every day<lb/>to sit down &amp; write, but that is impossible so my letters  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4168_img_3540_2"/>
             are scrappy.  11th Nov.  Your news came last night about Rothamps.<lb/>Ted is wildly exciting. Brown Wolf is dreadfully alarmed<lb/>best he finds on his return a PR in a top hat with<lb/>big <seg type="unclear">bone</seg> spectacles, <hi rend="superscript">sitting in</hi><seg type="del">  </seg> a laboratory labelled on the door<lb/>Dr Lilian...? Silence No admission except to Germs<lb/>on duty; &amp; a monster official outside warning off all<lb/>wolves &amp; other persons with the caution Her Doctorship<lb/>is not to be disturbed. I wonder what you will decide<lb/>&amp; if you go whether you will live in town or take<lb/>a house then! The journey to &amp; thro' in the winter<lb/>does not inspire me especially the part from the King's +<lb/>to your flat in ? . It is lucky you haven't taken one<lb/>yet. I wonder what Lady Carson will say if you<lb/>tell her you have taken up the mantel of a<lb/>DSC LPRS <seg type="del">DO</seg> DOPR. You won't guess  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4168_img_3540_3"/>
             the meaning of these. I can hardly wait for this<lb/>morning's post to know what you are doing but <seg type="unclear">suppose</seg><lb/>in any case I shall not hear until another week at<lb/>any rate.  Not much news. <seg type="unclear">Gus'</seg> will probably be in<lb/>bad temper today having been sent for by Corps Com<hi rend="superscript">∨</hi>.<lb/>He does not like being a subordinate &amp; like many<lb/>hectoring people resents anything in the way of orders<lb/>received. I am afraid our Divisional exercises have been<lb/>stopped because he is <seg type="unclear">unwilling</seg> that the new Army<lb/>Com<hi rend="superscript">∨</hi> should come &amp; criticise. It reminds me of my<lb/>old difficulties &amp; I wonder if Russell protests as I<lb/>should.  I hope to get out this afternoon for a scamper, but<lb/>the weather reports which is rather good foretell a<lb/>rainy afternoon &amp; it is bright sun now. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4168_img_3540_4"/>
             11 Nov  I shall want to know full particulars of your visit<lb/>to Miss Blunt &amp; who else was there; &amp; what No<lb/>11 is doing of course.  If a b w can get rid of a bad cold in 2 days<lb/>without help, will then p r be convinced that<lb/>cinnamons &amp; <seg type="unclear">tableltoids</seg> &amp; suckies etc are<lb/>are not cures for us &amp; and let him off in future.  Probably after this he will have a cold for a month<lb/>at least!  It is curious that the Divs in the trenches do<lb/>not wish to exchange with us for a rest behind,<lb/>even tho' winter is on. I admit I should be glad<lb/>to do so in their place. as regards the contrary I cannot<lb/>make up my mind. The experience would be very valuable,<lb/>&amp; would <seg type="unclear">insure</seg> our not young elsewhere, but trench life is<lb/>in many respects not good for the men who pick up a mode<lb/>of life which is not altogether good training for more active<lb/>work later.   Best of love from your bw    Wilfrid BS  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>