<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5872">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Lemass, solicitor, to Sir John Maxwell, 20 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Lemass</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916) was a pacifist, feminist, and suffragist, a freelance journalist and an author. During the Easter Rising he was on the streets trying to muster a civilian force to prevent looting. On 25 April 1916, Skeffington, and two others, pro-British journalists, Thomas Dixon and Patrick McIntyre, were arrested by Captain J.C. Bowen-Colthurst (1880-1966), an Anglo-Irish officer of the Royal Irish Regiment. On 26 April all three were summarily executed by firing squad at Portobello Barracks.
Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full detail emerged. 
Sir John Maxwell (1859 - 1929) was primarily responsible for government policy in the immediate aftermath of the Rising. 

Henry Lemass is acting for Hanna Sheehy-Sheffington in the matter of the murder of her husband and subsequent raids on their home by the military.
The solicitor requests all letters, papers, and other documents taken from the person of Mr. Sheehy-Skeffington or from his residence, or an opportunity to view and copy them in good time before an inquiry, and that they be produced at the inquiry.
He asks for full details of the circumstances of the arrest and execution of Mr. Sheehy-Skeffington and details in relation to the raids on Mr. Sheehy-Skeffington&#39;s residence and those involved in them. Mrs. Sheehy-Skeffington&#39;s two sisters called to Portobello Barracks enquiring after Mr. Sheehy-Skeffington and were questioned and detained there for some time – reports and explanations of this incident are also requested.
This copy was enclosed in a letter, (MS6387/23/1) of 23 May 1916 from the writer to John Dillon MP. This letter also survives.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>Ms. 6837/23/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5872</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0457">Henry Lemass</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0359">Parliament Chambers, 31 Parliament Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir John C.Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1009">Parkgate, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5872_img_969_1"  type="Letter"  url="ccebc99ac4f49523754bb7b16dc592ca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5872_img_969_2"  type="Letter"  url="79bea1ee3d676229402a94f48109eb38.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5872_img_969_1"/>
              Copy     May 20th    Sir,   Referring to previous correspondence with you on the <lb/>subject of the Public Investigation which in accordance with <lb/>the promise of the Prime Minister in the House of Commons is <lb/>to be made into the circumstances under which Mr. F. Sheehy <lb/>Skeffington met with his death — I now beg to make formal <lb/>application that all letters papers and other documents <lb/> whether taken from the person of the Deceased or seized at <lb/> his residence should be returned to me forthwith. In the <lb/>alternative I would ask that I should be afforded an <lb/>opportunity of examining these documents a sufficient time <lb/>before the Inquiry to enable me to master their contents and <lb/>make copies of such as I may consider necessary and in addition <lb/>that they should be produced at the Inquiry.   I would also ask you to let me know at your earliest <lb/>convenience the time when, the place where and the grounds <lb/>upon which Mr. Sheehy Skeffington was arrested; I should also <lb/>be furnished with the names and rank of the parties who effected <lb/>the arrest, also of the persons who were present at the trial <lb/> (if any), at the execution and at the subsequent search of <lb/>Mr. Sheehy Skeffington's residence and in addition the name and <lb/>rank of the several persons interviewed by Mrs. Kettle and Mrs. <lb/>Culhane when they called at Portobello Barracks.   I must also seek to be furnished with a copy of every report <lb/>by whomsoever made which was reduced  to  writing dealing <lb/>either with the arrest trial or execution of Mr. Sheehy <lb/>Skeffington or verifying the cause of death or explaining the <lb/>reasons why the search was made  at  Mr. Sheehy Skeffington's <lb/>residence after his arrest, why Mrs. Kettle and Mrs. Culhane were <lb/>placed under temporary arrest, why my client has not yet <lb/>received any official notification of the death of her husband <lb/>and why her request that his remains should be handed over to <lb/>her for burial was altogether ignored. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5872_img_969_2"/>
             I have no doubt that the Authorities will be only <lb/>too anxious to facilitate a thorough investigation of all the <lb/>circumstances under which Mr. Sheehy Skeffington met with his <lb/>death. They will I feel sure recognise that unless the <lb/>information asked for above is supplied to me that I will not <lb/>be in a position to <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> properly instruct the Counsel who <lb/> will appear at the Inquiry on behalf of my client.   Of course all the information asked for should be given <lb/>some days before the actual date of the Inquiry that all <lb/>documents having any bearing on the matter should be available <lb/>for my inspection several days before and should be produced <lb/>at the Inquiry.    Your obedient servant,  <lb/> Henry Lemass     Sir John G. Maxwell <lb/>Commanding-in-chief <lb/>the Forces in Ireland <lb/>Parkgate <lb/>Dublin.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>