<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5542">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, early February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
This short note speaks of local gossip and the reaction to their engagement and her liking for Lady Gregory&#39;s the Workhouse Ward.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5542</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2121">Togherstown, Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5542_img_638_1"  type="Letter"  url="c0a124804dda3433d9655be1d400d3bd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5542_img_638_2"  type="Letter"  url="7bbc9076efa15323c9cdcecbfaeb4df5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5542_img_638_3"  type="Letter"  url="1543efece2622f5cb7d3660a867cc90f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5542_img_638_1"/>
            <!-- End of the letter written on the left-hand side of the letter --> come across that Dialogue “The Work House Ward”<lb/>to give it to me I’d like to show it to the lads.<lb/>No news at all except<lb/>lots of warmest love<lb/> from your <hi rend="underline">only doting little girl</hi> <lb/> May    <lb/>    <!-- Beginning of letter -->  Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea,<lb/>Mullingar,    My dearest James   I was glad to get<lb/>your letter this morn the post<lb/>was late &amp; I was just beginning<lb/>to feel very cross when<lb/><hi rend="underline">Mrs</hi> Post put her beautiful 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5542_img_638_2"/>
            <!-- Transcription of page 2 and 3 of the letter --> face round the door - there<lb/>was a letter also from<lb/>Mary Kelly Castletown one<lb/>on <seg type="unclear">brusress</seg>  you know the<lb/>only remark she made<lb/>about us was “I heard of<lb/>May’s choice” not a wish<lb/>or another word. The bride &amp;<lb/>groom are coming home<lb/>next week. Jimmy Duffy,  <lb/>Rose Kelly’s man is  <lb/>    spending his holidays in<lb/>Balrath at present, himself<lb/>and Dan having a royal<lb/>time. J. Cunningham heard<lb/>nothing yet Josephine called<lb/>here yesterday to congratulate<lb/>me she was in great humour<lb/>I must surely write to your<lb/>Mother tomorrow I’m<lb/>such a bad hand at the<lb/>pen that I hate taking<lb/>it up but it is so ungrateful  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5542_img_638_3"/>
            <!-- Page 4 of the letter --> not to have written straight <lb/>away. Mother is in M. gar <lb/>today, we are a bit busy <lb/>I am giving this letter to <lb/>the breadman to post. I <lb/>hope it will go alright <lb/>All hands think I got fat <lb/>while I was away. The change <lb/>did me a lot of good anyway. <lb/>I can’t say I would like to get <lb/>anything fatter tho’ I got through <lb/>most of performances in the Abbey <lb/>they enjoyed them if you ever
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>