<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0394">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Campbell to the Chief Crown Solicitor, 26 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Campbell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Campbell, on behalf of the Assistant Financial Secretary for the War Office, Sir Charles Harris (1864-1943), to Henry Arthur Wynne concerning private Michael McCarthy. According to Campbell McCarthy has falsely claimed for dependence allowance and given false testimony upon re-enlistment.Henry Arthur Wynne was the chief crown solicitor for Ireland following the death of Malchy Kelly (1850-1916).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, 1916/5613/9105</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/394</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0054">Campbell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0363">War Office, St. Martin&#39;s Place, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0815">Henry Arthur Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0394_img_1657_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc0dec99a6033f8629c2827c9812ec0d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0394_img_1657_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Solicitor General</hi><lb/>Please advise as to a <lb/>prosecution <lb/>Henry Arthur Wynne <lb/>29.5:16    War Office,  St. Martin's Place,  London, W.C.   26th May, 1916.  Sir,   With reference to War Office letter of the 20th of July, <lb/>1915, No.46/690 (Accounts 3.) I am directed to transmit the <lb/>enclosed documents which have been forwarded to this Department <lb/>by the Board of Customs and Excise in connection with a claim <lb/>for a Dependant's Allowance for the father of 5282, Private <lb/>Micheal McCarthy, 3rd Leinster Regiment, and to request that <lb/>you will be so good as to take the necessary action with a view <lb/>to the prosecution of the <hi rend="underline">soldier and dependant</hi> in accordance <lb/>with instructions contained in the letter quoted.  It has been ascertained that Private McCarthy is <lb/><hi rend="underline">serving at Cork</hi>.  The soldier was a reservist in the 3rd Bn. Royal <lb/>Irish Regiment at the date of mobilization but discharged on <lb/>the 25th June, 1915 as no longer physically fit for war service. <lb/>Application for Dependants' Allowance was made by him and his <lb/>father in November 1914, and the documents in connection with <lb/>this claim are enclosed for reference.  He re—enlisted in the Leinster Regiment on the 13th <lb/>January last, but did not disclose his previous military service <lb/>and the <hi rend="underline">necessary action is being taken in connection with the <lb/>offence of false statements on attestation.</hi> <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  <seg type="unclear">Wm.</seg> Campbell <lb/>for the Assistant Financial Secretary.   The Chief Crown Solicitor,  Dublin Castle.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>