<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2690">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Bishop Edward Thomas O'Dwyer to General John Grenfell Maxwell, 17 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer  to Sir General John Grenfell Maxwell. This letter refers to Maxwell’s request that O’Dwyer remove two priests in his diocese so that they cannot interact with the general population. The priests concerned are Fr Thomas Wall (1877 – 1956), and Fr Michael Hayes (1873 – 1934). Maxwell reportedly called for the pair’s removal because they were providing moral support to the rebels of Easter Week 1916. 

According to the letter O’Dwyer, cannot see any justification for the priest’s removal. Defending the two men, O&#39;Dwyer describes them as &#39;excellent priests who hold strong national views&#39; before going on to describe Maxwell as a &#39;military dictator&#39;. In a strong attack on Maxwell&#39;s handling of the rebellion, O&#39;Dwyer states, in relation to the first exectuions, that the &#39;first information which we got of their fate was the announcement that they had been shot in cold blood&#39;.

In 1916 O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917) was serving as the Bishop of Limerick. He took up the position in 1888 and retained it until his death in 1917. Maxwell (1859 – 1929) was stationed in Ireland as he had been appointed commander in chief of the British forces in Ireland after the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/239/1/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2690</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date>1916-05-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2091">Ashford, Charleville, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1039">Irish Command Headquarters, Parkgate, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2690_img_2111_1"  type="Letter"  url="51e09b921c52efb7f0ba5f4bf03089db.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2690_img_2111_2"  type="Letter"  url="379b690a7343bbd2d736375d627997e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2690_img_2111_3"  type="Letter"  url="8a09e0fda9602e0489e965b013c6c42c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2690_img_2111_1"/>
             Ashford, Charleville   17 May '16   Sir   I beg to acknowledge the re- <lb/> ceipt of your letter of 12th. which <lb/> has been forwarded to me here.    I have read very carefully <lb/>your allegations against Mr<seg type="unclear">Thomas,</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Wall,</seg> and <seg type="unclear">Mr.</seg>. Michael Hayes, <seg type="unclear">I</seg> <lb/> do not see in them any justification <lb/> for <seg type="unclear">disciplining</seg> action in any part<lb/> <seg type="del">against them</seg>.   They are both excellent <lb/> priests, who hold rather <lb/> but I do not know that they have <lb/> violated any law, civil or ec- <lb/>-clesiastical.    In your letter of 6th inst. <lb/>I'm appealed to me to keep free &amp; <lb/>the further area of town walk &amp; <lb/>Dublin hertlin of Ireland. Even
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2690_img_2111_2"/>
            <lb/>to you in Dublin. If their  first  information <lb/>which we get of their fate was the <lb/>announcement they had been <lb/>shot in cold blood. Personally <lb/>I defend their actions with heroism <lb/>and I believe that it has <seg type="unclear">entrapped</seg> <lb/> the conscience of the country.   Then the deporting <seg type="unclear">by hundreds</seg> <lb/>and then murdered by their <lb/>fellows, without trial of any kind <lb/>seems to me an abuse of power, <lb/>as fatuous as it is arbitrary, and <lb/>altogether your regime has <lb/>been one of the worst and <lb/>blackened chapters in the keeping <lb/>of the government of this country   I have the<seg type="unclear">happily</seg> <seg type="unclear">who</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Mrs</seg>     w. <lb/><seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">Sir</seg></seg>General <lb/>Sir <seg type="unclear">G.G. Maxwell</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Commander, Dublin</seg>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2690_img_2111_3"/>
             if active in that <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">parish</seg></seg> it was not inside <lb/>my province <seg type="del">that circumstances</seg> <lb/>the events of the past <seg type="del"></seg>  few    locally would <lb/>make it impossible for me to have <lb/>any part in proceedings which   <lb/>as wantonly cruel and oppressive.   In December the government <lb/>said, when a number of British <lb/><seg type="del"></seg> mercenaries invaded a friendly <lb/>state and fought the <seg type="unclear">republican</seg> <lb/>lawful government <seg type="unclear">If each case</seg> <lb/>deserved the supreme punishment <lb/>it was they. But officially and <lb/>unofficially then if influence of the <lb/>British Government was   <lb/>them, and it succeeded.   You took care that   plea of   <lb/>mercy   interpose no unlikely <lb/>often   young   like a <lb/>surrendered. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>