<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3822">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Harriet Reed to Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 4 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Harriet Emily Reed</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Harriet Emily Reed to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) stating the support of the Irish Matron&#39;s Association for the application of the Midwives&#39; Act to Ireland. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T81</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3822</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0191">Harriet Emily Reed</persName>
              <date>1916-06-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1345">34 St. Stephen&#39;s Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3822_img_3202_1"  type="Letter"  url="45b0e8fbbe120306f202397d32068ca6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3822_img_3202_1"/>
             THE IRISH MATRONS' ASSOCIATION, <lb/>34 ST. STEPHEN'S GREEN, <lb/>Dublin   June 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   Dear Sir,   At a meeting of the above Association <lb/>held on Saturday evening, June 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1916 <lb/>the following resolution was proposed by <lb/>Miss Reed, seconded by Miss Michie and <lb/>passed unanimously - <lb/>"That on hearing of the discussion at <seg type="del">the</seg> <lb/>a meeting at the College of Physicians on <lb/>June 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> re the application of the Midwives <lb/>Act to Ireland, the members of the Irish <lb/>Matron's Association wish to record their <lb/>opinion that a Midwives Act is an <lb/>urgent necessity for Ireland."   Yours faithfully   Harriet E. Reed   Maer C. <lb/>7.VII.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>