<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3099">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Katie Mooney to her brother Peter Mooney, 4 February, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Katie Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Katie Mooney to her brother Peter confirming that Peter will be coming home the following week on leave. Katie writes to Peter about taking cookery classes in the old school in Dunboyne and mentions many people who they both know. Katie also wishes Peter a happy birthday.  Katie mentions a family friend who was married recently and tells Peter about the wedding and sends all her love to him. 

Peter Mooney was born on 5th February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne. Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie (b. 1884) were brought up by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18th October 1915. 

He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St.Omer and Passchendael, in Belgium.Peter was an avid correspondent with his sister Kate and this letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>mooney-1916-02-04-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3099</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-02-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0342">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0517">101267 29th Battery, Royal Field Artillery, Ballincollig, Co. Cork</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3099_img_2506_1"  type="Letter"  url="4e31a2f43da429eb3ac4bb7f1a9f7bee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3099_img_2506_2"  type="Letter"  url="e01bffb5c6344f324fbf6747cdfe736c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3099_img_2506_3"  type="Letter"  url="02024c6809375d5b24534f255a3209e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3099_img_2506_4"  type="Envelope"  url="abbe40ffb7be3f8c7fcc47cabcc0f923.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3099_img_2506_1"/>
             Caulstown  <lb/> Dunboyne, <lb/> Co. Meath.  <lb/>  4th Feb’16  <lb/> My Dear Peter,   Delighted to receive <lb/> your ever welcome letter <lb/> today containing the good <lb/>news that we will see you <lb/> next week for certain. <lb/>I am writing a few lines <lb/> to the Governor this evening <lb/> telling him that you are <lb/>coming next week I am <lb/> sure he will be delighted. <lb/> I am going to Dunboyne <lb/> this evening to attend a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3099_img_2506_2"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">2.</hi> <lb/>committee meeting regarding <lb/>Cookery Classes which are <lb/>starting next week in the <lb/>old school. Our nurse's <lb/> meeting is tomorrow evening. <lb/> Tom Bracken was married <lb/> on last Wednesday. It was <lb/>a very nice, quiet wedding <lb/> no wreaths or veils or bouquets <lb/> nor white silk or satin. <lb/>McCarthy sent the carriage <lb/> with them to the chapel. <lb/>Miss Walshe gave the wedding <lb/> breakfast. Hugh Mullaly was <lb/> best man and Lillie Murray <lb/>was bridesmaid. <lb/> They are living in the <lb/> front lodge. I wonder <lb/>what will you say when <lb/>you hear that George Moran <lb/> is listed as a favourite in the Dublin Fusiliers. Himself <lb/>and Little were having a <lb/> good time drinking before <lb/> this. So I hear that the old man cleared him. <lb/> Don’t say anything about <lb/> this if you write to Padraig <lb/> as it wasn’t there I heard the <lb/> news. I didn’t get any word <lb/>of how Mrs Farrell was yet. <lb/> I expect a letter in the morning. <lb/> I won’t send the Drogheda <lb/> or sport tomorrow, as they <lb/>will be here when you come. <lb/> Bridget says she will give <lb/> you a rare feed in the mornings.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3099_img_2506_3"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">4.</hi> <lb/>I got a new tyre and tube <lb/> for my bicycle as the other <lb/> one blew up and left me <lb/> on the road. Before I <lb/>close this letter I must <lb/>wish you every joy from <lb/> all here as today is your <lb/>birthday. Many happy <lb/> returns of same to you. <lb/>I have tobacco here for you lb/> also socks and gloves.  <lb/> I will now say a fond good bye <lb/> to you with best love from all <lb/>here.    May God <lb/> Bless &amp; Protect you is the <lb/> sincere prayer of your fond <lb/>Aunt &amp; Sister. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3099_img_2506_4"/>
             Driver Peter Mooney <lb/>101267 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Battery <lb/>R T A Ballincollig <lb/><hi rend="underline">Co Cork</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>