<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0017">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cis M. Coyle to James Ryan, 2 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cis M. Coyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Cis M Coyle to James Ryan (1891-1970) on 2 July 1916. was written after Ryan was transferred from Stafford to Frongach in Wales. The writer refers to other prisoners with whom whom she is friendly and asks about the camp rules in Frongach.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P88/27(5)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/17</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0736">Cis M. Coyle</persName>
              <date>1916-07-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0473">58 Aughrim Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0981">Frongach, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0017_img_1046_1"  type="Letter"  url="1022daaf529fd60c87cfb3bd88198652.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0017_img_1046_2"  type="Letter"  url="dc99c7c45f9cd77e5149955826f1fdb3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0017_img_1046_3"  type="Letter"  url="7f1d7ecdb1dc8a21d42439bb8247b275.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0017_img_1046_4"  type="Letter"  url="2bd5253338282fd78235e97012e5cb24.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0017_img_1046_1"/>
                58 Aughrim St     July 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>. 1916   My dear Jim   Your letter of June 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>. received yesterday morning <lb/> for which many thanks. <lb/> You are I presume in <lb/> Frongoch by this time <lb/> and I hope you find <lb/> the change pleasant  I know you can write <lb/>but one letter per week <lb/>now and of <seg type="unclear">course</seg> you <lb/>will send that one home  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0017_img_1046_2"/>
              naturally, but I will <lb/>write to you all the same <lb/> and when Michael is <lb/>writing home if he says <lb/> how you are etc. his sister <lb/>will let me know. She &amp; <lb/> I are great friends. I am <lb/>expecting a letter from Liam <lb/> I wonder he has not <lb/>written. I don't know what <lb/>are the rules of the camps, <lb/> &amp; are you allowed to <lb/> smoke? I wonder do you <lb/>know a friend of mine <lb/> Peter Moran only a day <lb/>or two ago I found out <lb/>that he had been in  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0017_img_1046_3"/>
              Stafford. I thought he was <lb/>in Wandsworth and asked <lb/>Liam to look him up. He <lb/>is now in Frongoch. The <lb/>Councillor is laid up <lb/>with influenza in Wandsworth <lb/>but I suppose he will <lb/>join you later on. It <lb/>will be quite a  <lb/>meeting for you all. I <lb/>am glad your sister has <lb/>been to see you, a visit <lb/>from home must be a <lb/>great treat to you at <lb/>present. I want you to <lb/>look up S. Donnelly <lb/> Wexford St. I don't know him <lb/> but his brother is a friend  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0017_img_1046_4"/>
              <lb/>of mine and some of them <lb/>may be going over to Wales <lb/>later on. If so I will get <lb/>them to see my friends <lb/> also. I am told that you <lb/>have the use of a piano <lb/>in Camp &amp; that you have <lb/>concerts amongst yourselves <lb/>Is it true I wonder. If <lb/>it is ask Peter Moran to <lb/>sing a few ?comic? songs <lb/>for you. Tell Liam to <lb/>write to me &amp; tell Michael <lb/>I was enquiring for him.<lb/> I will write again when <lb/>I hear some news from the <lb/>Camp. Kindest regards <lb/>from all. <seg type="closer"> Very Sincerely Yours  Cis M.Coyle </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>