<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2243">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to George Francis Stewart, 17 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of a  letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to George Francis Stewart (1851-1928). Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland. Stewart was a land agent and southern unionist. He became vice-president of the Land Owners Association and became heavily involved in southern unionists campaigns against partition due to Home Rule. His willingness, with other southern Unionists, to strike a deal with John Redmond (1856-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, regarding partition resulted in a dispute within the Irish Unionist Alliance.
In this letter Montgomery discusses his support for Edward Carson (1854-1935), Unionist leader, to enter negotiations about Home Rule based on the exclusion of six counties in Ulster. Montgomery states he will explain his view in an enclosed letter he previously sent to Unionist leaders including Edward Carson, James Craig (1871-1940), and Walter Long (1854-1924). Unfortunately this enclosure is not available. Montgomery goes on to describe a private meeting he had with Craig, in with Craig described the pressure America is putting on Britain to grant Home Rule to Ireland, noting that David Lloyd George MP (1863-1945) will arrange the settlement. Montgomery also notes that Carson will not continue talks unless the six county scheme is the basis for negotiations, noting that rejection of this by Unionists will alienate them from other British parties. The letter also discusses the benefits of a Unionist majority in a six county Ulster than a minority in a nine county Ulster, stating the political position is embarrassing. Montgomery comments on the lack of leadership by Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), prime minister. The letter also discusses the view of Redmond that it is a provisional scheme and not a permanent one, stating that Carson wishes for the scheme to be enacted in a Government of Ireland Act and not simply an emergency provision.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/39</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2243</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-17</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Francis Stewart</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2243_img_1687_1"  type="Letter"  url="29f20d42ffed9d491df53f20b05a6e28.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2243_img_1687_2"  type="Letter"  url="e23f0a54b58416a074be38952da46f5e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2243_img_1687_3"  type="Letter"  url="8e4170be9d5cecb1b0dcdedc1bf3c84e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2243_img_1687_4"  type="Letter"  url="5280098f6c6e7ab53592363926b740b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2243_img_1687_5"  type="Letter"  url="1221e14d132e714ea27eee6e18d78c1b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2243_img_1687_1"/>
             0627/429  <lb/>Copy   17th June, 1916.    My dear Stewart,   If you think it would be better for me, having been<lb/>a party to the decision of the Ulster Unionist Council last<lb/>Monday, not to attend the meeting of the Executive Committee<lb/>of the I.U.A. please tell me so. It will be time enough if<lb/>you do so at the landowners' meeting at noon on Wednesday;<lb/>otherwise I propose to attend, as I think it very important<lb/>that Northern &amp; Southern Unionists should keep in touch,<lb/>in spite of having to take somewhat divergent lines in the<lb/>present crisis.  I cannot, or course, take up the time of the meeting<lb/>on Wednesday, if I attend, by explaining my position at length;<lb/>but I should like you to be acquainted with it.  I cannot describe the frame of mind in which I approached<lb/>the crisis better than by enclosing a letter which I wrote<lb/>last month when the rot in the English papers began. Before<lb/>sending it for publication, however, I consulted a well-informed<lb/>permanent official in London of strong Unionist views. I<lb/>send you his answers in accordance therewith. I sent copies<lb/>of the letter to Carson, Craig, Sclater, Stronge and Walter Long.  When I went to Belfast on Monday night the 5th inst.<lb/>Craig asked me and two others into a private room at the<lb/>club to explain his and Carson's position. I cannot put all<lb/>he told me, or all Carson told the standing Committee and the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2243_img_1687_2"/>
             0627/429  <lb/>-2-  <lb/>Council at private meetings subsequently into a letter. The<lb/>upshot of it was, that they were at the end of their tether,<lb/>as the Cabinet had really unanimously decided, that under the<lb/>pressure of difficulties with America, the Colonies aand in<lb/>Parliament, but chiefly with America, they must offer Redmond<lb/>Home Rule at once; but that they did not wish to coerce Ulster,<lb/>&amp; had authorised Lloyd George to arrange a settlement. Carson<lb/>had agreed to submit to his followers the exclusion of six<lb/>counties as a <hi rend="underline">basis of negotiation.</hi> Till they had agreed to<lb/>this basis he refused to go any further or to meet any Nationalists.<lb/>They  Carson and Craig  found all the ground they had gained in their  anti  Home Rule<lb/>Campaign before the war had slipped away under the influence of<lb/>the war, and that the majority of the Unionist Members and<lb/>voters took the same views as the majority of the Unionist<lb/>papers as to the necessity of a settlement.  If Ulster Unionists refused to consider such a settlement<lb/>they could not hope for any sympathy or support in Great Britain<lb/>now or hereafter. The Home Rule Act was on the Statute Book<lb/>and now that the Unionists Leaders in the Coalition Government<lb/>were parties to a proposal to bring it into immediate operation<lb/>there was no hope of removing it from the Statute Book. If we<lb/>did not agree to a settlement we should have the Home Rule Act<lb/>coming into operation without the exclusion of any part, of<lb/>Ulster. *  We should either  have  to submit to this, or to fight.<lb/>To begin fighting here at the end of the Great War would be<lb/> *or subject only to some worthless amending act which Asquith<lb/>might bring in in fulfilment of his worthless pledge.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2243_img_1687_3"/>
             D627/429  <lb/>-3-  <lb/>hopeless, &amp; we could not hope for any support. If in spite<lb/>of these drawbacks, our fighting succeeded, we could not hope to<lb/>get more than we are now offered,<sic>ize.</sic> the exclusion of six<lb/>counties. We should be in a better position to hold our own and<lb/>help our friends with six counties returning 16 Unionist<seg type="del">s</seg> &amp;<lb/>9 Nationalist Members than we should be with nine counties<lb/>excluded returning 17 Nationalist and 16 Unionist Members.  We should be in a better position to help Unionists in any part<lb/>of Ireland if we were excluded than if we formed portion of a<lb/>permanent minority in a Dublin Parliament.  This is, I think, the pith of the more important part<lb/>of what Carson &amp; Craig told us; but it is only a part.  After considering the matter &amp; hearing what you had to<lb/>say in Dublin on 7th, I wrote to Carson (enclosure <seg type="del">three.</seg> 3   The Cavan, Donegal &amp; Monaghan protest &amp;  the  solutions<lb/>submitted to the Council by Casron appeared to me to fulfil<lb/>my conditions, &amp; I therefore very reluctantly became a party to the decision.  The position is humiliating, but the humiliation is brought<lb/>on us by His Majesty's Ministers. I can only suppose that the<lb/>reasons for such a extraordinary &amp; humiliating policy must<lb/>have been very strong in order to overcome the objections of<lb/>Walter Long, Bonar Law, etc. Had our ruler been a man and<lb/>not an Asquith some other way would have been found; but our<lb/>Government &amp; Parliament has, as the Morning post calls it,<lb/>been Asquixiated. As regards the question between definitive 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2243_img_1687_4"/>
             D627/429  <lb/>-4-  <lb/>and provisional. I have no doubt that what Carson put before the<lb/>Unionist Council was what Lloyd George had put before him. Redmond<lb/>finding he had to deal with such determined opposition to the<lb/>partition of Ireland  has  tried to smooth it down by making it appear<lb/>that the Amending Bill is to be a Provisional Emergency Measure.<lb/>Whether Lloyd George has given any countenance to this version<lb/>we, of course, do not know. I think Asquith's statement, which<lb/>is in some quarters being represented as a confirmation of the<lb/>truth of Redmond's version is ambiguous.  Carson in addressing the Unionist Council made mention<lb/>of the proposed Imperial Conference; but in view of possible<lb/>changes of the Constitution consequent on that Conference Asquith<lb/>might call the proposed Irish settlement provisional without<lb/>being supposed to contradict Carson's view that the exclusion<lb/>of the six counties should be embodied in a definitive Government<lb/>of Ireland Amendment Act &amp; not in a mere Emergency Provisional<lb/>Measure. Carson Laid stress on the importance of the Imperial<lb/>Conference finding an excluded Ulster and not an unamended  or inadequately amended  Home<lb/>Rule Act on the Statute Book.  To sum up: - As there seems no alternative between this<lb/>miserable Asquith Coalition Government and <seg type="del">  </seg>  chaos,  we must<lb/>submit to a decision positively come to by the Ministry &amp; put<lb/>the whole responsibility upon them.  Under these circumstances I agreed to the Belfast Resolutions<lb/>with great disgust (1) because I believed that if we did not, neither<lb/>Ulster <seg type="del">n</seg> or any other Irish Unionists would be able to get any effective 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2243_img_1687_5"/>
             D627/429  <lb/>-5-  <lb/>sympathy in Great Britain. (2) that if we refused the settlement<lb/>now offered we should either find ourselves under Home Rule<lb/>without any counties excluded, or possibly with only four or<lb/>two counties excluded. There would be a risk of Belfast<lb/>agreeing to some such arrangement &amp; leaving the rest of us<lb/>out in the cold; lastly because I believe that we could help<lb/>Southern Unionists better if we were, so to speak, on dry<lb/>land than if we agreed all to drown together in a Home Rule<lb/>flood.  I am sorry to inflict such a long letter on so busy a<lb/>man; but I wanted you to understand my position more clearly<lb/>then I shall probably have any opportunity of making it when<lb/>we meet in Dublin next week.   Yours very truly,   P.S. All the Ulster Unionist Council decided was, to approve<lb/>of Carson entering into negotiations on the six county basis.<lb/>He can still break off negotiations on any other point. We<lb/>have so far merely<seg type="del">being</seg>  been  manoeuvring for position. There is<lb/>a good deal of breathing time      (1) before the basis of negotiations<lb/>is accepted by both sides. (2) before the negotiations come to<lb/>anything; (3) if they do come to anything, before John Redmond<lb/>gets his Parliament into motion: meantime I suppose Sir John<lb/>Maxwell sits tight in spite of County Council Resolutions, etc.. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>