<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1537">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff to Lady Clonbrock, 29 February 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs. Arthur Goff</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff, honorary secretary of the Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation, to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Mrs. Goff had a similar role to Lady Clonbrock in the Irish Women&#39;s Association, formed in London in the Spring of 1915 for the purpose of providing food and comforts for prisoners of war belonging to Irish Regiments. 
Mrs. Goff is writing about overlap between organisations and possible duplication of parcels, though she doesn&#39;t think it is widespread.
She goes on to discuss what appears to be differences of opinion as to the treatment of prisoners from other Regiments where adopters are involved, especially when the Government and the Director General are encouraging private adoption. She mentions a specific case where two named prisoners got practically the same items both from Mrs. Goff&#39;s organisation and Lady Clonbrock&#39;s.
Enclosed with this letter is an information sheet setting out details of the Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation&#39;s modus operandi.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers. Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1537</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1236">Mrs. Arthur Goff</persName>
              <date>1916-02-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0673">Belfort House, Dundrum, Co. Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1537_img_1005_1"  type="Letter"  url="4c57e76f9016ed4b0a3d962e1f0a61d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1537_img_1005_2"  type="Letter"  url="f8710e3f4400142b7e8e59b460dbe7e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1537_img_1005_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="6710a6c4abe7d40b7ebd495978215e9b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1537_img_1005_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">The Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation</hi> <lb/>APPROVED BY THE WAR OFFICE <lb/>AND <lb/>Under the auspices of the Central Advisory <lb/> Committee, R.D.F.   Hon.Sec., <lb/>MRS ARTHUR GOFF, <lb/>Belfort House, Dundrum, <lb/>Co. Dublin.   Dundrum, <hi rend="subscript">Co. Dublin.</hi>   Feb. 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.1916   Dear Madam   Many thanks for your letter.   I do not think that there has really been <lb/>much over lapping in the case of your circle <lb/>&amp; me. The Irish Womens Assocation only commenced <lb/>in May. 1915. I had an acknowledgement <lb/>back from Harley just before Xmas1914. <lb/>He and Mahon got a weekly parcel from <lb/>that on, until I saw the Irish Womens group in <lb/>the day papers. I as my idea has always been <lb/>to prevent overlapping I at once wrote to the <lb/> commanding officer as I told you. Mahon was <lb/>the only man I asked to keep. I see his wife <lb/> often &amp; she subscribes to his parcel. All the <lb/>other men I gave up only sending to them when <lb/>they wrote &amp; and asked me for something such as boots: <lb/>Walpole I have also been sending to for a <lb/>year. Only a few weeks ago I found out what <lb/>Dept he belong to as he never put it on his card. <lb/>Gillard I commenced to send to again <lb/>the beginning of Dec as I was asked by an adopter <lb/>for a Connaught Ranger. I felt it was no <lb/>good asking the I.W.A. about him as well
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1537_img_1005_2"/>
             As unless adopters sending through their society <lb/>they will have nothing to do with them. <lb/>It seems a pity to work like this as <lb/>often one is asked for or offered money to <lb/>send parcels to a man of a certain Dept. <lb/>Personally I cannot understand it especially <lb/>as <seg type="del">its</seg> I understand that it is the wish <lb/>of the Government and the Director General to <lb/>encourage private adopters &amp; more so when they <lb/>are willing to send through an approved   <lb/>any regular adopted men on our list (  <lb/>Yours) McMahon &amp;Walpole fit exactly the <lb/>same clothes as you have sent, with the exception <lb/> of the great coat &amp; coat &amp; trousers. We sent out <lb/>things in Nov. &amp; Dec. Every man whose names <lb/>had ever been on our list got a Xmas parcel. <lb/>containing 1 1/2 lbs of home made plum pudding <lb/>besides other foodstuffs. All our foods we get <lb/> wholesale. This week the parcels contained <lb/>tin roast mutton, tin salmon, tin milk, 1/4 lb tea, 1 lb sugar <lb/>1 1/2 lb gingerbread, 1/2 lb cabin biscuits besides the bread from Berne <lb/>&amp; tobacco from London, 250 cigarettes a month or 1 lb of tobacco. <lb/>Please do not trouble to answer this. I am to see about the <lb/>prisoners myself that I think everyone must be able   Yours Truly   missus Goff 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1537_img_1005_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">The Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation</hi> <lb/>Approved By the War Office <lb/>and <lb/>Under the auspices of the Central Advisory Committee, R.D.F.    The funds of the above organisation entirely keep the men. It undertakes to look after <lb/>each prisoner by a weekly parcel of foodstuffs, a supply of bread from Berne, tobacco <lb/>and cigarettes out of bond from the British and American Co., London, besides underclothing, <lb/>boots, etc.   Every man costs under 5s. per week, which includes everything except clothes.   A parcel is also despatched at once to every new appeal., of which there are many. No <lb/>matter what regiment the man may belong to the parcel is sent and continued until such time <lb/>as the man is taken on by his own Regiment or Depot.   Any man already on the list can be adopted for 2s. 6d. per week, all goods being sent in <lb/>the adoptor's name; or 6s per week for a new man or one of the adoptor's own choosing.   All contributions of money, clothes (new or old), boots etc., will be gratefully received.   Office hours at No. 1 Sydenham Road. — 11 a.m. until 1 p.m. every day except Wednesdays <lb/>and Saturdays; Tuesday afternoons from 2-30 until 6.30 p.m. for labelling and packing, when <lb/>all visitors are welcome.   Tea — 4.30 p.m.   A Committee Meeting will be held every Friday morning at 12 noon, this being formed <lb/>of any subscribers who may wish to attend.   All work absolutely voluntary.   Communications and contributions to be addressed to the Hon. Secretary —   MRS. ARTHUR GOFF, <lb/>Belfort House, Dundrum, <lb/>Co. Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>