<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6657">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of a letter from Charles Murphy to Bishop Michael Francis Fallon, 29 March 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Murphy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter Charles Murphy provides Bishop Michael Francis Fallon with an overview of the measures he has taken so far in order to support the Irish Parliamentary Party in its struggle for constitutional rights. The letter is a reply to a letter from Bishop Michael Francis Fallon to Charles Joseph Doherty, T. W. McGarry and Charles Murphy, 12 March 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Folder: Box 2. f.2 Joseph C. Walsh Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6657</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0594">Charles Murphy</persName>
              <date>1917-03-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0236">Michael Francis Fallon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1372">London, Ontario, Canada</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1935</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6657_img_None_1"  url="php0zTZ8H.png"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6657_img_None_2"  url="phpwbCocj.png"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6657_img_None_3"  url="php6PZrgU.png"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6657_img_None_4"  url="phpvPd2kv.png"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6657_img_None_5"  url="phpuLbcq6.png"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6657_img_0_1"/>
             (COPY)   March 29th, 1917.    His Lordship,    Bishop M. F. Fallon,    London, O n t.    Dear Bishop Fallon:-   Dear Bishop Fallon:-  A word of explanation<lb/>is due you as to the delay in sending this reply<lb/>to your letter of March 12th, addressed to Hon.<lb/>C.J. Doherty, Hon. T.W. McGarry and myself.  On March 15th and 16th<lb/>I was engaged at the Sittings of the Parliamentary<lb/>Committee on Returned Soldiers at Montreal. I came<lb/>up to Ottawa on the night of 15th to speak at<lb/>an Irish Meeting in St. Patrick's Parish Hall, and<lb/>after the Meeting I received your letter of the12th<lb/>inst. I returned to Montreal on the morning of the<lb/>16th inst., and upon the conclusion of the Committee's<lb/>sittings I remained over in that City until March<lb/>17th to fill an engagement at the Reform Club, where<lb/>I again discussed Home Rule.  On Monday, the 19th, I<lb/>went to Toronto, and was engaged at the Sittings of<lb/>the Parliamentary Committee there until the 24th<lb/>inst. Since my return to Ottawa this is the first<lb/>chance I have had to write to you.  In a general way your<lb/>letter asks each of those to whom it is addressed what<lb/>has been done, and what is to be done by way of answer<lb/>to the latest appeal of the Irish Parliamentary Party 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6657_img_0_2"/>
              March 29th, 1917.    His Lordship,    Bishop M. F. Fallon - 2.   for assistance in the struggle for their consti-<lb/>tutional rights.  Answering for myself, I<lb/>may say that in addition to the two speeches<lb/>above mentioned, I sent a cablegram to Prime<lb/>Minister Borden on March 8th, which was prior to<lb/>the publication in this Country of the Irish Par-<lb/>liamentary Party's appeal and 4 days before your<lb/>letter was written. That cablegram was in theseterms:-  Ottawa, March 8th, 1917   Sir Robert L. Borden,    London.   The advocacy of immediate Home Rule for Ireland<lb/>by your fellow-Premier, Sir Edward Morris, closely<lb/>followed by Lloyd George's newest act of treachery,<lb/>supply both contrast and lesson to the friends of<lb/>small nations in all parts of the world.<lb/>How can the people or representatives of Canada<lb/>trust a Government headed by a man who has been<lb/>false to his leader and his principles, more par-<lb/>ticulary when that Government is dominated by Car-<lb/>son, the inciter of armed resistance to constituted<lb/>authority and the avowed friend of the German<lb/>Emporer?<lb/>The action of Lloyd George and his Government in<lb/>treating the Home Rule Act as another scrap of paper<lb/>will seriously damage the cause of the Allies and<lb/>will inevitably help the Germans to prolong the war.  Charles Murphy.       
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6657_img_0_3"/>
              March 29th, 1917.    His Lordship,    Bishop M. F. Fallon -3.   On March 9th, a copy of the<lb/>foregoing message was cabled to Mr. John Redmond.<lb/>On the evening of the same day I sent him a second<lb/>cable consisting of an extract of 175 words<lb/>from the Montreal Star editorial of March 9th.  On March 10th, I sent Mr.<lb/>Remond a cablegram embodying 165 words from the<lb/>Toronto Globe editorial of March 9th.  On March 12th, - the day<lb/>your letter was written - I received a cable mes-<lb/>sage of thanks from Mr. Remond.  On March 13th, I received<lb/>from Mr. Redmond the following cablegram:-<lb/><lb/>Honourable Charles Murphy  Ottawa.  May we publish your cablegram to Borden.  (Sd.) Redmond  To the foregoing, I cabled<lb/>Yes on March 13th, and the publication in the<lb/>Brtish press immediately followed.  Further cablegrams relating<lb/>to additional action here were sent by me on March<lb/>19th and March 24th to Mr. Renomd, and in due course<lb/>I received his replies. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6657_img_0_4"/>
              March 29th, 1917.    His Lordship,    Bishop M. F. Fallon - 4.   On March 26th, I sent Mr.<lb/>Redmond a cablegram of 70 words taken from the<lb/>report of Mr. N. W. Rowell's speech at a public<lb/>meeting in Toronto on the night of March 23rd.  There are other details as<lb/>to further local action still receiving attention,<lb/>but it is not necessary to enumerate them in this<lb/>letter.  So much for my personal con-<lb/>nection with what has been done. I need scarcely<lb/>add that in matters of this kind there is always<lb/>the danger of being accused of playing to the<lb/>gallery, and, for that reason, I preferred to<lb/>trust to our people's sense of doing what was right<lb/>rather than attempt to dictate to them in any way.<lb/>The number meetings already held, and the resolu-<lb/>tions adopted, not only justify this course, but<lb/>point to local action over a wide area as the most<lb/>effective way of influencing public opinion, both in<lb/>this country and in Great Britain.  Now, as to what further may<lb/>be done. In my opinion, no more practical service<lb/>could be rendered at the present time than to have a<lb/>representation made by Mr. Lionel Curtis to his fellow-<lb/>members of the Round Table, who are now the control-<lb/>ling force in the British Government, as to the<lb/>enormous benefit it would be to Empire unification if<lb/>they would apply to Ireland the principle which they<lb/>desire to preserve for Belgium and other small nations.<lb/>I am not personally acquainted with Mr. Lionel Curtis,<lb/>but I have always heard him spoken of as a gentleman<lb/>of single purpose and unselfish ideals, and accepting    
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_6657_img_0_5"/>
              March 29th, 1917.   His Lordship,<lb/>Bishop M. F. Fallon - 5.  him as such, I assume he would be willing to help<lb/>on his life's work in the way I have suggested if<lb/>a strong representation were made to him form the<lb/>proper quarter.  Let me thank you for the<lb/>copy of the London Advertiser that you were good<lb/>enough to send me with the report of the Meeting of<lb/>Sunday, March 18th.  In conclusion, allow me to<lb/>extend my congratulations upon your eloquent and<lb/>whole-hearted support of the cause in which all our<lb/>people are so deeply interested.   Your sincerely,      CM/LB.<lb/>ENCL. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>