<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5909">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Lawson to Reginald H. Brade, 11 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Lawson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Major General Henry Lawson (1859-1933) to Reginald Brade (1864-1933) confirming Patrick Alphonsus Carroll&#39;s arrival at the Curragh on 9th February 1916.Patrick Alphonsus Carroll was a veterinary surgeon based in Carlow town who had qualified from the Royal College of Veterinary Surgeons. The Army Veterinary Corps was well tested throughout the Great War. There were about 2.5 million admissions mainly on the Western Front and 80% of injured animals were treated and returned to duty. Major Rainey would survive the war and later document the story of the AVC in the Great War in 1925.Sir Reginald Brade served as the Under-Secretary of State for War from 1914 to 1920.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Pat Carroll</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5909</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0315">Henry Lawson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1446">Reginald H. Brade</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0014">London</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5909_img_1155_1"  type="Letter"  url="68f83a65e41f7af6b8d653a81f8ed651.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5909_img_1155_1"/>
                Head Quarters, Irish Command,  Parkgate,    Dublin, 11th February, 1916.   V.S./568.  Sir,   With reference to your No. 1045/16 (V.D.),<lb/> dated 19th January, 1916, I have the honour to report <lb/> that Mr P.A. Carroll, M.R.C.V.S., arrived at the <lb/> Curragh on the 9th February, 1916, and reported <lb/> himself to the Officer Commanding, Station Veterinary <lb/> Hospital there, for duty, in anticipation of being <lb/> gazetted to a temporary commission as Lieutenant in <lb/> the Army Veterinary Corps. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be,<lb/> Sir,<lb/> Your obedient Servant,  Henry Lawson Major <lb/> for Major-General,<lb/> Commanding the Troops in Ireland.<lb/>  The Secretary,  War Office,  London, S.W.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>