<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1900">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William M. Nolan to Robert Chalmers, 2 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William M. Nolan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from William M. Nolan (1855-1941), town clerk for Limerick, to Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), the under-secretary for Ireland. Chalmers obtained the position for a brief period following the resignation of Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), due to his administration&#39;s failure to anticipate and react to the 1916 Rising. The letter regards the superannuation allowance to  Patrick Reidy, a former labourer for the local gas works. The letter states that Reidy was awarded £67:3:4 annually. It goes on to state that his excellency of the council should be informed of this. The letter also discusses and enclosure of a medical, which has since been lost.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5612/9459</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1900</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1399">William M. Nolan</persName>
              <date>1916-06-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0556">Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1900_img_1351_1"  type="Letter"  url="d7e8f44f506b538891f08dd2dbf8b6ad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1900_img_1351_1"/>
             TOWN CLERK'S OFFICE, <lb/> TOWN HALL. <lb/>Limerick   2nd June 1916 . <seg type="del">1912</seg> <lb/>5711  Sir,   Referring to my letter to you of 7th April last, on the subject <lb/>of the superannuation allowance to Mr P. Reidy, late foreman at the <lb/>Gas Works, and forwarding you copy of the resolution adopted by the <lb/>County Borough Council on the 6th April agreeing to grant him an <lb/>allowance of £67:3:4 a year. I beg to inform you that, at the meeting <lb/>of the Council, held last evening, (which was the next meeting held <lb/>since the said 6th April ) the said resolution was unanimously <lb/>confirmed pursuant to the Local Officers Superannuation Act, 1869, <lb/>and I was directed to intimate said confirmation to you, so that you <lb/>may inform His Excellency of the Council's decision and obtain <lb/>His sanction to the Superannuation Allowance being paid to Mr Reidy.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your Obedient Servant,   W. M. Nolan  <lb/>Town Clerk.  P. S. In addition to the Medical Certificate, already sent you, I am <lb/>desired to enclose the first Certificate, dated July 1915, <lb/>furnished by Dr O' Sullivan.   The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>