<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0654">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras BГ©aslaГ­, 17 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Patrick Langford Beazley (1855-1924) to his son Piaras BГ©aslaГ­ (1881-1965). Patrick discusses Piaras submitting an article under a pseudonym on the Irish language for the St. Patrick&#39;s day edition of an unnamed newspaper. He suggests that Piaras should mention the fact that Irish was the language St. Patrick used.Piaras BГ©aslaГ­ (born Percy Frederick Beazley) was an English born writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, journalist and a member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the FГ inne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He wrote twenty plays between 1913 and 1939.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Piaras BГ©aslaГ­ Papers, Collection List 44, MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/654</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-02-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras BГ©aslaГ­</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0654_img_213_1"  type="Letter"  url="03a9ae73fa7b77ded8559be284629500.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0654_img_213_2"  type="Letter"  url="9f2073b728adc1852d72b76d0978521c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0654_img_213_3"  type="Letter"  url="ac4e299fa4e9948adfe35f047802c864.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0654_img_213_1"/>
                'GLENGARIFF'  RUDGRAVE SQUARE,  EGREMONT,  CHESHIRE.    17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb., 1916.   My dearest Pierce,   I just lost the post in<lb/>writing this letter. I find I<lb/>cannot now catch the 8 o'clock<lb/>post, which would bring this<lb/>letter to you in the morning,<lb/>but you ought to have it<lb/>toГўВЂВ”morrow evening. About<lb/>that article, which you sugГўВЂВ”<lb/>gested for next week. I canГўВЂВ”<lb/>not take one for next week<lb/>because I have one, and had<lb/>it when I got your letter in<lb/>hand for next week, and<lb/>I have received for considerГўВЂВ”<lb/>ation two others or so to which  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0654_img_213_2"/>
              I am more or less committed.<lb/> The position, as I explained to you,<lb/> is rather delicate and diffiГўВЂВ”<lb/>cult for me. You would have<lb/> to use a pseudonym beГўВЂВ”<lb/>cause it would not do to<lb/> let people think I was writГўВЂВ”<lb/>ing the articles myself or<lb/> favoring my son by giving<lb/> prominence to his writings<lb/> ГўВЂВ” one or other of which that they<lb/> would be sure to think if<lb/> you wrote under your name.<lb/> But with a good pseudonym<lb/> ГўВЂВ” the name, as it were, of<lb/> some living person ГўВЂВ” I might<lb/> be able to get in an occasГўВЂВ”<lb/>ional article. They would have<lb/> to be good and appropriate so<lb/> that no obligation could be<lb/> raised on that score, and not<cb/> more than about a column in<lb/> length, that is, about fourteen or<lb/> fifteen hundred words. I would<lb/> suggest that you should send<lb/> me <hi rend="underline">by Monday, March 2</hi> ГўВЂВ” nothing<lb/> can be done for next week<lb/> as I have indicated ГўВЂВ” an article<lb/> for <hi rend="underline">the issue of March 10</hi>, in<lb/> preparation for St. Patrick's Day,<lb/> showing how desirable it is<lb/> that <hi rend="underline"> with English</hi>the Irish peoГўВЂВ”<lb/>ple should grip the language<lb/><seg type="del">as well as</seg> St. Patrick used as<lb/> well as the faith he preached<lb/> so successfully in Ireland. It <lb/>seems to me that the subject is a<lb/> charming one and might be<lb/> made a great deal of by pointing<lb/> out some of the beautiful reГўВЂВ”<lb/>ligious expressions in the old<lb/> tongue (giving only the English<lb/> translation, except in two<lb/> or three particular cases, perГўВЂВ”<lb/>haps, to <seg type="del">give</seg> impart  a tone to the article),  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0654_img_213_3"/>
              explaining how the old tongue<lb/> was associated with the most<lb/> flourishing periods of the faith<lb/> in Ireland, how it is, as it were<lb/>, turned round the old ruin s ГўВЂВ”<lb/> the ruins of chapels and wells ГўВЂВ”<lb/> towers whose bring it to<lb/> mind, and dwelling on the conГўВЂВ”<lb/>trast between the cold secular<lb/> spirit indicated by the language<lb/> of ordinary social life in English<lb/> speaking lands and the brotherly,<lb/> Christian warmth conveyed in<lb/> Irish in the language of social interГўВЂВ”<lb/>course. Make your sentences<lb/> fairly crisp and let yourself go.<lb/> If you throw in some strengthen<lb/>ing figures in the middle or so,<lb/> so much the better. I have an<lb/> article on St. Patrick (to which I am<lb/> committed) for the issue of <hi rend="underline">March 17</hi>,<lb/> but it does not touch on this.<lb/> Don't forget to choose a name. If you<lb/> think of a good heading so much the better.  You will have had mother's letter.<lb/> Don't forget to write <hi rend="underline">very soon again</hi><lb/> if you want another such letter.<lb/> We are well thank God. I dont know<lb/> yet what affect the shortening of paper supplies<lb/> will have on the C.T. <seg type="closer"> With fond love form mother,<lb/> Ever affectionately  Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>