<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3521">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, to the Secretary to Council, Royal College of Surgeons of Ireland, 7 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Typescript letter informing RCSI that RCPI have &#39;amended in some particulars, and then adopted as amended&#39; the repost of the Conference Committee. The amendments appear to relate to procedures and regulations for examinations.  (See related letters RCPI/2/3/1/58/T48 and RCPI/2/3/1/58/T59 - T60)</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-146</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3521</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0845">Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date>1916-02-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0272">Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Secretary to Council, Royal College of Surgeons of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1035">Royal College of Surgeons of Ireland, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3521_img_2926_1"  type="Letter"  url="12be7b04196b5e5a57f022bf8c390ada.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3521_img_2926_2"  type="Letter"  url="1becc2aa2530faea92fd7d5482c0ee5d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3521_img_2926_1"/>
              RCP1/2/3/2/13/146    7th FEBRUARY 16.    The Secretary to Council,<lb/>R.C.S.I., Dublin.    Dear Sir,   I beg to inform you that the President and Fellows of the<lb/>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland have amended in some<lb/>particulars, and then adopted as amended, the report of the<lb/>Conference Committee with the Royal College of Surgeons in<lb/>Ireland held on the 28th ult.  The amendments adopted by this College are set out in the<lb/>accompanying paper.  There are only two of these amendments which in any way<lb/>alter the scope of the report as adopted by the Conference<lb/>Committee.  The President and Fellows are of opinion that the 'Extern-<lb/>Examiner' should set the paper or papers in conjunction with<lb/>the Professor. This is the procedure adopted in the Uni-<lb/>versitites of Dublin, Oxford and Cambridge, and in the former<lb/>University at all events the procedure has been attended with  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3521_img_2926_2"/>
             (2).  <lb/>benefit to the examinations.  In regard to the selection of clinical cases the President and<lb/>Fellows feel that the privilege accorded to the Professor is<lb/>more theoretical than real since the clinical cases that are<lb/>available have usually to be selected. The limitation of the<lb/>selection to the Professor might hence be attended with incon-<lb/>venience, since if that course were adopted no student could begin<lb/>his study of the patients until after the arrival of the Professor.<lb/>Were the Professor unavoidably prevented from attending at the<lb/>opening of the examination quite an unnecessary delay might be<lb/>caused.  The President and Fellows feel that the amendments they are<lb/>introducing do not in any way interfere with the objects desired<lb/>by the Colleges that the Professors of the Schools of Surgery<lb/>of the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland should have the<lb/>same influence in the examinations of the Students as a<lb/>Professor in a University usually has.  I remain, dear Sir,<lb/>Yours faithfully,<lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>