<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4890">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the 1918 Convention Committee, Irish Race Convention</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert E. Ford</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Requests funds for the Irish Race Convention.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>American Irish Historical Society</repository>
                  <collection>Friends of Irish Freedom, Office of the National Secretary, 1918-1939, Box 3 Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4890</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0402">Robert E. Ford</persName>
              <date>1918</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4890_img_None_1"  url="27d1bb5ddb23064021b9c1ecfd2028a4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4890_img_0_1"/>
             Telephone Cortland 373  Friends of Irish Freedom<lb/> Room 614<lb/>26 Cortlandt Street<lb/>New York City   1918 Convention Committee  Robert E Ford Chairman Peter Golden Secretary<lb/>Hugh Montague, Pasenic N.J., John F. Healy, Wilmington, Del, Michael F. O'Rourke, Brooklyn<lb/>John Curley, Boston, Mass, Michael Doherty, New Rocchelle, N.Y.<lb/>Thos. J. Mathews, Providence, R.I., Rev John H Dooley, New York<lb/>Miss Una Ford, New York   Dear Friend   As you will no doubt have seen in the newspapers by this<lb/>time, the National Executive Committee of the Friends of Irish<lb/>Freedom have decided to call a second Race Convention at the<lb/>Central Opera House, 205 East 67th St. New York, on Saturday and<lb/>Sunday, May 18th and 19th, 1918.  The wisdom of this decision is obvious to all, as well<lb/>as the need of combating the campaign of calumny and misrepre-<lb/>sentation carried on, not only against the People of Ireland and<lb/>the Cause and principles they stand for, but against the men and<lb/>women of our Race in the United States, without whose sacrifice<lb/>and assistance, in every hour of the Nation's trial, America<lb/>would not be today the proud and splendid country that it is.<lb/>A Race Convention will meet and solve successfully problems<lb/>that effect the welfare of our people here, and will, by the<lb/>wisdom and dignity of its proceedings, take the proper and<lb/>necessary steps to safeguard their interests and counter any<lb/>movement made to asperse their motives, or that would try to put<lb/>them in a false light.  To carry on the work of the Convention is <sic>is</sic> necessary<lb/>that the Commiuttee have funds as soon as possible. For this<lb/>reason we appeal to you and ask that you do everything in your<lb/>power to aid. Checks or other remittances should be made pay-<lb/>able to the Convention Committee's Treasurur, Mr. Michael F.<lb/>O'Rourke, 426-67th St., Brooklyn, N. Y.  Assuring you that no efforts will be spared to make the<lb/>Convention an epoch in the history of the Race in America,<lb/>we are   Yours respectfully<lb/>ROBERT E. FORD, Chairman, PETER GOLDEN, Secretary<lb/>Convention Committee<lb/>MICHAEL F. O'ROURKE Treasurer     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>