<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4371">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 14 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/19/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4371</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1333">30 Upper Pembroke Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4371_img_3726_1"  type="Letter"  url="1799860c8d6e2f0f20957da10547876c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4371_img_3726_2"  type="Letter"  url="9de69c80f3b97be2c392a4a73c499f28.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4371_img_3726_3"  type="Letter"  url="97fdd8221ff58e69e189d9fe6f60c71d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4371_img_3726_4"  type="Letter"  url="3c7ac603b6b8760b4c635c4e4bdc8deb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4371_img_3726_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Confidential</hi>  TELEPHONE 2794.  34   <hi rend="underline">14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Oct</hi> <lb/> 30 UPPER PEMBROKE STREET,<lb/>DUBLIN   D1507/A/19/12   My dear Ned   The situation here<lb/>is growing more dangerous every<lb/>day and I greatly fear that<lb/>Duke is unable or unwilling to<lb/>tackle it. You will under-<lb/>stand the situation better<lb/>if you read the enclosed which<lb/>is a copy of a letter I have<lb/>just written him. He is<lb/>desperately slow in making<lb/>up his mind &amp; very weak.<lb/>To give you true illustrations  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4371_img_3726_2"/>
             Hue and Cry for months was arrested a week<lb/>ago. I advised and Gen. Maxwell agreed with<lb/>me that he should be handed over &amp; tried<lb/>by Court-Martial, as Civil Trials are at<lb/>present suspended in the case of all<lb/>offences against Defence of Realm Regulations.<lb/>Duke has now directed that this man<lb/>should be had <hi rend="underline">summarily</hi> before the<lb/>Magistrates for unlawful assembly, but<lb/>I have protested against this as a farce<lb/>in the case of a man guilty of high treason 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4371_img_3726_3"/>
            <!-- This, the 3rd page is page 2 --> 35  A man named Athy who was<lb/>the ringleader of every form of<lb/>lawlessness in one of the worst<lb/>parts of Co. Galway, led the<lb/>party who on Easter Monday<lb/>attacked the Oranmore Police<lb/>Barracks &amp; fired upon the<lb/>police inside. Most of the<lb/>party were afterwards arrested<lb/>&amp; got four years penal servitude<lb/>from Courts Martial<lb/>on charges under Defence of<lb/>Realm Regulations. This man<lb/>Athy absconded and after<lb/>being on the run &amp; on the  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4371_img_3726_4"/>
             36  again I prepared many weeks<lb/>ago elaborate directions to the<lb/>Police as to seizing seditious<lb/>publications, dispersing meetings<lb/>seizing disloyal pamphlets,<lb/>badges etc but I cannot get<lb/>him to express his approval<lb/>&amp; meanwhile the Police are at<lb/>their wits end for want of a<lb/>lead. All this is <hi rend="underline">private</hi> of<lb/>course but I thought you would<lb/>like to know how the land lies.<lb/>I hope to be over for the Irish<lb/>debate on Wednesday  Yours ever.   <lb/><hi rend="underline">James</hi>  Don't refer in the House<lb/>to what I mention to<lb/>Duke about the  <lb/>  rather assurance<lb/>come about his dinner    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>