<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2308">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. E. Sinclair to Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery, 18 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. E. Sinclair</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Mrs M. E. Sinclair was a member of the Women&#39;s Union in Northern Ireland. Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery was a landowner and a Northern Ireland senator, born 14 August 1844. He spent most of his life at Blessingbourne, and was a captain of the Fermanagh militia and high sheriff of Fermanagh (1871) and Tyrone (1888). Montgomery was a firm unionist and opposed Irish Home Rule. In this letter, Sinclair writes to Montgomery to ask for his feedback on a statement describing the various feelings regarding the Solemn League and Covenant, as well as the question of Home Rule for all of Ireland. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers, D/627/429/63	</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2308</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0292">M. E. Sinclair</persName>
              <date>1916-09-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2084">Holyhill, Strabane, County Tyrone, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2308_img_1755_1"  type="Letter"  url="adff5d82bfa6e401d15c0bc3b0dfc282.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2308_img_1755_1"/>
            Copy  Hollyhill, <lb/>Strabane,   18th Sept. 1916.   Dear Mr. Montgomery,   Please do not be afraid. I do not intend to add a correspon- <lb/>dance to your busy life, but just to fill an omission in our talk.   I think I told you I had got Canon Stack to go a little slower <lb/>by the assurance I share his feelings to this extent:-   I consider it is very solemn to break our Covenant and "expediency" <lb/>is no answer - <hi rend="underline">But</hi> there is distinctly a doubt in many minds <hi rend="underline">is</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">it broken?</hi> So he drew up a fair statement of the various views <lb/>which shows the "feelings" and I placed a copy with the Women's <lb/>U. Secretary at Old Town Hall for reference if any inclined -   It has since occurred to me I would like you to read it over.   <hi rend="underline">Just mark with pencil</hi> if you note anything "not proven" please.   I would like to know if Covenant was to stop Home Rule for all <lb/>Ireland or only the Covenanter's Provinc e- Ulster,-   Just pencil margin "orthodox view". I want you to have no <lb/>trouble more than if just speaking to me please - I may repeat <lb/>that I hold the Men's Ulster Council should be quietly and con- <lb/>fidentially informed of doubts, as it is only fair to the Leader <lb/>who might possibly clear some away. But make no mistake, "expediency" <lb/>would not mean the same as "right" to all minds, though the reasoning <lb/>of "expediency" is plain.   I personally pine for someone to step forward and revive 4 Prov. <lb/>Councils idea if this Lloyd George arrangement is thrown over - <lb/>As J. Redmond accepted it before he could not object, and it would <lb/>be in the 'step by step' thoery they have steadily worked.   Yours,   M. E. Sinclair 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>