<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0254">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward H. Andrews to Lewis Harcourt, 5 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward H. Andrews</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Lewis Harcourt (1863-1922), Liberal politician, from Edward H. Andrews, the Secretary of the Chamber of Commerce. The letter acknowledges an enclosure regarding a resolution passed by the Council of the Dublin Chamber of Commerce. The enclosure states that the Council wish to express their loyalty to the king, It goes on to state that the rebellion of Easter 1916 would not have happened if not for the mismanagement of the Irish Government. It ends stating that all funds necessary to restore Dublin buildings should be provided. Although Harcourt is addressed as chief secretary of Ireland, he in fact never held the position.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5611/7876/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/254</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1327">Edward H. Andrews</persName>
              <date>1916-05-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lewis Harcourt</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0254_img_1437_1"  type="Letter"  url="6adde3b7dd28423cc2dd5803ec112337.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0254_img_1437_2"  type="Letter"  url="f96b3599659afdba1160c5f13cea34df.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0254_img_1437_1"/>
              Telephone Dublin 2575 &amp; 2576<lb/> Telegraphic address 'Commerce, Dublin' <lb/> Code-5th edition A.B.C    Chamber of Commerce  Dublin    5th May 1916   Sir,   I beg to enclose you herewith copies of resolutions unanimously<lb/> passed by the Council of the Dublin Chamber of Commerce at a<lb/> specially convened meeting held this day. <seg type="closer"> I am,<lb/> Sir,<lb/> Your obedient servant, <lb/> Edward H. Andrews <lb/> Hon. Secretary.<lb/>  Rt. Hon. Lewis Harcourt, M. P. ,  Chief Secretary for Ireland  Dublin Castle  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0254_img_1437_2"/>
              CHAMBER OF COMMERCE , <lb/> DUBLIN.<lb/> TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS<lb rend="hyphen"/>COMMERCE DUBLIN.<lb/> TELEPHONES 2575 &amp; 2576.  'The Council of the Dublin Chamber of Commerce at a Special <lb/> Meeting convened at the earliest possible opportunity <lb/> after the quelling by His Majesty's troops of the recent <lb/> disturbance, hear by assures His Gracious Majesty of the <lb/> loyalty of the Commercial Community to his person and to the<lb/> throne.  They also desire to record their abhorrence of the dreadful <lb/> scenes of murder, carnage and destruction resulting from <lb/> the action of a section of the community in the city.'  'The Council of the Dublin Chamber of Commerce desire to <lb/> place on record their considered opinion that the outbreaks<lb/> which have occurred in the Metropolis and throughout the <lb/> country should have been impossible but for the gross and <lb/> unpardonable laxity, long continued, of the administration <lb/> of the Irish Government.'  'In view of the foregoing the Council of the Dublin Chamber <lb/> of Commerce are of the opinion that the funds necessary for <lb/> restoring the buildings and the property of unoffending <lb/> citizens destroyed in the course of the rebellion should <lb/> be provided by the Imperial Treasury without delay.'  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>