<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4285">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 19 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4285</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1915-11-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1086">Tynan Abbey, Tynan, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4285_img_3649_1"  type="Letter"  url="16314ff8dc8651f7b299dd082d25a172.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4285_img_3649_2"  type="Letter"  url="425da1696930ddb4d0933bb9e46f51be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4285_img_3649_3"  type="Letter"  url="f9478d65001c652ec01b4d3d6f8b81ce.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4285_img_3649_1"/>
             or draw fine <lb/>distinction <lb/>between <lb/>Degrees <lb/>of mischief <lb/>Yrs very truly <lb/>James H. Stronge.   Nov<hi rend="superscript">r </hi>19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915   TYNAN ABBEY, <lb/>TYNAN, <lb/>Co. ARMAGH   Dear Sir Edward   I have been asked to write <lb/>to you about this present <lb/>position of <hi rend="underline">"The Home</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Defence"</hi> question. I <lb/>can't say that I am <lb/>well acquainted with <lb/>it, for, like most of <lb/>us here, I have been <lb/>trusting to our represent <lb/>-atives in the House
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4285_img_3649_2"/>
            of Commons to keep us safe <lb/>about it    But I find that there <lb/><hi rend="underline">is</hi>  an uneasy feeling <lb/>that in some way <lb/>the National Volunteers <lb/>are going to get Official <lb/>recognition &amp; to be <lb/>helped to organize them <lb/>-selves with a view <lb/>to preventing the <lb/>Amendment of the Home <lb/>Rule <seg type="del">Bill</seg> Act   I should like very <lb/>much to know your <lb/>views on this <seg type="unclear">latest</seg> <lb/>and what line our <lb/>MPs mean to adopt <lb/>in the House in <lb/>order to make this <lb/>move harmless. <lb/>Also whether we <lb/>should not have a <lb/>meeting of the Com <lb/>-mittee in Belfast <lb/>to back up any action
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4285_img_3649_3"/>
            <lb/>taken in the House. <lb/>Personally I consider <lb/><hi rend="underline">all</hi> these "Home Defense" <lb/>Volunteer Corps to <lb/>be distractions from <lb/>the main business of <lb/>providing Reserves for <lb/>the Batt<hi rend="superscript">ons</hi> now in the <lb/>Field.   It has been suggested to me <lb/>that Redmond is anxious <lb/>to have a Force with which <lb/>to keep in check the Irish <lb/>Nationalist Party. But I <lb/>do not feel much interest in <lb/>their internal rivalries
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>