<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0642">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 15 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Celia Duffin (1882-1979) to Maria Duffin, Celia writes about a recent trip to Eastbourne with her cousin Olive, giving news of the people they met. She wonders about her cousin Charley who is at war and whose mother, Mrs. Margaret Duffin, has died recently. She writes that things are very quiet at work - where she is looking after the editor of the Gazette, whom she describes as &#39;an ugly little man.&#39;This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous group living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France and with the YMCA. Celia Duffin was a VAD with the 3rd London General Hospital in Wandsworth which opened in 1914. She was an accomplished poet and published a book of poetry with her sister Ruth among other volumes.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/642</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1592">3rd London General, London SW, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0642_img_2113_1"  type="Letter"  url="c11b7eb6c9d605bd0ed4210cd59df1af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0642_img_2113_2"  type="Letter"  url="72778962cd0dbce227ca8fd5a63ee4b8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0642_img_2113_3"  type="Letter"  url="0e2e2e6fb1e45d51ac5957c8254fd333.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0642_img_2113_4"  type="Letter"  url="48350990a88959bf8ef4b074765e2f4a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0642_img_2113_5"  type="Letter"  url="7a09815bc8b58b1e3ec797e00cc0997c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0642_img_2113_1"/>
              reference D2109 /10/1/C   3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> London General  <seg type="unclear">SW</seg>     <hi rend="underline">March 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>   Dearest Mamma   Many thanks for your letter<lb/> which I got this morning as I was at East<lb/> bourne all yesterday. I heard at 9—30<lb/> that I was having my day off next day so<lb/> sent a hasty wire to Olive and in the <lb/> evening rushed home to my billets and<lb/> gathered my goods together. I missed<lb/> the first train by 5 minutes which was<lb/> bad luck and had to wait an hour<lb/> at Victoria before I got another. However<lb/> I had some tea at the station and got<lb/> to Eastbourne at about 9 o'clock.  Emmie <seg type="unclear">Hulbin</seg> is still there, a pretty little  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0642_img_2113_2"/>
              girl with a soft baby face and Miss<lb/> Roberts was very kind and gave me a<lb/> specially good dinner. It turned out <lb/> a fine day next morning so we wandered<lb/> down by the sea and then walked round<lb/> by the Goffs to see the Donnets. We met<lb/> Winnie who is pretty but rather second—<lb/> rate looking and, according to Miss<lb/> Donnet <seg type="del">has</seg> is more or less engaged to<lb/> two or 3 people at once. A little<lb/> further on we met the Colonel. I was<lb/> sorry for him he seemed so down in<lb/> his luck and so much more the<lb/> little old gentleman. He reminded me<lb/> more than ever of the rat with the <sic>astracham</sic> collar. He was asking affec—<lb/> tionally about you and seemed to<lb/> have pleasant memories of Belfast and<lb/> Dunowen teas. After lunch,<lb/> we walked over the Downs towards<lb/> Beachey Head, and it was really<lb/> pretty there and quite hot the gorse<lb/> just ready to break into flower—<lb/> We sat on a plank of wood looking<lb/> over the sea and I quite enjoyed it.<lb/> We called in to see Miss Randall's <lb/> school. <seg type="del">and</seg> It is wonderful the way<lb/> she runs it she is very dark &amp;<lb/> energetic looking and not at all<lb/> like Harry, but she reminded me  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0642_img_2113_3"/>
              of him when she suddenly swept<lb/> two large cakes off the table and<lb/> said I must take them home for<lb/> my supper. She had a funny<lb/> collection of pupils, including one<lb/> sporting old man with a white<lb/> beard, who said as it was war<lb/> time and they could not <seg type="del">to</seg> keep a<lb/> servant, he must learn to help his<lb/> wife in the kitchen.  Mrs Donnet turned up at Miss Roberts<lb/> for tea as she heard I was there. She<lb/> looks much the same as ever and <lb/> had been riding over the Downs. I <lb/> think Winnie must be a bit of a <lb/> disappointment to both of them —  Many thanks for sending  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0642_img_2113_4"/>
              me the <seg type="unclear">verses</seg> which arrived safely.<lb/> Please let me know what I owe<lb/> for them.  I am writing this on my knee<lb/> over the fire as I have an afternoon<lb/> off and it is raining outside.  Work is still slack, and a quarter<lb/> of us could easily have holidays<lb/> instead of hanging round the wards<lb/> trying to be busy. We have<lb/> only ten patients left in our<lb/> ward now, and only 3 of them<lb/> are in bed.  Olive was looking very well but<lb/> I think is very sick of her job<lb/> and needs a change. There ought<lb/> to be plenty of jobs going these days  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0642_img_2113_5"/>
              Has anything been heard of poor old<lb/> Charley yet? It is sad for him hearing<lb/> the news out there— I suppose Danes—<lb/> fortwill be closed for a bit—  I was sent in the other afternoon to<lb/> look after the Editor of the Gazette who<lb/> was alone in one of the side wards<lb/> with Bronchitis. He is an ugly little<lb/> man, in private life on the staff of<lb/> the Daily Mail, and now a stretcher<lb/> bearer. He used to be a ward orderly<lb/> before the males were banished—  Well best love, dearest, I hope<lb/> we may all meet at Dunowen<lb/> before long. <seg type="closer"> Ever your own  Celia </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>