<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0561">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert Wood to Sir Robert Chalmers, 29 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert Wood</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Herbert Wood (1861 – 1955), assistant deputy keeper with the Public Record Office, to the Under-Secretary Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 – 1938). This letter was sent by Wood to forward on the Forty-Eighth Report of the Deputy Keeper of the Public Records and Keeper of the State Papers in Ireland in accordance with the twenty-fourth section of the Public Records (Ireland) Act.Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the Easter Rising in 1916. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13090, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13090</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/561</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1203">Herbert Wood</persName>
              <date>1916-07-29T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0614">Public Record Office of Ireland, Four Courts, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0561_img_1950_1"  type="Letter"  url="1677bc70682b7439e0980b1cd535d0be.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0561_img_1950_1"/>
                PUBLIC RECORD OFFICE  OF IRELAND    29 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916    Sir   I beg to forward herewith for submission <lb/>to Their Excellencies the Lords Justices pursuant <lb/>to the twentyâfourth section of the Public <lb/>Records (Ireland) Act and with the sanction <lb/>of the Rt Hon the Master of the Rolls, the <lb/>FortyâEighth Report of the Deputy Keeper of <lb/>the Public Records and Keeper of the State <lb/>Papers in Ireland and shall be obliged <lb/>for an early acknowledgement of the <lb/>receipt  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be <lb/>Sir <lb/>Your obedient servant   Herbert Wood  Asst <hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Deputy Keeper of the Records   The Rt Hon  The Under Secretary  <hi rend="underline">Dublin Castle</hi>  </seg> <hi rend="underline">A.N.S.</hi><lb/>I think this Report is <lb/>rightly addressed to the Lords <lb/>Justices as they were in <lb/>office on the <lb/>26 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July when the Report was signed by the Deputy Keeper   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>