<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4427">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell to Sir Ivor Guest Churchill, 27 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell to Sir Ivor Guest Churchill, Lord Wimborne, concerned with the report from 8 April 1915 regarding naturalization of Max Hinden. 

Sir Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926) served as the Assistant Under Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Guest Churchill, Lord Wimborne.

Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection> NAI/CSO/RP/1916/10950</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4427</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ivor Guest Churchill</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4427_img_3779_1"  type="Letter"  url="4eeea93ab6c36df67b8ed1a938dae49e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4427_img_3779_1"/>
             27th June, 1916.   The Under Secretary of State has to inform the <seg type="del">Chief</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Constable of</seg> Under Secretary, Dublin Castle, <lb/>with reference to his report of the 8th April, 1915, <lb/>(No. 5631.) on the naturalization application of <lb/>Max Hinden, <lb/>that a certificate of naturalization was granted, the oath <lb/>of allegiance has been duly taken by the grantee, and he is <lb/>now a British subject.   The grantee being under 41 years of age, the local <lb/>recruiting authorities should be informed that he is now <lb/>a British subject, in case they desire to invite him to <lb/>enlist or to attest.   Chief Commissioner <lb/>D.M.P. <lb/>Please note and return <lb/>29.6.16.    EOF    Supt. G. <lb/>Supt A. S <seg type="unclear">Fomte</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Liam</seg> 30/6 <lb/>Noted D White Insp for Supt 3/7   C.<seg type="unclear">Hoff</seg> <lb/><hi rend="underline">5-<seg type="unclear">July</seg>-16</hi> <lb/>Noted Owen Brian Supt. G. <lb/>The Under Secretary <lb/>Noted &amp; returned <lb/>J. Quinn <lb/>Asst Comm 5/7 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>