<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3922">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Margaret McCoubrey, 14 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,612/18-28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3922</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-01-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0264">Margaret McCoubrey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3922_img_3299_1"  type="Letter"  url="27a9cb3296aef5191030cdebd986f647.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3922_img_3299_1"/>
             11, Grosvenor Place, <lb/>Rathmines, Dublin.   14 - I. - 16.   Dear Mrs. McCoubrey,   Many thanks for your letter. I am now writing to Miss Lindsay, <lb/>asking her to help.   Mrs. McCracken has sent a small donation, unsolicited, to the <lb/> IRISH CITIZEN, fund; I should hardly feel justified in asking her to <lb/> do more at present. Of course if I could get talking to them in <lb/> Belfast about it it might be different.   There may be something in Miss Lindsay's objection to bringing <lb/> me to lecture under the auspices of the Ulster centre. If no soci- <lb/>ety will take up the idea, what about forming a committee specially <lb/> to run the lecture, consisting of members representing various secti- <lb/>ons and societies? What I really want to do is to exploit,  (while it lasts)  in the <lb/> <seg type="del">interest</seg> benefit of the IRISH CITIZEN, the personal interest <lb/> that is usually felt in anyone to whom the Government has recently <lb/> given an advertisement! and I am sure there must be a good many <lb/>people in Belfast who feel that interest. It might be made a <lb/>means of drawing some of these people into your movement, even if it <lb/> were not held directly under suffrage auspices.   <hi rend="underline">F. Sheehy Skeffington</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>