<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1792">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Robert O'Connell to Sir Matthew Nathan, 1 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Robert O&#39;Connell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Sir John Robert O&#39;Connell to Sir Matthew Nathan, under-secretary for Ireland. O&#39;Connell (1868-1943) was a solicitor applying for the chief crown solicitor position. Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 until 1916. In 1916 he faced criticism for failing to be aware of and to prevent the outbreak of the Easter Rising on 24 April. He resigned shortly afterwards. 
In this letter O&#39;Connell mentions that he is sending references from Cardinal Michael Logue (1840-1924), the Archbishop of Armagh, and from John Harty (1867-1946), the Archbishop of Cashel in reference to his application for the post of chief crown solicitor. O&#39;Connell adds that he has obtained a reference from John Mangan (1853-1917), the Bishop of Kerry, to the same effect.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1792</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0595">John Robert O&#39;Connell</persName>
              <date>1916-04-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1792_img_1247_1"  type="Letter"  url="36b2df95ca71baac06ce10fece00b087.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1792_img_1247_2"  type="Letter"  url="6ad00cfba905db96e5b190b5ef1c24dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1792_img_1247_1"/>
             34, KILDARE STREET <lb/>DUBLIN.  <lb/> 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> April 1916  Dear Sir Matthew Nathan   In further reference <lb/>to my letter to you of <lb/>27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ulto I send you <lb/>herewith letter from His <lb/>Eminence Cardinal <lb/>Logue, Archbishop of <lb/>Armagh and from His <lb/>Grace Most Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <lb/>Harty Archbishop of <lb/>Cashel in reference to my
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1792_img_1247_2"/>
            application for the office <lb/>of Chief Crown Solicitor <lb/>for Ireland. I may also <lb/>add that I have received <lb/>a very strong letter from the <lb/>Most Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mangan <lb/>Bishop of Kerry to the same <lb/>effect   I remain <lb/>Dear Sir Matthew <lb/>Yours Sincerely   John Robert O' Connell  <lb/>The Right Honourable <lb/><seg type="unclear">G.C.V.O. K.E.V.O.</seg> <lb/>Sir Matthew Nathan  The Castle Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>