<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2776">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr. Daniel Colohan, Assistant Bishop of Cork, printed in ‘Free Press', 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Daniel Colohan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Langford, Riobárd (1896 -1978) was born in 1896 in Cork City and lived at Ashburton, near Mayfield, Cork and later at South Terrace, Cork. His family was originally from Cobh. His father was Charles Lankford, who worked as a printer in the Cork Examiner newspaper. 
This is a copy of letter from Dr. Daniel Colohan, Assistant Bishop of Cork, printed in ‘Free Press’ Saturday May 20th 1916. The letter concerns negotiations whereby the Irish Volunteers surrendered their arms in April 1916 and correcting the account which was given ‘in a recent issue of a London daily newspaper’. The letter gives a daily account of events, including meeting with the Lord Mayor and a British Military representative, and Volunteer leaders and men. It also details the various conditions which has been agreed for the hand over of arms and the events surrounding the hand over, including arrests of members of the Irish Volunteers and also describes the Church’s chaplaincy arrangements for volunteers in the County Gaol and in the Military Prison (near Victoria Barracks). It also includes MS. annotations by Riobárd Langford. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork City and County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>U156/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2776</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1178">Daniel Colohan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0872">Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1952</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2776_img_2192_1"  type="Letter"  url="f690fa557202edeab99968387ae5f96e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2776_img_2192_2"  type="Letter"  url="3725048eed96d28eb2892a0079e01129.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2776_img_2192_3"  type="Letter"  url="f8bd66bfa42679f2dc868c023f8708af.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2776_img_2192_1"/>
            Address to reply to :- <lb/>  C1036 James Fitzgerald,<lb/> Irish Prisoner,<lb/> (Wakefield).<lb/> c/o Chief Postal Censor,, London   Mon. night 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June 1916   P.S. Convey thanks to Mr. Campbell<lb/> and Mr. Grogan for what they've done   My Dearest Aunt and "Uncle",   Your<lb/> welcome letter reached me today, —<lb/> with stamps enclosed.l Before you<lb/> begin to read further just get <lb/> my letter to Patrick first and<lb/> read on after his, for I find<lb/> that to write to all I must<lb/> divide my news — or would you<lb/> rather call it experiences —<lb/> amongst you all, and you can<lb/> get all by reading the ones <lb/> I sent to Mother, Patk, Bob , and<lb/> <seg type="del">yourselves</seg> then the one I am<lb/> just writing to yourselves.   P.S. Convey thanks to Mrt. Campbell and Mr.Grogan for what the,ve done
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2776_img_2192_2"/>
             Wakefield is a rather dirty,<lb/> sleepy little manufacturing town,<lb/> corresponding to practically what<lb/> Carlow is in Ireland — at least<lb/> this is what the nurse, or rather<lb/> one of the nurses who so<lb/> kindly visited me, told me. Of course<lb/> I don't know, having seen<lb/> nothing excepting perhaps the<lb/> station we alighted and<lb/> of course the edifice, which at<lb/> present holds me.   This noble pile consists of<lb/> four large halls as per figure<lb/> with a large block and<lb/> tower in the centre. <lb/> Each of these halls consists<lb/> of four wards numbered1, 2,<lb/> 3, and 4. No. 1 ward is on the<lb/> ground floor, no.2 on the next<lb/> ,and so on. Each ward contains from 40 to 60 cells<lb/>. Thus I am in C Hall, no. 1 ward,<lb/> and in no 27 cell;— which<lb/> incidentally was also the number<lb/> of my cell in Cork, — thus you<lb/> can understand the "Insignia"<lb/> C1/27 on the corner of the first page. <lb/> This is also the number on the badge<lb/> which we wear for distinguishing<lb/> purposes. Thus you can see<lb/> it is in reality a convict prison<lb/> like Kilmainham and others.    We dont get black tea to<lb/> drink as mother stated — it is<lb/> black coffee and very objectionable<lb/> stuff it is, too. She guessed<lb/> right, partly, when she stated dry<lb/> bread, for they manage to give<lb/> us margarine with it for our<lb/> supper. The meat for dinner<lb/> has been easily discerned to<lb/> be horseflesh which may be
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2776_img_2192_3"/>
            nice at times. One potato, two<lb/> tablespoonfuls of beans and some<lb/> soup make up the dinner proper. <lb/> The other course is dry bread again.<lb/> Still mind you it is better than<lb/> what we got in Cork, but of that<lb/> it will be sufficient to tell<lb/> you later on. For 12 days we<lb/> suffered what Dillon described<lb/> in Parliament recently. He<lb/> erred slightly in his numbers<lb/> "22" or "23". To be strictly exact <lb/> we were 231/4 hours out of every<lb/> 24 in solitary confinement without<lb/> distraction of any kind.<lb/> However, the conditions are better<lb/> now as you can see by letter to<lb/> Mother.   To return to a nicer sphere; you mention<lb/> a Miss Carroll enquiring about me. Why<lb/> not ask her to write to me. I sure she <lb/> wouldn't refuse. Show her this. With remembrances<lb/> to all other kind friends, I conclude,<lb/>  Dear mom &amp; Lily, with love <lb/> from your loving nephew,  Jim  P.S.Rem<hi rend="superscript">ees</hi> to Mother's <seg type="unclear">ham</seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>