<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5080">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 1, November, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his mother. £20 enclosed, £10 for a canon and £10 for a birthday present for Bobbie.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5080</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-11-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5080_img_None_1"  url="81a73d947d9831a8cd312a4b98d43497.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5080_img_None_2"  url="020ecd5647fdb9eaf79d872df5c8d55b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5080_img_None_3"  url="c6046ad39c63c49dca5c28b3bd4e9576.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5080_img_0_1"/>
              <seg type="del">8</seg>1/11/17    My dear mammy <lb/>I was delighted to get your long<lb/>letter yesterday. I have not got any<lb/>of the parcels yet. I suppose they<lb/>must have been held up by the<lb/>storm. It is too bad because the<lb/>pheasants will be rotten I am afraid.<lb/>However 'tis the fortune of war and<lb/>of course game should be high<lb/>before eaten . They will all come<lb/>without a doubt . Every ones <sic>parals</sic><lb/>have been held up the same way.<lb/>Enclosed is a cheque £1 - 0.0<lb/>for the Canon. I forgot all about it<lb/>till you mentioned it yesterday<lb/>but of course I will give it <hi rend="subscript">.</hi><lb/>I am living in luxury here. I have<lb/>a nice dug out all to myself and have<lb/>all my kit up so am very comfortable .<lb/>The C.O orders me to bed every night 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5080_img_0_2"/>
             as soon as dinner is over and I<lb/>cannot say Ah! C.O. just another<lb/>5 minutes!!! I was sort of<lb/>offended at first at being ordered<lb/>to bed but last night he ordered<lb/>the major to go to bed too and he<lb/>had to go.  I have nothing at all to do. I<lb/>just go and pay visits to my<lb/>friends when I feel inclined and<lb/>keep out of the way for the remainder<lb/>of the time so as not to show<lb/>to plainly that I have nothing to<lb/>do - I am adding another 10/-<lb/>to the cheque for you to get<lb/>something for Bobbie for his<lb/>birthday. Get him anything you<lb/>or he likes. I can't' suggest<lb/>anything.  No news at all. The weather is<lb/>fine and the trenches dry so<lb/>nothing else matters at present 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5080_img_0_3"/>
             The apples did not come as yet but we<lb/>had apples and nuts galore last<lb/>night and a nice stove to roast the<lb/>chestnuts.  Wasn't that great.  I only<lb/>wish you could see us here and<lb/>you would never worry.  We are<lb/>just as happy and comfortable as<lb/>we could wish to be.  Rather an<lb/>amusing thing happened yeserday as<lb/>we were coming up the road.  We have<lb/>a new officer named Phillips.  He<lb/>was doing something wrong and the<lb/>C.O. yelled at him Can you read?<lb/>the officer said No sir: I'm Phillips  Best love to all from<lb/> Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>