<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0679">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his father, Harford Hugh Montgomery, 19 November, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Montgomery to his father, Harford Hugh (1856-1933). Montgomery thanks his father for food that he sent. This letter provides details of his time as second in command and the prospect of his becoming a lieutenant colonel. He gives a detailed account of his position in the army and his achievements.The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/679</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-11-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0757">Messrs Wm Montgomery &amp; son, 2 Wellington House, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_1"  type="Letter"  url="0947923d83afa99617f1380f90fa3985.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_2"  type="Letter"  url="099714c347de2ccfd94973e389e616e9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_3"  type="Letter"  url="43cd2a3978d0fab2383c976d35128862.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_4"  type="Letter"  url="daaa88b2e846374ef7f6c342aca2a6e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_5"  type="Letter"  url="0166ac0c7db96e115727a14001df378e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_6"  type="Letter"  url="dce745bd49b9470f72ad19ccb67f1577.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_7"  type="Letter"  url="ea1114d5f8c7f39ca239a21b0018f5c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_8"  type="Letter"  url="6101c5d8f4133873fc3f3da719cf43ef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_9"  type="Letter"  url="1682d71d1d15f25af49b68de225a83d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0679_img_2171_10"  type="Envelope"  url="d35a525b3d51bbcf36d1801d2c9ef534.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_1"/>
              Replied  <hi rend="underline">26 Octr 1916</hi>     In the Field    19.11.16   My Dear Father/   I have to acknowledge <lb/> your very interesting letter of 11<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> inst <lb/> also to convey my thanks for the <lb/> bread and two pots of lemon cheese <lb/> which <hi rend="underline">did</hi> turn up quite all right. <lb/> A little more stale than you would <lb/>touch at home, but one afternoon <lb/> tea just absolutely finished the <lb/> whole bag of tricks <hi rend="underline">almost</hi> including <lb/> the paper wrappings.  Yes. I would love that <lb/> salvage amusement. I fear for a <lb/> year or two after this thing finishes <lb/> I shall miss the movement and <lb/> excitement of it terribly  No sign of Horace yet. There <lb/> would appear to be some considerable <lb/> delay in the arrival of his relief where <lb/> he is now. We are all at a loss to <lb/> understand what has caused this <lb/> delay as almost a month ago we got <lb/> official <seg type="unclear">information</seg> to the effect that <lb/> he would be with us quite soon.  Today, like other days, I of <lb/> course expect Horace to arrive &amp; I go <lb/> back to command my Coy. but instead  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_2"/>
              I find myself in command of the <lb/> Battalion. About 4oc.p.m. the C.O. got a <lb/> wire telling him to take over command <lb/> of a Brigade. He didn't know where it was, <lb/> who they are, or anything but he left <lb/> here to take them over at <hi rend="underline">5.35</hi>p.m.  Mother would think it a frightful <lb/> rush. Some career in this war <lb/> he has already had. Captain to <lb/> Temporary Brigadier General in two <lb/> years &amp; a month. He told me before <lb/> he left that he would send for me <lb/> just as soon as he finds a good job <lb/> for me - preferably a staff job.  Our Adjutant has also had a career <lb/> in this war - Thro' Mons as <hi rend="underline">a Corporal <lb/> in the Grenadier Guards</hi>, also Aisne on <lb/> the Marne wounded, got his Commission <lb/> posted 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Lieut East Lancs. attached to <lb/> us as 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> &amp; Adjutant promoted Lieut <lb/> then Captain &amp; Adjutant &amp; now he will <lb/> probably follow the C.O. as brigade <lb/> Major. Before this thing finishes <lb/> there will be some extraordinary <lb/> records of service. For instance, my <lb/> own in its way is odd enough  I have been wearing a major's crown <lb/> for about a week now, because I  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_3"/>
              have been performing the duties of 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/> in Command of a Batt for upwards of 30 <lb/> days. I will also continue to draw pay as <lb/> such until some one senior to me joins <lb/> when I revert to my rank as Captain. <lb/> Again, if by any chance, I am left in <lb/> command of the Batt. for 30 days I will <lb/> be given permission to put up a <lb/> star in addition &amp; become for all <lb/> practical purposes a Lieut. Colonel. <lb/> Extraordinary when one thinks of it?  The responsibility is, of course, heavy <lb/> but I am glad to say it does not now <lb/> &amp; never has worried me in the very <lb/> slightest. Settling a £50 loss has often <lb/> caused me a lot more worry &amp; I didn't <lb/> do it as well. Some little time ago I was <lb/> officially approached to see if I would <lb/> take a permanent commission, but <lb/> I said most definitely &amp; finally - NO I <lb/> would hate it in peace time anyway <lb/> apart altogether from all the other <lb/> impossibilities. If by any chance I <lb/> happened to get knocked out whilst I <lb/> wear the crown as Major Montgomery <lb/> (as I just now find myself) Emmie would <lb/> draw a Major's pension. It is a <lb/> great war &amp; as my old namesake <lb/> foreman used to say 'You never know  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_4"/>
              the minute'. Please don't address my <lb/> letters as 'Major'. It is quite correct <lb/> to do so&amp; all that &amp; I sign my name <lb/> as such but I don't care about it <lb/> until such time as it may in the <lb/> future appear in the Gazette.  The much more gratifying part <lb/> of the business to both you &amp; me is <lb/> undoubtedly the fact that a very <lb/> pukka regular Brigadier is satisfied <lb/> to leave me responsible for a Battalion <lb/> front in the line. It all goes down <lb/> on an official document known as <lb/> my record of service &amp; I don't lose by <lb/> it in the end, even if I do revert to <lb/> Captain again for a bit. From what <lb/> Brigadier General F.P. Crozier said to me <lb/> just before he left, it won't be for long <lb/> if he can help it. I have some good <lb/> friends at court here apart altogether <lb/> from my late C.O. No more Coy. <lb/> cmdg. for me if I can possibly <lb/> avoid it. I have 13 months of it to <lb/> my credit &amp; I like my present <lb/> temporary job - <hi rend="underline">no, my this morning's <lb/>temporary job</hi> much better. I also <lb/> have a great curiosity to do a bit of <lb/> the staff end of the game. In fact <lb/> if it lasts as long as I think it will  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_5"/>
              the sooner I start the Staff side the <lb/> better for me. Don't bother about <lb/> a fountain pen nib for me thanks <lb/> I rather fancy a pal of mine in <lb/> town intends to send me a whole <lb/>complete pen.  This game presents extraordinary <lb/> contrasts conditions &amp; circumstances. <lb/> I was just thinking of this tonight <lb/> at dinner &amp; comparing our present <lb/> circumstances with those which <lb/> prevailed with us last winter. As I <lb/> sit commanding a Batt in the line tonight <lb/> I am not at all certain that I am <lb/> not quite as comfortable as you are.  Counting a Doctor, a Chaplain &amp; an <lb/> Artillery <sic>Liason</sic> Officer we set down <lb/> 11 to dinner - <hi rend="underline">my</hi> H.Q. mess. We had <lb/> excellent soup. Beautiful Fresh sole, <lb/> very good roast beef &amp; Yorkshire <lb/> pudding, , stewed figs &amp; custard, Coffee. <lb/><sic>Savories</sic> we cut out some ten <lb/> days ago because we could only <lb/> manage 4 kinds &amp; we are tired <lb/> of those for a bit. To drink we have <lb/> a coice of anyhting one likes. <lb/> The only thing there is any <lb/> difficulty about is liqueurs. I <lb/> Personally drink the best of good  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_6"/>
              Guinness Stout &amp; every now &amp; then <lb/> I get a few of the best cigars, either <lb/> given me or bought by me when <lb/> I dine out in style. You will <lb/> think it ridiculous, I know, but <lb/> nevertheless the men love their <lb/> officers to have good sticks &amp; whips <lb/> &amp; spurs &amp; <seg type="unclear">kit</seg> &amp; to smoke good stuff.  Do you remember those spurs you <lb/> were good enough to send me. Wel l<lb/> the first day I wore them, one of <lb/> my sergeants, accompanied by <lb/> a sergeant of another unit came <lb/> to my temporary home &amp; asked me <lb/> to settle a bet. It appeared he had bet <lb/> the other fellow they were silver. I <lb/> was sorry to disappoint him, but <lb/> that is the point &amp; the spirit. And <lb/> no one can even dimly estimate <lb/> its value when it comes to <lb/> leading &amp; obedience in face of <lb/> the last thing in grim hellishness.  No one knows just what little <lb/> thing one does or says to a man or <lb/> men which makes them yours in <lb/> all things when the big times come.  I know of several cases where <lb/> this has undoubtedly been so.  Our men are also just as  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_7"/>
              comfortable as constant thought <lb/> &amp; unremitting labour can make <lb/> them. It is however necessary that <lb/> officers are maintained <hi rend="underline">very</hi> comfortable <lb/> in order that they can be at their <lb/> best to do the best either for their <lb/> men or in the use of them.  The old 'share the hardships of <lb/> their men idea' which is so truly <lb/> British is still with us but <lb/> modified. The Bosch started this <lb/> war so very much more scientifically <lb/> than we did &amp; this was one of his <lb/> great points.  I dont suppose you get time for <lb/> much reading, but if you do &amp; you <lb/> care to read a really human <lb/> readable history of this war get <lb/> the Strand Magazine. It is <lb/> excellent &amp; your son knows <lb/> almost every little rise &amp; fall of <lb/> ground &amp; line of much of the line <lb/> that is there written of.  It will give you a faint <lb/> impression of what our original <lb/> Expeditionary Force did &amp; was. No <lb/> one can really know just what <lb/> it was except those who were <lb/> through the first 6 months of it.  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_8"/>
              But perhaps with your old Puritan <lb/> Blood  you  wont care about it. Still <lb/> as effort alone it stands as <lb/> colossal. I am convinced now <lb/> that the end is certain &amp; that we <lb/> will be the senior survivors. If <lb/> it is protracted as long as I think <lb/> it will be, the expression 'WIN' will <lb/> not be accurately applicable in its <lb/> popular sense. I forgot in <lb/> describing our mess to mention that <lb/> some of my young officers are <lb/> now playing Ping pong whilst one <lb/> with whom we dined is prowling <lb/> about NO MANS LAND on patrol &amp; <lb/>others are inspecting the line &amp; <lb/> sentries &amp; guns etc etc etc &amp; so <lb/> it goes on. The really awful part <lb/> of the thing is that this time <lb/> 2 years ago I was junior 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Lieut <lb/> on a month's probation in the <lb/> Battalion I tonight command &amp; am <lb/> the only officer with it tonight who <lb/> have served in France etc right <lb/>thro' with it. It is one of the <lb/> most decorated if not <hi rend="underline">the</hi> most <lb/> decorated Battalion in our Corps. <lb/>It is by far the most decorated <lb/> Batt. in our Division &amp; that is  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_9"/>
              a very special honour to begin <lb/> with. The awful pity of it is <lb/> that more of our home birds <lb/><sic>arnt</sic> coming out to us. I would <lb/> rather have them than any <lb/> others in all the world.  Well this all seems to be about <lb/> me, but there is so little else I <lb/> am permitted to write about that <lb/> you will please accept this fact <lb/> as my excuse.  I am well &amp; in the very best of <lb/> form &amp; very much looking <lb/> forward to my next leave <lb/> which I hope to have in the <lb/> forepart of next month.  All my love to mother <seg type="closer"> Your affectionate son  <hi rend="underline">WM</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0679_img_2171_10"/>
               <hi rend="underline">26 October 1916</hi>     Harford H. Montgomery Esq  c/o Messrs W<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi> Montgomery &amp; Son  2 Wellington Place  <hi rend="underline">Belfast</hi>    PASSED FIELD CENSOR 2188  <hi rend="underline">WA Montgomery</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>