<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5646">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter of receipt to Mary O'Leary and copy of her original letter, 3 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Secretary to the Director</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter acknowledging the receipt of Mary O&#39;Leary&#39;s letter concerning the appointment of a dressmaker and nurse to the asylum at Killarney.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_3755_5_4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5646</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0363">Secretary to the Director</persName>
              <date>1916-02-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary O&#39;Leary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0682">Scartaglen, Farranfore, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5646_img_738_1"  type="Letter"  url="a309fc7eca364d079212de163b028973.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5646_img_738_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="a75f7489c57f472b53822133eacfe02b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5646_img_738_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="bae197c1cf8182063fa69757d9e32821.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5646_img_738_1"/>
             3rd February, 1916  252  Madam,   I am directed by the Inspectors to acknowledge<lb/>the receipt of your communication of the 1st instant,<lb/>and to inform you that the appointment of a Dressmaker<lb/>and Nurse in the Killarney District Asylum is vested<lb/>solely in the Committee of Management, to which body<lb/>any representations you may wish to make on the<lb/>subject should be addressed.   I am<lb/>Madam<lb/>Your Obedient Servant <lb/><lb/><lb/> Miss Mary O' Leary<lb/>Scartglen<lb/>Farranfore,<lb/>Co Kerry  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5646_img_738_2"/>
             252<lb/> Scartglen,<lb/>Farranfore<lb/>Co. Kerry <lb/> 1/2/'16 <lb/> Sir,   May I most respectfully call your<lb/>attention to the appointment of<lb/>Dressmaker and Nurse, which has been<lb/>carried through at the last meeting<lb/>of Committee of Managmenr, Killarney<lb/>District Lunatic Asylum.  The meeting was held on the 27 Inst<lb/>and out of three applicants one was<lb/>only qualified as regards age; Miss Cremmin<lb/>was therefore duly elected as Seamstress<lb/>for a month pending observations from<lb/>Matron and R.M.S 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5646_img_738_3"/>
             2  Miss Cremmin had only one testimonial<lb/>accompanying her application, and<lb/>that one was from a local dressmaker<lb/>certifying that Miss Cremmin gave a<lb/>few months apprenticeship, she<lb/>produced no more credentials. —May<lb/>I point out, Sir, that the advertisement<lb/>issued for this important position<lb/>was : — that the lady elected should<lb/>be able to cut material, sew for the<lb/>female part of the house, possess a<lb/>knowledge of Nursing &amp; Housewifery,<lb/>and keep book-accounts, also responsible<lb/>for same when Matron is absent.  Miss Cremmin, Sir, does not show<lb/>or present <hi rend="underline">any</hi> qualifications what-<lb/>so-ever, and many of the members<lb/>of the Committee visibly expressed  3   the opinion that Miss Cremmin<lb/>was literally unqualified for the<lb/>position, and yet she was dumped<lb/>into a job that honestly she<lb/>knows nothing about.      May I also point out Sir, that<lb/>Miss Cremmin's mother died in<lb/>the Asylum some time ago, and at<lb/>present her aunt and first cousin<lb/>are there.  The facts are really valid and<lb/>I was one of the applicants fully<lb/>qualified only a fortnight short<lb/>of the age.   Thanking you in anticipation<lb/>for a favourable reply.   Signed — Mary O'Leary<lb/><lb/>3775/6 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>