<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3724">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edith Sanderson to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 10 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edith Sanderson regarding recent personal events and to tell her that they can not write an article for the upcoming &#34;Citizen&#34; edition. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/13-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3724</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_1"  type="Letter"  url="2e93c10633d063725f2649002c92c4c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_2"  type="Letter"  url="0fa591bae7932398bc787c2893ddc8ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_3"  type="Letter"  url="7e96eeb3a39fddeb5774acff53f3537d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_4"  type="Letter"  url="ea878075a63a3461292f9a02d96dd86f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_5"  type="Letter"  url="48438eeeac93de62d10a078db0306da6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_6"  type="Letter"  url="4ec3b1cd79ff6a404e6ca4554871fb19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3724_img_3113_7"  type="Letter"  url="f30a47996934d2f5547abe77ba2a6d1b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_1"/>
             7 Mt Temple Tce <lb/><seg type="unclear">Dalkey</seg> Rd   <hi rend="underline">Nov 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington   I went to the Four Courts this <lb/>morning &amp; heard the Seduction <lb/>Case Seeds v. Becks. I wish most heartily <lb/>I knew more of the ropes— I wonder if <lb/>it could be possible for Miss Duggan <lb/>to give those anxious to attend Court <lb/>a few hints as to legal positions <lb/>procedure etc! This Case appeared <lb/>very peculiar to my ignorant eyes. <lb/>The two Counsel were deep in <lb/>conversation when M Staunton &amp; I got into <lb/>our seats at five minutes to eleven. <lb/>&amp; at five minutes past they were <lb/>still discussing the case. I could <lb/>catch a word here &amp; there &amp; <lb/>I suspected the matter would be <lb/>settled out of court however <lb/>his Lordship made his appearance
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_2"/>
            (Mr Justice Dodd) to be told he was rather <lb/>soon! So he retired. Then the Registrar <lb/>who went out with him came &amp; <lb/>beckoned to the plaintiff Counsel <lb/>who also retired! At last they all <lb/>came back. &amp; I heard the plaintiff's <lb/>Counsel say "That's all right - I'll <lb/>just say ------------- something or <lb/>other. The jury was sworn &amp; the <lb/>case stated in a few words. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Bech.</seg>, a young farmer aged 21 had <lb/>seduced Lizzie Seeds aged 24 eldest <lb/>daughter of — Seeds farmer the seduction <lb/>had been denied but that was <lb/>withdrawn &amp; the matter for the jury would <lb/>simply be a question of damages — <lb/>Then the girl a slim delicate looking <lb/>creature very "<hi rend="underline">ladylike</hi>"! was put in <lb/>the witness box. The judge objected <lb/>saying "<hi rend="underline">"I understand</hi> our purpose <lb/>is to <seg type="unclear">save</seg> the girl. So she may stand <lb/>down. We only want to prove position <lb/>etc. Call the father." The father
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_3"/>
             3  an eminently respectable, indeed <lb/>fine looking man of superior class <lb/>gave evidence as to his daughters age. <lb/>Mother delicate family of 6. Eldest <lb/>girl practically mistress of the farm. <lb/>Baby born March. Girl and child still <lb/>living with him &amp; he intended keeping them, <lb/>told what he knew <lb/>of defendant well to do farmer <lb/>aged 21. <hi rend="underline">Nothing more.</hi>. JW Justice <lb/>Dodd then turned to the jury &amp; said <lb/>that in view of the fact that the <lb/>boy had withdrawn the denial to <lb/><hi rend="underline">spare the girl</hi>he would simply <lb/>ask the jury to award £120. <lb/>Remembering that the boy was a minor <lb/>&amp; in fact <seg type="del">to do so</seg> the common sense <lb/>plan with the law was always <lb/>the best &amp; he thought such a verdict <lb/><sic>wld</sic> satisfy everyone — this was <lb/>agreed to with some question <lb/>of waiting 21 days, which I couldn't <lb/>understand or follow. But Oh
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_4"/>
            the callousness of the whole affair! of <lb/>course the girl had been to blame. It <lb/>takes two but she had suffered <lb/>more than any <hi rend="underline">man</hi> could ever guess <lb/>&amp; to have these men laugh &amp; <lb/>quote Shakespere's Connection <lb/>with Anne Hathaway, talk about <lb/>human nature &amp; dismiss that <lb/>girl &amp; her baby with a wave of <lb/>the hand &amp; the insufficient <lb/>sum of £120 made my blood <lb/>boil. I overheard two men say talk as <lb/>we left court — one said — "Im <lb/>glad that case was settled like <lb/>that" "Yes" said the other "I hate <lb/>these cases"! That was all! That <lb/>silly brazen looking boy got off <lb/>with a lightened pocket. The <lb/>girl has a millstone round <lb/>her neck for the rest of her life. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_5"/>
              My <seg type="unclear">jury once</seg> makes it impossible <lb/>for me to write anything for <lb/>the Citizen but perhaps you <lb/>can pick a word or two out <lb/>of this that might serve.   Friday is the Conference of <lb/>reference to Women position <lb/>in Industry. They want me to <lb/>write an account for your paper
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_6"/>
             6  I wish I had chosen someone <lb/>better able but I'll do my best <lb/>to send you an idea as to how <lb/>things go. With heaps of <lb/>apologies for this scrawl.   <sic>Yrs vy</sic> sincerely   <hi rend="underline">Edith Sanderson</hi>   I was at Lady Wrights this afternoon <lb/>a "Dublin Union of Women Workers" <lb/>is <seg type="foreign">fait accompli</seg>, the Vice presidents <lb/>were chosen, also provisional <lb/>Committee. Miss James of the <lb/>U.U.W.W. spoke splendidly. The idea <lb/><seg type="unclear">if</seg> <seg type="unclear">Gork</seg> if it could be worked — <lb/>the <hi rend="underline">Cooperation</hi> of all women <lb/>workers of all shades of opinions <lb/>&amp; aims, I guess the Joint Committee <lb/>may lapse! Lady <seg type="unclear">Fryell</seg>. Lady <lb/>Arnott, Lady Wright. Mrs Haslam &amp; <lb/>Mrs White &amp; another are Vice president <lb/>Miss R. Barrett. Miss Buchanan. Miss Hayden
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3724_img_3113_7"/>
            Mrs   etc. etc. are on the <lb/>provisional Committee. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>