<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2266">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jerome J. Ronayne to Margaret O'Brien, 14 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jerome J. Ronayne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Jerome J. Ronayne, town clerk, Urban District of Midleton, County Cork, Ireland, to Margaret O&#39;Brien.

Mrs. O&#39;Brien has applied for permission to move her deceased husband&#39;s remains from one grave to another within the Protestant church graveyard.
As sanitation authority for the area, the Midleton Urban District Council approves the move, provided she gets the consent of the church authorities.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/10140/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2266</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0911">Jerome J. Ronayne</persName>
              <date>1916-06-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2120">Midleton, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Margaret O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2066">The Green, Midleton, County Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2266_img_1709_1"  type="Letter"  url="391bdef1525f0eab8d06dae040ad4643.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2266_img_1709_1"/>
             JEROME J. RONAYNE <lb/>TOWN CLERK   Urban District of Midleton, <lb/>CO. CORK,   14th. day of June 1916   Mrs. Margaret O'Brien, <lb/>The Green, <lb/>MIDLETON   Dear Madam/   With reference to your application for <lb/>permission to remove the remains of your husband <lb/>from one grave to another in the burial ground <lb/>attached to the Protestant Church, I am directed <lb/>by the Midleton Urban District Council to inform <lb/>you that they, as Sanitary Authority for the <lb/>District, express their consent to this course, <lb/>on the understanding that you are able to obtain the <lb/>consent of the church Authorities.   Yours faithfully   <hi rend="underline">Jerome J. Roynane</hi>   I. Instruct police not to interfere <lb/>with Mrs. O'Brien or her agents <lb/>when engaged in the transfer <lb/>of the remains   II. Inform Mrs. OBrien.   III. —   <lb/>EOF <lb/>16:6:16 <lb/>I.II done 07/6
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>