<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5855">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Anne MacDonald to Lady Clonbrock, 3 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Anne MacDonnell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Anne MacDonnell, honorary secretary of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton). The Irish Women&#39;s Association was set up to provide aid and assistance to Irish regiments and to Irish members of the British army who were being held in prisoner of war camps.
McDonnell writes with a list of items sent to members of the Connaught Rangers</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No 54; Ms. 35,796</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5855</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1071">Anne MacDonnell</persName>
              <date>1916-02-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1880">65 Victoria Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5855_img_953_1"  type="Letter"  url="835162e6ec9c517dd4be0412fd7e65c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5855_img_953_2"  type="Letter"  url="de6aff8d02f3014ed23560aa616873c4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5855_img_953_1"/>
             The Irish Women's Association <lb/>(to aid Irish Regiments and Prisoners of War), <lb/>65, Victoria Street <lb/>London S.W.   The clothing which we send by order to <lb/> Prisoners of War consists of four parcels to <lb/>each man, the contents being: <lb/>Thick Greatcoat. <lb/>Coat and trousers (very warm) <lb/>Thick cardigan. <lb/>2 flannel shirts. <lb/>2 warm vests. <lb/>2 warm pants. <lb/>2 pairs of socks. <lb/>Cap. <lb/>Gloves. <lb/>1 pr. Boots. <lb/>1 pr. Canvas Shoes. <lb/>The Connaught Rangers are almost all provided <lb/>with this complete outfit. Those who are not  yet   <lb/>provided for, will be by the end of this week. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5855_img_953_2"/>
             1916 - Feb. 3   <hi rend="underline">Lady McDonnell</hi>   List of clothes sent. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>