<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5955">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert A. Johnson, Royal Mint, to Edward Carter Preston, 25 January 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert A. Johnson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Liverpool Record Office</repository>
                  <collection>Edward Carter Preston, 730 PRE, 4/7/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5955</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0328">Robert A. Johnson</persName>
              <date>1923-01-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0133">Royal Mint, London E.1., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Carter Preston</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5955_img_None_1"  url="phpdHPpO6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5955_img_None_2"  url="phpJLE5Qz.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5955_img_0_1"/>
             730 PRE 4/7/2   ROYAL MINT, LONDON, E.J.,    25th January, 1923.    Dear Carter Preston,   Your letter of the 23rd inst. I am glad that<lb/>you are ready to have a shy at the Great Seal for<lb/>Northern Ireland.    As regards the wording of any<lb/>inscription, it is suggested that the inscription should<lb/>only appear on the Seal bearing the effigy of His<lb/>Majesty on horseback;  and not on the Counterseal which<lb/>is to be armorially treated.    As regards the words, I<lb/>find that the following words appear on the King George<lb/>V. Great Seal for England:-  GEORGIUS V.D.G: BRITT: ET TERRARUM TRANS MAR<lb/>QUAE IN DIT: SUNT BRIT: REX F: D: IND: IMP:  I see that the Counterseal also has Dieu et mon driot<lb/>inscribed upon it both in the Georgian and Edwardian<lb/>Seals, but we doubt whether this is necessary.  As regards date for submitting designs, there<lb/>is no great pressure about an important matter like a<lb/>Great Seal, and I do not wish to hurry you.   Perhaps<lb/>you would kindly, therefore, let me know within what<lb/>sort   E. Carter Preston, Esq.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5955_img_0_2"/>
             sort of time you think you could be ready to<lb/>send your designs in?  Believe me,   Yours sincerely,    Robert A Johnson  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>