<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0524">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Collins to Mollie Woods, 24 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Collins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Michael Collins (1890 - 1922) to Mary (Mollie) Woods, written from Stafford Prison. Collins writes of an impending transfer to &#39;the old camp&#39;, most likely Frongoch, and notes that, although the conditions are supposedly more unpleasant there, he shall be happy to be reunited with friends in the camp. Collins also warns of a rumour that prisoners will only be permitted to send one letter a week and so he may not be able to write to Woods for a time. Michael Collins (1890-1922) served as aide-de-camp to Joseph Plunkett in the GPO during the Rising and was imprisoned in Frongach. He went on to become Minister for Finance in the First Dáil, IRA Director of Information and President of the Provisional Government.Mary (Mollie) Woods, wife to Andrew Woods, was an active member of Cumann na mBan after joining in 1916. Although Mollie did not participate in the Easter Rising the family were well connected within the Republican movement and actively participated in the War of Independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Museum of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>HE, EW.1351</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/524</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1129">Michael Collins</persName>
              <date>1916-06-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2031">Stafford Prison, Stafford, Staffordshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mollie Woods</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0524_img_1896_1"  type="Letter"  url="63eca759fcfad4d12c7a282f8c2c224e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0524_img_1896_2"  type="Letter"  url="b9227c6d8296c1b79231c1b0729b6452.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0524_img_1896_1"/>
              They tell me that <lb/> the cream has <lb/> improved my<lb/> complexion.<lb/> Much obliged<lb/> for sending<lb/> it.<lb/> Remember me to <lb/> Murnaine etc.    Irish Prisoner u8F  Stafford    June 24th 16   Dear Mollie    Very many thanks <lb/> indeed for that parcel. The <lb/> fruit especially was <lb/> beautiful. Indeed I don't <lb/> know in the world what I <lb/> shall ever be able to do for <lb/> all my friends who are being <lb/> so kind.  I think we shall be <lb/> off to the old camp sometime <lb/> during this coming week. <lb/> By all accounts it will hardly <cb/> be a change for the better <lb/> but at any rate we shall <lb/> have some beautiful scenery. <lb/><seg type="del">by all a</seg> also a dismantled <lb/> brewery or distillery. This <lb/> latter will recall happy <lb/> memories at any rate.  I was very pleased <lb/> to hear some account of Dan <lb/> Murphy. He never answered <lb/> a letter which I wrote him about <lb/> November last so we have got<lb/> out of touch. They can all <lb/> be having a good laugh at us <lb/> now but I don't think they <lb/> are somehow. Even if <lb/> the Camp is a more unpleasant  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0524_img_1896_2"/>
              place than this it is something <lb/> to look forward to meeting many <lb/> of my old friends again.   We've been doing <lb/> greatly here for the last few <lb/> days. Someone brought in <lb/> a melodion &amp; a flute so we <lb/> so we have music go leor. It will <lb/> be better still when we get to <lb/> the camp. I'm afraid though <lb/> that we shall be only allowed <lb/> to write one letter each week <lb/> so it will take me some time <lb/> to reach all my friends. <lb/> Of course we may receive <lb/> all the letters that are sent us.  We had Mr Ginnell <cb/> here not long since. He said<lb/> a few words to us and we <lb/> gave him a great ovation.  Well goodbye - if <lb/> you don't hear from me you'll <lb/> know it's because we are on the <lb/> one letter a week. I hope <lb/> Statia &amp; Bessie are having <lb/> a fine time in the old <lb/> country. I fear it will be some<lb/> time before any of us see it <lb/> again. <seg type="closer"> With many thanks <lb/> &amp; best wishes <lb/> Yours Sincerely   M Collins </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>