<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1992">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kevin R. O’Shiel to Diarmid Coffey, 23 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kevin R. O’Shiel </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Diarmid Coffey (1888-1964) joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914 and became secretary of the Irish National Volunteers after the organisation split in 1915 (it was the other group who participated in the Rising). He later served as assistant clerk of the Seanad.
Kevin Roantree O&#39;Shiel (1891-1970) also joined the Irish Volunteers but left after the split and became increasingly influenced by separatism, joining the Irish National League, then Sinn Féin and later served as a judge for the Dáil Land Commission.
In the letter, O&#39;Shiel refers to a missed opportunity to meet with Coffey while both were in Omagh. He refers to the work of the Irish National League and begs Coffey to cut ties with the Irish Parliamentary Party (&#39;the rotten old British imperial party&#39;) and join the INL.
The INL (originally the Anti-Partition League) was originally founded by northern nationalists to oppose the Irish Parliamentary Party.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Coffey &amp; Chenevix Trench Papers, Collection List No 153; Ms. 46,307/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1992</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1225">Kevin R. O’Shiel </persName>
              <date>1916-08-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0521">Hill View Cottage, Fougher, Port na Blagh, County Donegal</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0284">Diarmid Coffey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1970</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1992_img_144_1"  type="Letter"  url="915f131b7d632c6e7caa917d5bc78941.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1992_img_144_2"  type="Letter"  url="e24f406e1e94eaaf0d2f036610d3c2d3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1992_img_144_1"/>
             Hill View Cottage, <lb/>Tougher, Ballymore P.O. <lb/>Port-na-Blagh <lb/>Co. Donegal   23-viii-'16   My Dear Coffey,/    You must excuse me for my seeming <lb/> rudeness in not seeing you when you passed through <lb/> Omagh the other day &amp; in not writing you until now, <lb/> but really you can't know how busy I've been with <lb/> the I.N.L. campaign. I should certainly have made <lb/> it my business to get you that day you were in Omagh <lb/> had you given me any data. When you were not on the <lb/> morning train from Derry I concluded that you had not <lb/> come. I was in the Herald office until just a quarter <lb/> of an hour before you came. I hear you remained <lb/> in Omagh until 4oc. Is that so? Why in the <lb/> name of Goodness did you not turn up to us? <lb/> I am here for a bit of a holiday. We are only about <lb/> 8 miles from Cloghaneely. Do you know of any
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1992_img_144_2"/>
            stalwarts there that it would be worth my while interviewing? <lb/> The people here are all splendidly anti—English &amp; <lb/> anti—Partition &amp; this is Dr.O'Donnell's Tetrarchy! <lb/> I am pleased to say that the I.N.L. is going along <lb/> bonnily. I have already asissted at the establishment <lb/> of 5 branches &amp; we have now over 40 on our <lb/> books. When are you coming in? For Heaven's sake <lb/> leave the rotten old Imperial British Party in Ireland; <lb/> it is contaminating even to be a passive supporter <lb/> of it. Write a strong letter to the paper denouncing <lb/> them &amp; join us. This is a time when no Irishman <lb/> can afford to hide his light under a bushel.    Did you see that we have several branches already <lb/> established in London  &amp; other English towns  &amp; preparations have <lb/> been made to establish branches in the States. <lb/>I sent you a copy of the "Fermanagh Herald" the other day giving <lb/> account of our great meeting there. I shall send in <lb/> some of our papers from time to time.   Yours Ever, <lb/>Kevin R.O'Shiel 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>