<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3917">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Miss Lawless, 1 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,612/18-14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3917</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-02-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lawless</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3917_img_3294_1"  type="Letter"  url="ae01a08d6b8d901a3e15912190d0415e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3917_img_3294_1"/>
             11 Grosvenor Place, <lb/>Rathmines  <lb/>2014; 2014;16  <lb/> Dear Miss Lawless,  <lb/>I have heard of you for a long time, and I have no idea how <lb/>you regard my latest essays in rebellion. Never the less, I venture <lb/>o appeal to you once more on behalf of the IRISH CITIZEN. <lb/> You may remember (I think I wrote to you about it at the time) <lb/>that in September 1914, in order to meet the printers pressing de-; <lb/>mands, I raised a loan of £100 from a bank, on a guarantee signed by <lb/>three names in addition to my own. Owing to the continuous, (though <lb/>slight) loss on the paper, I have not been able to pay off this; nor <lb/>would the bank press for repayment so long as the interest is paid <lb/>regularly, which of course has been done. Now, however, one of the <lb/>guarantors withdraws her name, 2014;because she favours conscription, <lb/>and objects to the line we have taken with regard to that matter. <lb/>Unless I can find a third name to replace that withdrawn, the bank <lb/> will call up the entire sum, which at present would be disastrous. <lb/>Could you assist me in this emergency, or suggest anyone who would? <lb/>It is very difficult to find anyone of financial stability who does <lb/>not object to the IRISH CITIZEN (or to its proprietor) on some ground <lb/>or other!   The other two guarantors (whose names I will give you on hearing <lb/>that you are prepared to consider the matter) are both good financial sureties.   <hi rend="underline">user comment</hi>All letters sent to me through the post are opened by the secret <lb/>censorship, 2014; steamed and 2014;gummed. A note left in at the I.W.F.L <lb/>rooms would reach me.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>