<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0676">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 2 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson describing the various logistical tasks and difficulties. He thanks various family members for their correspondence, and explains that the Bangor Ladies should not send any comforts to the men they will be left behind if a move takes place. He also asks his family for help in the replenishment of his uniform (particularly boots and leather leggings), as well as medicine. Since the letter is written in Dec, he asks for no presents as there is no room in his luggage.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/676</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-12-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0676_img_2169_1"  type="Letter"  url="2c532f69cfa1231f9e139a9ae347c465.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0676_img_2169_2"  type="Letter"  url="a0679ce775b33db11c2a84c6db76697a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0676_img_2169_3"  type="Letter"  url="1c6b8814a8ec94125488200e92d84633.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0676_img_2169_4"  type="Envelope"  url="a342379d89f403cbd19e87c333cf5624.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0676_img_2169_1"/>
                2/12/15   My dearest Mother   I have practically <lb/>no news since I wrote <seg type="unclear">you</seg> on <lb/> Sunday as we have all simply <lb/> been settling down and making <lb/> arrangements for re-starting <lb/> the various kinds of training. <lb/> For instance I had to hunt about <lb/> for an M.G. range &amp; when I found <lb/> one, have it inspected &amp; and get the <lb/> necessary permits from the <lb/> French Authorities. This has <lb/> now all been done &amp; we <lb/> begin work on Monday. <lb/> The weather has been very wet <lb/> but much milder. I wish it <lb/> would dry up for it is awful <lb/> at present getting about the <lb/> country. There have been <lb/>no reliable rumours as to where  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0676_img_2169_2"/>
              <lb/>we are going after this but we <lb/> are now, as a Division, supposed <lb/> to be fully trained, &amp; will probably <lb/> be called upon first for any <lb/> special move. I had your welcome letter of 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> two days <lb/> ago &amp; would you please thank <lb/> May for her letter of 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; Kathleen <lb/> &amp; Father for theirs of 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. <lb/> I am sorry I have no time to <lb/> acknowledge them separately. <lb/> May asks if there is anything <lb/> in the way of comforts that the <lb/> Bangor Ladies could send to the <lb/> men but really I don't know <lb/> of anything for they get served <lb/> out with shirts, socks etc &amp; if <lb/> they have more than the regulation <lb/> number it simply means they <lb/> can't carry them and the things are <lb/> left behind when a move takes <lb/> place. Was glad to hear from  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0676_img_2169_3"/>
              <lb/>Father that he has made further <lb/> improvements in the Pistol &amp; <lb/>expects to have it ready soon. <lb/> He asks who our Brigadier is. <lb/>Tim Hackett-Pain is still in <lb/> Command so perhaps after all <lb/> he is going to remain with us. <lb/> He seems to be in much better <lb/> health recently   My <hi rend="underline">boots</hi> are now beginning <lb/> to show signs of wear so would <lb/> you please have the pair of <lb/> new ones made by <hi rend="underline">Manfield</hi><lb/> sent out as soon as possible. <lb/> I don't mean the top boots that <lb/> were made in London, these I <lb/> won't require for a little while <lb/> longer. Would you also please <lb/> send with the boots my <hi rend="underline">leather leggings</hi> as I find they will <lb/> be more useful and serviceable <lb/> than puttees. There is another <cb/> thing I must trouble you with <lb/> also Mother Dear and that is some <lb/> more medicines. The following <lb/> is a list of what I require. <lb/> 1 doz Aspirin tablets 5 grm. <lb/> 2 doz Blue Pill and Rhubarb 2 1/2 grm. <lb/>each(<hi rend="underline">Burroughs &amp; Welcomes make</hi>). <lb/> 2 doz Bizmuth &amp; Pepsin. <lb/> 2 doz Cockles pills. <lb/> Please don't send any more than these quantities <lb/> as my case would not hold them. <lb/> If they are put into separate envelopes <lb/> &amp; then all enclosed in a small cardboard <lb/> box they will come alright. <lb/> Was glad to hear such a good account <lb/> of K &amp; Baby. Hoping you are <lb/> feeling better&amp; with fondest love <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  Jim </seg><seg type="postscript"> As Xmas is coming soon please don't <lb/> think of sending any presents as I must <lb/> not add to my luggage and I have really all I <lb/> require. Eatables are of course all right as they <lb/> disappear. Jim  </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0676_img_2169_4"/>
              Rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dec /15    Mrs S. c. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  Ireland    JS Davidson   2/12/15   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>