<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2232">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Edward Carson, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924). Montgomery was a landowner and politician. Originally a liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter was addressed to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a lawyer and a politician. In 1916 he was at the peak of his parliamentary influence. It was in 1916 that he accepted the first lordship of the admiralty. In addition to this, Carson was also a leading unionist figure in Irish politics. He sanctioned the formation of the paramilitary Ulster Volunteer Force in January 1913; and he helped to found the Ulster provisional government of September 1913.
This letter concerns nationalist and unionist politics. Montgomery writes about a nationalist repudiation of Redmond&#39;s provisional consent to the six counties plan. If, however, this does not occur, Montgomery authorizes Carson to enter into negotiations on a six county basis. Montgomery states that any resolution resulting from these negotiations are a result of the stresses of war and cannot be held as binding. Montgomery goes on to express his opinion that Home Rule is an act of treason and a breach of his oath of allegiance.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Royal Irish Regiment Papers; D/290/1/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2232</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2232_img_1677_1"  type="Letter"  url="00524342b384b0d3d474d07b9b95591f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2232_img_1677_2"  type="Letter"  url="187404138fd5699db4052c43c2b2d3ea.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2232_img_1677_1"/>
             copy <lb/>Private   9th June, 1916.   My dear Carson,   The contents of this day's Nationalist<seg type="del">s</seg> papers look <lb/>as if we might have a repudiation of Redmond's provisional consent <lb/> to the six Counties plan before Monday, which would save us from <lb/> a considerable difficulty.   If this does not occur it will be obviously right <lb/>tactics for us to authorise you to enter upon negotiations on <lb/>the six counties basis.   I hope, however, that you will arrange to have a <lb/> resolution proposed which will make it clear that we only do this <lb/> under great stress on account of the war, &amp; that we are not <lb/> bound by what we do on Monday under any other circumstance that <lb/> may arise.   The resolution should contain some plausible excuse <lb/> (1) for breaking or stretching the terms of the Covenant (2) <lb/> (which I think quite as important) for giving even a n  <seg type="del">co</seg> i mplied assent <lb/> to the setting up of Home Rule for any part of Ireland at present, <lb/> involving as it does most serious danger to the Realm and with  which  <lb/> even implicit consent appears to me to amount to an act of treason <lb/> which requires a very valid excuse. I feel that it is as big <lb/> a breach of my oath of allegiance as the <seg type="del">abtaining</seg> abandoning  of the three <lb/> counties is of the covenant!   I attended the Unionists Alliance meeting yesterday <lb/> Some of them had been seeing Lloyd George and had received certain <lb/> offers from him, after considering which they passed the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2232_img_1677_2"/>
            resolution in to-day's papers. I got them to tone one part of <lb/> it which I <seg type="del">think</seg> thought  very unwise down a little, but did not try to <lb/> prevent them issuing it. Not knowing, however what sort of <lb/> resolution I might find myself obliged to vote for on Monday <lb/> I left the room before the resolution was put and they have consider- <lb/> ately omitted my name from the list of those present.   Yours very truly,    Hugh Montgomery.   Monday's resolution sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> also contain a strong instruction <lb/> to you to get the best safequards you can for unionists <lb/> outside the 6 counties — not to ginger you up - <lb/> but to show Southern Unionists that we are not <lb/> forgetting them. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>