<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0108">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Lewis Martin, 2 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (n茅e Moore). In this letter Marie thanks her mother for her letter and refers to hearing the sad news of the death of her brother Charlie (1895-1915). Marie gives her mother the details of her day before signing off.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM). She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother Charlie in battle until be called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/146/1916/07/02, B/F/146/1916/07/02</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/108</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0108_img_1190_1"  type="Letter"  url="619c23d3129b0457bbc8615ade335f8e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0108_img_1190_2"  type="Letter"  url="0ca2e06ddecc392b11d7cefb3f2e61c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0108_img_1190_3"  type="NULL"  url="7dcc55c249a0ed45e6b536ff2bbda5b8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0108_img_1190_1"/>
                25 General Hospital  B. E. F.    2<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">nd</hi></hi><hi rend="underline">July 1916</hi>   My very dearest Mother芒聙聰   A thousand thanks for your <lb/>very long letter, I really got quite a <lb/>shock about poor Charlie although <lb/>I had practically given up hope of <lb/>him turning up I still thought <lb/>there might be a chance &amp; really <lb/>was hoping against hope. as you say <lb/>when one realizes it is really <lb/>a great consolation to know he <lb/>did not suffer for long &amp; feel <lb/>sure Our Lady took care of him <lb/>&amp; that he is out of all suffering <lb/>now芒聙聰 What a brave boy he was &amp; <lb/> like him to have his wound dressed <lb/>&amp; then go on again. It is really <lb/>impossible to realize we shall never <lb/>see his dear face again, how we shall  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0108_img_1190_2"/>
              all miss him 芒聙聰 all the poor Mothers the <lb/>anxiety these days, until it really <lb/>like this touches oneself so much it <lb/>brings this terrible war home to us. <lb/>I do hope it will end soon every one <lb/>has had <sic>queit</sic> enough sorrow &amp; trouble <lb/>I have been very busy these <lb/>last few days 芒聙聰On Friday we <lb/>evacuated at 11 <sic>O芒聙聶ck</sic> except for one <lb/>patient got all beds made up in <lb/>morning, in the afternoon I was on <lb/>duty alone with two orderlies <lb/>had just <sic>finish</sic> scrubbing my lockers <lb/>&amp; making up new kits when <lb/>a convoy came in &amp; before <sic>5 O芒聙聶ck</sic><lb/>we were full up 芒聙聰 We had a new <lb/>Sister on the block who knew nothing <lb/>about Military ways &amp; as she would <lb/>have been alone I went back so <lb/>had a fine days work most of <lb/>them are being cleared out again <lb/>to芒聙聰morrow, so I suppose we shall  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0108_img_1190_3"/>
              only just get time to clear up <lb/>again for a new batch芒聙聰 <lb/>I think I had better end there <lb/>is a great deal I want to say <lb/>but it is 11芒聙聰-30 &amp; lights are <sic>suppose</sic><lb/>to be out 10芒聙聰-30芒聙聰 I shall write <lb/>to芒聙聰morrow all the news &amp; answer <lb/>any question you asked芒聙聰 <lb/>With my very fondest love to <lb/>you dearest Mother and although <lb/>I am so far away I am always <lb/>with you in spirit芒聙聰 <lb/>Hoping you have had good <lb/>news from Tommy芒聙聰 <seg type="closer"> A fat X &amp; heap of Love <lb/>Good芒聙聰night  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>