<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4314">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Mr. Seeds, 23 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Mr. Seeds. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4314</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-05-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr. Seeds</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4314_img_3675_1"  type="Letter"  url="9e97f2ba683c5877d52b949356022ee3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4314_img_3675_2"  type="Letter"  url="9f6dd1418b510cc58d0a85c497e3d7a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4314_img_3675_1"/>
             23rd May, 1916.   Dear Mr. Seeds,   In reply to the letter sent by yourself and some <lb/>others of the 15th of May, I hope you will be satisfied for <lb/>the moment with a very short answer. I am fully <lb/>aware of the uneasiness that prevails with reference to <lb/>the present situation, and I can assure you that I am <lb/>watching everything with the fullest desire and intent— <lb/>tion to uphold the principle s  to which we are bound by <lb/>our Covenant. It is never absent from my mind for a <lb/>moment. So far as I am concerned you may reply upon it <lb/>that I have not taken and will not take any action in <lb/>the matter without the fullest submission to our Execu— <lb/>tive Council and I shall never be a party to advising <lb/>anything which would be a breach of our Covenant. I <lb/>think for the moment it is better not to publish the <lb/>correspondence as I am anxious to hear what the Govern— <lb/>ment propose to do, having regard to the recent disgrace— <lb/>ful conduct of the rebels in the South and West,
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4314_img_3675_2"/>
            but you are quite at liberty to show my answer to any of <lb/>the Ulster Volunteer Force whom you think proper.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>