<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3595">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to Sir Arthur Stanley, 31 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) to Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) regarding Irish representation on the Council of the new College of Nursing. In the opinion of the RCPI in order to preserve unanimity existing among Irish nurses, and to further the interests of the college, the question of Irish representation on the college council should be settled as quickly as possible. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-163</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3595</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-05-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1166">Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3595_img_2995_1"  type="Letter"  url="2c11425b27c4a9726c462561b9f4afa5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3595_img_2995_1"/>
             31st MAY 16.   The Hon.Arthur Stanley, M.V.O., <lb/>85 Pall Mall, London, S.W.,   Dear Sir,   I am directed by the Committee of the Royal Colleges of <lb/>Physicians and Surgeons, Ireland, to write to tell you that in <lb/>the opinion of the Members of the Committee it is most desirable, <lb/> in order to preserve the unanimity at present existing among <lb/>Irish Nurses, and so to further the interests of the College of <lb/>Nursing, that the question of the Irish representation on the <lb/>Council of the College should be settled at as early a date as <lb/>possible.   The Committee is anxious to call together a meeting of Irish <lb/>Nurses and I shall be glad if you can inform me of the date on <lb/>which I may expect to have a definite answer on the subject.   I remain, <lb/>Dear Sir, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar, R.C.P.I.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>