<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0198">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Joseph Duignan and Timothy Murray to George Ormsbry, 25 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Joseph Duignan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from James Joseph Duignan (b.1884) and Timothy Murray (1857-1923), secretaries for Carrick-on-Shannon district, to George Ormsrby (1855-1938), lord lieutenant of Leitrim. The letter concerns the town of Carrick-on-Shannon and the effect of the war on its economy. It states that the population has dropped from 1,000 to 850 due to recruitment for the war. The men state that the middle landlords are extorting their tenants for rents that they are unable to pay due to the economic depression. The tenants are being threatened with writs for rent that is not due for two months, the letter refers to one which had been enclosed. The letter ends stating the area&#39;s loyalty, citing the fact that only two arrests were made when the military arrived in the town after the Easter Rising, both of whom where released within minutes. The enclosure is written to a Mr Bernard Bennett and calls for his payment of rent, with threat of summons.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9279/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/198</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1331">James Joseph Duignan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0256">Carrick-on Shannon, County Leitrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Ormsbry</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0198_img_1341_1"  type="Letter"  url="5bd91e563915f1ffa3d4769b2c9ec283.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0198_img_1341_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="f8f7ddb94d1e1268c5cf70b4f5dc24e2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0198_img_1341_1"/>
              Ack Irish Office <lb/>Miss Stevenson    CARRICK-ON-SHANNON,  COUNTY LEITRIM,    25th MAY, 1916.   The Right Honble. Lord George,   We the Town Tenants of Carrick-on-Shannon, a small <lb/>town of originally <hi rend="underline">1000</hi> inhabitants but, owing to the War <lb/>now only <hi rend="underline">850.</hi> This town has sent close on <hi rend="underline">300</hi> Soldiers to <lb/>the colours, reservists, volunteers, &amp;c. As you are aware <lb/>this causes a great depression in trade generally. This town <lb/>as like many others<seg type="del">is,</seg> is, in the hands of middle Landlords, <lb/>who are only too anxious to extort their Rack Rents from <lb/>Tenants that are suffering from the depression in trade <lb/>caused by the War. Their burden has been borne in silence <lb/>but owing to the causes mentioned, the local Landlords have <lb/>become unbearable not content with their rents being paid <lb/>when due, we are threatened with <hi rend="underline">Writs</hi> for rent not due for <lb/>two months, as an instance of this we enclose you a specimen <lb/>received by one of our tenants.  We would respectfully ask you to look into this <lb/>matter specially, we are confident that you will be able to <lb/>suggest some means to keep us over these oppressive war times.  As an instance of the loyalty we have, we may <lb/>mention that on the visit of the Military to our Town a few <lb/>weeks ago, only two arrests were made on suspicion, these <lb/>were liberated in a few minutes. <seg type="closer"> James J Duignan <lb/><hi rend="underline">Timothy Murray</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">Secretaries</hi> </seg> <seg type="unclear">H</seg><lb/>For a report please <lb/>on this matter. <seg type="unclear">W</seg> 1-6-16   <seg type="unclear">To J.</seg> Carrick on Shannon <lb/>for report <seg type="unclear">W N O'Connell</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">S.H.</seg> 2/6/16   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0198_img_1341_2"/>
                JAMES A. KIERNAN,  Solicitor   DUBLIN OFFICE.  12. Dame Street    Ballinamore  Co.Leitrim    22nd May 1916    Mr. Lernard Bennett,  Carrick.   Walshe Estate  Sir,   Unless I receive payment of rent due by you to the 1st May <lb/>last by return of post, my instructions are to issue Writs of <lb/>Summons forthwith for recovery thereof. All the other tenants <lb/>have paid their rents and I cannot allow you to go into arrear. <seg type="closer"> Your obedient servant,  Kiernan </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>