<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5930">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick O'Loughlin to Ellen O'Loughlin, 23 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick O&#39;Loughlin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Patrick O&#39;Loughlin (1875 - 1937) to his wife Ellen (1881- 1964). Patrick made a number of trips to a Mrs C. Henry in Glasgow to purchase goods from the shop. This letter was written while on one of those trips and refers to the journey over and the goods he intended to buy. Included is a postcard of an image of Patrick and Ellen that was posted at a later date.Patrick and Ellen ran a small shop at 39 Lower Kevin Street in Dublin, selling second-hand clothes/boots/shoes.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Rory O&#39;Loughlin</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5930</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0398">Patrick O&#39;Loughlin</persName>
              <date>1916-08-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0254">4 Steel Street, Glasgow, Scotland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen O&#39;Loughlin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1380">Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5930_img_459_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa34ea98ebfb3fbdaaad8f521cd574b0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5930_img_459_2"  type="Letter"  url="56f847270ca0c24e7d0782110d48e260.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5930_img_459_3"  type="Letter"  url="2d42365cd6e3ad013b2b5ec56b86deca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5930_img_459_4"  type="Letter"  url="2d42365cd6e3ad013b2b5ec56b86deca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5930_img_459_5"  type="Photograph"  url="fc707ce06757b0df9a48226d9fbb1174.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5930_img_459_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">August 23 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> 1916 </hi>   Dear Nellie   Just A few lines <lb/> to let you know I <lb/> arrived all right it <lb/> was a Bitter cold Night <lb/> going over there was a <lb/> heavy fog raised and <lb/> the Boat had to go very <lb/> slow an the fog horn <lb/> going Continually however <lb/> it improved as we got to <lb/> Greenock so I decided at <lb/> going up the Clyde  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5930_img_459_2"/>
              And it was grand so <lb/> I did not arrive at M <lb/>M. <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Grahams till 2 o C <lb/> in the day and the were <lb/> Expecting me And had <lb/> Given me up so It was <lb/> All right Called on M. <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi><lb/> Henry And <sic>don</sic> A bit of <lb/> work she has no Nicks <lb/> or Boys Clothes nor Cant <lb/> get them so I will have <lb/> to do the Best I can <lb/> sorry for Mary for them <lb/> is the very things she told <lb/> me to look for hoping  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5930_img_459_3"/>
              yourself and the <sic>Kidds</sic><lb/> are All right with  <seg type="closer"> Best love I remain   <hi rend="underline">Paddy</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5930_img_459_4"/>
               Dear Nellie   If you intend <lb/> to <sic>Writ</sic> the same <lb/> Address M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Graham <lb/> 4 steel st <lb/> Glasgow   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5930_img_459_5"/>
                Glasgow    <hi rend="underline">9/7/21</hi>   Dear Paddy   We are in Glasgow this Week <lb/> got your Mother to go away at <lb/> last she is Enjoying it very <lb/> much the Weather is grand we are <lb/> not going Home till next Weeks so I <lb/> thought <sic>i rite</sic> and let you know <lb/> hoping you are keeping in the Best <lb/> of Health  <seg type="closer"> With very Best Love </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>