<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0619">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B. Abraham to the Chairman, General Prisons Board, 19 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Benjamin Abraham</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Benjamin Abraham (b. 1965), Clerk of Works for General Prisons Board, to the Chairman, General Prisons Board. This letter forms part of a large volume of correspondence between the Mountjoy Prison authorities and N. C. Laundry Ltd. concerning a dispute over responsibility for the collapse of a wall between the two properties and a claim by the laundry for a contribution towards reconstruction.In this letter Abraham gives estimates of the cost of reconstruction of the wall to its original height and also an alternative and less expensive construction of a wooden 6 ft fence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7190</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/619</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1037">Benjamin Abraham</persName>
              <date>1916-04-19T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0619_img_2037_1"  type="Letter"  url="4674a45614b0fca687938031cd1bc234.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0619_img_2037_2"  type="Letter"  url="449d04b6115a8b25fbbac0188f88d450.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0619_img_2037_3"  type="Letter"  url="da648c25d8145ef09fdd0848995155c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0619_img_2037_4"  type="Letter"  url="e58b0cefba72ebc582cda628c4d5d65d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0619_img_2037_5"  type="Letter"  url="73c84890a6e395ee67a187344c95d420.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0619_img_2037_1"/>
              1483   General Prison's Board  Dublin Castle     19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April 1916   <lb/><hi rend="underline">Mountjoy Prison</hi><lb/>Damage to wall  Chairman   I beg to state that the <lb/>Estimated cost of rebuilding to <lb/>its original height the damaged <lb/>portion of the wall between the <lb/> N. C. Laundry Yards Mt Joy <lb/>Prison Grounds would be £116.12.6   To provide and erect a <lb/>substantial wooden fence say <lb/>6tf high would cost £38.10.9  <seg type="closer"> B. Abraham <lb/>Under Secretary <lb/>Submitted in reply to <lb/>minute of 15.4.1916 <lb/>Max S. Green <lb/>20.4.16 <lb/>Under Secretary <lb/>Submitted in reply to your <lb/>minute of the 14 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. <lb/>I.J.T <lb/>20.416 <lb/>I. Rec. from cate U.S. 5/5 <lb/>II. Spoke to Mr. HeadCon. <lb/>III. Pending Treasury reply. <lb/>I.J.T. <lb/><hi rend="underline">13.v.16</hi></seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0619_img_2037_2"/>
                NORTH CIRCULAR ROAD  (TOP OF BERKLEY STREET).  DUBLIN,    April <seg type="unclear">10</seg><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916     C Munro Esq  H. M Prison  Mountjoy  Dublin   Dear Sir   We duly received yours 5 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and <lb/>we are pleased to know that something <lb/>may be done about our wall but the <lb/>erection of a wire fence we are very <lb/>much afraid does not quite meet the <lb/>situation and we feel certain would <lb/>be unsatisfactory to both you and <lb/>ourselves. We suggest your sending <lb/>us a contribution towards cost <lb/>of the wall and we shall then have <lb/>a close fence built at our expense <lb/>If you fix a reasonable sum we <lb/>will not be hard to satisfy.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  <hi rend="underline">N.C. L.D.</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0619_img_2037_3"/>
              From the GOVERNOR   H. M. PRISON Mountjoy, Dublin    5th April 1916    To Messrs the North City Laundry Coy.  North Circular Road,  Dublin.    With to previous corresponence relative to the fallen <lb/>wall I am to enquire whether your Company would offer any objection to the <lb/>erection of a wire fence at public expense in lieu of the proposal to replace <lb/>the fallen wall.  <seg type="closer"> CTMunro  Governor. </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0619_img_2037_4"/>
                NORTH CIRCULAR ROAD  (TOP OF BERKLEY STREET)  DUBLIN    29th Mar 1916.    Chief Crown Solicitor's Office,  Dublin Castle,  DUBLIN   Dear Sirs   We have been expecting to hear from you re our wall <lb/>tumbled by your ivy. As we are anxious to have this matter dis— <lb/>posed of and if possible without unpleasantness, we should be <lb/>glad if you would let us have your decision as soon as possible.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  N. C. LAUNDRY, LTD </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0619_img_2037_5"/>
                30th March 1916  <lb/>re Alleged damage to Wall  Dear Sirs   I am in receipt of your letter of 29th March which I <lb/>have forwarded for the necessary instructions and shall communicate <lb/>with you immediately on receipt of same.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly  A Percy Lynch  Asst. C.C.S.S   Messrs N.C. Laundry Ltd.,  N.C. Road,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>