<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4321">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur Warren Samuels to Edward Carson, 14 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Warren Samuels</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Arthur Warren Samuels (1852-1925) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Samuels was a Unionist MP and later Solicitor General for Ireland. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4321</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0743">Arthur Warren Samuels</persName>
              <date>1916-06-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0501">80 Merrion Square Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1925</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4321_img_3681_1"  type="Letter"  url="9b6f3415baa35007916c19924631e448.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4321_img_3681_2"  type="Letter"  url="ebcd4ba4a418203cf7f09f2bff1a7697.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4321_img_3681_1"/>
              D1507/A/17/15    80 Merrion Square,<lb/>Dublin.    <hi rend="underline">Private</hi> <lb/> 14 June<lb/>1916.    My dear Carson   Asquith &amp; Lloyd George<lb/>are deep tricksters.  For you the Exclusion<lb/>is to be permanent, for<lb/>Redmond provisional.  As the Unionists in<lb/>England have chucked<lb/>over the Irish Unionists, I<lb/>think our course ought to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4321_img_3681_2"/>
             be to declare that<lb/>upon the present proposals<lb/>being withdrawn &amp; the<lb/>Home Rule Act provisionally<lb/>abandoned we would be<lb/>prepared in Ireland to<lb/>meet representatives of all<lb/>Irish parties in conference<lb/>&amp; consider whether a basis<lb/>of settlement cannot be<lb/>reached among ourselves<lb/><lb/>to be embodied in a<lb/>scheme of Imperial<lb/>Federation after the War.  If something constructive<lb/>is not done by us nothing<lb/>remains but absolute<lb/>Ruin.  England has reverted<lb/>to her ineptitude of 1782.  [Questionable reading.]   <lb/>Arthur W.Samuels.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>