<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0603">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B. Abraham to General Prisons Board to the General Secretary's Office, 25 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>B. Abraham</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from B. Abraham, Clerk of Works, General Prisons Board to the General Secretary&#39;s Office. This correspondence concerns a claim by N.C. Laundry against Mountjoy Prison in respect of alleged damage to a wall which divides the prison and the laundry. Accompanying the correspondence are several letters about the incident and about the wall (over 90 years old), and the poor condition of it. Accompanying this letter is a note, dated 24 January, 1916, from the General Prisons Board to the Clerk of Works asking for his report, which was required for the Assistant Under-Secretary. Also attached is a letter addressed to the N. C. Laundry Ltd., dated 19 January, 1916, from M. Kelly, acknowledging its letter of 18 January and saying that he will communicate further when he receives instructions.The aforementioned letter of 18 January from N.C. Laundry Ltd. to M. Kelly, Chief Crown Solicitor’s Office is also uploaded. The writer says that the company is not concerned as to whether legal liability is admitted but believes that the authorities have a moral liability because of the ivy which grew to an extent that its weight combined with a large amount of water it held following a recent storm was the cause of the collapse.The company doesn&#39;t wish to engage in litigation against a Government Department, notwithstanding the fact that it is confident of victory, but instead asks for a small contribution towards reconstruction.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/429</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/603</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0167">B. Abraham</persName>
              <date>1916-01-25T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0603_img_2014_1"  type="Letter"  url="54eaffc8d174fd25d93e97799f2e652b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0603_img_2014_2"  type="Letter"  url="aeb478e062ad531600129b8dfcd4718b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0603_img_2014_3"  type="Letter"  url="ba03dacee64b9d480e6f13db671ef01f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0603_img_2014_4"  type="Letter"  url="e6a673aa263236f03f5742f90c7fe8f2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0603_img_2014_5"  type="Letter"  url="67a30c4de3f6d3c110e01c49d283917f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0603_img_2014_6"  type="Letter"  url="4890c6efdc3f1984c12aa266698bfa52.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0603_img_2014_1"/>
                General Prison's Board  Dublin Castle    25th Jan 1916  <lb/>367/16 <lb/><hi rend="underline">Mountjoy Prison</hi><lb/>re Claim by N.C. Laundry <lb/>for alleged damage to Wall  Chairman   I beg to report that the wall <lb/>forming the boundary between the grounds <lb/>attached to the Medical Officers Quarters <lb/>Mountjoy Prison and those of the N.C <lb/>Laundry Co was built nearly a Century <lb/>ago of an inferior blackcalp laminated <lb/>stone. The wall is about 15 feet high <lb/>from the prison ground level and 22 <lb/>inches wide and appears to have been <lb/>built without any under surface <lb/>foundation. The building mortar <lb/>used and the workmanship were of <lb/>the poorest quality. I am informed <lb/>on reliable authority that the wall <lb/>was noticed to have been bulging <lb/>and overhanging the prison grounds <lb/>for the past 35 years, and I have <lb/>made inquiries covering that space <lb/>of time and can find no evidence <lb/>to show that the Prison Authorities <lb/>even planted ivy against the wall, <lb/>the seed may have been dropped by <lb/>birds, or blown there by the wind, or <lb/>the Ivy may have been growing there <lb/>at the time the Prison was built.  The greater bulk of the ivy was growing <lb/>about 11 feet from the Quoin Stone next <lb/>to prison and that portion of the wall <lb/>is  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0603_img_2014_2"/>
              is still standing. Another spray <lb/>much smaller had been growing <lb/>36 feet from the quion and nearer the <lb/>part of the wall which fell as shown <lb/>on rough sketch herewith.  At the laundry side I noticed <lb/>against that part of the wall which <lb/>fell a bank of rubbish, earth, and old <lb/>brick averaging 3Â½ feet high which <lb/>in my opinion must have exerted <lb/>a considerable thrust against the <lb/>bulged part of the wall especially <lb/>during the exceptionally heavy rain <lb/>storm which prevailed on the evening <lb/>of the 12th Nov.  It appears from the evidence obtain <lb/>able that the wall is built about 90 <lb/>years, or between 30 &amp; 40 years <lb/>before the prison, but there is <lb/>nothing to show what arrangements <lb/>(if any) were entered into between the <lb/>parties, regarding this wall at the time <lb/>the prison was built.] The plans in <lb/>this office show that when the site <lb/>for the prison was being plotted <lb/>an offer for the exchange or purchase <lb/>of the part of the Laundry grounds <lb/>was made in order to square out <lb/>the prison property. This was not <lb/>carried into effect. Consequently <lb/>a strip of the laundry garden <lb/>about 130 feet by 100 feet fits in <lb/>between  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0603_img_2014_3"/>
              between the prison grounds <lb/>almost to the boundary wall â a <lb/>very undesirable &amp; unsatisfactory <lb/>Arrangement I strongly <lb/>recommend that if possible the <lb/>ground in question as Coloured <lb/>Yellow and marked A on sheet <lb/>herewith be acquired so as to <lb/>square out the prison property <lb/>and it would be a nice site <lb/>for a Deputy Govenors or <lb/>Medical Officers residence <seg type="closer">  B. Abraham </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0603_img_2014_4"/>
                GENERAL PRISONS BOARD  DUBLIN CASTLE,  <lb/>No. 367   24 Jan 1916   Clerk of Works   Please furnish <lb/>the full statement <lb/>asked for in the <lb/>asst. under Secretary's <lb/>minute of 22nd inst. <lb/>attached <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">JM</hi>   24.1.16  </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0603_img_2014_5"/>
                19th January 1916   Sirs,   I am in receipt of your letter of 18th instant which I <lb/>am submitting for instructions and will further communicate <lb/>with you. <seg type="closer"> Your obedient servant  <seg type="unclear">M. Kelly</seg>   N C Laundry Ltd.  North Circular Road,  Dubin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0603_img_2014_6"/>
              <lb/>Solicitor General <lb/>M. Kelly <lb/><seg type="unclear">Jan 1916</seg>  NORTH CIRCULAR ROAD,  (TOP OF BERKLEY)  DUBLIN    18th Jan 1916.    M. Kelly Esq.  Chief Crown Solicitor's Office,  Dublin Castle,  DUBLIN>   Dear Sir,   We are in receipt of yours 13th instant, and in <lb/>reply have to say that we are not concerned whether you admit <lb/>legal liability at present or not, but this question apart you <lb/>are morally liable to us undoubtedly for the tumbling of our <lb/>wall. You allowed a heavy growth of ivy which was planted in <lb/>your ground to grow to such an extent that the weight of itself <lb/>with the enormous amount of water it held and the vibration <lb/>caused by the wind during the great gale in November last unâ <lb/>doubtedly tumbled the wall; and you have since admitted that you <lb/>had no right to use our wall for such a purpose as holding up <lb/>your ivy, by having the remaining portion of the ivy taken away <lb/>in response to our call on you  to have this done   We have no wish to have litigation with a Government Dept. <lb/>over this matter and would be prepared to accept a comparatively <lb/>small sum in satisfaction of our claim, especially as we have <lb/>already gone to considerable expense in getting the Engineers and <lb/>other experts reports as to the cause of the tumbling of the <lb/>wall and what conduced to this, and in order to end the matter <lb/>we would be glad if you could see your way to pay us something <lb/>towards the cost of reâerection, as on the advice we recâ <lb/>eived we feel certain that if we have to go into Court we could <lb/>enforce our claim for a much larger amount than we would be preâ <lb/>pared to accept rather than have the trouble of law proceedings. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  N.C. LAUNDRY LTD. <lb/><unclear/> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>