<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1087">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to The Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 18 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sir Arthur Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) regarding the new college of nursing. This letter outlines some of the necessary procedures that will be required over the coming months as the college of nursing becomes more firmly established. Stanley requests that the college appoint two Irish representatives to sit on the Consultative Board of the College, as per the RCPI&#39;s stipulation of one fifth Irish representation. Stanley&#39;s explanation of procedure highlights the degree of urgency underlining the creation of the nursing college. Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-3-15-21, RCPI-2-3-3-15-21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1087</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0219">Sir Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-04-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_1"  type="Letter"  url="32639f7003e622c59132f002fea45111.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_2"  type="Letter"  url="8f73bd98e1ac8de8e328942f91178b60.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_3"  type="Letter"  url="c18eb7bfb984d11b34e891e51a69e8a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_4"  type="Letter"  url="287a7c87c994b64861572a1bce37a86c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_5"  type="Letter"  url="0b4586cdc7f6c6fc15647af925a07160.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_6"  type="Letter"  url="7285d9c979af595e379d5403d71bb33a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_7"  type="Letter"  url="df6c3bd1435e89b6c449d06b8875fcf5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1087_img_3235_8"  type="Letter"  url="7c28d1f72249f1f0aada0e6f8679a94f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_1"/>
               THE COLLEGE OF NURSING, LIMITED.   83, PALL MALL  LONDON, S.W.    April 18th. 1916.   Dear Sir,   The response to the letter which I addressed on the 1st. <lb/>instant to many of the Hospitals, Infirmaries, and Nurse-Training <lb/>Schools throughout the Country was so prompt and wide-spread that <lb/>at the Conference held a week later at St. Thomas's Hospital more <lb/>that two hundred representatives were present from England and <lb/>Wales, Scotland and Ireland. I then took the opportunity of ex— <lb/>plaining the circumstances which led to the establishment of the <lb/>College of Nursing, and I laid stress upon the desire of the Coun— <lb/>cil to form as speedily as possible such a Consultative Board as <lb/>would be representative of all parts of the United Kingdom and of <lb/>all branches of Nursing.   The Council has learnt with regret that, as through unavoidable <lb/>reasons the notice I was able to give of the Conference was some— <lb/>what short and some of the letters miscarried, many Nursing Author— <lb/>ities failed to receive my communication in time to take formal ac— <lb/>tion upon it. I am, therefore, desired to give expression to the <lb/>earnest hope of the Council that your Board of Management may be <lb/>pleased <hi rend="underline">within the next month</hi> to nominate not more than two Repre— <lb/>sentatives upon the Consultative Board of the College, and, as some  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_2"/>
              guide to the lines on which we are working, I am amplifying certain <lb/>points in the constitution of the College to which allusion only was <lb/>made in my letter of 30th. December, 1915.   To the reasons which induced me to lay before the Managers of <lb/>Hospitals and Infirmaries proposals for the establishment of a Col— <lb/>lege of Nursing at the time I did I need not recur, but I ought per— <lb/>haps to say that, whilst it was originally my intention to ask the <lb/>Board of Trade to register the College without the word 'Limited', <lb/>I found on enquiry that such a proceeding would lead to probable <lb/>difficulties and to certain delay, which it was my object to avoid. <lb/>Accordingly, the signing of the Memorandum and the Articles of <lb/>Association became largely a formal matter, and the original Council <lb/>of 15 appointed by the Signatories has already been increased by co— <lb/>optation to 23, and may be further enlarged up to 30 Members. A <lb/>list of the present Council is enclosed herewith, and I shall be <lb/>glad also to furnish on application a copy of the Memorandum and <lb/>Articles of Association, which it should be remembered have, in <lb/>accordance with the usual practice in these cases, been drawn so as <lb/>to give the widest possible powers, and not as a precise indication <lb/>of the present or future policy of the College.   As I stated in my original letter, we have for the time at least <lb/>to rely upon a voluntary scheme of co-operation amongst the Nurse— <lb/>Training Schools throughout the Kingdom, but, concurrently with the <lb/>activities of the College as regards the training and certification <lb/>of Nurses and other women-workers in Hospitals, opportunities will <lb/>be taken for friendly conference on the one hand with those who are  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_3"/>
              altogether averse to State interference and on the other with those <lb/>Societies whose primary object is the registration of Nurses <lb/>by Act of Parliament. To meet Representatives of such Societies <lb/>a Registration Committee has already been appointed, and, <lb/>whilst it would be idle to ignore the many difficulties which <lb/>have to be overcome before the Nursing Profession wins the legal <lb/>recognition it deserves, no-one will rejoice more heartily than <lb/>myself when, as the outcome of our common efforts, such a degree <lb/>of substantial unanimity has been reached within the ranks as <lb/>to enable us to present to Parliament an agreed Bill to gain legal <lb/>status for the results attained by the combined activities of all <lb/>who, working at present on different lines, have as their one ob— <lb/>jective the betterment of the Nursing Profession. In these aims <lb/>I feel assured that we can rely upon the sympathy and all-important <lb/>help of the Medical Profession with which nursing is so closely <lb/>allied.   Another point upon which I have laid emphasis is that the <lb/>College is ultimately to be self-governing. Primarily, it is true, <lb/>the scheme is based upon the co-operation of the Matrons and Lady <lb/>Superintendents of the leading Nursing Schools, whose knowledge and <lb/>experience in matters of curriculum and examination, supported and <lb/>amplified by the work of the Consultative and Examination Boards, <lb/>are made use of to initiate the undertaking. Accordingly the ori— <lb/>ginal Council has been thus nominated and co-opted, but in 1918, and <lb/>every year afterwards, one-third of the members retire from office, <lb/>and vacancies are filled by the votes of the Members of the College,  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_4"/>
              i.e. from the general body of Nurses upon the Register. To ensure <lb/>for them an effective influence in the result there is provision <lb/>for a postal vote, not dependent upon personal attendance at the <lb/>Annual Ordinary Meeting at which elections to the Council are made. <lb/>Whilst, therefore, the College in its early years will be largely <lb/>guided by the experience of the Heads of the various Training <lb/>Schools who form a majority of the first Council, it will, when <lb/>it attains maturity, become broad-based and democratic in consti— <lb/>tution.   The third and fourth points upon which I have insisted are: <lb/>uniformity of curriculum, and the one-portal system of examination, <lb/>and it is just in these matters that the Council feels the urgent <lb/>necessity of help and counsel from Nursing Schools, from the Medical <lb/>Profession, from Nursing Associations, and from Nurses in the active <lb/>practice of their calling.   The solidarity of the Nursing Profession being a matter of <lb/>paramount importance, it is essential that there should be only one <lb/>Certificate of General Training for all Nurses wherever trained. <lb/>At the present time, however, the Nurses of the best London and <lb/>Provincial Hospitals and Infirmaries are able to make a living on <lb/>the reputation of the Nursing Certificates they hold from their own <lb/>Schools, and thus have comparatively little inducements to enter for, <lb/>and incidentally to pay fees for, any further qualifying Examina— <lb/>tion. Hence the importance to the scheme of the countenance and <lb/>active participation in the Authorities of the leading Nurse—  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_5"/>
              Training Schools, and hence the provision, under stringent safe— <lb/>guards as to standard, for accepting the internal Examinations of <lb/>recognised Schools as qualifying for the Certificates of Profi— <lb/>ciency to be granted by the College. Moreover, such a concession <lb/>avoids excessive centralisation, whilst it gives an incentive to <lb/>backward Institutions to improve their curricula, teaching facili— <lb/>ties, and tests, so that they may gain the status of recognised <lb/>Schools, and thus be saved the necessity of sending their Nurses <lb/>elsewhere to sit for the College Examination.   In view of the inclusion of the whole of the United Kingdom in <lb/>the Scheme, and the geographical difficulties thus introduced, <lb/>power is taken in the Articles of Association to establish Local <lb/>Boards, which may exercise in their respective areas 'any of the <lb/>powers, authorities, and discretions for the time being vested in <lb/>the Council', and some progress has already been made in regard to <lb/>Scotland.   Reverting to the constitution and functions of the Consulta— <lb/>tive Board, for which, as I have already said, the Council now <lb/>invite your Managers to nominate not more than two persons, I would <lb/>remark that under the Articles of Association, it is to consist of <lb/>'such number of persons as the Council shall from time to time de— <lb/>termine', and to be 'elected from amongst Physicians, Surgeons, <lb/>Hospital Matrons and Principal Officers, Superintendents of Nursing, <lb/>Trained Nurses, and persons interested in the relations between <lb/>Nurses and the Public'. Amongst the functions assigned to the  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_6"/>
              Consultative Board are :— (1) To deliberate in regard to any question submitted to it by the <lb/>Council, and to report to the Council the result of the consulta— <lb/>tion thereon.   (2) On the initiative of any Member of the Consultative Board to <lb/>consider, if thought advisable, any subject within the scope of the <lb/>Memorandum of Association; and, if thought advisable, to report <lb/>thereon to the Council.   In order to ensure for the Consultative Board the fullest pos— <lb/>sible influence and the authority in the College compatible with the <lb/>position of the Council as the Governing Body, it is laid down that <lb/>the Council shall always invite and receive a Report from the Con— <lb/>sultative Board before coming to a determination upon any of the <lb/>following matters, viz:—   (1) The courses of study and technical training for persons <lb/>intended for the Nursing Profession.   (2) The conditions under which recognition may be extended to <lb/>Nursing Schools.   For facilitating the work of the Consultative Board the Council <lb/>has formed a Consultative Committee, with power to add to its num— <lb/>bers from amongst persons appointed to the Board, so that business <lb/>may be put before the full Board in such a way as not to make too <lb/>great claims upon the time of its Members, many of whom can only <lb/>give occasional attendance in London.   From what has been said it will be evident that the work of the  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_7"/>
              Board is chiefly of a professional character, but Managers of Hos— <lb/>pitals may find that the revision of Nursing curricula entails <lb/>extra expense in the matter of lectures, class-rooms, and proper <lb/>facilities for study. Consequently some representation of the <lb/>Lay element in the management of Hospitals and Infirmaries appears <lb/>to me to be desirable, in order that this point of view may receive <lb/>due attention at the deliberations of the Board.   Until it is seen what response is made to this invitation, the <lb/>Council is not in a position to elect the Consultative Board, or to <lb/>fix its number, but, if the nominations are too numerous for effi— <lb/>cient working, it may be necessary either to make a selection <lb/>amongst them or to formulate some plan for representation on the <lb/>Board by groups or districts. This, however, will be a matter for <lb/>subsequent consideration, and meanwhile it is most important that <lb/>as little time as possible should elapse before attacking some at <lb/>least of the many problems which await solution before the College <lb/>can take its place as the Central Organization of the Nursing Pro— <lb/>fession throughout the United Kingdom.   Again apologising for any inadvertent error in the transmission <lb/>of my previous communications, and requesting the favour of an early <lb/>reply,  <seg type="closer"> I am, dear Sir, <lb/>Yours sincerely,   Arthur Stanley <lb/>Chairman of the Council.  </seg> 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1087_img_3235_8"/>
              Letter from Mr Stanley <lb/>April 18, 1916 <lb/>Re Meeting of <lb/>Consultation Board <lb/>of College   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>