<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3496">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edmond Joseph Frewen to John Redmond, 25 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edmond Joseph Frewen</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edmond Joseph Frewen (b. 1867) to John Redmond (1856-1918). Frewen is writing to Redmond about the newspaper the Freeman&#39;s Journal and to report on his meeting with Timothy Healy at which the prospect of ‘re-uniting the different sections of the national side’ under Redmond’s leadership was discussed. 

Edmond Joseph Frewen was a Tipperary-born business man who led a London-based Trading Company. John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 15,188/8/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3496</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0417">Edmond Joseph Frewen</persName>
              <date>1916-03-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0427">8 Waterloo Place, Pall Mall, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3496_img_2903_1"  type="Letter"  url="899894390b811e71f5da100a93cbc53d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3496_img_2903_2"  type="Letter"  url="939f6ae135005c5f67d8891b9c9abcbb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3496_img_2903_3"  type="Letter"  url="fff1c1cbc94a2d525a98820fe0cd68e7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3496_img_2903_1"/>
             8, Waterloo Place, <lb/>Pall Mall, <lb/>London. S.W.   25 March 1916   Dear Mr Redmond   I saw Mr Donald of the "Daily <lb/>Chronicle" today and had an interesting <lb/>interview with him in regard to the Freeman <lb/>which I hope will lead to something.   He recommends abandoning the idea <lb/>of journalistic departures in the states, <lb/>but has agreed to keep me in the Irish <lb/>sphere. He thinks the money should be largely <lb/>Irish. I will communicate with you <lb/>further on <hi rend="underline">the matter</hi> at a later date.   I saw Healy last week and broached to <lb/> him in the form of a personal recommendation <lb/> the advisablity in the national interests at <lb/> the present time of reuniting different sections <lb/> in the national side under your leadership <lb/> After a somewhat lengthened recapitulation
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3496_img_2903_2"/>
            of grievances most of which seemed to me to be <lb/>of the variety usually associated with feminine <lb/>"amenities" of the personal type, I got him to <lb/>agree to consult O'Brien. I had a further <lb/>interview after he had done so the gist of <lb/>which appears to be - when the usual <seg type="del">when <lb/>the usual</seg> <seg type="unclear">expands</seg> "fighting for an <lb/>opening" statements were strained off - <lb/>that they seem desirous of coming into <lb/>the fold again. I told him if anythng <lb/>was likely to ensure something more <lb/>definite must be done.   The following which I took down in <lb/>writing is what he then said. <lb/>"If Mr Redmond will forthwith call" <lb/>"a meeting to consider the reorganisation" <lb/>"of the national movement on broader" <lb/>"lines with a view to national unity" <lb/>"and make all nationalist members" <lb/>"including those non members of the" <lb/>"Party to a conference on the subject" <lb/>"Mr O'Briens party will attend."   I immediately told Healy that in my 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3496_img_2903_3"/>
            opinion any such conferences would almost of necessaity result <lb/>in the accentuation of differences and personal bitterness <lb/>rather than in the reuniting of the different sections, and that <lb/>all at stake would be at the mercy of the irresponsible firebrands <lb/>in both sections. I said it seemed to be hopeless to put forward <lb/>any such suggestion and that I would like to think over the <lb/>advisability of my doing so for a few days (I thought it best <lb/>to say this so as to leave it open for me to tell him, in case <lb/>you are averse to the idea, that I had abandoned all idea of <lb/>seeking to do anything in the matter). I also said I thought <lb/>a much better course to take, if unity was to be established <lb/>between the principle people on both sides first with <lb/>a view to seeing if it would be at all possible to <seg type="del"> </seg> arrive <lb/>at a working basis and if so <hi rend="underline">then</hi> to have the meeting <lb/>he suggested. He seemed not indisposed to this <lb/>course.   This is how things were left when I parted with <lb/>him. If you would care for me to act in any way <lb/>further in this matter please let me know and <lb/>of course if you would wish me to act in any way in <lb/>bringing about an informal preliminary meeting I will <lb/>do all I can in the metter.   Yours sincerely   Edmund J Frewer 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>