<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0247">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maurice de Bunsen to Sir Matthew Nathan, 26 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maurice de Bunsen</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Maurice de Bunsen (1852–1932) to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). de Bunsen writes that he is directed by Sir Edward Grey (1862–1933), foreign secretary, to state that Grey is in communication with the Swiss government regarding the arrest of British subjects in Switzerland. The letter concerns the ability of British subjects who have been arrested in Switzerland to contact the representative of their country. De Bunsen notes that this courtesy exists in England and Grey wants to ensure that it also exists in Ireland so that he can insist that British subjects arrested in Switzerland will be able to communicate with British representatives.Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. De Bunsen was a diplomat serving as assistant under-secretary in the Foreign Office from March 1915 to March 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7564/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/247</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0899">Maurice de Bunsen</persName>
              <date>1916-04-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1469">Foreign Office, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1857">Irish Office, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0247_img_1427_1"  type="Letter"  url="eb09b7864bf2c32b43af5522e319185d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0247_img_1427_2"  type="Letter"  url="615257f17366e5ab6b72c77bb4f48e9b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0247_img_1427_1"/>
                The Under- Secretary of State  Foreign Office  London.  <lb/>Foreign Office   April 26th, 1916.  <seg type="unclear">ack. </seg> day instructions <lb/>have been issued to <lb/>the Police. <lb/>II W. <lb/>III Chief <seg type="unclear">Com</seg><lb/>Will you <lb/>please have the <lb/>necessary <lb/> instructions <lb/>EOF <lb/>8/5/16 <lb/>I done <seg type="unclear">JhD</seg><seg type="unclear">11/5</seg><lb/>I <seg type="unclear">despd</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">Jois 11/5</seg> Sir:-   I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to <lb/>state, for the information of Mr Secretary Birrell, <lb/>that he is in communication with the Swiss Government <lb/>regarding the arrest of British Subjects in <lb/>Switzerland. Various cases have recently occurred <lb/>in which the arrested persons were not permitted for <lb/>a long period after their apprehension to communicate <lb/>with His Majesty's Minister or Consular Represent- <lb/>atives in that country.  It is a generally admitted principle of inter- <lb/> national courtesy that foreign subjects or citizens <lb/>arrested or detained by the policy in any country <lb/>should at once be permitted to communicate in writing <lb/>with the Representative of their country. This <lb/>practice is invariably followed in this country and I <lb/>am to enclose herein a copy of the instructions, <lb/>issued by the Home Office to the Police in England, <lb/>which govern the matter.  Sir E Grey is, however, unaware whether the <lb/>regulations issued by the Home Office are also <lb/>applicable to Ireland. In order that he may be <lb/>enabled to insist on the Swiss Government granting <lb/>permission to British Subjects arrested in Switzerland <lb/> to  <lb/>1. Instruct 1.4. &amp; <seg type="unclear">Homme</seg> in <lb/> at Belfast by calling attention to <seg type="unclear">42c 1351</seg><lb/>2. Ch. <seg type="unclear">former</seg> D.M.P. <lb/>transmitter <lb/> Connell <lb/>12.5.16    The Under Secretary <lb/>Irish Office  <lb/>I <seg type="unclear">Done 15/5</seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0247_img_1427_2"/>
              to communicate with His Majesty's Representatives, <lb/>I am to suggest, for Mr Birrell's consideration <lb/>the advisability of issuing to the Irish Police <lb/>instructions with regard to foreigners arrested <lb/>within Ireland similar to those issued to the <lb/>English Police if such instructions are not <lb/>already in force.  A copy of this letter has been sent to the <lb/> Home Office and a similar letter addressed to the <lb/>Scottish Office. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your most obedient, <lb/>humble Servant,  Maurice de Bunsen </seg> <hi rend="underline">Office</hi><lb/>copy of attached instructions (65343) <lb/>to be sent to all divisions &amp;attention <lb/>drawn to 'Foreigner' p. 190 .code <lb/> mdp <lb/><hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">CC</seg>10/5/16</hi><lb/>Done 18/5/16    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>