<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0597">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Henry Gill SJ to Fr Thomas V Nolan SJ, 24 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry V Gill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr Henry Gill SJ (1872-1945), Irish Jesuit Chaplain, to Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941). Fr Gill writes a letter of appreciation to Fr Provincial Nolan, thanking him for keeping him updated about the goings on of other Jesuits. He hopes that things will calm down in Ireland soon, expressing distaste that some consider Irish men in the British army to be unpatriotic. The son of H.J. Gill, head of the publishing firm, M. H. Gill &amp;amp; Son, Henry was educated at Clongowes Wood College and University College Dublin. He possessed an acumen for mathematics and science and studied in Louvain and under Professor J.J. Thompson, Cavendish Laboratories, Cambridge (1906 - 1908). Fr. Gill had a special interest in seismography: &#39;Experiments with Spinning Tops to illustrate earthquake reactions&#39; was the title of a lecture given by Henry Gill at the Cavendish Laboratory, 16 June 1908. It is recorded that the hardship of four years as a chaplain in WWI, had a lasting effect on Fr. Gill. Fr. Henry Gill SJ was awarded the Military Cross and the Distinguished Service Order with the 2nd Royal Irish Rifles.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/25/49, IE IJA/CHP1/25/49</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/597</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0012">Henry V Gill</persName>
              <date>1916-06-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0735">2nd Royal Irish Rifles, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2104">Dolphin's Barn, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0597_img_2009_1"  type="Letter"  url="e9b9cbea53ac8009dd54997ecfa27331.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0597_img_2009_2"  type="Letter"  url="2e41037c0e65f6425655a6d7e20d3ccc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0597_img_2009_1"/>
                2/R. I. Rifles  B.E.F. France     24/6/1916   Dear Fr Provincial P.C.   Many thanks <lb/> for your kind letter of <lb/> congratulation. I am glad <lb/> to hear such good accounts <lb/> of the other chaplains. What <lb/> F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Browne says about <lb/>himself is still true about <lb/> me. Please renumber us <lb/>specially in your Mass <lb/> these days. I am much <lb/> better than when I was on <lb/> leave. The week helped me  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0597_img_2009_2"/>
              to pick up. I do hope things <lb/> in Ireland will soon settle <lb/> down. I think everyone must <lb/> admit no matter what their <lb/> sympathies that 'England' <lb/> has asked for trouble. The <lb/> thing which annoys me is the <lb/> suggestion that we out here are <lb/>unpatriotic. I fear this is a <lb/> dull letter but there is nothing <lb/> to tell you, even if we were free <lb/> to do so again thanking you <lb/> for your kind letter. <seg type="closer"> Believe me dear F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Provincial<lb/> Your very sincerely yours in Xt  H.V. Gill S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>