<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1227">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from W.M. Connolly to the Magistrates, Petty Sessions, Templemore, 22 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.M. Connolly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is a directive from the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland and sent by W J. Connolly in Dublin Castle to the Templemore Magistrate&#39;s Office. The letter request information on a judgement in the case of Richard Carroll, sentenced to six months with hard labour for assaulting his wife. Enclosed is a petition by Connolly, requesting that his sentence be revoked as there is nobody else to look after his wife and children, and his prisoner record.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>CSO RP/1916/6834/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1227</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0886">W.M. Connolly</persName>
              <date>1916-04-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Magistrate&#39;s Office in Templemore</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1558">Templemore, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1227_img_413_1"  type="Letter"  url="911456ee0557de319890f215989fd37f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1227_img_413_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="2bef85bd27bc8f63c782bc9ba93fc052.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1227_img_413_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="dc18d414eff42fc92d03fea90083fa71.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1227_img_413_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Form 36</hi>    Dublin Castle    22nd April 1916   GENTLEMEN,   I am directed by the Lord Lieutenant to transmit a Memorial in behalf <lb/> of Richard Carroll <lb/> and to request you will report the facts of the case, and favour me with your <lb/> opinion thereon for His Excellency's information, and with your reasons for any <lb/> recommendation you may desire to make.    If a Fine has been imposed, you will be so good as to state : <lb/> (1.) To whom it has been awarded, and <lb/> (2.) If paid, whether any portion of it has been paid over to the party to <lb/> whom it was awarded.  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/> Gentlemen, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,   W.M. Connolly </seg> N.B.—Papers to be returned. <lb/> The Magistrates <lb/> at Petty Sessions <lb/> Templemore   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1227_img_413_2"/>
              Petition from a person undergoing Imprisonment with hard labour    Limerick Prison    Date: 20 April, 1916   To His Excellency the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.   The Petition of 130 Richard Carroll  Humbly Sheweth I was <sic>conviced</sic><lb/> at Templemore petty session and <lb/><sic>senticed</sic> to six <sic>caldren</sic><lb/> months with hard labour <lb/> for <sic>assulting</sic> my wife <lb/> would you <sic>conedder</sic> my case <lb/> and take some of my <lb/> sentence off as my wife <lb/> and three children as nobody <lb/><sic>ells</sic> to look after them <lb/> but me and you petitioner as <lb/> in duty bound will <sic>everpray</sic> <seg type="closer"> Richard Carroll </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1227_img_413_3"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Form 17</hi>. <lb/> A.D. <lb/>  Form to be attached to all Petitions from Prisoners  (In cases of convicts a copy of the convict's <hi rend="underline">photograph should accompany</hi> the first petition after reception into Convict Prison.)   Date of previous Petition, <lb/> Decision on Previous Petition,   Name and Reg. No., - - -Richard Carroll. 130/16 <lb/> Age on conviction - - - 24 years <lb/> If in custody before trial state date of <lb/> committal for trial, ----Was not in custody <lb/> If bailed before trial, state date of discharge — <lb/> Date of conviction, - - -5 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April 1916 <lb/> Place of conviction and name of tribunal, Templemore Petty Sessions <lb/> Before whom tried, - - -M.Hornibrook Esq R.W. <lb/> Whether pleaded guilty or not guilty, - Convicted summarily <lb/> Crime, - - Aggravated assault on his <lb/> wife - Sarah Carroll. <lb/> Sentence, - - -6 cal. moths HL <lb/> &amp; 3 cal.months or Bail} consec. <lb/> Date from which sentence takes effect, - 5 April 1916 (warrant to commit <lb/> in default of bail <lb/> not yet lodged.) <lb/> Date of termination of sentence of im- <lb/> prisonment, - - - 4 October 1916 <lb/> Date when eligible for release on licence, <lb/> or on remission of sentence if well <lb/> conducted in meantime, - 5 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Septr. 1916 <lb/> If fined, state to whom fine is payable, - no fine imposed <lb/> Previous character and circumstances, - 3 times previously convicted <lb/> Circumstances unknown.   PREVIOUS CONVICTIONS. <lb/> (The previous convictions will only be given in connection with the first petition after each conviction. With subsequent <lb/> petitions the number of previous convictions will be summarised and a reference made by date to the first petition.) <lb/>  Date. Offence. Sentence. <lb/> 21.4.15 Steal a wooden post value s1/0 7 Days Impt or 5/ <lb/> 15.9.15 Drunk &amp;Disorderly I 14 Days or 12/- <lb/> ' ' ' malicious damage to <lb/> door of Lock-up 11 14 Days or 13/- <lb/> consec   If convicted jointly with other prisoners, <lb/> state names and sentences of such <lb/> prisoners Convicted alone   Conduct in Prison Satisfactory. <lb/> Report of Governor as to truth <lb/> of statements contained in <lb/> petition,&amp;c Statements as to offence, sentence <lb/> &amp; place of conviction correct. Truth of other <lb/> statement unknown by me.  <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">W Webb Chief Warder</hi><lb/> for Governor. sick    <hi rend="underline">H.M.Prison, Limerick</hi>   <hi rend="underline">Date, </hi> <hi rend="underline">21 April 1916</hi>  </seg> State of Health <lb/> (If the prisoner be under medical <lb/> treatment, please specify the <lb/> disease, state whether it is <lb/> of a serious character, and <lb/> whether his life is in danger <lb/> or likely to be endangered <lb/> by confinement)    <seg type="unclear">Health <lb/> W Watt <lb/></seg> Medical Officer   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>