<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2576">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Monteith to Mollie Monteith, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Monteith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Monteith (1879-1956), a founder member of the Irish Volunteers, to his wife Mary Florence (Mollie) Monteith (née McEvoy, 1877-1960). In 1909 Monteith, a Protestant, and McEvoy, a Catholic widow with three children, were married against his family&#39;s wishes. 

In 1915 Monteith was selected by Thomas Clarke (1858–1916), a veteran of revolutionary politics, to accompany Sir Roger Casement (1864–1916), to Germany to assist with recruitment of an Irish Brigade from the Irish prisoners-of-war.


In this letter Robert is missing his family in the lead up to Christmas. Robert writes that he has no news himself but asks Mollie for news of home. He reports that he is well and just waiting for further instruction. Robert tells Mollie about the snow in Berlin and asks her to past on his regards to everyone before signing off.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Brother Allen Collection, IE/AL/RM/2/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2576</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0377">Robert Monteith</persName>
              <date>1915-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0296">Limburg, Hesse, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Florence Monteith (née McEvoy)</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2576_img_2003_1"  type="Letter"  url="e88e0d4c111f190274396f178168e770.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2576_img_2003_2"  type="Letter"  url="9e7457748d91846cff99feb6403ebe24.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2576_img_2003_3"  type="Letter"  url="a392450425c31c5628d40f6fa9a561db.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2576_img_2003_4"  type="Letter"  url="0caae1ec096997b64b6b0b13979c86e1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2576_img_2003_1"/>
             Irish Brigade   22.XII.15 <lb/> Mollie Sweetheart   No letter met my own, God but the<lb/>writing is hard. It is so near Xmas again.<lb/>You remember back when we were separated by<lb/>only a hundred odd miles - today we have to<lb/>reckon in thousands, then we thought the<lb/>distance long but now it is so long that I<lb/>am prohibited from seeing you - a year ago I<lb/>was counting the hours until you would reach<lb/>Limerick - but now I cannot count the hours till<lb/>you reach Berlin. However I do so hope that<lb/>you will have a good time, you and all of yours. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2576_img_2003_2"/>
             I saw (or at least I take it so) Florries name in<lb/>the Gaelic American in the last <seg type="unclear">?</seg>   we<lb/>received here In conversation with the  <lb/>Blair - &amp; poor Joe have you heard from her?<lb/>I hope the path is smoother than I have been able<lb/>to make yours. — Have you heard from any<lb/>of the people at home? I am going crazy<lb/>for news. You saw the photo of the A.C.O. of the<lb/>1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> Company of the Brigade. These are my <seg type="unclear">?</seg> <lb/>one of them is a brother of John Jo. It is such<lb/>a small world ! I knew him immediately I<lb/>laid eyes on him, he is a good chap — so<lb/>are they all, another of them is brother in law<lb/>to McGuirk. They said McGuirks <seg type="del">broth</seg> photo<lb/>is hanging in his room —      I have no news darling - that is that    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2576_img_2003_3"/>
             I can send to you - I went to Berlin for<lb/>a week end on last Saturday. I tried to<lb/>think of you meeting me at the Potsdamer<lb/>Banhof as you used to meet me at Amiens<lb/>in the days gone by - but no such luck—  I am doing al right so you need<lb/>not worry about me, the only thing is waiting<lb/>for the word Go it will come sometime, but the<lb/>waiting,   is so tedious  —  How are the little ones? Do they<lb/>ever speak of me? Will Pat know me when I<lb/>come back - is she as   as ever and<lb/> <seg type="unclear">?</seg> she should be able to guess and<lb/>calculate some by now—    How do you say as to the weather<lb/>over there, we have snow everywhere<lb/>beautiful crispy dry snow, such as we 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2576_img_2003_4"/>
            never see in poor old Ireland —  Give my best wishes to any friend of <lb/>mine whom you may drop across —   Now darling I will close, fondest love <lb/>to you &amp; all at home. You will be ready <lb/>to meet me when my work is done, with <lb/>your old sweet smile &amp; your kiss that <lb/>used to make life so worth living for me.    Write me soon, a long long letter   Yours only   <hi rend="underline">Bob</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>