<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0785">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 6 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender writes that he is &#39;very fat&#39; after receiving three letters (&#39;big meals&#39;) from Lillian that morning. He expresses anxiety that Lillian is not getting enough rest, and advises her to take time off in September when her workload is likely to have lightened. He writes of his embarrassment after accidentally sleeping in following an exhausting late night. He briefly discusses work colleagues and mutual acquaintances, and points out the irony that he is writing dispatches in which his own name is not mentioned due to some unspecified past indiscretion.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/376</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/785</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0785_img_2321_1"  type="NULL"  url="6dd4aed97dc2953c31581186404f5bb9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0785_img_2321_2"  type="NULL"  url="41096835da8639f558d1dfb41a3ef3c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0785_img_2321_3"  type="NULL"  url="4392990952b9ed05a6c9198d859f23f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0785_img_2321_4"  type="NULL"  url="aaa7b00b15da77a77173446ee77a023d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0785_img_2321_1"/>
                6 Aug   My pr   A BW very fat B with 3 <lb/>big meals today 2 dated the 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> and one <lb/><seg type="unclear">direct</seg> dated the 3rd, also rather a rather <lb/>swollen W with pr's compliments. I am glad <lb/>you have picked up another real friend <lb/>in Mrs Henry, but pr's always do <lb/>when the bw is away &amp; can't scare <lb/>them off. My letters come by King's <lb/>messengers now about at least so I <lb/>believe or perhaps only the papers do  Lavender very nice to smell tho' it <lb/>has been nearly a week getting here.  Rather anxious about you. I <lb/>think you will have to go away in  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0785_img_2321_2"/>
              September if not before and someone <lb/>do in the committee ought to be able <lb/>to manage by them as the work <lb/>should be less. Then an other splendid <lb/>woman about even if no other <lb/>pr ! !  I was up til 12 30 on <lb/>one report and had told Douglas to <lb/>call me for 7 30 sevice but thought <lb/>no such <seg type="unclear">warn</seg> of it that I slept on <lb/>till 8 20 ! ! and was too ashamed to <lb/>have breakfast so had chocolate in my <lb/>room &amp; thus got in with the first <lb/>flight at 8.40. I ate extra good <lb/>lunch and must get exercise today as <lb/>yesterday I got none tho' I bustled about  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0785_img_2321_3"/>
              rather <sic>hecticly</sic> in a car visiting the <lb/>Reserve army HQ when I was known <lb/>by someone whom I don't recognise now. <lb/>At the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Army <seg type="unclear">Barge</seg> is a good friend of useful <lb/>information â just a little jealous of a Col but <lb/>very nice. Sammy Wilson gave me <lb/>a look in the other day and has made <lb/>me promise to visit him at the first <lb/> opportunity at the First army so at <lb/>nearly all the Armies I have a pal at <lb/>HQ.  Do you remember a man at <lb/>Chatham in our <seg type="unclear">House</seg> called <seg type="unclear">Mathison</seg><lb/> now a Lt Col. A rather quiet shy <lb/>elderly sapper. He turned up today, which <lb/>various MP people are about.  I forget when your ban is up, but  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0785_img_2321_4"/>
              if in Dept why not take a holiday then <lb/>before getting into a new abode. poor pr.  Yes I think then an other Capt <seg type="unclear">GS010</seg><lb/>but any how I am by no means a chicken as <lb/>GSO in <seg type="unclear">know ways</seg> It is rather funny <lb/>that I should be writing the dispatch in which <lb/>my name is not even to be mentioned <lb/>only to 'the' letter.  I must stop prattling <seg type="closer"> still your   bw  (in spite <lb/>of Fanny's distinct charms)   WB Spender  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>