<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0133">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from D. M. R. to Mary Ellen O'Rahilly, 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>D. M. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Mary Ellen (‘Nell’) O’Rahilly. The letter concerns the death of Mary O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s brother, Michael, in which the author offers their condolence and praises Michael for his actions. She informs Nell that she has cut Michael&#39;s photo out of the paper as his name will &#39;live in History&#39;.Michael Joseph &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875–1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill and Bulmer Hobson who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on the Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated. Nell was also involved in the Nationalist movement as a member of Cumann na mBan and was imprisoned after the Rising for her role.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/121/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/133</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0522">D. M. R.</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Ellen O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0133_img_1227_1"  type="Letter"  url="f6ae3a0ef38cca2ed6be8f0404e39632.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0133_img_1227_2"  type="Letter"  url="71f6d45013b9f2e19e3d906e8019c47c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0133_img_1227_3"  type="Letter"  url="75414552c5d0f3d59d794d76d948de77.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0133_img_1227_4"  type="Letter"  url="3d87fb1a4090fb906aa0b938fb0517e4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0133_img_1227_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">20th May 1916</hi>   My dear Nell   I cannot tell <lb/> you how much I feel<lb/> for, &amp; sympathise with<lb/> you, &amp; dear Anna on the<lb/> death of poor Michael R.I.P.<lb/> Since the Post was <hi rend="underline">allowed</hi><lb/> to come here I've been<lb/> trying to write to you<lb/> but I feel things <hi rend="underline">too</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0133_img_1227_2"/>
              much to be able to <lb/> speak of them, especially<lb/> as my letter must be public <lb/> &amp; <hi rend="underline">common property!</hi>  However one thing must<lb/> ever be a comfort to<lb/> you, &amp; that is that <lb/> Michael is <hi rend="underline">surely</hi> in<lb/> Heaven. I cut (&amp; mean to keep)<lb/> his Photo out of the Paper.<lb/> He died as a hero, &amp; his<lb/> name shall live in History.<lb/> I am proud of being  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0133_img_1227_3"/>
              Irish. This Isle of ours is <lb/> indeed worthy to be called<lb/> 'the Island of Saints &amp; Martyrs'.<lb/> I must call to see you<lb/> as soon as I can. Poor<lb/> Dick, how I feel for him.<lb/> But we can only pray. <lb/> I know you'll be brave<lb/> &amp; strong during this terrible  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0133_img_1227_4"/>
              time of trial. You<lb/> &amp; Anna are far braver<lb/> than I should be<lb/> under the circumstances.<lb/> But enough now till<lb/> we meet, which I<lb/> hope shall be <hi rend="underline">very<lb/> soon</hi>. With fondest<lb/> love to you &amp; Anna<lb/><sic>Shelia</sic> &amp; <sic>Emmit</sic>. <seg type="closer"> Yours affectionately <lb/> D.M.R. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>