<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4256">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 7 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/92</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4256</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-07</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4256_img_3622_1"  type="Letter"  url="327e1e4925ba46b60eaba3c2225350aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4256_img_3622_2"  type="Letter"  url="0d8bc4ce540944221b25214499f4fc43.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4256_img_3622_3"  type="NULL"  url="a6d2eddd6de2b85547f700dcb8a72883.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4256_img_3622_4"  type="NULL"  url="b4d57f1a8a599972b34e02b8db181d14.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4256_img_3622_1"/>
             7 Dec 15   My <seg type="unclear"><seg type="del">fa</seg>2</seg>   No letter, &amp; I wanted one so badly. I expect it is a case of Sunday <lb/>posts, &amp; hope most sincerely it does not mean a poor little pale animal <lb/>with a very bad head—ache.   I want to hear you are safely back from your Mission to the <lb/>wild Irish, &amp;to know you have not been knocked down by the wild sea <lb/>horses or the other terrible animals you may have had to contend with!   I have replied to Hugh's letter &amp; suggested that the speech which he <lb/>proposes <seg type="unclear">Carm</seg> should make should be on these lines "Now that Irishmen <lb/>&amp; Englishmen &amp; Scotsmen have shed their blood side by side in the cause of <lb/>. . . . it is quite unthinkable that any one of them will wish to <lb/>cut himself adrift from the other, or to found a separatist parliament!"   I asked him whether he would approve &amp; to say what the result would <lb/>be in Ireland!   I also pointed out that the principal points in the political <seg type="unclear">fence</seg> from <lb/>the Irish point of view had been 1) to pass Home rule after the war had begun <lb/>(this I omitted) 2) to stop the temperance reform initiated by L G <lb/>3) to prevent any  steps  (<seg type="del">last</seg> except  an emasculated form of <lb/>registration in Ulster) <seg type="del">stop</seg> being taken in Ireland like the rest of the U K for <seg type="unclear">Servia</seg> <lb/>4) to contribute the smallest possible numbers to <lb/>the forcing of their coreligionist.   I might have told him on the other hand what was done by the Ulster <lb/>men who were fighting now against Germany who in former days they <lb/>regarded as the brave ideal of Protestantism, but instead I tried an olive branch <lb/>saying that I did think the religious divisions, which were an unhappy <lb/>factor (tho' not the principal one) in the case were being broken down &amp; <lb/>reconnected here last Sunday our men who <hi rend="underline">in the dark</hi> were <seg type="unclear">marching</seg> through 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4256_img_3622_2"/>
             the streets singing hymns, hushed as <lb/>they passed the RC church in service.   Last night there was a great discussion between  L  Farnham on the one <lb/>side &amp;Singleton &amp; Gus Nugent on the other as to whether the Irish were <lb/>musical. I supported the former in saying they were naturally very musical <lb/>tho' they were not good performers themselves either from lack of means or <lb/>opportunity. S was very contemptuous &amp; when I supported F was inclined to <lb/>be rude about my qualifications. L F got very heated &amp;I thought it a pity <lb/>again that G N should as usual <seg type="unclear">deny</seg> his countrymen, tho' it is of course <lb/>quite reasonable for him to hold such a view. Unfortunately it is the rule <lb/>with him to do so &amp;I hear that he regretted that the 108<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Bde should <lb/>have got a GOC Griffith with Irish blood! What are your views about the Irish <lb/>musical tastes??   H P left yesterday &amp; I hear the men gave him quite a good send off <lb/>&amp;that he was much touched. I think they believe he had more <lb/>to do with things in the past than was the case. This will, I fear <lb/>lead to further distrust, &amp;to less of the Ulster spirit, but the reconsti <lb/>tution of the 108 &amp;109 Bdes takes place on Friday, &amp; the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> under <lb/>their new CO Ashton rejoins the latter, &amp; the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> their former 108 <lb/>Bde. This will simplify your transactions as now there is <lb/>one complete Bde 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, with which you will have no dealings.   I hope to get a 1/2 day out tomorrow &amp;may perhaps visit <lb/>Gen Rimington of the Indian <seg type="unclear">Comt</seg> before he leaves. We expect to settle <lb/>in to our new Corps next week without having to move just yet, <lb/>but we are very much on the balance if anything turns up.   I can so sympathiz with McPherson in having found himself <lb/>dropped because he came out too late or too soon!   Must end, but I still find the pr very <seg type="del">troublesome</seg> persistent  at night tho sometimes she is more helpful than troublesome.   Wilfrid B Spender Your B W 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4256_img_3622_3"/>
             I meant to go to bed early but I see a chance of 10 mins peace &amp; <lb/>will begin a letter to you.   1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> when you are working &amp;have to consider not only your com— <lb/>forts but also your health &amp;work I want you to feel that I think it <lb/>right for you to do things comfortably to travel 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> class &amp;to take taxis.   The time may come when we shall not be able to manager to do <lb/>such things, but at present thanks to the rubber bounce we can quite <lb/>well in spite of the fact that we are giving over 1/3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> of our income <lb/>to the Government. If rubber continues over <seg type="unclear">3/—</seg> we shall actually be as <lb/>well off this year as when the pr popped the bw into her burrow.   Of course this cannot last, &amp;after the war rubber will collapse with <lb/>a pop — the market thinks so by the low price of shares —, but I want <lb/>my pr not to be worn to a scarecrow whilst she is alone, but to have <lb/>a nice little plump hug for the bw. You realise <seg type="unclear">Matur's</seg> view &amp; <lb/>will I know do nothing to spoil the happiness you have been to her. <lb/>I am writing this lest the pr may think she must try to hard to <lb/>act up to the b'w's former instructions, &amp;to please him by stinting her <lb/>real requirements.   By the way bw sounds uncommonly like bow wow!   Just got your Belfast letter telling of a calm crossing to Ireland <lb/>I do hope your return will be as good but we are having gales here &amp; I <lb/>hardly think it possible.   I have got enough work on hand to keep me quite busy &amp; have rather <lb/>taken the bit in my teeth in regard to 2 jobs letting others correct, but <lb/>doing the work myself first 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4256_img_3622_4"/>
              7 Dec,    HP learns today. I saw him yesterday &amp; I fear had to fib. He said he was <lb/>not sorry to leave, but I hastily changed the subject!   The 108 &amp; 109 are to rejuvenate to their old conditions, ie the <lb/>11 RIR goes back to the former &amp; the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to the latter very shortly. I am very <lb/>glad of this. A new Col has been appointed to the command of the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><seg type="unclear">Phan</seg> <lb/>inform Sir G. Col Ashton — I know nothing about him.   You had perhaps better not know of the change of battalions in the <lb/>committee till it is officially out tho' you can tell Lady that it is in the air.   I had a rather angry letter from Hugh in answer to mine <seg type="del">of</seg> on <lb/>Redmond's speech, which I will forward later. Apparently my letter has been <lb/>forwarded to J. Redmond!! It will do him good as I suggested he should <lb/>be muzzled till the end of the war.   Yes a Div has a rest camp of its own under one of the F <seg type="unclear">Ambus</seg> <lb/>at present the 109 F Am, but I should consult the OC FA before sending instru— <lb/>ments. I'm not mute if I should appreciate music. Last night several bodies <lb/>of our men were marching through the streets singing hymns &amp; quite <lb/>well. It was very dark or they would not have done it. Doesn't <lb/>that prove the latent Covenant spirit?   Longing to hear of your safe returns. I'm most anxious <lb/>to keep you altogether! Says it is like having the b w in the house!!!   Ever your b w   <lb/>Wilfrid B Spender <lb/>Please thank Jon for his letter always welcome
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>