<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5204">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cornelius Daly to Charlie Daly, 19 February 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cornelius Daly </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/8/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5204</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1388">Cornelius Daly </persName>
              <date>1923-02-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1113">KnockaneCoolteen, Ballyfinane, Firies, Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1693">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Tirconail, Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1937</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5204_img_None_1"  url="33d5d43db2f5b1fd6c006c9723dde209.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5204_img_None_2"  url="187ed2b6afc4086334fde24a64c1c8e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5204_img_None_3"  url="5d256e50f840a1a6473850d9a8fa344a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5204_img_0_1"/>
              Mr Charles Daly<lb/>Drumboe Castle<lb/>Stranorlar<lb/>Co Donegal  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5204_img_0_2"/>
             P41/8/5   Knockaneainleen    Feb 19th 1923    My Own Dear Charlie   I would have written to you<lb/>long since but your Mother prevented<lb/>me from doing so, Oh Charlie I had an<lb/>awful anxious time about you, but some<lb/>how I had a feeling that nothing would<lb/>happen to you, for Charlie you were always<lb/>very good. I knew your feelings very well<lb/>Charlie and the Sirit that would sustain<lb/>you to face any <seg type="unclear">Pater,</seg> Oh I am so Proud<lb/>of you Charlie - Well Charlie I went<lb/>to see my big cousin he wasnt in<lb/>very good humour when I went in to him<lb/>but I was prepared for him, here said I will<lb/>talk about ourselves &amp; Old times so we had<lb/>a long shanachee so I got him into the<lb/>humour I wanted him I can make very<lb/>bold on him we were grat chums in<lb/>our young days. so I find he has enough<lb/>of of the Old Nature in him he is a<lb/>grand Old Fellow after all - Oh by the way<lb/>he asked a good deal about you. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5204_img_0_3"/>
             Well Charlie we are all well Thank God<lb/>our Friends are all well, there was a<lb/>letter from Tom today from Mountjoy<lb/>he is well Poor Thomas he is a Gallant<lb/>Lad too. oh by the way I ought to tell<lb/>you that Father Brennan is very<lb/>anxious about you, I am sure he is<lb/>very good Natured, of course May &amp;<lb/>your Mother tells you all the news<lb/>by the way Charlie your Mother<lb/>is holding up bravely thank God<lb/>and your Grandmother of course she<lb/>poor woman is Praying away like<lb/>mad for you. there was a letter from<lb/>Katty Allman today she is well and<lb/>she is offering up a lot of prayers for you<lb/>herself and the Nuns, Now give my best<lb/>wishes to your Dear Comrades.<lb/>now Dear Boy have no more to say<lb/>ah yes I was very well with your letter<lb/>to me, now I will say once more that<lb/>I feel I know that you will be all right   Your Verry Fond Father<lb/>Good Bye for a while  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>