<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0844">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard O'Carroll, 10 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard O&#39;Carroll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Richard O&#39;Carroll (1876-1916) to an unknown person. In this letter, O&#39;Carroll asks the recipient to help a Mrs. Tracy[?] to get &#39;one of the houses on Church St.&#39;. He notes that &#39;her husband is one of our best members&#39;. A note on the letter reads that O&#39;Carroll died in action in 1916.O&#39;Carroll was a bricklayer, a trade unionist, and a nationalist. He served from 1906 as the general secretary of the Ancient Guild of Incorporated Brick and Stonelayers, in 1912 he succeeded James Larkin (1876-1947) as the head of the Labour Party in Dublin Corporation, and in 1913 he was active in the Lockout. A member of the Irish Republican Brotherhood, O&#39;Carroll fought in the area of Camden Street during Easter Week 1916. He was shot through the lungs by Captain J.C. Bowen-Colthurst (1880-1965), and died in Portobello military hospital on 5 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br Allen Collection, Green Autograph Book 1, IE/AL/GAB1/66</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/844</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0787">Richard O&#39;Carroll</persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0094">49 Cuffe Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0844_img_2402_1"  type="Letter"  url="5be2bff3095ee074d2b44e2aff36dd80.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0844_img_2402_1"/>
              Killed in <lb/> action 1916   THE ANCIENT GUILD OF INCORPORATED BRICK AND STONELAYERS, <lb/> HEAD OFFICE: 49 CUFFE STREET, DUBLIN    Dublin Branch,  10-11 1915   Dear Sir,    Kindly help Mrs   to <lb/> get one of the cottages in Church <lb/> St. Her husband is one of our best <lb/> members.  <seg type="closer"> Yours etc.  R. O'Carroll </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>