<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1452">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay 18 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.James tells of his colleague who have been arrested under flimsy pretexts and are being kept in poor conditions. He also talks about Sheehy Skeffington and Casement and the good potato harvest.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1452</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-16T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1452_img_889_1"  type="Letter"  url="fe01e4f853cf550c6104547a7a448719.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1452_img_889_2"  type="Letter"  url="0b420cdf2e382d918e41fdc79a5a29f0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1452_img_889_1"/>
                NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION (IRELAND),  PEMBROKE HOUSE,  UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN.    18th May, 1916.   My dearest May,   I intended writing to you yesterday but I couldn't <lb/>manage even five minutes all the morning and as the post still <lb/>closes at 3 p.m. it was too late when I managed to have <seg type="del">you</seg><lb/>a few minutes to myself in the evening. John FitzGerald was in <lb/>the office yesterday for a while recounting his experiences in prison. The <lb/>only charge against him was that he 'spoke Irish continually in his home <lb/>and played Irish and German music on his piano' and his neighbour, <lb/>a man named Casey over 50 years of age, was charged that 'between <lb/>the 22nd April and 1st May he was seen speaking to people who were <lb/>believed to be Sinn Feiners'. Absolutely nothing else on the charge sheet of <lb/>either party and although they were kept in prison for five days, they were <lb/>never examined or called upon to answer any charge whatsoever. Both <lb/>were released on Tuesday morning. They slept 25 in one room on the floor <lb/>with one blanket each and neither chair, table, pillow, knife, fork, spoon <lb/>or  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1452_img_889_2"/>
              or any other means of making themselves clean or comfortable. When they <lb/>wanted to sit down they could sit on their <seg type="unclear">pug</seg> He tells me also <lb/>that there were 7 men in all shot without trial in Portobello Barracks, <lb/>that is SheehyâSkeffington and 6 others and that Skeffington was not shot by <lb/>a firing party but by a Captain Colthurst (one of the Coltshurts of Cork) <lb/>by his own hand with a revolver. I haven't seen any news of the <lb/>Casement trial worth relating. Up to the present the only evidence produced <lb/>was the usual tall yarns about his founding an Irish Brigade in Germany <lb/>and his landing at Ardfert.   About Father Moran, I will write to him to day asking <lb/>him to do the job for us. Why do you hope it will go off all <lb/>right. I'm quite sure now that we will be all right after all the dangers <lb/>and troubles we have all been through and I am trusting therefore in <lb/>God's goodness that for some reason or another I have been thought worthy to <lb/>be married to you. We were all delighted to hear about Johnnie's journey and <lb/>hope that his troubles are now over. Glad to hear that you are all <lb/>busy with the spuds. This weather is grand for all the spring work. How did <lb/>you manage to get the pains in your legs. Aren't you very silly to be running <lb/>the risk of getting your death of cold. I'll have to take better care of you <lb/>than you do yourself when I get possession of you. No news otherwise <lb/>except that we are nearly evicted out of house and home these days with the <lb/>painters. Regards to all and with fondest and dearest love to my dear &amp; darling.  <seg type="closer"> Ever your loving  James. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>