<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0816">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. J. Loughborough Ball to Augustine Birrell, 1 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A. J. Loughborough Ball</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by A. J. Loughborough Ball to Augustine Birrell. In this letter Ball refers to the recent damage caused in Dublin city due to the Easter Rising and promotes his own candidacy as an insurance surveyor in connection with assessing this damage.Birrell (1850-1933) served as the chief secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish education system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares and, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred leading to his resignation on 1 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7451</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/816</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0630">A. J. Loughborough Ball</persName>
              <date>1916-05-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0712">6 King&#39;s Bench Walk, Inner Temple E.C., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0816_img_2359_1"  type="Letter"  url="0c1ddd06bdd2671285242f6aa539e1f4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0816_img_2359_1"/>
                6 Kings Bench Walk  Inner Temple E.C    1st May 1916    The Secretary of States for Ireland,  Dublin Caste.   Sir,   I should be very glad if your Department would avail<lb/> themselves of my services in connection with assessing the<lb/> recent damages in Dublin due to Civil commotion and Usurped <lb/> power. I have been acting for the various Insurance Companies<lb/> throughout the British Isles for the last eighteen years, <lb/> and, more recently, I have been dealing with Aircraft losses<lb/> on behalf of His Majesty's Government, and any work entrusted<lb/> to me by the Irish Government would receive my immediate <lb/> personal attention. <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,  <hi rend="underline">A. J Loughborough Ball</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>