<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0245">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Advertising Manager of the Belfast Telegraph to Sir Matthew Nathan, 19 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Advertising Manager of the Belfast Telegraph</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from the Advertising Manager of the Belfast Telegraph to Sir Matthew Nathan. The advertising manager requests that the Belfast Telegraph be added to the list of newspapers that receiving the Belfast Police Courts advertisements, as it claims to have the largest circulation of any newspaper published in Ireland. The letter also encloses a newspaper advertisement concerning the election for the position of an assistant clerkship in the police courts Belfast.Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7109/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/245</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0323">Advertising Manager of the Belfast Telegraph</persName>
              <date>1916-04-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0050">Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0152">Sir Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0245_img_1421_1"  type="Letter"  url="56e0006afc0721b26a47ad1befd5aad3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0245_img_1421_2"  type="Letter"  url="0c36c90688613c0eb46b8d4da3d7a6a1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0245_img_1421_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="84b6047369e4398db226fe8e20c5f05f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0245_img_1421_1"/>
               Belfast,  19th April, 1916    The Under-Secretary,  to His Excellency the Lord Lieutenant,  Dublin Castle,  DUBLIN.   Dear Sir,   I understand the system of advertising vacancies <lb/> in the Belfast Police Court has been arranged so that two <lb/> newspapers only receive these advertisments, namely, the <lb/> ''Belfast News-Letter'',which represent the Unionist side.   I claim that the 'Belfast Evening Telegraph' is <lb/> a newspaper which should be availed of to advertise all <lb/> Government appointments in Belfast. It has the largest <lb/> circulation of any newspaper published in Ireland, and as <lb/> that circulation is confined to Ulster, two-thirds of same <lb/> being in the city of Belfast and one-third through the <lb/> province, there is no newspaper which can equal pub- <lb/> licity. While I have no desire that either of the news- <lb/> papers mentioned should be deprived of these advertisements, <lb/> I think that the 'Belfast Telegraph' should be added.   The Constabulary of Belfast have for many years <lb/> appealed to the 'Belfast Telegraph' for free publicity of  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0245_img_1421_2"/>
              To The Under-Secretary <lb/> to His Excellency the Lord Lieutenant. <lb/> information they desire to convey to the public. In fact, <lb/> the 'Belfast Telegraph' is the only newspaper the Police <lb/> utilize in endeavoring to obtain information as to the <lb/> owners of lost property, persons missing and, when necessary, <lb/> the identification of dead bodies found, etc., etc. This <lb/> testimony to the value of the 'Belfast Telegraph' as a means <lb/> of reaching the public is my reason for suggesting that this <lb/> paper should be added to the list of newspapers receiving <lb/> these and other official advertisements.   I am certain if you would address the Commissioner <lb/> of Police, or any official who has resided in Belfast, he <lb/> would corroborate the above statement.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  The Advertisement Manager </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0245_img_1421_3"/>
              The Proprietors of the 'Belfast Evening Telegraph' <lb/> would feel obliged by an order to insert enclosed <lb/> Advertisement.  <seg type="head">APPOINTMENT <lb/> ASSISTANT CLERKSHIP, <lb/> POLICE <hi rend="underline">COURTS</hi>, BELFAST. <lb/></seg> HIS EXCELLENCY THE LORD LIEU- <lb/> TENANT has directed that an ELEC- <lb/> TION shall be held for an ASSISTANT <lb/> CLERKSHIP ( 3rd Class ) in the POLICE <lb/> COURTS, BELFAST. The ELECTION to fill <lb/> this Post will take place at the POLICE COURTS, <lb/> BELFAST, on WEDNESDAY, the 3rd day of <lb/> May, 1916, at the hour of Three o'clock p. m.   The order of the Lord Lieutenant, made under <lb/> 7 Edward VII., Cap. 22, directs that a Candi- <lb/> date for the Post of Assistant at Belfast shall for <lb/> the period of the War be between the ages of 41 <lb/> and 50 years.   Candidates will be required to have a know- <lb/> ledge of Typewriting and Shorthand, and should <lb/> present themselves to the Chief Clerk one week <lb/> before the Election with a view of this qualifica- <lb/> tion being tested.    The Salary for the vacant Clerkship will com- <lb/> mence at &amp;#163;80 per annum, increasing to &amp;#163;150 per <lb/> annum by increments of &amp;#163;7 per annum.   The Candidate elected will be examined by the <lb/> Medical Officer of the Registrar of Petty Ses- <lb/> sions Clerks' Department, and will be required <lb/> to satisfy the Registrar as to his educational <lb/> qualifications for the appointment. <lb/>  ( By Order ) <lb/> ( Signed ) JOHN G. BALLENTINE., <lb/> Chief Clerk <lb/> 862 <lb/> 18th April 1916. <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>