<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0730">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Flossie Briggs to George Hackney, 1 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Flossie Briggs</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Flossie Briggs to George Hackney (1889-1977). Flossie opens the letter with an account of her train journey from Sheffield back to the Guest House in Hope, Derbyshire, where she works. She tells him that &#39;we have the full number of guests for the weekend (over 60)&#39;, but they will be less busy during the week. She apologises that her visit to George coincided with the visit of his sister-in-law, and she worries that her own presence as a stranger spoiled the visit. She finishes the letter by making arrangements for her next visit.This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney , a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/730</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0576">Flossie Briggs</persName>
              <date>1916-10-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1173">The Guest House, Hope, Derbyshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1546">31 Ward, 'D' Block, Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0730_img_2236_1"  type="Letter"  url="1bbd88d710c200fd6781b93b6a8ed6ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0730_img_2236_2"  type="Letter"  url="8470a2f72468b301c730229215e4bf49.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0730_img_2236_3"  type="Letter"  url="874ae3d907cd1112add881f7bb05bdb8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0730_img_2236_4"  type="Envelope"  url="7a7781fa95d842a9ee948b99fff2b630.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0730_img_2236_5"  type="Letter"  url="f1e2b88788cf31e291004d3051b30982.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0730_img_2236_1"/>
                The Guest House  Hope  via Sheffield    Oct 1st 1916   Dear Mr Hackney,    After a mad rush and scramble I <lb/>managed to get the train I aimed for. The <lb/> station was packed with people &amp; somehow I <lb/>lost sight of my luggage (and the porter in <lb/> whose charge it was!) However 'alls well'- <seg type="unclear">ek</seg> - <lb/> and I arrived safely — bag &amp; baggage — here!  The Staff all seemed pleased to have me <lb/> back again, (I'll be getting spoiled &amp; conceited!) <lb/> and now, today, when in harness again. <lb/> Eastbourne seems like a dream — though a happy <lb/> one.  We have the full number of guests for the <lb/> weekend (over 60), but during the week the <lb/> number goes down to less than half, I <lb/>believe.  Now I must tell you how pleased I was <lb/> to spend a short time with you yesterday, &amp; <lb/> that you are progressing favourably in health.  I was sorry that the visit of your <lb/>sister-in-law &amp; her sister happened the same  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0730_img_2236_2"/>
              time as mine — for I fear they would not <lb/> enjoy the time with you as much as they <lb/> anticipated, with me, a stranger to them <lb/> being present. I was selfishly sorry, too. <lb/> But never mind, I say, another chance may <lb/> turn up ere long.  In fact I already have a proposition to <lb/>offer. Owing to a large number of Free <lb/> Guests coming here next week &amp; then my <lb/>'Head's' absence on holiday I shall not be <lb/> able, I'm afraid, to have a full 'off' day during <lb/> that time so I am to have one <hi rend="underline">this</hi> week, and <lb/> as far as I know today, it will be <hi rend="underline">Thursday</hi><lb/>. Now, if you would like, I will come over to <lb/> see you on that day. it would be a pleasure <lb/> to me to do so. I know you are expecting <lb/> your brother some time this week — that's right <lb/> isn't it? — so <hi rend="underline">please</hi> if he is to come on <lb/> Thursday, <hi rend="underline">don't</hi> think I shall be offended if <lb/> you ask me not to come. I <hi rend="underline">quite</hi> understand, 'Patsy'. And in that case we <lb/> can arrange something later. See?   I don't know when you will get this letter — <lb/> the posts from here are very erratic, but perhaps you <lb/> wouldn't mind answering as soon as it is  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0730_img_2236_3"/>
              convenient.  Of course I should go to Sheffield in the <lb/> morning so could be up to the Hospital early <lb/> in the afternoon. Do you think you would <lb/> be allowed out by then? Or only just to <lb/> the gate again?   But no thinking about that till I hear again <lb/> from you. Now mind! just please yourself <lb/>and I will fall in with your decision.  So, for tonight, goodbye. <seg type="closer"> Every good wish to you <lb/>from  <hi rend="underline">Flossie Briggs</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0730_img_2236_4"/>
               envelope  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0730_img_2236_5"/>
               envelope   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>