<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0147">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles E. Jacob to Joseph Brennan, 6 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles E. Jacob</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Charles E. Jacob to Joseph Brennan (1887-1976). The letter concerns the occupation of Jacob&#39;s Biscuit Factory, Bishop Street, Dublin, during the Easter Rising by rebels. According to Jacob the building is relatively unharmed by the occupation and that business will continue. The author of this letter, Charles E. Jacob (1860-1941), was the acting director of W. &amp;amp; R. Jacob&#39;s Biscuit Company in 1916.The letter was addressed to civil servant Joseph Brennan (1887-1976). Brennan was then serving as private secretary to the under-secretary for Ireland, Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7645/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/147</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0893">Charles E. Jacob</persName>
              <date>1916-05-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0558">Bishop Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0244">Joseph Brennan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0147_img_1269_1"  type="Letter"  url="05bcecf534d5064c1d3fe0c0bb04f047.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0147_img_1269_1"/>
                May 6th 1916    J. Brennan Esq.  Dublin Castle   Dear Sir,   In reply to your letter just received, we write to<lb/> say that our factory is practically uninjured after the<lb/> occupation by the rebels, &amp; that we have already resumed<lb/> business, &amp; we can take delivery of any goods intended for<lb/> us in the usual course. We do not know what particular<lb/> cargo your correspondent refers to but it is evidently in-<lb/> tended for us &amp; we note that it is perishable. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully, <lb/><seg type="unclear">On behalf of<lb/> Charles E Jacob</seg></seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>