<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1161">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 13 January 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the death of Father Hogan and the transfer of Father O&#39; Mahony in Egypt. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/20, IJA/CHPI/54/20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1161</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-01-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0786">Bombay, India </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1161_img_3838_1"  type="Letter"  url="db02e7e1c3d3c41d312d01718d1fc47b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1161_img_3838_1"/>
                13 Jan 1918   Dear Reverend Father Provincial, P.C.   I got news of father Hogan's death <lb/>yesterday and shall say the two masses. I am sorry <lb/>so many of the province seems to be in doubtful health. <lb/>Father Cullin would be a great loss.  F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> O'Mahony, as you probably know by this, has been <lb/>sent to Egypt again. He is in no 38. Gen. Hosp. Alexandria, <lb/>at least I think 38 in the number. His boat the 'Egypt' <lb/>came back without him. I had a card from <lb/>F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Farley also. I hope the printers strike won't delay <lb/>the Card long. Quite a large number of Irish papers <lb/>ranging from 2nd week of October to end of November came <lb/>to the wireless operator of my ship; so I am fairly well <lb/>informed as to Irish matters. The reading of the Ashe case <lb/>was very interesting. I see that President Wilson in his <lb/>statement of the American war aims says he is 'out' for the <lb/>freedom of the seas. I saw no protest from any English paper. <lb/>When the Pope mentioned the freedom of the seas as part of his <lb/>peace proposals he was at once snowed under with editorial <lb/>insults, and called a pro-German. Truly hypocrisy is a <lb/>strange thing. I hope all our chaplains are well. <lb/>I did not know of F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Monteith's death, until F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Farley's note came. <lb/>There are a number of Irishmen in high places out this <lb/>way; but I'm afraid they are not much credit to this <lb/>religion. The mail closes this evening, so I must be <lb/>brief. I saw F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Gunther's prayer yesterday. He is going up country to <lb/>a Division. <seg type="closer"> Yours obediently in Christ,  Francis M. Shaw </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>