<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0929">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arnold Graves and Thomas Bodkin to the Under Secretary of Ireland, 3 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arnold Graves</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Bodkin (1888-1961) and Arnold Graves (1847-1930) to the under secretary of Ireland regarding the Irish Estimates Debate.After studying and practising law Bodkin was appointed secretary to the commissioners of charitable donations and bequests in Ireland (1916–25). Bodkin&#39;s position with the commission and his knowledge of legal matters, placed him in an influential position within the National Gallery of Ireland. Bodkin was a close friend of Hugh Lane and was nominated in Lane&#39;s contentious codicil to help obtain premises for the proposed gallery of modern art in Dublin. An early promoter of technical education Graves was appointed secretary to the commissioners for charitable endowments and bequests in 1886 and held the post until his retirement at the age of 70 years in 1918. At the time this letter was written Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was serving as the under secretary for Ireland. Chalmers was sent to Ireland as the replacement for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916-5616-11326</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/929</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0366">Arnold Graves</persName>
              <date>1916-07-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1374">2 Kildare Place, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0929_img_2697_1"  type="Letter"  url="d231498e15bb9f579d02baa1a45239a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0929_img_2697_1"/>
                Commissioners of Charitable Donations and Bequests for Ireland.  2 Kildare Place, Dublin,    3rd day of July, 1916   Sir,   In reply to your Circular of the 1st inst., <lb/>I beg to acquaint you that in addition to the information <lb/>supplied in the Notes to the Estimates there does not <lb/>appear to be any matter which would suggest itself as <lb/> likely to form the subject of discussion in Parliament <lb/> or upon which a Memorandum would assist in connection <lb/> with the Irish Estimates Debate. <seg type="closer"> We are, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servants,  Arnold Graves <lb/><hi rend="underline">Thomas Bodkin</hi> <lb/>Secretaries.   The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>