<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2869">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 29 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>WIlfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

Spender mentions the awful weather at the front and the upcoming anniversary of the Battle of the Boyne (12 July). He tells Lillian of his views and advice for Sir Edward Carson (1854-1935). He admits his belief that a separate Ulster state would be stronger without Monaghan, Cavan, and Donegal, but insists that their excision from a future Northern Ireland would constitute a violation of the Solemn League and Covenant. He states that if Carson is working with Prime Minister David Lloyd George (1863-1945) against the wishes of other Unionists, the men of the Ulster Division will &#39;never forgive him&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/329</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2869</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0708">WIlfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-06-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2869_img_2281_1"  type="NULL"  url="29d06f048a4f840f19127080efc007e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2869_img_2281_2"  type="NULL"  url="928de5bb8bc7d6648b45370c1c9fc8a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2869_img_2281_3"  type="NULL"  url="9436e3fd776f0ba2431b7e7c09a8a834.JPG"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2869_img_2281_4"  type="NULL"  url="d4c8c158ffc1520af73a30f97d674a63.JPG"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2869_img_2281_1"/>
             29.   My pr   Just up to the line for <lb/> a visit when things are pretty busy. <lb/> The weather is against us as usual <lb/> which is a very great nuisance but here <lb/>it is as bad a winter.    The day after tomorrow is the <lb/> anniversary of the Boyne Battle, &amp; <lb/> our men are not forgetful of this. <lb/> I fancy the weather conditions are 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2869_img_2281_2"/>
            the same there?    Very sorry not to send proper letters <lb/>now.   As regards my view for Sir Edward <lb/> they are as follows:-   The compromise was only right for <lb/> imperial necessities, eg. the american ammun— <lb/>ition factor.   I have seen a foreign office letter <lb/>saying this did not enter into affairs at present, <lb/>so either Sr Edward was misled or he unwitting— <lb/>ly — I know — but more than he completely — <lb/>misled the 3 counties into agreeing to their
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2869_img_2281_3"/>
             self sacrifice.  I personally believe Ulster if it has to<lb/>be separated will be stronger without the<lb/>3 counties but the Covenant cannot be<lb/>broken unless they <seg type="unclear">reban</seg> the others without<lb/>any misunderstanding.  I think the Unionists made an awful<lb/>mistake in not having a consultation of<lb/>leaders but B L <seg type="del">&amp; Cur</seg> seems to have<lb/>conveyed quite a wrong impression to<lb/>Carson who acted on it without <sic>virifying</sic><lb/>facts.  If Carson is now working with L G &amp;<lb/>A for the proposals which W L &amp; the other 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2869_img_2281_4"/>
             Unionists dislike, this Division will never<lb/>forgive him, even <sic>tho'</sic> he is acting on<lb/>what he believes to be good grounds.   Your B W<lb/>W B Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>