<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1178">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 23 January 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s transfer. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/40, IJA/CHPI/54/40</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1178</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1919-01-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0786">Bombay, India </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1178_img_3855_1"  type="Letter"  url="023d6e72cc9d1365665276df2710f6ca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1178_img_3855_1"/>
                Archbishop's House  Wodehouse R<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">d</hi></hi>  Bombay.    23/2/19   My dear Father Provincial P.C.   Another letter arrived from your <lb/>Reverence, with news of the invasion of Germany by our <lb/>chaplains, and the capture of Cologne by F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> MacSheahan. <lb/>There is constant changing of demobilization schemes out <lb/>here, but we are informed that we shall get away before <lb/>long. Six Catholic chaplains are wanted to stay with <lb/>the Army of occupation, and there are six willing. <lb/>But only the Lord knows what will happen. My senior <lb/>chaplain tells me I will get away at the end of <lb/>March or sooner. I hope he means it. On my <lb/>last journey round my hospital I had 7 Catholic patients, <lb/>and three of them left next day. At my Mass here on <lb/>Sunday there were 9 persons present, and at the second <lb/>Mass two miles away 10.  The suffragia for Fathers Sydes, P. Kane, and Hayden <lb/>reached me. But F<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Browne should not address them <lb/>to 16 C.S.S. I left that unit last April. They go <lb/>wandering about Mesopotamia.  I am very thankful to your Reverence for helping <lb/>my sisters. Angela has great pluck.  A few days ago five of our chaplains and the <lb/>Patriarch of Babylon (Chaldean) with the bishop of <lb/>Sinna in Kurdistan, and eight or ten Chaldean priests <lb/>were photographed together. I shall send a copy to <lb/>your Reverence.  Is there any news of the exiles in Austria?  Masses for January 20.  ' ' February 20.  I recommend myself to your Reverences Masses &amp; prayers. <seg type="closer"> Yours obediently in Christ  Francis M Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>