<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5278">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 17, October, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell is in a very remote area with no houses. He wonders if the post will be slower and suspects some parcels have &#34;gone west&#34;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5278</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-10-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5278_img_None_1"  url="ffd3ce6f69116ca8c6b837690fc6307b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5278_img_None_2"  url="74f3565ea1fc53055d47e27ef2414e0f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5278_img_None_3"  url="7f417380d997b0ee834657086621432e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5278_img_0_1"/>
              Saturday 17th Oct 17    My dear Daddy   There is really very little news that I<lb/>can tell you. We are in an absolutely<lb/>desolate part of the world. We are in<lb/>quite a nice camp and are quite<lb/>comfortable and warm which is the great<lb/>thing. I was delighted to get your<lb/>parcel of 10th yesterday. I think tho' that<lb/>some parcels must have gone West or<lb/>in any case been considerably<lb/>delayed. however they may all come<lb/>in time.  So far my efforts to find Garrett have<lb/>been no good. I have not even<lb/>found his company but I got<lb/>information tonight which may<lb/>lead me to were he is. I hope so<lb/>any way but sure he may be on<lb/>leave by now.  We have a lot of new officers and<lb/>men, many of whom I knew before. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5278_img_0_2"/>
             The weather is quite respectable. We<lb/>have not had any rain for some<lb/>days.  I got no letters from you yesterday<lb/>or today but no doubt they will<lb/>all come in a bunch.  I scribled a line in a great hurry<lb/>to you today to catch the post as<lb/>I was just going out.  I don't know if my letters will<lb/>take longer now but I should<lb/>not think so. However time<lb/>will tell that.  I wrote Bobby a line today<lb/>too as I had not written to<lb/>in for 3 or 4 days.  The only thing really peculiar about<lb/>this part of the world is that there<lb/>is not a single house anywhere<lb/>standing. Parts of the country<lb/>all the trees were cut too but we 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5278_img_0_3"/>
             are on the edge of a big wood.  I will write you as long a letter<lb/>as possible again soon but there<lb/>is no news here as we never see<lb/>anyone to get any news from.  With best love to all<lb/> Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>