<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6704">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frank P. Walsh to all State Chairmen, 12 December 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frank P. Walsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Frank P. Walsh (1864-1939), was an American lawyer and political reformer. He was one of the chief architects of the legislative struggle against industrial exploitation of children and an advocate of Irish and anti-imperialist causes. He also fought for civil liberties and was a labour partisan and staunch New Dealer. Walsh was a member of the Irish-American delegation (along with Michael J. Ryan and Edward F.Dunne) who were appointed to represent Ireland at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919.10 April 1919 the delegation arrived in Paris. The men returned to America in July 1919 where Walsh began working with the Dail External Loan (Bond Drive).
This letter was a good news bulletin to all state chairmen of the bond drive. States involved in preparations for the bond drive are listed with a brief description of the positive results seen in the bond drive to date. The Letter ends with the brief sentence asking chairmen to make their needs known to Walsh to ensure a successful Bond Drive.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>William Burke Cockran Papers, Box 13, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6704</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0925">Frank P. Walsh</persName>
              <date>1919-12-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">All State Chairmen</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1646">New York</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6704_img_None_1"  url="phpK1kKpw.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6704_img_0_1"/>
             AMERICAN COMMISSION ON IRISH INDEPENDANCE  FRANK P. WALSH, CHAIRMAN  411 Fifth Ave.,  New York, N.Y.  GOOD NEWS BULLETIN NO. 1- TO ALL STATE CHAIRMEN.  December 12, 1919.  <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">Alabama</hi></hi>:</hi> Mobile reports Committee with Chairman, Vice Chairman, Secretary<lb/>Publicity agent and Executive Committee of Ten.  <hi rend="underline">California:</hi> State Offices established in San Francisco: Captain Edward M.<lb/>O'Reilly, 504 Grant Bldg., San Francisco, Permanent Secretary.  <hi rend="underline">Connecticut:</hi> State Chairman reports acceptance by City Chairmen in fifteen<lb/>cities.  <hi rend="underline">Idaho:</hi> Three County Chairmen- including Boise.  <hi rend="underline">Indiana:</hi> Judge J.M. Deery, National President A.O.H. , State Chairman, reports<lb/>organization well under way in Indianapolis and Terre Haute, and chairmen ap-<lb/>pointed in six other cities.  <hi rend="underline">Michigan:</hi> Committee of five outstanding citizens directing operations in Detroit.  <hi rend="underline">Minnesota:</hi> State Committee formed with officers in St. Paul, Minneapolis and<lb/>Duluth where drive is being prepared.  <hi rend="underline">Nebraska:</hi> Central committee of sixty, in Omaha completing, with approval of<lb/>Archbishop and, on His Grace's suggestion, organization in all parishes.  <hi rend="underline">New Jersey:</hi> City Chairmen appointed in eight principal cities.  <hi rend="underline">New York:</hi> Organization in Greater New York proceeding by Assembly Districts.  <hi rend="underline">North Carolina:</hi> Organization completed in Charlotte.  <hi rend="underline">Ohio:</hi> Central Committee and officers appointed and organization in twenty eight<lb/>parishes in Cleveland. 364,000, advance pledges. Same plan being developed in<lb/>other cities.  <hi rend="underline">Oregon:</hi> Chairman, Vice Chairman, Secretary, Treasurer and representative committee<lb/>of ten appointed and at work.  <hi rend="underline">Pennsylvania:</hi> City Chairmen appointed in all most important cities and many<lb/>counties.  <hi rend="underline">Wisconsin:</hi> City of Milwaukee organized with City Chairman, Secretary, Treasurer,<lb/>Committee of ten, over 100 workers, men and women, lists completed and indexed,<lb/>ready to start December 14th.  <hi rend="underline">Washington, D.C.:</hi> Conference, December 12, of over twenty State Chairmen with<lb/>President De Valera.  <hi rend="underline">Special:</hi> Letter issued by Mrs. Mary McWhorter, President, to all officers of<lb/>Women's Auxiliary A.O.H. urging energetic co-operation in plans of State Chair-<lb/>men.  To all State Chairmen-- What are your needs?  Frank P. Walsh, Chairman             
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>