<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1279">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Bernard Shaw to Gertrude Bannister, 12 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Bernard Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from playwright George Bernard Shaw (1856-1950) to Gertrude Parry (née Bannister). The letter refers to an enclosure that has not survived, and a letter by Shaw that was refused for publication in the Times and Daily News newspapers. Gertrude Bannister was a cousin of Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written while Casement was imprisoned after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. Bannister and Shaw were heavily involved in raising public support for Casement during his trial for treason. Casement was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List A15, Ms. 10,075/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1279</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0018">George Bernard Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-07-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1977">Ayot St Lawrence, Hertfordshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1365">Gertrude Bannister</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0816">45 Connaught Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1279_img_482_1"  type="Letter"  url="9b96ca2df4aa981b37e59c0067b7dc86.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1279_img_482_2"  type="Envelope"  url="a8ab894caadef63c655ce17f66c1b082.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1279_img_482_1"/>
                Ayot St. Lawrence, Welwyn, Herts.  Station : Wheathampstead, G.N.R. 21/4 miles.  Telegrams : Bernard Shaw, Codicote.  10 Adelphi Terrace W.C.    12 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916.    Dear Miss Bannister   Read the enclosed, which you need not return. Shorter is married <lb/> to Dora Sigerson : hence his sympathy. I have told him that you have <lb/> copies of three other petitions. Please send him copies of them : he might <lb/> get signatures.   Both the Times &amp; the Daily News refuse my letter : the D.N. <lb/> because it wishes to prevent the sentence being carried out and the T. probably <lb/> for the opposite reason.  <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely  G. Bernard Shaw.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1279_img_482_2"/>
                Miss Gertrude Bannister,  45 Connaught St  W.    Bernard Shaw  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>