<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5498">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty to Sir Roger Casement, 16 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from the Dominican priest Fr. Thomas Crotty (d. 1930, born James but took the name Thomas after he joined the order) to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written during Casement&#39;s eighteen month stay in Germany, where he was attempting to gain German support for an Irish rebellion against British rule. The letter refers to Casement&#39;s attempts to create an Irish Brigade of Irish-born British army soldiers who were then held as prisoners of war in German camps. It was the camp at Linberg, in the Lahn valley, that was designated for the project. Fr. Crotty was one of the priests who administered to the men in the camp at Limberg. The project was, however, largely unsuccessful and only fifty-six men signed up. In the letter, 

Crotty refers to a message that he had sent regarding permission to attend prisoner of war camps that had yet to receive a reply and meetings with a Major in Berlin and Robert Monteith (the officer in charge of the Irish Brigade).
Casement was later arrested in County Kerry having returned to Ireland in a submarine to try and prevent the Easter Rising from taking place as he felt German support was insufficient. He was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,085 /20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5498</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0444">Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</persName>
              <date>1915-11-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0529">Limberg, Lahn, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1930</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5498_img_530_1"  type="Letter"  url="1ee65a67c334687c33a4f1248c870c97.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5498_img_530_2"  type="Letter"  url="e9f6459b55cab554bc4c0f4746157e54.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5498_img_530_1"/>
             Limburg a/ Lahn <lb/>Missionshaus   16.XI.15   Dear Sir Roger   I have been anxiously <lb/>awaiting a line from you. I wrote <lb/>you as you remember not <lb/>long since, to say that I had for- <lb/>warded a letter to M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Meyer, and <lb/>to beg you to remind him of it.   I hope you are quite well, and <lb/>that it is not ill health that is the <lb/>cause of the delay.   Yesterday I had the honour of <lb/>a conversation with Major from <lb/>Berlin. He said some things which <lb/>led me to believe that he has been <lb/>informed by some of my <hi rend="underline">friends</hi> <lb/>about my protestation against <lb/>the action of <hi rend="underline">the Irish</hi> Prisoners. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5498_img_530_2"/>
             I hope I succeeded to convince him <lb/>of my duties here. I tried to. He seemed <lb/>to me a fine type of gentleman. I was <lb/>sorry I had such a short interview with <lb/>him. Should you have an occasion to <lb/>meet you may be able to supply <lb/>what I had not time to say to him. <lb/>I was very much surprised to hear <lb/>him question my Nationality. At <lb/>any rate he asked me. If I were an <lb/>Irishman, I told him I was one to <lb/>the backbone.   You may be interested to know that <lb/>my late Superior General, at present <lb/>Nuntius Apostolicus at Munich, is <lb/>to be soon a Cardinal Prince of Rome. <lb/>This is a great honour in my Order <lb/>and in Germany. In a few days I <lb/>mean to be in Munich, when I <lb/>hope to meet his Eminence, according <lb/>to appointment already made. I shall <lb/>have to give him a statement of <lb/>accounts of the past twelve months, which <lb/>he has promised to dispatch to Rome. <lb/>I shall let you see a copy some time.   Since the arrival of M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Monteith <lb/>I have met his companion more <lb/>than once. He shall be able to con- <lb/>vey more detailed news on his return <lb/>to Berlin.   In the meantime I wish you <lb/>all good blessings &amp; beg to remain   Yours sincerely    Fr T. Crotty O.P. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>