<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2910">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras on his article on the Irish Language.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the father of Piaras Béaslaí to Piaras on his article on the Irish Language. The contrasting attitude of Welsh policemen to the Welsh language compared to the Irish policemen to the Irish language is referred to. He states that if a Welshman was ordered to speak English instead of Welsh by the police, the whole country would be furious. However in Ireland only English is allowed. The continuing blackout is also mentioned.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2910</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2910_img_232_1"  type="Letter"  url="cda406c1f313f227829d1da88dcded0a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2910_img_232_2"  type="Letter"  url="b0bce2872292fb5ee13754865c08c2fd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2910_img_232_3"  type="Letter"  url="3ebe63aadf1ee5e3efbf8236158bad8d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2910_img_232_1"/>
             GLENGARIFF<lb/>RUDGRAVE SQUARE,<lb/>EGREMONT,<lb/>CHESHIRE.   30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March, 1916.    My dearest Pierce,    We were right glad to<lb/>get your letter. To tell the<lb/>truth, until we got it we<lb/>had been wondering why<lb/>you did not write! I hope<lb/>that shorthand special will<lb/>prove very remunerative. I<lb/>should think Collins has<lb/>done well through opportunities<lb/>of that kind. I hope he<lb/>is well. No doubt he has<lb/>quite got over the sorrow caused<lb/>by the death of his wife. I<lb/>have seen your articles on<lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2910_img_232_2"/>
             <!-- Written in 2 columns --> the Irish language in the <seg type="unclear">Leader</seg>.<lb/>The idea of continental practice<lb/>in speaking the old tongue<lb/>is excellent, but I notice<lb/>that somewhere up in Donegal<lb/>a member of the Gaelic<lb/>League has been arrested<lb/>for talking it and refusing<lb/>to speak English to the<lb/>policeman who arrested<lb/>him. That ridiculous policy<lb/>is not attempted in Wales<lb/>where the police speak <seg type="del">Irish</seg><lb/>Welsh as well as the people.<lb/>If it were made necessary for<lb/>the Welsh to speak English<lb/>at the demand of a policeman<lb/>the whole country would be<lb/>furious, but all sorts of  <lb/> stupid things are done in<lb/>Ireland with no other apparent<lb/>object than to create friction.<lb/>Here, as you say, we are in<lb/>about the safest part of Eng-<lb/>land, but for all that dangers<lb/>are plentiful enough. Being<lb/>out on Wednesday night, as I<lb/>am bound to be, is like going<lb/>through a skirmish. Last<lb/>night I had no one with me<lb/>when I left the printing works<lb/>and to get to Dale Street for<lb/>the electric car I had to go<lb/>through a little street beside<lb/>the <hi rend="underline">Courier</hi> office which has<lb/>not a single light in it. Mid-<lb/>way I could hear footsteps<lb/>quite near me, but could<lb/>see no one. The sensation<lb/>is not reassuring. However,<lb/>I got home quite safely,<lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2910_img_232_3"/>
              thank God, though I am sometimes<lb/>a little puzzled as to<lb/>where Rudgrave Square is<lb/>when coming in the car. That<lb/>question of Kitty Clancy's was<lb/>quite characteristic. The<lb/>Irish daily papers have been<lb/>very irregular in coming<lb/>of late. They give precious<lb/>little news about Ireland<lb/>and the Freeman's appearance<lb/>has become particularly ema-<lb/>ciated. We are well, thank<lb/>God, but, as usual without<lb/>news. Carey has slackened off<lb/>in his correspondence and it<lb/>is a month or more since<lb/>I have had a letter from him.<lb/>Dr Walsh and his wife often call<lb/>on Sundays. Take good care of<lb/>your health and don't fail to let<lb/>us hear from you soon.<lb/> With fondest love from Mother<lb/>and myself, Ever affectionately,<lb/>Father  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>