<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1562">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of last letter and statement by Éamonn Ceannt, 7 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Éamonn Ceannt</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a typed copy of a last letter and statement written by Éamonn Ceannt (1881-1916) on the eve of his execution in Kilmainham Gaol.
Ceannt was one of the leaders of the Easter Rising and a signatory of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic. During the Rising he commanded the garrison in the South Dublin Union. Following the surrender he was tried by court-martial and sentenced to death. He was executed on 8 May 1916.
A handwritten note by Eithne Coyle O&#39;Donnell notes that the copy was given to her by Ceann&#39;t wife, Áine (1880-1954), shortly before her death.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Eithne Coyle O&#39;Donnell Papers, P61/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1562</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0397">Éamonn Ceannt</persName>
              <date>1916-05-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1076">Kilmainham Gaol, Inchicore, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Last Letters before Death</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Last Letters before Death</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1562_img_1030_1"  type="Letter"  url="2a2a7c4ee1f5145245d04ece51b5d4e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1562_img_1030_2"  type="Photograph"  url="41e014360ea3c977ceed13491b7a1225.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1562_img_1030_1"/>
             Cell 88<lb/> Kilmainham Gaol,   May 1916    I leave for the guidance of the other revolutionaries who may tread the<lb/> path which I have trod this advice: never to treat with the enemy, never<lb/> to surrender to his mercy but to fight to a finish. I see nothing<lb/> gained but grave disaster caused by the surrender which has marked the<lb/> end of the Irish Insurrection of 1916 - so far at least as Dublin is<lb/> concerned. The enemy has not cherished one generous thought for<lb/> those who, with little hope, with poor equipment &amp; weak in members <lb/> withstood his forces for one glorious week. Ireland has shown that<lb/> she is a nation. This generation can claim to have raised sons as<lb/> brave as any that went before and in the years to come Ireland will<lb/> honour those who risked all for her honour at Easter 1916. I bear<lb/> no ill-will towards those against whom I fought. I have found the<lb/> common soldiers and the higher officers humane and companionable,<lb/> even the English who were actually in the fight against us. Thank God<lb/> soldiering for Ireland has opened my heart and helped me to see pure<lb/> humanity where I expect to find only scorn and reproach. I have<lb/> met the man who escaped from me by a ruse under the red cross but I<lb/> do not regret having withheld my fire. He gave me cakes. I wish<lb/> to record the magnificent gallantry and fearless calm determination<lb/> of the men who fought with me. All were simply splendid. Even I knew<lb/> no fear or panic and shrunk from no risk even as I shrink not now<lb/> from the death that faces me at day-break. I hope to see the face of<lb/> God even for a moment in the morning. His will be done. All here <lb/> are very kind.    My poor wife saw me yesterday and bore up; so the warder told me, even<lb/> she left my presence. Poor Aine, poor Ronan, God is their only<lb/> shield now that I am removed and God is a better shield than I.<lb/> I have seen Aine Nell Richard and Mick and <seg type="del">bid th</seg> bid them conditional<lb/> goodbye. Even now they have hope.   Eamonn Ceannt.   Received this copy of Eamonn Ceannt's last<lb/> letter from his wife before her death. <lb/>Eithne  Ni Dómnaill 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1562_img_1030_2"/>
              IRISH REBELLION. MAY 1916<lb/> EAMONN CEANNT<lb/> (Commandant of the South Dublin Area), <lb/> EXECUTED MAY 8TH, 1916. One of the signatories of the "Irish Republic Proclamation." 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>