<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0105">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Lewis Martin, 21 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). In this letter Marie writes about the difficulty and delays of sending and receiving mail. She talks about her daily activities and how she is enjoying her post. She also asks after her two brothers Tommy (b. 1891) and Charlie (1895-1915) who were serving as members of the British army. Charlie had been missing in action since December 1915 on the Salonika front.Marie was later the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary. At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle until be called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/143/1916/06/21, B/F/143/1916/06/21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/105</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-06-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0105_img_1187_1"  type="Letter"  url="8e3306b6d907d0f1c5d4df354add77b6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0105_img_1187_2"  type="Letter"  url="2722bfc3e47f16b4cb5b8fb7dc446216.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0105_img_1187_3"  type="Letter"  url="2d786f7fe2c90865af25fec2f606e6c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0105_img_1187_4"  type="Letter"  url="2005790dd8daf6a00c5f79ed7e10e1f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0105_img_1187_5"  type="Letter"  url="fccacf7a0b98279713dcb87e4d98ef6d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0105_img_1187_6"  type="Letter"  url="29afb0e0878035712a11f262b0473060.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0105_img_1187_1"/>
               21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Juneâ   25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> General Hospital  B. E. F.   My very dearest Mother,   I hope you received my <lb/> letter with my birthday wishes <lb/>to you toâday. I must start <lb/> off by telling you do not <lb/>worry if you do not get <lb/> many letters. I shall try <lb/> &amp; write you a card every <lb/> day, we have to be most<lb/> particular what we say. all <lb/> our letters are censored, which <lb/> takes some time, so that they <lb/> may be delayed very much. <lb/>I have had a very busy day <lb/> so am writing this in bed <lb/> &amp; we had a concert here for <lb/> the patients in the evening <lb/>I did not sing. I do wish <lb/> I had taken lessons so that <lb/> I could have helped in this <lb/> way also. Now that I am  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0105_img_1187_2"/>
              getting to know my sister <lb/> I think I shall like my <lb/> work very much, of course <lb/> we have a great deal <sic>mor</sic><lb/> house work to do than in <lb/> Malta. We gave the few <lb/> men that were left toâday <lb/> a Tea, but unfortunately it <lb/>was very scrappy as it <lb/> is impossible to buy any <lb/> thing out here. &amp; I have <lb/> not had time to get <lb/> to Boulogne yet, as one<lb/> can only get there when <lb/> we have half a day <lb/> which I believe are going <lb/> to cease owing to the rush <lb/> we are expecting any <lb/> time nowâThere is so <lb/> much I would like to <lb/> say but think it safer <lb/>not as they are very <lb/> particular out hereâ I shall  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0105_img_1187_3"/>
              try and keep a <sic>dairy</sic><lb/> Imagine I have not seen <lb/> a paper since I left <lb/> england so do not <lb/>know what is really <lb/> happening, there seems <lb/> to be a fair amount <lb/> of fighting as we heard <lb/>the guns <sic>queit</sic> distinctly <lb/> all day toâdayâ We were <lb/> really busy toâdayâ <lb/>My toe is rather trouble <lb/> some. I have not been <lb/> able to wear any other <lb/> shoes than my patent <lb/>leather pair as for the <lb/> new ones they are <lb/> impossible as yet but <lb/> am waiting till toe is <lb/>alright. I may have to <lb/> get a pair of Walking shoes <lb/> just like my P. leather ones <lb/><seg type="unclear">only</seg> in <seg type="unclear">Cold</seg> for the work  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0105_img_1187_4"/>
              it is a very hard place <lb/> on shoesâ However I shall <lb/> let you knowâ  No letters from home yet <lb/> we get a Mail every <lb/> day, but the last few <lb/> days it has been very <lb/>late. Will you send <lb/> me Bernards &amp; the <seg type="unclear">other</seg><lb/> O'Kellys address I may <lb/> be fairly near B. baseâ <lb/> I am feeling A.1 &amp; live <lb/> a very out of door life<lb/> really. Paul &amp; I have <lb/>a charming room toâgether <lb/> in a Villa, we were very <lb/> lucky as a great number <lb/> have to sleep on Camp <lb/> bedsâ Matron seems very <lb/> nice so do all the sisters <lb/> Did you get the Â£5â00 <lb/> note I am very worried <lb/> about that?  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0105_img_1187_5"/>
               22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><hi rend="superscript">superscript text</hi>  I hope you have had <lb/> good news of Tommy lately <lb/> I hope they are doing <lb/> nothing out there. I suppose <lb/>you have heard nothing more <lb/>of poor Charlieâ?  How are all the family at <lb/> home, 28 &amp; poor Aunt May <lb/> I very often think of her <lb/> &amp; poor Uncle Bernard R.I.P. <lb/>we have a sweet little <lb/> church here &amp; there is <lb/> daily mass here at <lb/> 6â30 &amp; several on Sunday <lb/>so we were able to get <lb/> mass toâday â when I <lb/> Remember all your <seg type="unclear">intending</seg><lb/>also Aunt Maysâ  I hope by this you <lb/> have heard something <lb/> of me but am afraid <lb/> mails are badâ  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0105_img_1187_6"/>
              Now I must close as <lb/> it is time for lights <lb/> outâ With my fondest <lb/> love, every loving thought <lb/> good wishâ <seg type="closer"> Your fond daughter  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> P.S. I suppose you have <lb/> heard nothing of G.G. ?  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>