<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4393">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 26 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers; D2109/9/4/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4393</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-26</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4393_img_3747_1"  type="Letter"  url="4fc7e3a2c77312b87681f3cb3b09e6ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4393_img_3747_2"  type="Letter"  url="9b224dc814682c83ab5ce9c9303f17bf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4393_img_3747_3"  type="Letter"  url="8169a66c67cb59be87e6139e619f4fd8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4393_img_3747_1"/>
             1915 Nov. 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   Dearest Mamma   Thank you for sending on the Aunts £1 <lb/>should I thank them now or wait till Xmas? <lb/>What are the others doing? It is funny I think <lb/>christmas coming again. I wish I could get <lb/>home for it. I suppose D. will be back <lb/>any way. I wish she would bring Leslie <lb/>over with her. I want a <lb/>hand glass badly for Xmas, as mine has <lb/>been smashed to smithereens, or a white <lb/>silk skirt, or woolen gauntlets, very <lb/>large, to pull over my hands going to and <lb/>from the hospital, or a pair of black silk <lb/>stockings for visiting. I seem to have quite <lb/>a collection of wants in spite of living <lb/><seg type="del">a the</seg> in uniform, and books would
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4393_img_3747_2"/>
            <lb/>be very welcome too—   I went Left. Fidwell's on Tuesday night <lb/>and was very spoiled. It is a nice big house <lb/>but a little too much like an hotel, <lb/>and the girls were so nice, it was fun <lb/>seeing them again. <lb/>They and their father <lb/>all came down to breakfast in riding <lb/>kit, as they always go for a ride in <lb/>the mornings and they looked very nice <lb/>in it. There was a nice little nephew <lb/>staying there such a handsome little <lb/>fellow and full of chit chat. He <lb/>took me into the billiard room and <lb/>explained some wonderful game he <lb/>played with the cues and billiard balls. <lb/>In the morning Marjorie and I went <lb/>for a short walk and did a little <lb/>shopping, then we had early lunch and <lb/>motored <seg type="del">int</seg> in to see "The Man Who <lb/>Stayed at Home," quite an exciting play <lb/>with Denis Eadie as the hero. On the <lb/>way back we picked up a sister in <lb/>law. Who was working at one of these <lb/>war depots at Cavendish Square, and <lb/>they dropped us at <seg type="unclear">Forning's</seg> for tea <lb/>as she was going home via Victoria <lb/>too. She saw me off and wants <lb/>me to go see her at Sutton, but I <lb/>have no time to pay visits. I had <lb/>another letter from Miss Bruce asking <lb/>me there again but I am saving up my <lb/>next half day on the chance of seeing <lb/>Dorothy on her way to Eastbourne.    Emma seems to have a good deal of <lb/>time off, but I suppose it is awfully hot <lb/>in the middle of the day.   It is sad about old Mrs Coates, her <lb/>Annie will feel very lonely without her -
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4393_img_3747_3"/>
            <lb/>What did Sam get the Legion of Honour for? <lb/>It is splendid. Aunt Margaret will be pleased. <lb/>Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Caldicott has been ill with <lb/>some inflammation and been removed to <lb/>hospital and I don't think will be <lb/>coming back to nurse here. She was <lb/>a regular Irishwoman and reminded me <lb/>so of Aunt Sally. I am sorry she has <lb/>gone from this house as she was awfully <lb/>decent to me always -   Miss Haig and I have just been having <lb/>a cup of tea in the kitchen before <lb/>going back to hospital. My new coat <lb/>is very warm and comfortable, I am <lb/>glad I have got it. Pay day to-morrow <lb/>so I shall be quite well off again, <lb/>and have few expenses -   Best love dearest, I hope <lb/>you are keeping well this winter, <lb/>How is Papa. Give him my love.   Ever Yours   <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>