<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2678">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael O'Riordan to the Right Rev. Monsignor Denis Hallinan, 23 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael O&#39;Riordan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Monsignor Michael O&#39;Riordan (1857-1919), rector at the Irish College in Rome, to the Right Rev. Monsignor Denis Hallinan, D.D., P.P., Newcastle West; later bishop of Limerick, 1918-1923..

In this letter O’Riordan thanks the Monsignor for his commission, which will be put to use straight away. O’Riordan writes that he is grateful to have the information of changes in the diocese. O’Riordan then refers to the statement he has issued and is glad that it pleased the Monsignor. O&#39;Riordan goes on to discuss the difficulties he is having with economising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/I/239/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2678</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0177">Michael O&#39;Riordan</persName>
              <date>1916-10-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0191">Irish College, Rome, Italy</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Monsignor</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2678_img_2100_1"  type="Letter"  url="e405639ed5d333310a0b15309130777d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2678_img_2100_2"  type="Letter"  url="7f18d0fa2412e54c9b4bdf9ce99d6a99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2678_img_2100_3"  type="Letter"  url="460f879825fc4b1fdf5dd425ec0dd258.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2678_img_2100_1"/>
             Irish College<lb/>Rome   23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>Oct 1916    My Dear <sic>Mgr</sic>   Thank you for your<lb/>Commission, which I shall<lb/>have carried out at once.<lb/>I am glad to have the items<lb/>of information you send, about<lb/>the T.F.S, and about the<lb/>changes in the diocese. I think<lb/>Fr Hallinan was wise to get<lb/>relieved of all responsibility.<lb/>He was much crippled the last<lb/>time I saw him. Where is he 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2678_img_2100_2"/>
             <lb/>living?  I am glad you are pleased<lb/>with my statement. You have<lb/>of course missed in it some items<lb/>of importance. But I had the<lb/>Roman mind before me whilst<lb/>I wrote. Things which matter to<lb/>you &amp; me would convey no meaning<lb/>to them — or worse, a wrong one.<lb/>I have some strong letters from some<lb/>Cardinals in it. <sic>Card</sic> Maffi asked<lb/>me for some more copies.  I was not asked by the <sic>Bps</sic> to<lb/>do anything like it. I therefore<lb/>have taken all the responsibility<lb/>of it on myself. I have made<lb/>it clear here that I only am<lb/>responsible. I have told that to those<lb/>of them to whom I have sent<lb/>copies. Nobody therefore can<lb/>complain: if any should not agree<lb/>with my view - in fact<lb/>I have no view in it: I merely<lb/>set forth facts, with chiefly<lb/>views from the other side.  I am just back from<lb/>Tivoli. The Vice Rector is getting<lb/>better. I am quite well - I<lb/>have not time yet to get ill<lb/>&amp; go to hospital. I have been 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2678_img_2100_3"/>
             buying grapes and making<lb/>wine. I have spent 13000<lb/>lire on grapes. I fear that wine<lb/>will become dearer &amp; dearer these<lb/>next few years. Hence I have enough<lb/>wine for nearly three years.<lb/>Living has so gone up that it<lb/>is hard to live. The pensions<lb/>do not at all maintain a<lb/>student since the war began.<lb/>So I am trying to economise. I<lb/>don't like to raise the pension.<lb/>Come out for a short time, &amp; I'll<lb/>teach you domestic economy —<lb/>from buying grapes to repairing water—<lb/>closets. And I can give you the<lb/>best <hi rend="underline"><seg type="foreign">bicchiere</seg></hi> of wine in Rome,<lb/>although I am a teetotaller!   I am Yrs very truly  MO'Riordan    I'll be eleven years here on Nov 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. How fast time runs, or years<lb/>go on and duties multiply. I have made some useful improvements in<lb/>Tivoli. It's in fine order now. Mr Lawper<lb/>does well. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>