<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6683">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Sturge Moore to WB Yeats, 20 August 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Sturge Moore</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 8. Folder: Letters 2: Correspondence with Moore, Thomas Sturge. Moore to Yeats (1 of 2)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6683</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0794">Thomas Sturge Moore</persName>
              <date>1922-08-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1640">Steep, Petersfield, Hampshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1944</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6683_img_None_1"  url="phpjNF9JT.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6683_img_None_2"  url="phpmNrqoG.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6683_img_0_1"/>
              Hillcroft<lb/>Steep<lb/>Petersfield Hants    20/8/22    My dear Yeats.  I was very glad to get your<lb/>letter as I have often thought of you<lb/>anxiously though consoling myself<lb/>that if anything serious happened to you<lb/>it would doubtless find its way into the<lb/>papers. I shall be very pleased to look<lb/>through your proofs for you should that<lb/>prove to be necessarry but I think we<lb/>may hope that things will soon begin<lb/>to be better and communications be<lb/>re established it seems <sic>likly</sic> that the<lb/>De Valera party are on their last legs<lb/>and can hardly hold out another week<lb/>so by then the worst will be passed, though<lb/>it will take long to get everything into<lb/>working order once more. We are just<lb/>off to Paris for a month my address<lb/>will be c/o Mme G Appna 9 rue Val de Grace<lb/>Paris.<seg type="unclear">France</seg> The proofs would be sent on to<lb/>me or you could let Werner Laurie have<lb/><seg type="del">it when yo</seg> my address when you next write 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6683_img_0_2"/>
             I will drop them a card in case you<lb/>should not be able to do this.  Hoping that Ireland's troubles are<lb/>nearly over and that they will not be<lb/>followed by similar ones here or in<lb/>France.   Yours ever<lb/>T.S. Moore   I hope Mrs Yeats and the little <lb/>ones are well &amp; happy in spite of<lb/>explosions etc. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>