<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2788">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 29 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James assures his mother who might have noticed his name on Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson. He writes that she might have seen his name on the the wounded list, but assures her that his wound is a slight cut on his left arm from a shell fragment sustained while doing his rounds of the HQ billets with a sergeant.  The shell was dropped from a high -flying German plane and he &#34;neither heard or saw it till afterwards&#34;. James thinks reporting such slight injuries &#34;ridiculous&#34; and again reassures his mother he is okay.

James tells her the move referred in his last letter (of 27 Feb) has been cancelled; he asks that a pair of riding breeches be ordered so that he can try them on when he gets home. 

This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/32</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2788</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0606">Somewhere in the field, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_1"  type="Letter"  url="c41e3e56c7fdaa072b8452a2da67755b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_2"  type="Letter"  url="356c3d5150d9e2bfef8779e73a622224.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_3"  type="Letter"  url="ba3d927a2c9600fd2538b6e5723c836e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_4"  type="Letter"  url="1949122e6eca230f439f94b9372e8817.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_5"  type="Letter"  url="51cd302a584bdf3a37f8308a79297e2f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_6"  type="Envelope"  url="2dccf4060f74078fbcc20d6d0e7f0aec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2788_img_2206_7"  type="Letter"  url="b8a5bc6a332466330ea19295d90a6504.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_1"/>
             29/2/16   My Dearest Mother  —  It is only <lb/>2 days since I wrote you but <lb/>in case you should see my <lb/>name in the wounded lists <lb/>I want you to know that there <lb/>is absolutely nothing to worry <lb/>about. I have had a very <lb/>close escape today in fact. <lb/>I was lucky beyond anything <lb/>for the only mark I have is <lb/>a tiny wee cut on the upper <lb/>part of the left arm where a <lb/>fragment of the shell just touched <lb/>me — there is really no more <lb/>mark than a good vaccination. <lb/>It occurred this morning. I <lb/>was going round the billets here <lb/>in Headquarters with one of my <lb/>Sergts when suddenly there <lb/>was a most extraordinary noise
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_2"/>
            from somewhere above rather <lb/>like an express train coming <lb/>straight at one, &amp; then came <lb/>a terrific explosion about 10 yds <lb/>away. It was a bomb dropped <lb/>from a German aeroplane at great <lb/>height but I neither heard or saw <lb/>it till afterwards, probably <lb/>because so directly overhead, as <lb/>others had observed it &amp; were <lb/>watching it. I was at the <lb/>time passing through a farm <lb/>yard at the back of the billet <lb/>where my men were just collecting <lb/>before parade but by great good <lb/>luck the bomb fell on a large <lb/>manure heap which greatly lessened <lb/>the effect of the explosion though <lb/>as it was it did plenty of damage <lb/>to the buildings. All the windows <lb/>of the farm house beyond me <lb/>were absolutely shattered but
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_3"/>
            beyond the scrape I got the only <lb/>other casualties were 1 Corp, a <lb/>small puncture in leg &amp; 1 L/C <lb/>a cut in neck from a falling <lb/>slate or tile. When the bomb <lb/>burst I fell flat down as did <lb/>the Sergt wandering what was <lb/>coming next &amp; we had scarcely <lb/>done so when down came the <lb/>next one about 20 yds on the <lb/>other side. This one landed <lb/>in an orchard where the ground <lb/>was hard &amp; the effect of it <lb/>was horrific &amp; the explosion <lb/>deafening . Quite large size <lb/>trees were cut through but as <lb/>we were lying down not a <lb/>fragment touched us or anyone <lb/>else. It seems very ridiculous <lb/>to return any such slight casualties <lb/>but it has to be done &amp; <lb/>it is only because I am
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_4"/>
            afraid they may be published <lb/>&amp; to prevent your feeling at all <lb/>alarmed that I give you the <lb/>full details. At any rate <lb/>dear Mother you know I am <lb/>quite all right &amp; when I tell you <lb/>I did a ride, after getting a small <lb/>piece of dressing on my arm &amp; <lb/>went round the trenches till <lb/>1pm you will feel certain <lb/>that there is not much the matter. <lb/>The move has now apparently been <lb/>cancelled at which we are all <lb/>delighted &amp; we hope that leave <lb/>will soon be started again. <lb/>Would you please tell Reuben Payne <lb/>&amp; Ireland to &amp; to put a pair of riding <lb/>breeches in hands &amp; have them <lb/>ready for trying on when I get <lb/>home. I shall also want <lb/>to pay a visit to Dentist <lb/>but of course I cant make
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_5"/>
            any appointment till I know <lb/>when I will be leaving.    Now Mother dear I must close.    With love to all <lb/>Your loving son   Jim 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_6"/>
             R<hi rend="superscript">cd </hi>3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> March /16   Mrs. S.C. Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor <lb/>Co Down <lb/>Ireland   Jim Davidson   29/2/16 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2788_img_2206_7"/>
            <!-- Date Stamped Bangor Co Down -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>