<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5782">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Atwell to Malachy J. Kelly, 4 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Atwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter Thomas Atwell who was a solicitor in Co. Roscommon, to Sir Malachy J. Kelly (1851-1916), the Chief Crown Solicitor of Ireland. The letter talks of the death of Kate Patterson (1854-1916) of Roscommon. An issue involving Pattersons will is discussed and Atwell asks whether or not the Attorney General is going to interfere. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/4200/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5782</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0981">Thomas Atwell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1318">Main Street, Boyle, County Roscommon, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1023">Malachy J. Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5782_img_881_1"  type="Letter"  url="3be3ce8b9ca066f294647b64f2099de4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5782_img_881_1"/>
             Attorney General. <lb/>I presume you must not interfere. <lb/>M. Kelly <lb/>6/3/16"   The Atty. Gen. will not <lb/>interfere. <hi rend="underline">J.G.</hi> <lb/>7/3/16.   Main Street <lb/> Boyle   4th March, 1916  <lb/>Kate <hi rend="underline">Patterson</hi> deceased.  <hi rend="underline">Sir</hi>   The deceased died at Boyle on 7th December, 1915. She <lb/>was 62 years of age. She took out a Policy of Insurance on her <lb/>life in 1914 a copy of the particulars which  I enclose  She made her will <lb/>on 24 November 1915 leaving the Policy to Mrs Kate Lavin. <lb/>I enclose copy will. You will see by the particulars the amount <lb/>payable on death of deceased is £9.12.0. I prepared the <lb/>papers for administration with the will annexed on behalf of Mrs <lb/>Kate Lavin and sent them to Mr. Concannon the Dist. Registrar Tuam <lb/>who found there was some difficulty in the matter as Mrs. <lb/>Lavin was no relation of deceased. He laid the matter before <lb/>the principal Registrars Dublin and I enclose the reply quoted in <lb/>Mr. Concannon's letter to me of 24 February last. I got the <lb/>affidavit <seg type="del">Mr Concannon</seg> suggested by the Registrar sworn as to the <lb/>previous history of the deceased of which I enclose a Copy. <lb/>In order to let the matter through and as the Sum of money <lb/>payable by the Insurance Co. on the death of deceased is <lb/>so small. I will feel greatly obliged if you say that the Attorney <lb/>General will not interfere.   Your obedient Servant,   <hi rend="underline">Thomas Atwell</hi>   The Chief Crown Solicitor <lb/>Dublin Castle   P.S. Mrs. Lavin's Sureties are the two witnesses to the will and are merchants in <lb/>Boyle.  <lb/>T.A.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>