<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2632">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to her mother, Maria Duffin, January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Olive Duffin to her mother Maria. Olive writes that her mother would be surprised to her using a Remington typewriter. Olive had received a letter from her sister Emma (1883 - 1979) in which Emma writes that &#39;[she] will never regret coming out here...&#39;  Emma served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. She served initially in Egypt and was transferred to northern France just before the Battle of Somme, where she remained to the Armistice in 1918. Olive writes various tidbits of news and informs her mother of the dismal weather where she is stationed.

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Collection D2109/10/1/A/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2632</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2632_img_2058_1"  type="Letter"  url="6ea2422324cac09fab3e7042e56cca4c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2632_img_2058_2"  type="Letter"  url="8314286a5930a546ee0a563b8ce4d05c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2632_img_2058_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/A   Jan    Dearest Mamma,   you <sic>willbe</sic> surprised to see me using a typewriter<lb/>Miss Hollins had hired one by the month -a thing I did not know<lb/>one could do, and has left me a legacy of it, I strongly suspect<lb/>her of having got it for my benefit- any how I am very glad to have<lb/>it and mean to practise strenously. It is a Remington and not a<lb/>bad one at all t hough rather old-fashioned.  Miss Roberts wants you to keep the socks for the use of the<lb/>Ulster Division.  I had a letter from Emma which she says not to pass on as she<lb/>is writing to you herself, she evidently did not get some of our<lb/>letters, and had fears about your present having been lost.  She says, I shall never regret having come out here, part<lb/>of it is unpleasant, but all of it is Life and the more I see and<lb/>the older I grow, the more I think Life with a big L is something and<lb/>ought not to be muddled away in corners, and yet no doubt some of<lb/>us must live in corners! I am afraid <hi rend="underline">I</hi> am in a corner but it is<lb/>not too cramped and quite comfortable!  My cold is much better and I was out to-day, I was rather miserable<lb/>when I arrived.  Mrs Hollins latest idea is to send Emmie here to Miss Randall's<lb/>school, she will live here of <sic>courseand</sic> Miss Roberts is greatly<lb/>pleased at the prospect, another cousin, a Miss Dalbiac is to come<lb/>also, but she will board out. It seems a very sudden idea and as 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2632_img_2058_2"/>
             D2109/10/1/A  she knows nothing at all about it except what Miss Roberts spoke<lb/><sic>o e</sic> my having told her, I am rather surprised after all the talk<lb/>about keeping Emmie so exclusive! Those sort of people are<lb/>never consistent.  Saturday.  Dorothy's letter and the nougat from Emma has just arrived—<lb/>what lovely stuff!  Miss Roberts is as lively as ever and expecting two more elderly<lb/>ladies to stay, as well as Mrs Hollins and Emmie coming on<lb/>Monday, so she has plenty of amusement in store, and variety which<lb/>is the breath of life to her. The minute she is unoccupied she<lb/>begins to fuss the whole household with little messages and fusses<lb/>(which must be done at once) just by way of giving herself occupation.  My cold is nearly gone but it took a good deal out of me, <seg type="unclear">coughing</seg><lb/>at night, so I am taking things easy.  I hear Col. Donnet is better. I've not seen them yet.  There is driving rain and no sun here this morning but it is<lb/>extraordinarily warm.  <sic>I t</sic> must be very dull for poor Ruth, I do hope there will be no<lb/>more cases.  I'm glad the new cook promises well. I am most anxious to<lb/>hear about the disposal of <hi rend="underline">Mrs Hincks'</hi> things.<lb/>Much love to all.  Wife of the Rev. Thomas Hincks, uncle<lb/>of Mamma.   Ever your loving     Olive  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>