<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1251">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Michael Stanley to George Bernard Shaw, 28 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Michael Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from the printer Joseph Michael Stanley (1890-1950) to playwright George Bernard Shaw (1856-1950). Stanley refers to a raid on his printing firm during which a copy of Shaw&#39;s book &#39;Plays for Puritans&#39; was taken from an employee. Stanley asks if the military have declared the book &#39;seditious&#39;.Below is the reply from Shaw stating that he does not think that the raid was for copies of the book but suggests that a &#39;zealous police officer&#39; may have spotted a reference to King George and taken the book for that reason. Stanley&#39;s printing press would be later used to print the proclamation of the Irish republic.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Joseph Michael Stanley Collection, BMH CD/4/3/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1251</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0460">Joseph Michael Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-03-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1056">30 Upper Liffey Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0018">George Bernard Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1164">Adelphi Terrace, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1251_img_441_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc48a8ad60f1315175b6653cc78e3958.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1251_img_441_1"/>
              The Gaelic Press GENERAL PRINTERS AND PUBLISHERS  <hi rend="underline">Telephone No 78</hi>  30 Upper Liffey Street  Dublin    28th March 1916   Dear Sir,   Could you kindly inform me whether it has ever been officially <lb/> given as the opinion of the military authorities, that your book, <lb/> 'Plays For Puritans' contains seditious matter, or matter likely to <lb/> prejudice recruiting. My reason for putting this query to you is, that <lb/> a copy of this book in the possession of a journalist employed in this <lb/> firm, was seized by military authorities in the course of a raid, which <lb/> was made on these premises on Friday last, 24th inst. A newspaper <lb/> cutting in reference to same is enclosed.   An early expression of your opinion on the matter will be deemed <lb/> a great favour.  <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely, <lb/> Per pro Gaelic   Michael Stanley </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>