<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1696">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J. W. Rainey to Patrick Alphonsus Carroll, 19 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.W. Rainey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter approving a temporary commission of Patrick Alphonsus Carroll as Lieutenant in the Army Veterinary Corps.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Pat Carroll</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1696</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0378">J.W. Rainey</persName>
              <date>1916-01-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1328">Patrick Alphonsus Carroll</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0736">Riddy's Hotel, Carlow, Co. Carlow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1696_img_1153_1"  type="Letter"  url="392ba119d05bda47b0925eb95d3b0cc7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1696_img_1153_2"  type="Letter"  url="e878b878fcd0886118f4666581a50b6c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1696_img_1153_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="9c82be62ebcec23a8131a3df7456b55b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1696_img_1153_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="5a9b8e1ef6e806d2cb5045499e479567.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1696_img_1153_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="05e16d332cb88f2ca57a3ea61b495646.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1696_img_1153_1"/>
             19th January, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed to inform you that you have been <lb/>approved for a temporary Commission as Lieutenant <lb/>in the Army Veterinary Corps, and to request that <lb/>you will be good enough to proceed to the Curragh <lb/>on the 9th February, 1916, and report yourself to <lb/>the Officer Commanding, Station Veterinary Hospital, <lb/>Curragh, for duty.   I am to add that should you prefer, you can <lb/>postpone obtaining your uniform etc. until after you <lb/>have joined for duty, when you will receive every <lb/>advice and assistance.   I am,<lb/> Sir,<lb/> Your obedient Servant,   (Sd/-) J. W. Rainey,  Major,<lb/> for Major General,<lb/> Director General,<lb/> A.V.S<lb/> P.A. Carroll, Esq., M.R.C.V.S.,  Riddy's Hotel, <lb/>Carlow, <lb/>Ireland. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1696_img_1153_2"/>
             THE LONDON GAZETTE,  22 FEBRUARY, 1916 . 1951   Temporary Second Lieutenant A. M. <lb/>Lowery, Royal Artillery, and to be trans- <lb/>ferred to the General List. Dated 9th Feb- <lb/>ruary, 1916.   CAVALRY. <lb/> Reserve Regiment of 2nd Life Guards. <lb/> The undermentioned temporary Second <lb/>Lieutenants relinquish the temporary rank <lb/> of Lieutenant on ceasing to be employed <lb/> with a Reserve Regiment:- <lb/> W. S. Matterson. Dated 12th November, <lb/>1915. <lb/> E. W. Butler. Dated 27th December, <lb/>1915.   Remount Service. <lb/>Temporary Captain Major Sefton Purdey, <lb/> from an Adjutant, to be an Assistant Com- <lb/>mandant, and to be temporary Major, vice <lb/> temporary Major C. H. Fenwick. Dated <lb/> 11th February, 1916.   ROYAL REGIMENT OF ARTILLERY <lb/> Royal Horse and Royal Field Artillery. <lb/> The initials of temporary Captain E. A. <lb/>Chisholm are as now described, and not as <lb/>in the Gazette of 16th November, 1915.   CORPS OF ROYAL ENGINEERS <lb/>The undermentioned to be temporary <lb/> Second Lieutenants (on probation) :- <lb/> Dated 23rd February, 1916 <lb/>Lionel Perry. <lb/>John Walter Bullock.   FOOT GUARDS. <lb/>Grenadier Guards. <lb/> The appointment of Second Lieutenant <lb/> George Francis Pauling, notified in the <lb/>Gazette of 29th January, 1916, is ante- <lb/>dated to 14th August, 1914.   Coldstream Guards. <lb/>Lieutenant Charles, Viscount Marsham, to <lb/>be Adjutant of a Command Depot. Dated <lb/>31st January 1916.   INFANTRY. <lb/>The Bedfordshire Regiment. <lb/>Second Lieutenant (temporary Lieu- <lb/>tenant) William White, from the Queen's <lb/>(Royal West Surrey Regiment), Special <lb/>Reserve, to be Second Lieutenant, and to <lb/>retain his temporary rank until ordered to <lb/>join a regular unit. Dated 23rd February, <lb/>1916,with seniority as from 2nd February, <lb/>1916.   The Wast Lancashire Regiment. <lb/>Lieutenant Arthur Williams Long, from <lb/>a Special Reserve Battalion, to be Second <lb/>Lieutenant. Dated 23rd February 1916, <lb/> with seniority as from 15th February, 1915.   The South Stafordshire Regiment. <lb/>Lieutenant Charles Cecil Harland, from <lb/>the Hampshire Regiment, Regional Reserve, <lb/>to be Second Lieutenant, and to retain his <lb/>higher rank until ordered to join a regular <lb/>unit. Dated 23rd February, 1916, with <lb/>seniority as from 6th June, 1915. <lb/>Temporary Second Lieutenant Walter W. <lb/>Kirk is cashiered by sentence of a General <lb/>Court Martial. Dated 16th December, <lb/>1915.   The Dorsetshire Regiment. <lb/>Second Lieutenant W. J. Smith relin- <lb/>quishes the temporary rank of Lieutenant. <lb/>Dated 29th November, 1915.   The Highland Light Infantry. <lb/>Second Lieutenant Francis S. Jackson is <lb/>removed from the Service for absence with- <lb/>out leave. Dated 6th January, 1916.   MACHINE GUN CORPS. <lb/>Training Centre. <lb/>The undermentioned to be Instructors, <lb/>and to remain seconded:- <lb/>Dated 1st February, 1916. <lb/>Captain Douglas K. MacK.Herapath, <lb/>7th (Princess Royal's) Dragoon Guards. <lb/> Lieutenant (temporary Captain) Cecil A. <lb/>Bays). <lb/> Captain John R. G. Magrath, The Lin- <lb/>colnshire Regiment. <lb/> Captain Charles C. Tee, The Royal Irish <lb/>Rifles   The undermentioned to be Assistant In- <lb/>structors, and to remain seconded :- <lb/> Dated 1st November, 1915. <lb/>Second Lieutenant Edward Rosam, The <lb/>Royal Fusiliers (City of London Regiment). <lb/> Second Lieutenant Albert Rumbelow, The <lb/>Suffolk Regiment. <lb/>Second Lieutenant Patrick Ferrie, The <lb/>Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders. <lb/>Second Lieutenant Charles E. Gradwell, <lb/>The Rifle Brigade (The Prince Consort's <lb/>Own).   ARMY VETERINARY SERVICE. <lb/>Army Veterinary Corps. <lb/>The undermentioned to be temporary <lb/>Lieutenants:- <lb/>Dated 9th February, 1916. <lb/>Jerome Joseph O'Neill. <lb/>Patrick Alphonsus Carroll.   MEMORANDA. <lb/>Temporary Major (Honorary Lieutenant- <lb/>Colonel) H. N. G. Hinde, late Prince <lb/>Albert's (Somerset Light Infantry), Terri- <lb/>torial Force, relinquishes his temporary commission <lb/> on account of ill health. Dated 11th <lb/> February, 1916.<lb/> P.F.J. Burlet to be temporary Second <lb/> Lieutenant. Dated 18th February, 1916. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1696_img_1153_3"/>
             Lt. P.A. Carroll <lb/>a.v.c. <lb/>temporary commission   2 discharged in 1932. <lb/>Papers from 2 enclosed.   <seg type="del">V.D.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">M.S.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">King.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">V.D.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">M.S</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">King</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">V.D</seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1696_img_1153_4"/>
             Register No. <lb/>Minute Sheet No.   An application for a temporary commission in the <lb/>Army Veterinary Corps.   Mr. Patrick Alphonsus Carroll, M.R.C.V.S   Issue Orders for Mr. Carroll to join at the <lb/>Curragh on 9th February, 1916, and inform G.O.C in C. <lb/>Ireland.  <hi rend="underline">V.D.</hi>  19.1.16.   -2-   M.S.   I recommend the above gentleman for a temporary Commission <lb/>in the Army Veterinary Corps.   He should be gazetted from the 9th February, 1916.   14.2.16.   -3-   Submit to King.   M.S.2.   15.2.16   -4-   D.V.S.,B.E.F, recommends Lieutenant P.A.Carroll, <lb/>for promotion to temporary Captain on Completion <lb/>of twelve months' service. (4.A.)  <hi rend="underline">V.D.</hi>  7.2.17. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1696_img_1153_5"/>
             -5-   M.S.1.   Lieutenant P.A. Carroll, A.V.C., having completed <lb/>twelve months' satisfactory service, will you please <lb/>gazette him to the temporary rank of Captain, Army <lb/>Veterinary Corps, as from the 9th February, 1917.  <seg type="unclear">J. Hamilton</seg>  <hi rend="underline">V.D.</hi> 9.2.17. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>