<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1651">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 22 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie (1892-1975) joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle until being called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France. Marie later founded the Medical Missionaries of Mary.
In this letter Marie speaks of her financial affairs and remarks that the hospital is not at all busy. Marie asks her mother for news of her brother Charlie (1895-1915) who is missing on the front. Marie writes that she is thinking of her family and mentions that she will be travelling to London in two months time. Marie also remarks on the long battles that are occurring on the front in France.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF136</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1651</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-03-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1651_img_1111_1"  type="Letter"  url="89b63e242aa20800e47c56321aa4c2d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1651_img_1111_2"  type="Letter"  url="f221302b9c917304edcb00f76c66f982.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1651_img_1111_3"  type="Letter"  url="3887050d61fb511549239df0d30ab1f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1651_img_1111_4"  type="Letter"  url="252891e3963c322e95779aeb6578886d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1651_img_1111_5"  type="Letter"  url="bde2fe9e283a8d5b25988f9a9f7749f8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1651_img_1111_1"/>
             B/F/1/36  (1)<lb/><hi rend="underline">2.30 A.M</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline"> 22-3-16- </hi>   My very dearest Mother,   A 1000 thanks for your<lb/>two very nice letters dated 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>- &amp; 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.<lb/>Mr. also the enclosed which I was<lb/>just delighted to get as I have<lb/>spent all I can afford to give<lb/>out of my own months money<lb/>in fact I have only just<lb/>enough left to pay my washing<lb/>bills to the end of the Month, don't<lb/>think by this I have nothing<lb/>as I always keep £5.00 un-<lb/>touched <sic>incase</sic> of an <sic>immergency</sic><lb/>&amp; there is only another week, when<lb/>we shall be paid again, when we<lb/>shall get an extra pound Uniform<lb/>allowance which we should have<lb/>got last month. I had to go &amp;<lb/>buy my second <sic>pr</sic> of shoes &amp; a<lb/>new Corset to-day — A great advantage<lb/>in night duty is one cannot spend<lb/>so much money — as I generally<lb/>spend most of my day in bed —  A. Lily came up to see me<lb/>yesterday evening &amp; had dinner 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1651_img_1111_2"/>
             (2)<lb/>with me, she is very funny &amp;<lb/>thinks it such a terrible <sic>think</sic><lb/>for me to have to stay on<lb/>a month, in her Hospital V.A.Ds<lb/>do not go on N. duty.  I have been on a week to-day<lb/>&amp; really the time has passed<lb/>quite quickly, as I have<lb/>already told we are really<lb/>not a bit busy. It is really<lb/>a very funny life one seems<lb/>to live in quite a different world<lb/>where every thing seems so up<lb/>side down— however it is great<lb/>experience, the greatest difficulty<lb/>is keeping awake at this<lb/>hour of the night.  Is Gerald Martin in this fighting<lb/>also Gerald G— ? There is a very<lb/>large mail in today so perhaps<lb/>I shall get a letter from G—<lb/>with all his news. I had such<lb/>a bright &amp; cheery letter from<lb/>Bee— Also a P.C. from Alexandria<lb/>from Tommy— who seems in<lb/>great form &amp; had just had two<lb/>day up in Cairo. I wonder what 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1651_img_1111_3"/>
             (3)  really is going to happen to<lb/>the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div: — I have 2 Conn.<lb/>Ranger men one is Srg. Major<lb/>McKenna, &amp; the other is a<lb/>Hampshire boy attached to<lb/>the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> C. When are we going to<lb/>hear some news of Charlie?<lb/>It is a great <sic>relieve</sic> to hear the<lb/>prisoners are well treated as<lb/>soon as we get his address I<lb/>can send him some food<lb/>stuff from here. I feel quite<lb/>sure all your prayers will soon<lb/>be heard— How I long for the<lb/>day when I shall see you<lb/>all again, when I sit here at<lb/>night working etc &amp; I think<lb/>of you all sleeping in bed<lb/>at Greenbank— &amp; wonder how<lb/>you all are &amp; when I think<lb/>of my nice room with every<lb/>comfort in it, it almost makes<lb/>me cry &amp; poor Charlies bedroom<lb/>waiting for his return, I can only<lb/>pray that it will all end very<lb/>soon &amp; we shall all be together<lb/>happy once more— 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1651_img_1111_4"/>
            (4)  As I think I have already told <lb/>you some of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> lot of <lb/>V.A.Ds were sign on again <lb/>but <sic>evendently</sic> they are not <lb/>required for here any more so <lb/>that all 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> lot of V.A.Ds are <lb/>to be ready to leave at an <lb/>hours notice, so I think most <lb/>probably we shall just be <lb/>kept here to finish our time <lb/>&amp; then sent home &amp; if we <lb/>resign again the will either <lb/>take us or leave us— Do you <lb/>think I ought to, when I am <lb/>in London go at once &amp; see <lb/>Mrs. Furse &amp; sign on again for <lb/> France  or House   but telling her I would <lb/>like a month or two at home <lb/>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>? From what I hear out here <lb/>they seem to be going to have <lb/> a hot time in France — if they <lb/>could only have one big Battle <lb/>&amp; finish the whole show—   I have just been looking over <lb/>the Calendar &amp; find it is really <lb/>two more months before we are <lb/>due in London— 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1651_img_1111_5"/>
             (5)  I am so glad to hear Sister<lb/>Flynn went to see you. She<lb/>must have gone home as soon<lb/>as she <sic>arrive</sic> yes she is a very<lb/>nice girl— I suppose there was<lb/>no chance of getting Morrogh<lb/>to meet her, she missed<lb/>him at Torquay. I thought<lb/>you would like to meet someone<lb/>who saw me lately so<lb/>asked her if she were in Dublin<lb/>to call on you— Do not be<lb/><sic>surprized</sic> if at any time a<lb/>few soldiers turn up as I<lb/>gave my address to a few,<lb/>&amp; to go &amp; look you up &amp; tell<lb/>you all about the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div:<lb/>doings etc.  Now I shall close this with<lb/>every loving thought &amp; good<lb/>wishes.  Your ever loving &amp; grateful<lb/>daughter.   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> <lb/>I had a letter from Irene to-day<lb/>she likes Alexandria very much.<lb/><hi rend="underline">m.m.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>