<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2872">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 3 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

Spender urges Lillian to take care of her health, and to seek all the help she can get for her &#39;work with the wounded&#39;. He also offers her a donation towards her fundraising efforts. Spender then writes that the Ulster Division will be returning to its &#39;former area&#39; for refitting and rest, after the heavy blows it took in the fighting.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/332</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2872</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2872_img_2284_1"  type="NULL"  url="07dfff6da8fe857373792e3ca2ed61aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2872_img_2284_2"  type="NULL"  url="b773cd55551031f45d2420e3721a52e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2872_img_2284_3"  type="NULL"  url="82427ac7d7f5321ca93e30d8ae725ab1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2872_img_2284_4"  type="NULL"  url="99d8a82fac03c72f5a9a351ca005f53f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2872_img_2284_1"/>
              July 3. 16.   D1633/1/1/332  Very thankful for your letter. Very<lb/>sorry p r had such a time with that demon<lb/>Mrs V.  I cannot write much about affairs here<lb/>but have drafted out a very bald account<lb/> to  which I do not think the censor <seg type="del">will </seg>can<lb/>have any objection, &amp; which you might<lb/>show Sir Edward &amp; possibly to Mr G.  I am quite well &amp; much better for<lb/>your dear letters which are a great help.  It makes all the difference having a p r<lb/>to think of. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2872_img_2284_2"/>
             Now then on two pressing things - your<lb/>work and your fitness &amp; health. I shan't<lb/>forgive Mrs Spender if she lets the pr turn<lb/>into a white one whilst I am away.  Taxies which save her are no longer<lb/>a luxury. She must spare herself for the<lb/>bw's sake as far as she can, &amp; must get<lb/>all the help she can for her work with<lb/>the wounded.  I will glady give a 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> donation of<lb/>£50 to the funds whenever it seems time,<lb/>but may not be able to do so yet awhile<lb/>if you are giving payment for helpers.<lb/>I could give you many accounts of 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2872_img_2284_3"/>
             deeds of wonderful heroism which I have<lb/>seen and heard of but the tears come to<lb/>my eyes if I try to state them.  You will understand.  The Division - the remaining portion<lb/>of it - is being withdrawn to its former<lb/>area for refitting and rest.  The men were determined to be<lb/>before the regular division on our left<lb/>who have been called the incomparable<lb/>&amp; who did not succeed in getting forwards.  Our men succeeded in this only too<lb/>well.  No more now but let this family 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2872_img_2284_4"/>
             have all the news you can, without tiring<lb/>yourself too much.<lb/><lb/> Your own b w    W. B. Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>