<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4048">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eamonn O'Modhrain to his mother, Mary Moran from Wakefield Prison, England, June 5, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to his mother about conditions for the Irish prisoners, arrested during and soon after Easter week, in English prisons. Eamonn gives some farming instructions and mentions his brother, Louis, who was released from captivity in England only weeks prior.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O&#39;Modhráin Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4048</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1527">Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin</persName>
              <date>1916-06-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1424">Wakefield Prison, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Moran née Malone</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0200">Ballysax, The Curragh, Co. Kildare</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1955</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4048_img_343_1"  type="Letter"  url="2ab6a9e151fffc337110a14c39685d08.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4048_img_343_2"  type="Letter"  url="2c8fd571022caf0558f7307c746d94d1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4048_img_343_1"/>
             a <hi rend="superscript">3/56</hi> 963 <!-- [prisoner number] -->  Edward Moran,<lb/>Irish Prisoner, Wakefield,<lb/>c/o Chief Postal Censor,<lb/>G.P.O., London   5.IV.'16   Dearest Mother,   Your letter of 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> inst and Maire's<lb/>of 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ult. to hand just now. I was indeed glad<lb/>to get them and the parcels. I enclose a letter for<lb/>Lewie which came yesterday. I got 3 Independents<lb/>the Leader &amp; one Mail. Marie's letter to Lewie<lb/>in which she asked about sheep does not appear<lb/>to have got here. Yes the price was 58/=. Of<lb/>course send those that are fit to Newbridge.<lb/>Re mares, I did not intend sending them, no use.<lb/>Uncle Simon is very good, he is getting a lot<lb/>of trouble. I hope the press is right about the<lb/>prisoner's food but it is not in evidence<lb/>here yet. We get four hours exercise per day<lb/>now which is a great improvement and are<lb/>to get Mass every Sunday in future. Most<lb/>of the men in this wing, including myself, were<lb/>at Holy Communion on Sunday last. We<lb/>all hope to be released soon but of course<lb/>we know nothing definite. You will have all<lb/>the latest news per Lewie <!-- [arrested and transported to Wakefield Prison but released before his brother, Eamonn] -->, ask him to send me<lb/>an account of his trip home.  I am glad to hear that the youngsters are<lb/>enjoying themselves. I'm sure they are in<lb/>great form. I had two letters from Nancy,<lb/>or should I say one for Lewie &amp; one for myself.<lb/>As I believe these letters will not be posted until<lb/>Friday I will not write any more just now. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4048_img_343_2"/>
             Since writing above I have got Gus' parcel which was very welcome <lb/> as supplies were running low. Don't send any more tobacco for <lb/> a bit I have a lot, but send cigarettes &amp; matches. I have just <lb/> received letters from Maire, Nancy &amp; Gus. You are all <lb/> very good to us. Gus seems to think we are downhearted here. <lb/> We're not a bit, quite a jolly crowd, but of course would <lb/> give a lot to be in Ireland. Tell Gus that A. F. Macken <lb/> is here C. <hi rend="superscript">2/50</hi>. 539. I must try and get to see him tomorrow, <lb/> we are allowed to go to other wings now to see relatives.   All the letters and parcels do not reach us as Maire's letter to <lb/> Lewie and Nancy's parcels of butter. The stamps Gus <lb/> sent will be very useful.   Tell Marie I'll write to her the very first opportunity. <lb/>   You all understand that we cannot <lb/><seg type="unclear">react</seg> on our correspondence here so one letter will <lb/> have to suffice for a reply to all.   I got two "Heralds" to-night from Gus. The papers are <lb/> most welcome as we are all on the lookout for home <lb/>news.   Now, mother dear, I will say <seg type="foreign">slan leat</seg> and <lb/> I hope you and all are in the best of form.   With best love, From    Eamonn   6.VI.'16.   "Herald" to hand from Gus and "Guardian" and <lb/>100 cigarettes from Maire this morning. I <lb/> fear we are giving our people a lot of <lb/> trouble.   Good bye again dearest mother E 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>