<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5562">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Card from May Fay to James Finn, 6 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

This is a short card to cheer up James. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5562</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-03-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5562_img_658_1"  type="Letter"  url="e356a070d39cc61ce603a975f2849697.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5562_img_658_2"  type="Envelope"  url="859ed3a65d42c67777701ad66e473aad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5562_img_658_1"/>
             M .Gar.   Ever dearest James,   A moment to tell<lb/>you not to be lonely at all <sic>at all</sic>,<lb/>it’s not worth while <hi rend="underline">you will</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">soon see too much of me</hi><lb/>I hope you gave my love to<lb/>Mother, Nora &amp; Moll. Now<lb/>be a very good boy &amp; I’ll pray<lb/>&amp; fast for you during the Lent<lb/>if I can at all I hope we will <seg type="unclear">come</seg> <lb/>to have pleasant weather this<lb/>day is lovely. Hope no one will<lb/><hi rend="underline">touch</hi> you for breaking the eggs.<lb/>Tell me if they do.    <hi rend="underline">Very very, very</hi> best love from    May<lb/>Fay  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5562_img_658_2"/>
             J Finn Esq <lb/>39 Belgrave Sq <lb/>Rathmines <lb/>Dublin  <!-- Text on the back of envelope --> IF USED FOR TRANSMISSION TO ANY PLACE ABROAD TO WHICH THE 1b. RATE <lb/>OF LETTER POSTAGE DOES NOT APPLY, THE ADDITIONAL POSTAGE REQUIRED <lb/>SHOULD BE PREPAID BY MEANS OF ADHESIVE POSTAGE STAMPS.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>