<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2675">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael O'Riordan to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 10 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael O&#39;Riordan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Monsignor Michael O&#39;Riordan (1857-1919), rector at the Irish College in Rome, to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 until his death.  

O’Riordan begins this letter by referring to O’Dwyer’s ‘famous correspondence’ with General Maxwell (1859 – 1929). This included O’Dwyer’s letter to Maxwell on 30 May 1916 in which he denounced the shooting of the insurgency leaders of Easter Week 1916 ‘in cold blood’ and the deporting of thousands without trial, and declared Maxwell&#39;s regime ‘one of the worst and blackest chapters in the history of the misgovernment of this country’.In the letter O’Riordan also describes an event during which he was branded a Fenian by Bishop Dontonville and the subsequent fallout between the two.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/I/239/2/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2675</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0177">Michael O&#39;Riordan</persName>
              <date>1916-06-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0191">Irish College, Rome, Italy</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2675_img_2098_1"  type="Letter"  url="e790476c4fb59469000aa23e520c8e1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2675_img_2098_2"  type="Letter"  url="30a9720bcb05865d2f75a33cd5ec3699.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2675_img_2098_3"  type="Letter"  url="abccc69771edcc35166faa704fe6f1f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2675_img_2098_4"  type="Letter"  url="e7d3e81f16eb689093bb57fc10d923b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2675_img_2098_5"  type="Letter"  url="f43048f411a80c365256cef4c14f42eb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2675_img_2098_6"  type="Letter"  url="8cb88a199700365c1f94c70b89a2efdc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2675_img_2098_1"/>
             Irish College<lb/>Rome   10th June 1916    My Lord Bishop,   I write to thank you<lb/>for sending me the 'cutting' about<lb/>the famous correspondence. Since then<lb/>one from the <hi rend="underline">Evening Mail</hi> was sent<lb/>me from Dublin, and I have seen it<lb/>also in the <hi rend="underline">Catholic Times</hi>. Nothing<lb/>that pays, <hi rend="underline">disedifies the Irish Times</hi><lb/>or the <hi rend="underline">Mail</hi>; and thus <hi rend="underline">The Freeman</hi><lb/>pays for its piety. I have also read<lb/>your Lordship's reply to the Limerick  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2675_img_2098_2"/>
             Guardians. It nicely supplements<lb/>your reply to Sir John Maxwell.<lb/>Those good persons have been brought<lb/>up, and are so much in the habit<lb/>of thinking of, &amp; of dealing with<lb/>the Anglican Church as a department<lb/>of the Civil service, that he thought<lb/>he was making quite a natural<lb/>&amp; rightful claim in on you. That he<lb/>appealed to you lest he should have to<lb/>arrest the two priests is simply an<lb/>untruth; for I suppose that he has<lb/>no greater regard for a Limerick priest<lb/>than for a Dublin one; and a Fr Flanagan<lb/>of Ringsend was one of the first prisoners<lb/>made; and I believe that Fr Nevin of the<lb/>Passionists was also taken prisoner.<lb/><lb/>They were so blinded with anger that<lb/>he was as a mad bull rushing<lb/>blindly through the Country — <lb/>[questionable reading]<lb/>,as the poor old <seg type="unclear">Doitin</seg><lb/>used to quote from a Latin Grammar<lb/>he once learned. I suspect his is now<lb/>a sadder, and I hope a wiser man.  People are going mad — I thought<lb/>I was a very mutual person, till the<lb/><seg type="unclear">Vui — Rutn</seg> told me some days ago that<lb/>Bp Dontonvialle (lately Bp in Canada,<lb/>now   of the Oblates) had said to<lb/>a lady  What can you think when the<lb/>Rutn of the Irish College is a Fenian!<lb/>I laughed at it; but I wrote to him<lb/>at once however. He wrote very apologetically<lb/>saying he did not remember it, &amp; that he<lb/>was ready to do anything I asked — not<lb/>a very satisfactory, nor a very consistent answer     
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2675_img_2098_3"/>
             I wrote back today that what I wanted<lb/>was not an apology, but evidence of my<lb/>Fenianism; that presumably I should pass it<lb/>off without caring, but inasmuch as I am<lb/>intimately connected with a College here,<lb/>and with a hierarchy in Ireland, I cant<lb/>let it pass, specially as it was said by<lb/>one in his Lordship's position. He paid<lb/>me two visits in the mater. Although we<lb/>were very friendly, he will be more cautious<lb/>in future. I told him that I wanted no<lb/>apology; that he cant now prevent persons<lb/>whispering it as his authority. But if I<lb/>hear   being whispered, I shall log<lb/>a formal complaint before the Pope and<lb/><seg type="unclear">Lord .</seg> De Lai.   Here is another symptom of current<lb/>lunacy. they have been saying that the<lb/>Popes' recent telegram to   Logue was<lb/>dictated by me. When they saw from     
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2675_img_2098_4"/>
             Irish College<lb/>Rome  the papers that I had an audience<lb/>a few days ago, they said  That<lb/>darn man has been with the Pope<lb/>again, after <seg type="unclear">Lord Asquith</seg> They<lb/> [questionable reading] similarly because I happened<lb/>to have an audience a day or two<lb/>after Mr Asquith. And other things<lb/>equally foolish. It's not enough<lb/>to say nothing to or of them. One<lb/><seg type="del">deleted text</seg> must become a phonograph<lb/>or a parrot to speak their words,<lb/><seg type="del">deleted text</seg><lb/>and a toy worked of wires to dance<lb/>to their tunes. We are very friendly;<lb/>but it is <seg type="del">now</seg> new to them to find an<lb/>Irishman daring not to trouble about<lb/>them &amp; have his own way.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2675_img_2098_5"/>
             This would be a rare occasion<lb/>to start a strong daily paper in<lb/>Ireland — strongly &amp; truly national, and<lb/><seg type="unclear">House</seg>  with  Catholic instincts. If it<lb/>was controlled by a small but strong<lb/>Committee, giving a good Editor<lb/>a good deal of independence, it<lb/>would <seg type="unclear">take</seg> the Country. I suppose<lb/>it could not be safely begun without<lb/>a capital of £50,000 or £60,000.<lb/>For it should make a strong spur<lb/>from the very start. If the Bishops<lb/>should think of such a project, you<lb/>can put me down for shares to<lb/>the extent of £200 or £300,<lb/>or more if necessary. If the Bps should<lb/>think of such a project, Dr Cleary, the  Bishop of Auckland will be soon in Ireland. He will be a help for he is a<lb/>practised newspaper man <lb/><lb/>I enclose a Sermon I preached<lb/> in St Patricks Church on St Patrick's<lb/>Day. I was asked to prepare it for<lb/>publication; for I had not all written<lb/>before I preached it. But what is published<lb/>is practically the same as I spoke; in<lb/>fact is, I think nearly so, sentence for<lb/>sentence; for I had some parts written<lb/>out &amp; committed to memory, and the rest<lb/>thought out with great care.<lb/>The Vice— Rector sent a few passages<lb/>to the <hi rend="underline">Catholic Bulletin</hi>; but the <hi rend="underline">Censor</hi><lb/>excised some sentences abut the famine<lb/>— I draw a line about them on Page 22<lb/>&amp; 23. &amp; lest you should read them, &amp;<lb/>have   spirit &amp; historical truth<lb/>damaged. I thought I was speaking<lb/>a well-known truth; but evidently<lb/>the Government representatives still think<lb/>the Irish famine was a <hi rend="underline">real</hi> one, &amp; not<lb/>one manufactured by them and their Garrison<lb/>in Ireland.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2675_img_2098_6"/>
             I have a long note on the matter, on<lb/>pages 32 — to 35, letter from Cardinal<lb/>Perrauds' — <seg type="foreign">L'Irlande Contemporaire.</seg>  It is printed accurately enough.<lb/>But there are several errors in<lb/>the notes; but they are quite <seg type="unclear">illegible.</seg>  I am my Lord<lb/>Yours obediently  M O Riordan 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>