<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6658">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of a letter from Bishop Michael Francis Fallon to Charles Joseph Doherty, T. W. McGarry and Charles Murphy, 12 March 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Francis Fallon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Bishop Michael Francis Fallon wrote this letter after the Irish had again been denied self-government by the British Parliament. As Charles Joseph Doherty, T. W. McGarry and Charles Murphy all politically represent the Irish Catholics in Canada on a provincial level, Fallon asks them in what political direction they are going to lead their constituents.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Folder: Box 2. f.2 Joseph C. Walsh Papers</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6658</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0236">Michael Francis Fallon</persName>
              <date>1917-03-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1372">London, Ontario, Canada</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0594">Charles Murphy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0946">Ottawa, Ontario, Canada</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1931</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6658_img_None_1"  url="phpZMAJ2Q.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6658_img_None_2"  url="phpv7LPZA.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6658_img_0_1"/>
              London, Ontario.    March 12th , 1917.   The Honorable C.J. Doherty, M..P.,<lb/>Minister of Justice,<lb/> Ottawa, Ontario.   The Honorable T.W. McGarry, M.L.A.,<lb/>Provincial Treasurer,<lb/> Toronto, Ontario.   The Honorable Charles Murphy, M.P.,<lb/> Ottawa, Ontario.   Honorable Gentlemen:-  The people of Ireland have been<lb/>again denied self-government by the British Parliament.<lb/>Through their representatives, the Irish Nationalist<lb/>Party, they have sent forth an appeal for assistance in<lb/>the struggle for their constitutional rights. They<lb/>address themselves to the children of the Irish race in<lb/>the Overseas British Dominions, and in the American<lb/>Republic, and to the lovers of freedom everywhere.  Under the political system prevailing in Canada and in Ontario, you, Honorable          
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6658_img_0_2"/>
             Gentlemen, have been singled out to represent the Irish<lb/>Catholics in federal and in provincial political affairs.<lb/>They have no other recognized political leaders, no other authorized political spokesmen.  Not as Bishop of London, but as<lb/>one of those whom you represent in political life, I<lb/>write to inquire what, if any, direction you have to give<lb/>to your constituents in the present crisis, and when we<lb/>may expect to hear from you.  This letter, and any reply you<lb/>may see fit to send to it, I shall reserve the right to<lb/>consider as public documents.      I remain, Honorable Gentlemen,    Yours faithfully,   (Sgd.) M. F. Fallon.     Bishop of London.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>