<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0177">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard Canson to Herbert Henry Asquith, May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard Canson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Richard Canson (b. 1883), a Protestant farmer&#39;s son, to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), the British prime minister. The letter is written in the period following the 1916 Easter Rising. Canson states that he is writing on behalf of the Protestants of County Mayo and goes on to state that the county council&#39;s decision to convert the local prison into an asylum is a treacherous one, believing that the prison is needed to detain Sinn Feiners and nationalists. He goes on to state that more of a military presence is needed in the area, which may result in a boost in recruitment and prevent the arming of young men for the nationalist movement. He goes on to suggest a local workhouse as suitable for the asylum. Herbert Henry Asquith was Liberal Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1908 to 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9040/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/177</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0573">Richard Canson</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0923">Derrynadiva, Castlebar, Co Mayo</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0177_img_1313_1"  type="Letter"  url="df6ffec3d863af6dfaf35d2c7c376566.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0177_img_1313_2"  type="Letter"  url="76d7cafe4347bc3d453be8940db40510.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0177_img_1313_3"  type="Letter"  url="667cc3809e379ac203e6ffd566f3d284.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0177_img_1313_4"  type="Letter"  url="0c149d3b20db5bd6b991b113b8504e6b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0177_img_1313_1"/>
                Dernadiva  <hi rend="underline">Castlebar</hi>  <hi rend="underline">To</hi>  Right hon. H H Asquith Prime  Minister <hi rend="superscript">Lond</hi>   Sir    on behalf of the <lb/>Protestants of Co mayo i beg draw <lb/>your attention to the fact the Co Council <lb/>has wanted close Castlebar Prison <lb/>as in excuse wants it for mayo <seg type="del">asylu</seg><lb/>asylum enlargement. this we <lb/>consider if the Government would do <lb/>as <sic>trecherous</sic> because owing to the <lb/>disturbance in Ireland of Nationalists <lb/>and Sinn Feiners we require <lb/>it always  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0177_img_1313_2"/>
              <lb/>and only it was to be had a <lb/>few weeks ago there would be <lb/>no place to detain Prisoners of <lb/>which amounted to <sic>dosens</sic> of <lb/>Sinn feiners - and this the west <lb/>requires more military. Castlebar <lb/>having a Soldiers <sic>Barricks</sic> and <lb/>a rifle range which would want <lb/>very little repair at least a <lb/>regt of English soldiers should <lb/>be for training, it would also <lb/>encourage recruiting and not <lb/>have thousands of young men <lb/>armed with rifles both  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0177_img_1313_3"/>
              <lb/>nationalists and Sinn feiners <lb/>Castlebar where there are only 30 police <lb/>while the population is over 3000 70 <lb/>and a large Country around thickly <lb/><sic>populaited</sic> and is the same in all <lb/>the chief towns of mayo at <lb/>least Castlebar which was head <lb/>quarters should not be left without <lb/>soldiers and also the mayo Prison   in conclusion i ask respectfully <lb/>you shall comply with my only <lb/>request as you in England is <lb/>not aware how nationalists and Sinn <lb/>feiners is drilling with rifles and will <lb/>not join their Colours against the huns  <seg type="closer"> I remain kind sir respectfully yours  <hi rend="underline">Richard</hi> Carson Esq (Rgt hond H H Asquith) </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0177_img_1313_4"/>
              <seg type="closer"><sic>adress</sic>  Richard Carson Esq  Dernadiva  Castlegar  <hi rend="underline">Co mayo</hi>  </seg><seg type="postscript"> P S <lb/>there is a workhouse where <lb/>there is only a few inmates <lb/>is very suitable for <sic>adition</sic><lb/>to the asylum would hold hundreds <lb/>while the prison if it was <lb/><sic>remodeled</sic> would not hold many <lb/>and <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> spoil the County having <lb/>to <hi rend="underline">be sent</hi> to Co Sligo </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>