<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0683">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his parents, Harford and Sara Montgomery, 30 October, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from William Montgomery to his parents, Harford Hugh (1856-1933) and Sarah. Montgomery starts off the letter by thanking his parents for the parcels they have sent him which include soda bread and other foods. He writes of his wishes for a better position in the army and his plans to meet a friend for dinner in town. He also reminds his parents that he had received no parcels of tobacco.This letter is part of a large collection that William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/683</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-10-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0158">Monacherra, Malone Park, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_1"  type="Letter"  url="0bfe38668523687c3e8585608e818617.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_2"  type="Letter"  url="2c654e44fd6014745d98a0c07c25e766.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_3"  type="Letter"  url="914068e15dfb4ee55cd049debe4177e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_4"  type="Letter"  url="41333388d5054fa66c3827742c709c40.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_5"  type="Letter"  url="1233ac208495bc09f0b3d163ae5746c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_6"  type="Letter"  url="c5416e36111fcd0c2740b2d8f2b4812b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_7"  type="Letter"  url="f4371129d5c8cb3a65d62ef3bcb9badf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0683_img_2175_8"  type="Envelope"  url="3ff839f9f1b96509361eb455c8a12553.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_1"/>
              10 Nov 1916    In the Field    30.10.16   Dear father &amp; Mother   I thank <lb/>father for his letter of 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>inst. <lb/>&amp; mother for hers of 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>inst. <lb/>I haven't got the soda bread &amp; 2 <lb/>bottle of lemon cheese yet. In <lb/>fact as you will see from the <lb/>Certificate enclosed herewith our <lb/>parcels are not reaching us as <lb/>they should. You may take it <lb/>that I acknowledge receipt of all <lb/>parcels from you &amp; Emmie &amp; in <lb/>fact everybody else. Once or <lb/>twice I have when writing Emmie <lb/>asked her to advise you that I <lb/> had got a parcel from you. It <lb/> is possible that she may have <lb/>forgotten to tell you when she saw <lb/>you. ask her about it.  I have got that Acetylane <lb/>Syrup, the one you recommended  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_2"/>
              <hi rend="underline">2</hi><lb/>I am writing by it now. It is <lb/>just the very thing I was <lb/>looking for.  I have ordered those Trench <lb/> card things &amp; Tin holders direct <lb/>from Moore &amp; Coates.  I am very much obliged to <lb/>father for bothering with them <lb/>especially when he is so <lb/>busy. This fountain pen is <lb/>absolutely finished.  Major Haslett hasn't turned <lb/>up yet but he might be here <lb/>tonight, as a reinforcement <lb/>officer is notified to reach us <lb/>tonight. Meantime I am having <lb/>a delightful time as acting 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/>in Command - the best job in <lb/>the regimental side of the Army.  I had a very straight heart to <lb/>heart talk with the C.O today - <seg type="del">And</seg> &amp; <lb/>he has promised me that when <lb/>he leaves this Battalion, he will  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_3"/>
              <hi rend="underline">3</hi><lb/>fix it that I get a good job. <lb/>He won't of course let me go <lb/> before that except possibly <lb/> temporarily. I told him that <lb/>soldiering is I hope only an <lb/> incident in my life that I <lb/>have seen all I want of the <lb/>regimental end of the <seg type="unclear">achievement</seg><lb/>&amp; would now like to do a bit <lb/>in the side that I would be <lb/> better fitted for viz. Staff. I, <lb/>as the C.O says know this end <lb/>of it fro A to Z. I know it far <lb/>beyond the point of boredom.  The C.O.'s leaving the Battalion <lb/>depends on when he gets a Brigade <lb/>this I think must certainly <lb/>occur before the Spring.  I have the knowledge &amp; I <lb/>don't see why I shouldn't <lb/>personally benefit by its being <lb/>put to its best use in the <lb/>country's cause. The C.O has  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_4"/>
              <hi rend="underline">4</hi><lb/>been exceedingly nice about it. <lb/>He told me he had been thinking <lb/>of my position for some time <lb/>back particularly as it became <lb/>affected by Horace's return, and <lb/> that even if I hadn't spoken <lb/>to him he was going to see both <lb/>the Bridadier &amp; the Major General <lb/>about it right away. In fact I <lb/>think he is seeing the Brigadier <lb/>about it at this very moment.  I wouldn't leave the little <lb/>devil even if I were only in <lb/>command of a platoon &amp; of course <lb/>as he knows that, it made it <lb/>easy for him to have Haslett <lb/>promoted &amp; made acting 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> in <lb/> command during Woods absence <lb/>on his 2 1/2 month course &amp; thus <lb/>in his opinion increase the <lb/>efficiency of <hi rend="underline">his</hi>Battalion by <lb/>having both of us instead of <lb/>only one. His argument  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_5"/>
              <hi rend="underline">5</hi><lb/> to me in the beginning of the <lb/> having Horace back business <lb/> was that Horace was senior <lb/> to me, that it wasn't his fault <lb/>he was wounded &amp; that he <lb/>was both fit &amp; keen to return &amp; <lb/> therefore he would return. All <lb/>of which I most cordially agreed <lb/>with possible excepting the 'fit' <lb/>part. The C.O. &amp; I discussed <lb/>all this as far back as 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>July. <lb/>Later of course I got my <seg type="unclear">A.S.O.4</seg><lb/>that influenced him further to <lb/>give the majority to Horace.  I tell you all this just in case <lb/>you might happen to hear the <lb/>matter discussed. Horace is in <lb/>the devil of a stew about it.  I am very sorry to hear that <lb/>the Salvage business isn't going <lb/>on as you could wish. What is the <lb/>good of it if it can't be pushed.  About knitted things - Socks  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_6"/>
              <hi rend="underline">6</hi><lb/>Socks Socks. I wouldn't let <lb/> anyone bother about sweaters at <lb/>present. One can't have too many <lb/> socks in winter.  There is nothing else new <lb/>here that I can tell you. I <lb/>am in the best of health &amp; form <lb/>and very much looking forward <lb/>to taking Horace to dine at a place <lb/>where he can crack bottles to <lb/>'wet his crowns'. I haven't dined <lb/><seg type="del">there f</seg>'in town' for quite a <lb/>long time now. no money. <lb/>But Horace will make that all <lb/>right for once anway &amp; then <lb/>we expect a few more Military <lb/>Crosses to be announced shortly; <lb/>so this will tide us over for quite a <lb/>bit. We got 4 more military <lb/>medals for N.C.Os &amp; men within the <lb/>last week. Some beribboned <lb/>Battalion this. <seg type="closer"> Your Affect. Son  W.T Montgomery </seg> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_7"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> Certified that I have received <lb/>no tobacco from either England <lb/>or Ireland since 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>August <lb/>1916 when I was last in Belfast. <lb/>W. Montgomery Capt <lb/>9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Batt.R.I.Rifles <lb/>30.10.16 </seg> 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0683_img_2175_8"/>
                10 Nov 1916    F.H.Montgomery Esq  C/o Messrs W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Montgomery &amp; Son  2 Wellington Place <hi rend="underline"/>  <hi rend="underline">Belfast.</hi>    Wm.A. Montgomery  Passed Field Censor 2188  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>