<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1282">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Fitzgerald to Michael Gorman, 17 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Susan Fitzgerald (d.1980) to Michael Gorman. The letter card was written while Susan was working as a voluntary nurse for the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.), a voluntary organisation providing nursing to wounded British army soldiers, in Dublin. She refers mainly to being kept in owing to an illness and her desire to get out again. She also asks Michael to send her love to &#39;Stevie&#39;, Albert Stephenson, who was a staff lecturer in the Albert College.Michael Gorman was one a large Catholic family living at a farm in Ballinalug, County Laois (then Queen&#39;s County). Susan Fitzgerald (d. 1980) was one a Church of Ireland family living in Raheenahone House near Stradbally, County Laois, also in the Slieve Bloom mountains. At the time the letter was written they were involved in a courtship but owing to the religious difference the love affair had to be kept secret. Eventually both were in Dublin: he in the Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin (where he eventually became Professor of Agricultural Botany and Biochemistry) and she as a volunteer nurse in the Royal Hospital in Baggot Street. They eventually went to London to marry.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Michael Gorman</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1282</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1259">Susan Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-04-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0639">Ballsbridge, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Michael Gorman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1251">Albert Agricultural College, Glasnevin, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1282_img_488_1"  type="Letter"  url="3302df474f365485557ba48e22ff0f1c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1282_img_488_2"  type="Envelope"  url="6a922800f1de8568742f8d91a7389ecf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1282_img_488_3"  type="Envelope"  url="517f270da19712cea7b75db5eedec3ca.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1282_img_488_1"/>
               My darling Michael,   Ever so many thanks <lb/>for your nice letter. Im <lb/>getting on nicely &amp; I expect <lb/>to be able to go home <lb/>for Easter-so don't you <lb/>hurry out of the city too <lb/>quickly put off going until <lb/>to the end of the week anyway. <lb/>I'm longing to be knocking about <lb/>Grafton St. again. I'm dead <lb/>sick of doctors, nurses pointless <lb/>medicines etc. But I'm very <lb/>lucky to get out of this <lb/>illness so quickly. I'll <lb/>tell you all about it <lb/>when we meet. Yesterday <lb/>I was <seg type="unclear">allowed</seg> sit on <lb/> an armchair in dressing <lb/>gown &amp; blankets, for 20 <lb/>minutes.  Mrs.<seg type="unclear">Luigale</seg> Came into <lb/>see me, she is coming <lb/>again this afternoon.  I wonder when will I <lb/>be let out, I feel the <lb/>time so long and if I dare <lb/>cough it mean not letting <lb/>me up so I needn't tell <lb/>you every time I am asked <lb/>how I am. Oh! I'm feeling <lb/>all right, not a bit <lb/>weak. Tell me some <seg type="del">new</seg><lb/>news when you write. I <lb/>haven't any. This is the <lb/>'Long Sunday.' I wish I was <lb/>able to go out. How is <lb/>Glasnevin looking? Remember <lb/>me to Kearns &amp; Drew. &amp; give <lb/>my love to &amp; . I'm longing <lb/>to see you again. <seg type="closer"> With much love <lb/>from your own little girl </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1282_img_488_2"/>
               IF USED FOR TRANSMISSION TO ANY PLACE ABROAD TO WHICH THE 1d RATE <lb/>OF LETTER POSTAGE DOES NOT APPLY, THE ADDITIONAL POSTAGE REQUIRED <lb/> SHOULD BE PREPAID BY MEANS OF ADHESIVE STAMPS  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1282_img_488_3"/>
                M J Gormon Esq  Albert College  Glasnevin  Dublin    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>