<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1164">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, End of February 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding masses that took place in the place in the camp. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/22, IJA/CHPI/54/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1164</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1164_img_3840_1"  type="Letter"  url="cc66b5892d55c673bab0ebe7b885ca74.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1164_img_3840_1"/>
                End of February 1918    No. 16 Casualty Clearing Station  Mesopotamian  Expeditionary  <hi rend="underline">Force</hi>.   My dear F<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Provincial, P.C.   I hope you got my last note announcing change <lb/>of address. My journey up the river took the full two weeks <lb/>and as a second officer invaded my corner after the first couple <lb/>of days, I was only able to say mass four times and even at <lb/>the best, it would have been a rather make shift mass. The last <lb/>day, for example, I could only keep a light going, and then only one <lb/>candle, during the actual consecration, owing to the wind, from which <lb/>there was no shelter. It was not bad when I began, but afterwards <lb/>had to invert the pattern over the Host to save it from being <lb/>blown away. Of course there was no one present - not even a <seg type="unclear">crewman</seg>. On <lb/>our way up we had a barge attached to us with Indian troops on board. <lb/>Small-pox developed amongst them, with the result that all ours are <lb/>now in a segregation camp for sixteen days. There are about twenty <lb/>long mud huts, on the river bank, and in one of these, with a box for an <lb/>altar, I saw Mass. From what the priest I am replacing tells me, I <lb/>judge I shall have to say Mass ever morning in a tent which I shall <lb/>share with the C.of E. chaplain, with a screen between. That's what he used <lb/>to do. I hope the Lord does not mind - personally the 'make-shift' <lb/>Mass, is the one thing I can't get reconciled to.  I enclose at note - no - it will be letter to send it separately for F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Farley. <lb/>I could only give him 10 masses during February. I shall try <lb/>to make the number up afterwards. I passed through Amara on <lb/>my way; but at night; and so was unable to see F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Hartigan's grave. <lb/>I hope the Province is thriving; and that all our chaplains are still to <lb/>the fore. F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Walton S.J. (Eng. Prov.) is in Baghdad; but I have not <lb/>seen him yet. <seg type="closer"> I recommend myself to your Reverence's prayers. I want them badly.  Francis M. Shaw S.J.   no. 16 Casualty Clearing Station M.E.F.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>