<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1712">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Lonsdale to Sir Matthew Nathan, 28 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Lonsdale</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Robert Lonsdale, Crown Solicitor of Leitrim, to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), under-secretary for Ireland, offering his candidacy for the position of Chief Crown Solicitor, following the death of Malachy J. Kelly.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5760/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1712</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0239">John Lonsdale</persName>
              <date>1916-03-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1942">Manorhampton, County Leitrim</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1712_img_1169_1"  type="Letter"  url="2edba9518a1bdde3f95ef5f1701c64bb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1712_img_1169_1"/>
             Manorhamilton, <lb/>Co Leitrim.   <hi rend="underline">March 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916</hi>   Sir.   A vacancy having arisen in the <lb/>office of Chief Crown Solicitor. <lb/>I beg to tender myself as an <lb/>applicant for the vacancy. <lb/>I have been resident &amp; practising <lb/>as a Solicitor in the County of Leitrim <lb/>for the last 26 years and for over 15 of <lb/>which I have discharged the duties <lb/>of the office of Crown &amp; Sessional Crown <lb/>Solicitor for that County. If I am <lb/>appointed I shall endeavour to give <lb/>every satisfaction in the discharge <lb/>of the duties of the office.  I am Sir <lb/>Your Obedient Servant   Rob Lonsdale   To <lb/>The Under Secretary <lb/>Chief Secretary Office 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>