<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1016">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from The O'Rahilly to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 19 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) thanking Hanna for the tickets and wishes her well for the upcoming concert. O&#39;Rahilly also writes about the commonalities between the Irish suffragist movement and themes in Gaelic civilization. Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly (&#39;The O&#39;Rahilly&#39;) was a prominent member of the Irish Volunteers. Initially opposed to the Easter Rising he was active in trying to prevent it but once it went ahead he joined the garrison in the GPO. He was shot in Parnell Street/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 while leading a charge from the burning GPO and died some time later. Sean T. O&#39;Kelly was a politician and later president of Ireland.Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47;, Ms 33,604/16-27</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1016</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0015">Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date>1916-02-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1978">40 Herbert Park, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1016_img_2871_1"  type="Letter"  url="b576ab844062a19b61018ac762f547f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1016_img_2871_2"  type="Letter"  url="3ab610c129e842f5ac1b3f4e3ccd1f9e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1016_img_2871_1"/>
                <seg type="foreign">Páirc herbert a 40</seg>  <seg type="foreign">Át Cliat</seg>    Feab 19 1916   <seg type="foreign">A cára,</seg>   I am enclosing 4/= <lb/>for the tickets and hope <lb/>your concert will be <lb/>a success.  Would it be possible <lb/>to make the Irish Suffragist <lb/>movement rather more closely <lb/>associated with Gaelicism <lb/>than it is?  Music were features of <lb/>Gaelic civilization that were <lb/>quite in harmony with the <lb/>modern movement &amp; which <lb/>might with advantage be emphasized <lb/>now. The names of married  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1016_img_2871_2"/>
              women for instance  In the Gaeltacht still <seg type="del">and</seg><lb/><seg type="del">in</seg> when Ellen Stack marries <lb/>John Sullivan she does not become <lb/>Mrs Sullivan. She becomes Ellen <lb/>Stack, the wife of John Sullivan, <lb/>and in conversation she is <lb/> universally described as Ellen Stack.   It seems a pity that <lb/>the Suffrage Party should not <lb/>press this distinct feminist <lb/><seg type="del">etc</seg> custom. <seg type="closer"> <seg type="foreign">Mise de cára</seg>  Ua Raigaille </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>