<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5722">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 12 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
This letter speaks of the decision about the best man for their wedding.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5722</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-04-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2073">Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5722_img_823_1"  type="Letter"  url="bbeeaaadb9a3e8d3bfd8058c1506cf62.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5722_img_823_2"  type="Letter"  url="19bdd0a229593b36daefb4e4aea63f5d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5722_img_823_1"/>
             Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar   12th April 1918  <lb/> My dearest James   How are you feeling after your very<lb/>expensive trip I hope you got back safely I want to<lb/>take Jocie Casey’s advice &amp; not <sic>loose</sic> you too simply<lb/>but I dare say you have become so much accustomed to the journey<lb/>up &amp; down now there is no fear of you being lost or even<lb/>tired. How did you find your mother- lonely I am sure not<lb/>having Nora there. She must have felt it you to go &amp; leave her<lb/>alone &amp; of course someone else would feel it if you stayed<lb/>so God help my poor man he is really “between the Devil &amp;<lb/>the dark blue sea”. Like myself I suppose you looking<lb/>forward to Easter but you have not long to wait when<lb/>I see it coming so near I feel ashamed of myself to have<lb/>let you come so often during the Holy Season I don’t know<lb/>what to say to seeing you Holy week I know I won’t see<lb/>you Good Friday anyway for <hi rend="underline">sure</hi> &amp; for <hi rend="underline">certain</hi>.  Did your Mother inquire if you had decided on<lb/>your best man I wonder will Mrs S. be jealous<lb/>I had given her a hint of your intentions to have<lb/>some of her boys &amp; she was quiet pleased- Oh by<lb/>the way she got out of the bag about Louis. Mrs S. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5722_img_823_2"/>
             told him not on any account to tell Tommy – he told<lb/>him in a terrible secret &amp; Tom told C.- in another<lb/>awful secret so that’s the way the awful secrets go.<lb/>What harm when it comes off it will be all over.<lb/>I am going down now to meet Nora &amp; Moll<lb/>they will have a nice drive this evening if they have<lb/>a middling nag but it would be a bit chilly if they were slow.  My Mother is praising the snapshots of the Castle<lb/>to Jennie said Jack had an artistic eye Jennie<lb/>told Jack of course &amp; “he said he had a more<lb/>artistic eye than James ” I think has he, he did<lb/>not mean as far as snapshots goes you know.<lb/>We had a letter from her today she forgot to mention in yesterday’s that she liked <seg type="del">to</seg><lb/>the idea of the white satin for me &amp; to have it<lb/>very full &amp; I will look really <hi rend="underline">  looking <seg type="unclear"></seg> </hi><lb/>she said. Do you know Jennie admires <hi rend="underline">my</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">appearance</hi> in general more than Nano’s although<lb/>she knows Nano is the <hi rend="underline">best looking</hi> but good<lb/>looks are very little after all although they are<lb/>supposed to be better fortune in <hi rend="underline">girls</hi>   I have not a word of news now so I will say goodbye<lb/>with my very very best love to my dearest man<lb/> Your loving<lb/>May<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>