<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0349">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Gavan Duffy to John O'Connell Esq., LLD, 9 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Gavan Duffy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from George Gavan Duffy (1882-1951) to John O&#39;Connell. This letter concerns the cases of Irish Volunteers Austin Stack (1879-1929) and Cornelius &#39;Con&#39; Collins (1881–1937). The writer responds to J. O&#39;Connell&#39;s letter of 29 July 1916. He disagrees with Counsel&#39;s (Mr. Healy) opinion. He believes that the trial of these men by court martial is a flagrant violation of the law – he firmly believes the men are entitled to a civil trial by jury and that the matter should be pursued without delay.George Gavan Duffy was an Irish politician, barrister and judge. He unsuccessfully defended Roger Casement at his trial for high treason after the Easter Rising. His legal practice represented many of those detained in the aftermath of the Rising. Austin Stack was commandant of the Kerry Brigade of the Irish Volunteers in 1916. Con Collins had been on route to meet Roger Casement with Austin Stack at Banna Strand. Arrested soon after, both were held in Richmond Barracks and imprisoned in Frongoch Internment camp. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD/45/4/5/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/349</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date>1916-08-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0349_img_1583_1"  type="Letter"  url="d63287c339712229b101865dc23a7c7f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0349_img_1583_2"  type="Letter"  url="a89366cc38a0fe01ea77ce202a6889a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0349_img_1583_3"  type="Letter"  url="820964b30f1610a61d66f5c078d7f78c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0349_img_1583_1"/>
                9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> August 1916   John O'Connell Esq. L.L.D.<lb/> Dear O'Connell   <hi rend="underline">re Stack and Collins:-</hi>  I have now had an opportunity of considering the documents<lb/> contained in your letter of the 29th ult. I do not propose to<lb/> say anything about the weight of evidence for that is difficult<seg type="del">y</seg><lb/> ground, but I am inclined to think that you have a strong case  even <lb/> here in normal times and that something should be made of it<lb/> even now.  The main point is that of jurisdiction; the Habeas Corpus<lb/> Acts have not yet been suspended in this country and with the<lb/> greatest respect to Mr, Healy, who is <hi rend="superscript">a</hi> valued friend of mine, I am <lb/> quite at a loss to understand what difficulty there can be in <lb/> applying for Habeas Corpus in these cases. I do not say that we<lb/> are sure to win <seg type="del">because</seg> because that is a tall order in wartime, but on<lb/> the face of it I cannot conceive a more f<seg type="del">r</seg> l agrant violation of the<lb/> law than the trial of these two prisoners by Court Martial. I am<lb/> sending you under separate cover a print of the Defense of the<lb/> Realm Act and Regulations in case you have not got them, and you <lb/> will see that it is perfectly clear from Section 56 that your<lb/> Clients had a right under sub-section 8 to a written notice that<lb/> they could claim trial by a civil court with a jury, and there is<lb/> nothing that I can find in the Regulations passed after the rising<lb/> to make the application of martial law to Ireland and the <lb/> suspension of the right to civil trial in any way retrospective.  It follows if I am right that the military authorities  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0349_img_1583_2"/>
              would have the greatest difficulty in justifying the claim that <lb/> Stack and Collins were persons subject to military law and so <lb/> amenable to a court martial. I am of course assuming that no<lb/> notice of their right to civil trial was given to them. My own <lb/> opinion is that an English Judge would give us the writ and that <lb/> the case ought to be taken up without delay.  The question is whether the application should be made in <lb/> England or in Ireland. Stack and Collins are now in an English <lb/> prison. It is quite clear that the writ of Habeus Corpus at <lb/> Common Law ran from England to Ireland (Anon.1681 1 Vent 357). I <lb/> imagine the Habeus Corpus Acts do not over-ride Common Law and <lb/> that if the writ runs from England to Ireland it would run from <lb/> Ireland to England. However, to preclude any difficulty on this <lb/> score the writ could of course be applied for here.  It is equally clear that the writ of Habeus Corpus runs <lb/> in the case of a person wrongfully taken before a court martial. <lb/> You will remember Wolf e  Tone's case and there have been others <lb/> applicable to the case of persons not subject to martial law. I <lb/> am inclined to think that we are further helped by the fact that <lb/> the court martial appears to have acted on its general knowledge <lb/> rather than upon the evidence, and this is a fact which would <lb/> weigh with a Judge who saw the <seg type="del">facts</seg> <seg type="unclear">ward?</seg>  for the first time.  You do not say whether you have (as advised by Mr Healy) <lb/> applied for copies of the warrants on which Stack and Collins were <lb/> held and of the convictions recorded against them; these I think <lb/> we ought to have. And it is also necessary to know where they <lb/> are and who is the Governor of the prison in whose custody they <lb/> are detained.  I think it would be well worth while (as these seem to me <lb/> quite the best cases I have come across among the Irish Prisoners  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0349_img_1583_3"/>
              for Habeus Corpus) for you to get into touch with Corrigan of <lb/> Dublin the Solicitor to the National Aid Committee who I am sure <lb/> will be inclined to take the case up provided they are legally <lb/> advised that the view I have expressed is correct and has a <lb/> reasonable chance of being upheld.  It is a great pity that there has been delay in the matter <lb/> but the writ is a writ of right  and  I do not think the delay should <lb/> stand in our way; but we should lose no time now.  Any relation or friend may apply for the writ. We ought <lb/> to have the full names , descriptions  and address of the applicant.  Please state whether the trial was by Field  <seg type="unclear">guard</seg>  Court Martial, <lb/> or District Court Martial.  The former trials have been<lb/> quite illegal.  <seg type="closer"> Yrs  G. Gavan Duffy </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>