<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0179">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Edward Thrift to Sir Matthew Nathan, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Edward Thrift</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Fellow of Trinity College Dublin, Professor William Edward Thrift (1870-1947), to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), the under-secretary for Ireland. Nathan was under-secretary until the 1916 Rising after which he offered his resignation. In this letter Thrift is bringing to Nathan&#39;s attention a Dublin newspaper named &#39;Eye-Opener&#39; and claims that it is making terrible insinuations about some of the members of his Rathmines Parish Church. Thrift claims that the people being targeted are good people and that the paper is causing serious harm. He is calling for Nathan to act against the paper using the Defence of the Realm Act.Mathew Nathan had become under-secretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned as under-secretary due to his misjudgement and failure to stop the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5561/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/179</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0186">William Edward Thrift</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1458">80 Grosvenor Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0179_img_1315_1"  type="Letter"  url="0e534babe4b0ee4da35d4c7b17caa553.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0179_img_1315_2"  type="Letter"  url="f3c9ae5b51d2190d4b1e78e1b8da05b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0179_img_1315_3"  type="Letter"  url="18b09ce905c58a9fbec1b53481d118a1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0179_img_1315_4"  type="Letter"  url="d6f220baacff0c65642e1a7464202f2b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0179_img_1315_1"/>
                80, Grosvenor Square  Rathmines  Dublin    29th March 1916    The Rt. Hon. Sir Mathew Nathan G.C.M.G.  <hi rend="underline">The Under Secretary</hi>   Dear Sir   The serious and urgent <lb/> nature of the matter <lb/> about which I write is my apology <lb/> for troubling you with this <lb/> letter. A paper called the <lb/> 'Eye -opener', published in Dublin <lb/> and publicly sold has been <lb/> brought under my notice, owing  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0179_img_1315_2"/>
              its scandalous and <lb/><seg type="unclear">malicious</seg> insinuations, against <lb/> some of the members of the <lb/> congragation of Rathmines Parish <lb/> Church, and even our Rector. <lb/> The attacks are so thinly <lb/> veiled that no one in the <lb/> district is in doubt as to <lb/> the identity of those to whom <lb/> reference is made, and I <lb/> may say that they are old <lb/> and respected members of <lb/> the congregation. One of them <lb/> has been Hon. Secretary of the <lb/> select Vestry of the Parish for  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0179_img_1315_3"/>
              years. Needless to say, the charges <lb/> are absolutely without foundation, <lb/> but great pain is being caused <lb/> to worthy people, both ladies and gentlemen, and much have may <lb/> be, and i fear is being, done <lb/> by the circulation of such <lb/> statements and the gossip which <lb/> they incite   Civil proceeding are <lb/> useless to you to take steps to <lb/> suppress the paper, if this be <lb/> possible you will be confessing <lb/> a boon on the communities of <lb/> Rathmines and Dublin by stopping <lb/> a grave scandal.   I have been a member <lb/> of the congregation for some <lb/> 30 years and of its select Vestry  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0179_img_1315_4"/>
              some 20 years and know well those <lb/> whose characters are being defamed. I regard <lb/> the matter as really anxious and feel the <lb/> deepest indignation at it. I am sure you <lb/> will, under the circumstances, pardon me for <lb/> thus bringing it under your notice.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,   W <hi rend="superscript">m</hi>L Thrift <lb/> P.T.C.D.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>