<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0085">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Davie English to his brother, Patrick English, c. June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Davie English</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Davie English to his brother Patrick English (1894-1970), a prisoner in Frongoch. While this letter is undated, it is clear from the context that the letter was written not long after the Rising. In the letter, Davie tells his brother that he is not to worry about their mother, although she is very lonely. Davie writes about the lack of sport and enquires after other people he knows that are in Frongoch with his brother. He also mentions how sad he feels about the events of the Rising and how he hopes that peace will come soon. He ends the letter with a postscript that Patrick will have to find another girlfriend when he gets home as his one is now &#39;stepping out&#39; with a soldier.Patrick English was an Irish Volunteer imprisoned in the Stafford and later Frongoch Prisons. He had at least six cousins fighting with the British Army in France during his incarceration.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/85</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0966">Davie English</persName>
              <date>-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0231">Cabra, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0112">Frongoch Prison, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0085_img_1159_1"  type="Letter"  url="f8cb6017cf9ddc7986d25074c075c7f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0085_img_1159_2"  type="NULL"  url="18a8fdc60db451e2a4de88f9437b4b6f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0085_img_1159_1"/>
              Kathleen <lb/>Nellie &amp; Frank <lb/>sends their <lb/>love <lb/>— <lb/>you will have <lb/>to look out <lb/> for another <lb/>girl when <lb/>you get home <lb/>as I see <lb/><sic>you</sic> girl walking <lb/>out with a <lb/>soldier <lb/>— good bye    Hampton Cottages  Cabra   Sunday  Dear Patrick   a few lines hoping they may find you <lb/>well under the circumstances. I expect you must feel very lonely <lb/> but  you  must keep your heart up as you know the darkest  hour  is <lb/> before the dawn. you need not be fretting about my mother as you <lb/>know she will not be cold or hungry whhile we have anything <lb/> needless to say she is very lonely. I go to see her every night <lb/>when I am finished work. I <sic>supose</sic> you know we have to be up <lb/> early now, the daylight saving bill, then we are off early in the <lb/>evening, <sic>their</sic> is not much sport, no football no <sic>raceing</sic> but <lb/><sic>raceing</sic> is starting very soon. I had a bad day at Fairy House <lb/>on Easter Monday  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0085_img_1159_2"/>
              I had all my money on a stiff one in the last race <lb/>you need not trouble about answering my letter when you are <lb/> writing home you can say if you received my letter. I <sic>seen</sic>in <lb/>the papers a lot of names I know. I went to all the prisons <lb/> in Dublin before I seen your name in the Herald, when you are <lb/>writing home let us know if you are allowed <sic>cigraettes</sic><lb/> Mr Ginnell said yous are allowed some of that is so I will send <lb/>you some at once. tell M Cosgrave I was asking for him and <lb/> tell him Abbotstown garden is in the same place if you are <lb/> near any of the lads that I know tell them I send them <lb/> my best wishes and tell  them  from me that, Kathleen na <sic>Houilan</sic><lb/>sends them her love and hopes she will soon see them <lb/> all again. I think  the  whole thing is too sad for words, but I trust <lb/>in God that peace will soon come, I often think now that <lb/> the summer is here the fields &amp; trees in bloom that we were made <lb/>for <sic>nobeler</sic> things than fighting. <seg type="closer"> Your loving Brother <lb/> Davie </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>