<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5643">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Garret Sheehan, 14 February 1916. </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Garret Sheehan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Garret Sheehan explaining how, on his way to visit a friend, he was followed by a police officer and charged with the possession of a gun. Sheehan maintains that he was falsely charged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3747/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5643</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0010">Garret Sheehan</persName>
              <date>1916-02-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1139">Cloghane, Knocknagoshel, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5643_img_735_1"  type="Letter"  url="8f96cbc73a34b4a71d57252c5067ba6f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5643_img_735_2"  type="Letter"  url="1ca153e97f583a631939095d69301a2c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5643_img_735_1"/>
             Cloughane <lb/>Knocknagoshel <lb/>Co. Kerry   Dear Sir  <lb/>I beg to draw your attention <lb/>to a false case of which I had been <lb/>a victim, On the 11th day of Decr <lb/>1915, on proceeding to a place called <lb/>Gortroe, Knochnagoshel North, To <lb/>hear about a friend, and Niece of mine <lb/>who was shot at the Battle of Mons <lb/>when I was pursued by 2 police, And <lb/>charged with having a gun, of which <lb/>I had been, purely innocent, Were <lb/>I a farmers son, or a merchants son, <lb/>They would not have  <lb/>charged me with, having a gun of which <lb/>I had not in my possession on that day. <lb/>I would wish to know whether it is the <lb/>farmers sons, or the Labouring men <lb/>have done the most, to help keep out <lb/>the Common enemy of Ireland, and <lb/>the British Empire, I can assure you <lb/>that it is only all a concocted matter <lb/>between, a man named David Murphy <lb/>Knocknagoshel, who seems to dislike <lb/>me, and the present RIC Sergeant <lb/>Linehan, who both owns a greyhound for <lb/>hunting Game hares. They think that I <lb/>a man with licence, will shoot them <lb/>all, I mean the hares, There is 15 years <sic>years</sic>, Since I got first <seg type="unclear">ecevation</seg> licence <lb/>From District Inspector Woods Castle- <lb/>island, Co Kerry, And was not limited. And if you desire, a charac <lb/>ter of me, who is <hi rend="underline">75 years of age,</hi> you <lb/>may write Sergeant Foland or Sergea <lb/>nt Connell
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5643_img_735_2"/>
            and though its not the farmers sons <lb/>If I was a youth of 18 or 19 years I <lb/>would have been opposing the Germans <lb/>In France or Flanders Long ago, And <lb/>If my Services, are not any value to you <lb/>they are at your disposal, I would <lb/>be very pleased If I had a reply <lb/>from your Excellency for the 4th <lb/>of February, being the day of trial  I Remain Dear Sir <lb/>Yours Truly   Garret Sheahan 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>