<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1621">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 17 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. Marie Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM). In this letter from the theatre of war, Marie writes home to her mother to talk about family matters. These included the issue of her brother Charlie (1895-1915) being feared as missing in action during the war at this time, Martin explains the length she goes to in order to attempt to get any news on the well being of her brother.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF125</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1621</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-01-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_1"  type="Letter"  url="6270a00e10d96e4173e119edec166b7f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_2"  type="Letter"  url="d4b3d8b566ebe55660f645a4f8dd3399.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_3"  type="Letter"  url="8acff61a35daf6cb6992c1deb0b5b99f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_4"  type="Letter"  url="603346cb99e14701c02ecf4e9d645f75.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_5"  type="Letter"  url="c023f05648a6895407d6c95e25b502e3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_6"  type="Letter"  url="dfc498db236cfc3361363bfa4f2ae09a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_7"  type="Letter"  url="072e570807ac0e0d06b4991165299d09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_8"  type="Letter"  url="3e7c9e4eebddff83c5256a5f760b5c02.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_9"  type="Letter"  url="401d0cc780d5506b827eedb57eefafbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_10"  type="Letter"  url="ffe1c8be90624b1e4ed82c0d00f04d2f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1621_img_1084_11"  type="Letter"  url="7c84804d9d69a863e912517ba0b56602.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_1"/>
             The Club, <lb/> Malta   17th January   My very dearest Mother,   Your most welcome <lb/> and consoling letter dated Jan; <lb/> 6th arrived yesterday, it <lb/> is terrible not getting any <lb/>news of Charlie for so long <lb/> but I hope by the time <lb/> this reaches you, you will <lb/> have had some satisfactory <lb/> news as I think the <lb/>suspense is appalling. I <lb/>personally think he must <lb/> be a prisoner for any news <lb/> I could gather from the <lb/> men although most of them
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_2"/>
            seem. very surprised at hearing <lb/> he is missing- I sent you a <lb/> card after seeing Massy who <lb/> was also very surprised at <lb/> hearing he was missing, he heard <lb/> from an Officer of the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Divs <lb/> who was in the next bed to <lb/> him at Solonika that Charlie <lb/> had been slightly wounded <lb/> in the arm &amp; walked down <lb/> to dressing station with him <lb/> Of course Massey said if he had <lb/> known there was any question <lb/> about him missing he would <lb/> have got more particulars but <lb/> the way they all spoke of him <lb/>they thought he was alright <lb/> in Hospital, When Dicko told <lb/> him that Charlie was wounded <lb/> but spoke very lightly of it. <lb/> Sgt. Currie mentioned lt Turner &amp;  said he should know something <lb/> as he took over command after <lb/> Charlie had been hit . A great <lb/> number think he is safely <lb/> somewhere in Hospital but <lb/> owing to the retreat things <lb/> were rather muddled &amp; infor- <lb/>mation is hard to get <lb/> Others think if he has not <lb/> been very badly wounded, he <lb/> may have just gone down got <lb/> dressed( his wound), &amp; re join them <lb/> Otherwise he would be reported <lb/> missing but as you say <lb/> there is really very little <lb/> use in wondering what has <lb/> happened to him we must <lb/> only trust Our divine <lb/> Lord &amp; be ready for his <lb/> holy Will. What a <lb/> What a brave &amp;good Mother you are
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_3"/>
            &amp; I hope you will very soon <lb/> be rewarded by good news of <lb/> him, all the Nuns are praying <lb/> for him out here &amp; I try &amp; <lb/> do my little bit by offering <lb/> up my whole day for news. <lb/> How I wish I were at home <lb/> if I could be of any use but <lb/>the worst of it is there is so <lb/> very little to do but wait. <lb/> I am going off this afternoon <lb/> to see a couple more men to see <lb/> if they have any news of him <lb/> What a brave boy he has been <lb/> &amp;never a murmur from him <lb/> all the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Div. have gone through <lb/> words cannot express. I sent <lb/> him a large parcel of food <lb/> for Xmas but of course it <lb/> was no use as it was sent <lb/> after he was wounded -
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_4"/>
            Captain Massy was in great <lb/> form, he has not been wounded <lb/>again it is the old wound <lb/> which is gradually paralysing <lb/> his hand it was great luck <lb/> me seeing him although <lb/> I believe he telephoned me <lb/> up wanting me to go &amp; see him. <lb/> at Blue Sisters &amp; Rev: Mother <lb/> wrote which of course did not <lb/> arrive till after he had <lb/> left Blue Sister but I rang <lb/> up B.S. on my own &amp; heard <lb/> he was sailing on the Marne <lb/> at 1 o'ck. on Thursday last <lb/> so I got leave to go down <lb/> to the Wharf &amp; had to wait <lb/> till four before he arrived <lb/> Sister <seg type="unclear">Travers</seg> came with me <lb/> &amp; we had tea on board <lb/> but had to leave immediately
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_5"/>
            afterwards as I had to be <lb/> on duty It was such a pity he <lb/> did not know as he could <lb/> have got all news about Charlie <lb/> before leaving. He said Dick <lb/> was alright as luckily he <lb/> only arrived the day before <lb/> the big engagement &amp; they <lb/> kept him back , so that is <lb/> good news, he reports him <lb/> looking very well also Col. Cooper <lb/> is back again.-     Well a great number of things <lb/> have happened since I last <lb/> wrote which is quite a long <lb/> time but I have been very <lb/> busy owing to all the changes. <lb/> For the last 3 weeks we have <lb/> been getting slacker every day <lb/> &amp;the Colonel took it <lb/> into his head to close 2 blocks  for a bit F. as they have <lb/> had the hardest work since <lb/> the Hospital has been opened. <lb/> so we got orders on Friday to <lb/> have all patients moved &amp; <lb/> get the equipment &amp; wards <lb/>straight, you can imagine <lb/> or you can't what it meant <lb/> for me of course it meant mostly <lb/> scrubbing &amp; sweeping &amp; on <lb/> Saturday we were all told to <lb/> be ready at 9 O'ck. to go to <lb/> Antonio Palace for 48 hours <lb/> rest after making up our <lb/> minds to this order which <lb/> none of us relished very <lb/> much. We went to bed very <lb/> tired &amp; stayed in bed for <lb/> breakfast but when they <lb/> went down the others as usual
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_6"/>
            they found a notice saying <lb/> orders cancelled &amp;would those <lb/> 8 ladies go on duty as usual <lb/> so up I had to get &amp;down <lb/> to the empty wards &amp; the <lb/> next order was all differences <lb/> must be made up by <lb/> one O'clock then there was a fuss <lb/> trying to get mattresses etc. back <lb/> from fumigator. However we got through <lb/> every thing &amp; were really not <lb/> so very much out . I only know <lb/> I was never so tired in all <lb/> my life, all the staff were <lb/> off from 1 O'clock Sunday to <lb/> Wednesday morning the Matron <lb/> said as I had not been <lb/> out so long I was not to <lb/> take my 48 hours off but the <lb/> truth of the matter was she had
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_7"/>
            asked me to go &amp; call on <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Lady Matheun</seg> with her &amp; I think <lb/> she was afraid if she gave me <lb/> my time off I would not <lb/> go with her. Any how I went <lb/> &amp; I hope if I ever go again <lb/> it will not be with a Matron <lb/> Lady M. is such a nice simple <lb/> woman but I did feel a fool <lb/> with the Matron there as I had <lb/> to be very careful what I <lb/> said or I got a glare, it <lb/> was so trying when L. M. <lb/> asked if we had everything <lb/> we wanted &amp; that she had <lb/> a great number of Hot <lb/> Water bottles &amp; would we like <lb/> any for St. G. the Matron <lb/> said we had enough. L. M. <lb/> said how lucky we were to
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_8"/>
            have everything we wanted <lb/> how many had we for each <lb/> ward? &amp; the Matron said 12 <lb/> when we have only 12 for 70 <lb/> patients so you see how things <lb/> are done. However we must <lb/> not complain this new <lb/> Colonel is making things <lb/> look up &amp;the hot weather <lb/> will very soon be here. <lb/> Did I ever tell you that we <lb/> the Staff of 7 upper were the <lb/> proudest sisters in the whole <lb/> Hospital, as the patients all <lb/> clubbed together &amp; presented us <lb/> each with a very pretty gold <lb/> Maltese Cross broach in gratitude <lb/> for all our kindness &amp; as a <lb/> token of how much they <lb/> appreciate it &amp; what a jolly  Xmas they spent at St Georges. <lb/> So this is another sign of how <lb/> much they enjoy themselves &amp; <lb/> we have to thank all the <lb/> kind &amp;generous people at home <lb/> So will you please thank <lb/> them all as I am afraid <lb/> as yet have had time to <lb/> write nothing but a P. C. to <lb/> them -     I had such a surprise &amp; <lb/> beautiful present from Gerald <lb/> a few days ago. he sent <lb/> me a beautiful Attache case <lb/> from the Silver &amp; Goldsmiths <lb/> London, it is a beauty, brown <lb/> pigskin with fitted Green <lb/> Morocco lining, The funny <lb/> thing is I have not had a <lb/> letter for a very long time. <lb/> I am longing to know how he
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_9"/>
            is getting on I wonder if he <lb/> was in London about the 30<hi rend="superscript">th </hi> <lb/> Dec. as that is the date on <lb/> the parcel. I need not tell you <lb/> it was the greatest surprise <lb/> possible he will be very cut <lb/> up over Charlie I know as <lb/> he is very fond of him. <lb/> We really do not know <lb/> what is happening out here <lb/> just now every day new <lb/> Sisters &amp; V.A.D.s are being <lb/> sent out &amp; just at present <lb/> there is not enough for our <lb/> present staff to do as they <lb/> are clearing out all the <lb/> Hospitals on the Island. How <lb/> ever I suppose we must only <lb/> wait &amp; see. A Miss Smyth <lb/> Sir W Smyth's daughter arrived
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_10"/>
            yesterday so she gave me a <lb/> little Dublin News she seems <lb/> very disgusted with Dublin <lb/> as she says they are not <lb/> recruiting as they should <lb/> &amp; very annoyed they are <lb/> left out of the complusion <lb/> She is a very pretty little <lb/> thing &amp; I think very clever. <lb/> She is sharing our flat but <lb/> not in the same room as I <lb/> am. What about A. Liyl <lb/> has she started on her <lb/> travels yet, tell her as she <lb/> is coming so late to have <lb/> a cotton dress made so <lb/> that she can wear it out of <lb/> doors without a coat &amp; also <lb/> to bring a very light coat
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_1621_img_1084_11"/>
            &amp; skirt as they say after <lb/> this month it begins to get <lb/> very very hot.     Did I tell you a Captain <lb/> Leslie of Dundalk came to <lb/> see me the other day M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> <lb/> Mac Ardle wrote to him <lb/> about me, He is quite nice <lb/> elderly &amp; is finding out all <lb/> he can from his men about <lb/> Charlie for me, all my spare <lb/> time I try &amp; get information <lb/> as I know how terrible <lb/> the waiting is for news although <lb/> I am glad to say have not <lb/> much time for thinking <lb/> but it distresses me to think <lb/> of you all at home but I <lb/> feel assured with all those  prayers everything will end well <lb/> I hope you got my letter from <lb/> Birzebbuga safely   Well I shall end this now <lb/> as I have to meet a <lb/> V. A. D. who says the <lb/> Matron was looking for <lb/> me so want to hurry <lb/> back. One never knows <lb/> where you are at St. Georges <lb/> these times    With every loving thought <lb/> &amp; the very best of wishes <lb/> I live all day with you <lb/> although we are so far <lb/> parted &amp;only wish I could <lb/> do something,    Your most loving &amp; grateful <lb/> daughter     Marie. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>