<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0780">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 30 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender writes of a recently received letter, his recent promotion, and the spectacular effects of a new set of armaments the Germans have begun to use. The final page of the letter appears to have been lost.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. In July 1916, he was temporarily transferred to a Corps HQ on a separate section of the front. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/368</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/780</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-30T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0780_img_2314_1"  type="NULL"  url="cbed1aa161c6d3e388e394c88a507ffd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0780_img_2314_2"  type="NULL"  url="979ddb5402d878db22e3790b5f7f1521.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0780_img_2314_1"/>
                30 July   My pr   I'm not sure if last night's <lb/>letter left in time for the mail <lb/>but as it was Saturday it won't <lb/>matter so much, as you will get <lb/>Friday's. Your letter of 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> has <lb/>only just come via the Army <lb/>but I ought to have got one later. <lb/>Rather surprised you don't say if <lb/>the family are pleased or whether they <lb/>think it makes you rather elderly <lb/>Mrs Temporary Lt. Col. However by the time <lb/>you are used to it you will be Mrs Captain <lb/>again! I don't know what the war office will <lb/>do with Reserve officers after the war but  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0780_img_2314_2"/>
              think they will probably revert them to their <lb/> old ranks in order to prevent too many <lb/>senior officers from cumbering the land.  You will consider whether it is advisable <lb/>to send Rex's letters to me or to Mater <lb/>or perhaps let Ev decide this.  I saw a good deal of the battle <lb/>yesterday from near the ruins of an <lb/>old German village. There were explosions <lb/>of red smoke over another village <lb/>in front very wonderful cloud effects but <lb/> meaning I'm afraid some further new <lb/>German monstrosity. Later there were <lb/>some near shells bursting in the air <lb/>giving enormous cloud showers of <lb/>smoke and flame. None of us had <lb/>seen the like before. I have not yet <lb/>heard what their effect was. A great <lb/>fat budget so I must have another page <lb/>which you can pass round.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>