<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5902">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lady Mayo to Lady Clonbrock, 1 September, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Geraldine Sarah Bourke</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Lady Mayo, Geraldine Sarah Bourke (née Ponsonby), Countess of Mayo (1863-1944), was a committee member in The Royal Dublin Fusiliers&#39; County Kildare Committee. The Committee dealt with parcels for R.D.F. Prisoners of War abroad.
Lady Clonbrock, Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton, 1839-1928), wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock, (1834-1917) was one of a number of mainly well-to-do ladies who were members of the Irish Women&#39;s Association. Formed in London in the Spring of 1915, the IWA&#39;s purpose was to provide food and comforts for prisoners of War belonging to Irish Regiments. 
Lady Mayo refers to another letter (which has survived), which she has received, and encloses, from the P.O.W. Camp in Berne, Switzerland, concerning an Irish POW.
Lady Mayo recalls previous correspondence concerning this individual* and says that, even though he does not belong to the Royal Dublin Fusiliers, due to a mix-up, he has been supplied with bread by them. Lady Mayo asks Lady Clonbrock to take over his case.

*NLI35795/11/1a which has also survived.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5902</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1240">Geraldine Sarah Bourke</persName>
              <date>1916-09-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0076">Royal Dublin Fusiliers County Kildare Committee, Palmerstown, Straffan, Co. Kildare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName >None</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1944</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5902_img_997_1"  type="Letter"  url="418811a5b2fec254bf3e5049f92267f2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5902_img_997_1"/>
              Royal Dublin Fusilier's Country Kildare Committee, Nass<lb/>
Committee - THE COUNTRESS OF MAYO, MRS. LOVEBAND AND J. W. DANE  
  Palmerstown,<lb/>Straffan.  
  1st September 1916  
   Dear Lady Clonbrock,   
 I think we have corresponded about this man before now,<lb/>
 I send you the letter that we have received  from /Berne. They have<lb/>
 muddled him up with an R.D.F. Would you be so kind as to see<lb/>
 to him. I did allow him bread on my own<lb/>account till June. I remember 
 very sincerely 
 G. Mayo 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>