<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5091">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jennie Gallivan to Ellen Daly, 19 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jennie Gallivan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/4/6/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5091</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0631">Jennie Gallivan</persName>
              <date>1923-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1596">109 Bishop Street, Derry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5091_img_None_1"  url="9a3fe04111873acb1da35ce901c2a445.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5091_img_None_2"  url="7b1dc6fb828aeb46175e960e4c4acd0d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5091_img_0_1"/>
              P41/4/6/8    109 Bishop Street<lb/>Derry <lb/> 19<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> March 1923     <seg type="foreign">  A chara dhil   </seg>  Just a few lines from the black North<lb/>to tell you how sorry I am for your great loss.<lb/>We have got no particulars here yet but I shall<lb/>do my best to find out everything, all I know<lb/>at present is they died like heroes and Charlie<lb/>led them out and they all carried lighted candles<lb/>and sang let me carry my cross for Ireland. The<lb/>firing party were ex-black &amp; tans they were<lb/>supposed to have come from Dublin. They were<lb/>supposed to be shot as a reprisal <seg type="del">four</seg> for an<lb/>officer called Cannon who was killed at<lb/>Creeslough but Cannon was killed in a<lb/>mutiny of Free Staters in Creeslough. I shall do<lb/>all I can to find out everything but I must wait<lb/>for some little time yet. I had a letter from him<lb/>on Tuesday last little did I think. I may<lb/>tell you that all the people in the North<lb/>that new him are broken-hearted, there<lb/>is no need to tell you all we thought of him<lb/>a better or nobler man never lived &amp;it is 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5091_img_0_2"/>
             hard to think that it should have been in<lb/>Donegal such a tragedy should take place. I did<lb/>not know any of the other Kerry men, but I<lb/>must find out if there are any Kerry men left.<lb/>I would have sent you a wire on Wednesday but<lb/>I did not know your address and I did not<lb/>believe it possible and it is hard even yet to<lb/>realise it. One of the other men Larkin <seg type="del">live</seg> was<lb/>from Derry and his two sisters went off to America<lb/>on Saturday, my heart was sore for them I shall<lb/>never forget the sight. I shall send on all the<lb/>news that I can possibly get and sometime maybe<lb/>if I go to Kerry I am going to see you as I would<lb/>love to see you. My father is a Kerry man so I<lb/>may get a chance down to the Kingdom sometime.<lb/>Accept my sincerest sympathies in your great<lb/>loss, I shall pray for God to strengthen you to<lb/>bear your heavy burden.   Slán &amp; beannacht<lb/>Jennie Gallivan  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>