<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5862">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Paddy Guinness to Cesca Chenevix Trench, 6 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Paddy Guinness</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Paddy Guinness to Cesca Chenevix Trench (an Anglo-Irish woman who adopted Irish identity and took an Irish name Sadhbh Trinseac).  Guinness writes regarding the Irish Volunteers and Irish language.

Cesca Chevenix Trench, illustrator, was an Anglo-Irish member of the Gaelic League who took an Irish identity and changed her name to Sadhbh Trinseach. Her three brothers enlisted with the British Army in 1914 with her closest brother, Reggie (1888-1918), gazetted to the Sherwood Foresters. Trench served in the Stephen&#39;s Green garrison during the Rising, later writing that the Rising had been a &#39;tragic mistake.&#39; Trench later married Diarmuid Coffey on 17 April 1918. Cesca would perish, like so many others, from the virulent Spanish Flu in October 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 46,305 /4; Coffey &amp; Chenevix Trench Papers, Collection List 153</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5862</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0768">Paddy Guinness</persName>
              <date>1916-06-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Cesca Chenevix Trench</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5862_img_96_1"  type="Letter"  url="e99807efcd24001ce3cad5c62b750380.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5862_img_96_2"  type="Letter"  url="13e6f1ad39bd6191375f744d29d7c945.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5862_img_96_3"  type="Letter"  url="a0f1431e2af2e0ae23df650ac74b378b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5862_img_96_4"  type="Letter"  url="d46dae463cd4972c6d4ed3d073195618.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5862_img_96_5"  type="Envelope"  url="ed37b55544754d2a1cf2b580fae3306b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5862_img_96_1"/>
            Is maith liom go bFuairis amach mo sheóladh — creid mé le buidheachas mór Prionnsias Airmeas. (F.C.Ormsby) this case __________ perhaps you would be good eno' to assure me that the confusion created in my mind by your communication has no real cause. I <seg type="del">observe</seg> conclude from it that you are unacquainted with the language of this country &amp; of which your name proclaims you in no uncertain voice to be a native. <seg type="del">in no uncertain voice</seg>. These two <seg type="del">seeming</seg> contradictory facts force me to the conclusion that I have mistaken the identity of the person I am addressing.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5862_img_96_2"/>
            <lb/>the said window. You <sic>shd</sic> then face <lb/>to the east  deploy  &amp; advance in extended <lb/>order down the incline.  Very careful to avoid  future <lb/> lurching  movements I leave to <sic>yr</sic> own <lb/>discretion &amp; and the  military  strategical know <lb/>-ledge you will have acquired <lb/>from a study of the front page <lb/>of the <seg type="del">shrunken</seg> National Volun -teer.   4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. The nature of the party <lb/>is that known as the <seg type="del">small</seg> <lb/><seg type="foreign">céilid beag</seg> or 'small caylee' <lb/>which is <seg type="del">used for</seg> a generic <lb/>term for anything from a <lb/>friendly gathering to a ball. <lb/><seg type="del">In</seg> The circumscribed place at my <lb/>disposal precludes the latter <lb/>possibility, but I may mention <lb/>that a turf fire will be a <lb/>feature.   I trust that this explanation will prove satis<lb/> <lb/>-factory to you &amp; in
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5862_img_96_3"/>
            <lb/>Perhaps you <sic>wd</sic> be good <seg type="unclear">enough</seg> <lb/>to transfer my invitation<lb/> <lb/>to <sic>yr</sic> namesake together with <lb/>the expression of my profound <lb/>respect &amp; to pardon the error <lb/>into which I have fallen.   In conclusion may I urge upon you <lb/>the consideration that as <lb/>Mr Diarmuid o Cobhthaigh's <lb/>position as Sec: of the National <lb/>Volunteers, did not in his <lb/>opinion absolve him from <lb/>the necessity of <seg type="del">sp</seg> using <lb/>his native language, so your <lb/>position doubtless most <lb/>creditable, tho' unknown to <lb/>me does not absolve you.   I am Sir<lb/> <lb/>Your obedient servant    Paddy Guinness. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5862_img_96_4"/>
            <!-- It would appear to me that there is at least one page missing - page 2 doesn't make much sense in the light of what went before. Similarly, the transition from page 2 to page 3 is difficult-->
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5862_img_96_5"/>
             London S.W. <lb/> <lb/>12.15AM  6 Jun 16   Miss Cesca Chenevix Trench <lb/>Temple Hill <lb/>Terenure <lb/>Co: Dublin. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>