<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0773">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 22 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Spender gives an account of his feelings on being made Lieutenant Colonel and transferred to the General Staff of the 4th Army. He discusses his row with his current Division&#39;s General Officer Commanding, his worry that he is deserting his brother Rex, and the poor reputation of the unit to which he is being moved. He also suggests that Lillian manage their accounts after their war, as their joint finances are doing much better under her control than they did under his own.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/357</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/773</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0773_img_2306_1"  type="NULL"  url="45a16d81188e581f86947fc35faea466.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0773_img_2306_2"  type="NULL"  url="1d0854ce03c7241fbe0d8bb7ad56bbec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0773_img_2306_3"  type="NULL"  url="9fd12a4a5e303b6c78c274166c2a2907.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0773_img_2306_1"/>
                22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> July   My Pr   You will have got my news in the other <lb/> scrap.   I cannot describe my feelings. For some time <lb/>I hesitated, &amp; one of the main factors that has decided <lb/>me is the unpleasantness. Every one tells me <lb/>that it is impossible to refuse &amp; one would not <lb/>be allowed to do so, but I wold like to have tried, <lb/>but now I feel that the strain would make one's <lb/>work largely futile, &amp; might do harm. He is not <lb/>pleased &amp; shows that he has not forgiven me so <lb/>so there is no living down the misunderstanding.  I am off in a few minutes, going quite close <lb/>to the district where I was before. It will not <lb/>be a bed of roses as this particular lot has a  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0773_img_2306_2"/>
              way of scrapping people in order to cover their <lb/>failures. I am an extra so it is not exactly <lb/>permanent but it probably means my transfer <lb/>to a Division later if I am allowed to survive.  It is looked upon as rather better than a <seg type="unclear">GSO1</seg><lb/>Division but I don't think it is if it is only <lb/>as an extra.   I feel like deserting Rex &amp; am afraid he <lb/>may feel it too but in some ways it will be <lb/>easier for him &amp; for me too. He felt strange &amp; <lb/> I in some ways wish he could have had more <lb/>time before going into the trenches, but it is <lb/>supposed to be a quiet part, &amp; I hope may prove  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0773_img_2306_3"/>
              so at first.   Tell Mater  &amp; Ed  to whom I have not time <lb/> to write till I get to the train.   I have quite made up my mind that pr <lb/>had better manage the accounts afterwards instead <lb/>of the b w as they flourish much more under <lb/> her control !  <seg type="closer"> Your  b w <lb/> W B Spender. </seg><seg type="postscript"> Though I am only Temporary Lt Col I believe that <lb/>in one's letters one is always addressed as Lt Col GS. <lb/>I like to feel that, it is due to the success &amp; sacrifice <lb/>of our devoted Ulsterman that this reward has been given me. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>