<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2259">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to William Coote, 22 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to Coote. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter was addressed to William Coote (1853-1924). Coote was a politician and in 1916 he was representing South Tyrone as a Unionist MP and continued to do so until 1922.
In the letter Montgomery is discussing the Irish Question and the fears that Unionists have about Home Rule and the recent Rebellion in Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers - D-627-429-9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2259</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-05-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Coote</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2259_img_1702_1"  type="Letter"  url="31a2ecefc08431d67d4ff3f93dfe2ba3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2259_img_1702_2"  type="NULL"  url="85c0e7138306257871d158b751af0adb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2259_img_1702_1"/>
            Copy  22nd May, 1916   Dear Mr. Coote,   I suppose the Emergency Act with your Clause in it <lb/> is not printed yet. In this case could you let me have a <lb/> copy of the Bill as it left the Commons, or if you have not a <lb/> spare copy of the Bill, a copy of your Clause. In order to <lb/> save time on the 30th it may be well for me to draft a short <lb/> Memorandum as to the position we are dealing with.   The efforts of our enemies to create an atmosphere <lb/> favourable to the imposition of some Home Rule compromise upon <lb/> our leaders are very far-reaching and rather alarming. The <lb/> statements that Unionists in this country are inclined to enter <lb/> into any such compromise are totally false. I was at a very <lb/> representative meeting of Southern Unionists last Wednesday, and <lb/> they were absolutely unanimous in protesting against any form <lb/> of Home Rule. The publication of their protest was postponed <lb/> in order to ascertain whether our leaders considered it wise at <lb/> the present moment. Every Irish Unionist I have come across <lb/> considers that the objections to the establishment of an Irish <lb/> Parliament in any form are enormously strengthened by the recent <lb/> Rebellion and the mode in which it has been treated by John Dillon <lb/> and other Nationalists of the Parliamentary Party. I cannot <lb/> imagine Sir Edward Carson entering into any agreement with <lb/> John Redmond, if, for no other reason, because I believe John <lb/> Redmond has now a very small following in this country. <seg type="del">The</seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2259_img_1702_2"/>
            Belfast Daily telegraph of this morning prints in its first <lb/>column some most mischievous rigmaroles.   I tried to get some arrangements made in Dublin to <lb/>counteract the campaign for undermining the Unionism of English <lb/> Unionist papers, but cannot say whether my suggestions can <lb/>be worked.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>