<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0156">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alfred Gerald Crofton to Lady Clonbrock, 1 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alfred Gerald Crofton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Alfred Gerald Crofton (1882-1942) to his aunt, Augusta Caroline Dillon, Lady Clonbrock (1840-1928).. Written on British Expeditionary Force paper, provided by the YMCA whose volunteers aimed to provide comfort to soldiers at the front, the letter describes a day in the life at war for Albert Crofton. He also thanks Lady Clonbrock for £80 which she had sent to him his wife to cover debts he had accrued on his ranch in Canada. Lady Clonbrock paid the debt and Crofton survived the war, remaining in Ganges until his death.Crofton had emigrated to Canada aged fifteen and was a rancher in Ganges, Saltspring Island, British Columbia. Lady Clonbrock was a prominent member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, founded to provide aid and assistance to Irish prisoners of war and the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock.In December 1915 Crofton had joined the Canadian Expeditionary Force and has been been sent to the Western Front</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54, Ms. 35,797 (1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/156</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0824">Alfred Gerald Crofton</persName>
              <date>1916-10-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1381">Ahascragh, County Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0156_img_1285_1"  type="Letter"  url="5366969dfaf299c29760fe8c81aaf3cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0156_img_1285_2"  type="Letter"  url="5c007e482d23363ffdc33d459862e57d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0156_img_1285_3"  type="Letter"  url="4ba02dbc305ba5913c84c21df85a6d64.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0156_img_1285_4"  type="Letter"  url="dfa507e7e12ed010898e9e34056fdf9a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0156_img_1285_5"  type="Letter"  url="0ecc964f40215c6788149817cba60c72.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0156_img_1285_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Y.M.C.A. On Active Service</hi><lb/>WITH THE BRITISH EXPEDITIONARY FORCE   Sunday. .Oct 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> /1916.   My Dearest Aunt Tweety.   I cannot thank you enough for the <lb/>Â£80 you have sent to Nona. It has indeed lifted <lb/>a great weight off my mind as I had been <sic>worring</sic><lb/>all along about it. And I shall see that it is returned <lb/>as soon as possible. This certainly is a strenuous <lb/>life because you never know what will happen <lb/>next. I will give you a brief outline of our <lb/>days work. Breakfast 7 fall in at 8.15 &amp; build <lb/>huts till 11 'oclock then at 11.30 lunch or breakfast <lb/>for those out at night. In afternoon 1 hrs work <lb/>for those going out &amp; then rest till evening the <lb/>other lot continue what work we were doing  vice versa per day. <lb/> 6 o'clock tea &amp; at 7.30 fall in. Rifles helmets, gas <seg type="unclear">H</seg><lb/>&amp; 50 rounds of <sic>amunition</sic> everything is overhauled <lb/>&amp; then we march to trenches in single file after  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0156_img_1285_2"/>
              passing rendezvous. <seg type="del">in</seg>In certain places machine <lb/>guns &amp; snipers get a pot at us, &amp; so we continue <lb/>till we get to our appointed place of work &amp; when <lb/>the word comes <seg type="del">,</seg> over we jump the parapet &amp; start <lb/>filling sacks. At every flare we have to remain in <lb/>what ever position we might be in &amp; believe me you <lb/>feel pretty big when you see the German trenches <lb/>only 100 yds away, sometimes more, sometimes less. <lb/>All the time machine guns are spraying lead <lb/>about &amp; we have to duck &amp; let it pass over when <lb/>the order is given. However German snipers often <lb/>get a bead on the party &amp; its ping, ping, ping <lb/>everywhere. However we plug along filling sacks <lb/>&amp; building up the parapet. Of course we strike <lb/>places where the dead has been buried a little <lb/>time before &amp; its anything pleasant working in <lb/>that vicinity. Also water &amp; rats are very plentiful <lb/>the latter sometimes as big as cats. Still the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0156_img_1285_3"/>
              boys are very cheery &amp; make jokes &amp; jeer at Fritz's <lb/>shooting although sometimes he gets a bit too <lb/>close to be pleasant. Still it does not always do <lb/>to show what you really feel. But <sic>beleive</sic> me <lb/><sic>their</sic>is not a man in the whole division who <lb/>does not wish it all over now but it must <sic>been</sic><lb/>seen through, <hi rend="underline">now or never</hi>. We carry on in <lb/>this fashion till 12.30 or 1 &amp; then march home <lb/>&amp; about 2.30 turn in after having a tot of <lb/>rum (very small indeed) tea &amp; bread &amp; jam, <lb/>&amp; sleep till 11.30 (if possible). You must always <lb/>remember you have rats &amp; the sounds of guns <lb/>etc <seg type="del">ring</seg>wringing wet clothes to contend with. <lb/>But still here we are all merry &amp; bright. The <lb/><sic>Officiers</sic> are fine &amp; do their very best to make <lb/>life as easy &amp; enjoyable as possible under the <lb/>circumstances. The Major who commands my Co. 'D.' <lb/>is from Salt Spring &amp; put me with him. Our <lb/>platoon <sic>Officier</sic> seems very decent indeed but I dont <lb/>know him very well as yet, but he seems to know <lb/>his work which is such a great point. I hope <lb/>soon to hear poor Edward is reinstated. I think <lb/>although I only heard a rumour from my mother <lb/>that he has been shamefully treated &amp; that the  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0156_img_1285_4"/>
              other chap will be before long <lb/>on the mat. Well heres more <lb/>power to his elbow. Will drop <lb/>you a line or card from time <lb/>to time to show <seg type="del">we</seg> I am still <lb/>going. Again thanking you <lb/>from the bottom of my <lb/>heart. <seg type="closer"> Always yr affec nephew  <hi rend="underline">Fred-</hi>  P.S. One of the letters <lb/>I sent to you has <lb/>just been returned <lb/>to me I wonder if <lb/>the other will ever <lb/>reach you or me. <lb/><seg type="unclear">RB</seg> </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0156_img_1285_5"/>
               back of envelope postmarked Ballinasloe  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>