<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5604">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Sweetman to Herbert Pim, 14 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Sweetnam</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from John Sweetman (1844-1936) to Herbert Moore Pim (1883-1950). Sweetman was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. In 1915 he spoke out against conscription and was arrested in the aftermath of the 1916 Rising. Pim was a political activist and writer. He had joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914, published a pamphlet series entitled &#39;Tracts of our times&#39;, including writing by Patrick Pearse, and in early 1916 founded the literary and political monthly, &#39;The Irishman&#39;.
Sweetman refers to Sinn Fein politics in the aftermath of the Easter Rising, inquiring as to whether the &#39;Sinn Fein Bank&#39; could get any help from the Irish National Aid fund and remarking that Sinn Fein could bring in a number of financial systems, including a bond, in the future, although the idea makes people laugh now. He also refers to the latest issue of  &#39;The Irishman&#39;, founded by Pim. He asks whether James Stephens (1800?-1950), who had published a famous account of the Rising, and Stephen McKenna may take an interest in becoming members of Sinn Fein.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Family Papers, Collection List No. 156; Ms. 47,589 /12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5604</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0960">John Sweetnam</persName>
              <date>1916-10-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1116">Drumbaragh, Kells, County Meath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1003">Herbert Pim</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1936</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5604_img_698_1"  type="Letter"  url="fef729bb5430f88eec84510840538a16.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5604_img_698_2"  type="Letter"  url="dc627a62706f366d8aea143784e88170.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5604_img_698_1"/>
             Drumbaragh,<lb/>Kells,<lb/>Co.Meath.   October 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    My dear Mr.Pim   Thanks for yours of the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; the<lb/>correspondence which I return. When I saw<lb/>Alderman  Thomas  Kelly I thought he was not inclined<lb/>to do anything, but he said he was to <seg type="del">have</seg> be at <lb/>a meeting that evening which would consider<lb/>the question.  I made no suggestion about the Sinn Féin<lb/>Bank, but I wonder whether they could get<lb/>any help from the Irish National Aid fund.<lb/>I did not like to say anything about the matter<lb/>as I always refused to have anything to<lb/>say to the loan bank.  I was pleased with this week's The Irishman<lb/>and when in Dublin bought several copies to<lb/>distribute. By the way I wonder whether<lb/>James Stephens would take an interest in<lb/>Sinn Féin. From reading his graphic account<lb/>of the Insurrection in Dublin published by Maunsel<lb/>I think he is inclined that way. Then there is<lb/>Stephen McKenna. I think you agree with me<lb/>a new Sinn Féin League should not attempt 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5604_img_698_2"/>
             too much at first. Too extended a<lb/>program would frighten off people.  I think there is no doubt that <seg type="del">people</seg> the public <lb/>are ready if any leaders show a sensible<lb/>plan, but it should not be too elaborate.<lb/>Consular Representatives, Arbitration Courts,<lb/>a National Stock Exchange, &amp; a National<lb/>Bank may be possible in the future, but<lb/>just at present they only make people laugh.  I think your <seg type="del">work</seg>  endeavour  should be to get people<lb/>together as was done by The Nation in the<lb/>Forties.  I think the program you gave in your<lb/>issue of Oct. 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> would be enough to start<lb/>with. I shall not be in Dublin for<lb/>some weeks.  Yours truly<lb/>John Sweetman 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>