<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1192">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Fitzgibbon to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, circa 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Fitzgibbon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Fitzgibbon (1845–1919) to Fr. Nolan regarding Jack Fitzgibbon&#39;s son, John Fitzgibbon. John Fitzgibbon was a successful draper and MP for South Mayo from 1910-1918. He was also involved in the Gaelic League, the temperance movement and the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction (DATI). Father Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/15, IJA/CHPI/21/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1192</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0632">John Fitzgibbon</persName>
              <date>1918</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1192_img_3874_1"  type="Letter"  url="3d56ef3d579ae14f299a9fda9e54dd26.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1192_img_3874_2"  type="Letter"  url="9650d3772e46a25a507744515aa365f1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1192_img_3874_1"/>
                Castlerea    My dear Father Nolan,   The <lb/>enclosed is that <lb/>letter to plead <lb/>in I am happy <lb/>Gods holy work is <lb/>done. He was <lb/>my joy and pride <lb/>and the thought <lb/>that when he <lb/>Cheerfully gone <lb/>to God he would <lb/>have made more <lb/>use of him on <lb/>this earth, Jack  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1192_img_3874_2"/>
              was always full <lb/>of energy and <lb/>I have not the <lb/>slightest doubt <lb/>he is now a <lb/>busier Man than <lb/>ever, we naturally <lb/>feel the parting <lb/>but are consoled <lb/>in the thought of <lb/>Larry Shaw an <lb/><seg type="unclear">advocate</seg> to secure <lb/>for us a speedy <lb/>passage to the <lb/>Heavenly kingdom. <lb/>He loved the order <lb/>and I hope I am <lb/>not being too presumptuous <lb/>in saying that <lb/>it's <seg type="unclear">members mourn</seg><lb/>his loss and I feel <lb/>deeply for them. <lb/>With grateful thanks <lb/>for your touching <lb/>letter <seg type="closer"> I <seg type="unclear">remain</seg><lb/>Yours Faithfully  John Fitzgibbon </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>