<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3627">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Gill to John Redmond, 11 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Patrick Gill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Gill (1858-1931) to John Redmond (1856-1918) requesting a special grant for food production supplies. 

In 1916 Thomas Patrick Gill was serving as the secretary for the Department of Agriculture. He also worked with the Department of Technical Instruction from its establishment in 1900 until 1923.

John Redmond (1856-1918) was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers, Collection List No. 118; MS 15,193/3/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3627</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1255">Thomas Patrick Gill</persName>
              <date>1916-04-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1931</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3627_img_3025_1"  type="Letter"  url="9f11ac6a9151bbe87c8035f1b4dfb83a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3627_img_3025_2"  type="Letter"  url="cc6f23d17464cdf6039f1518f73d339e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3627_img_3025_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="d4ddc0a35c3b75013c6bc61425ab2d05.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3627_img_3025_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE <lb/>AND TECHNICAL INSTRUCTION. <lb/>DUBLIN.    11th April, 1916.     My dear Redmond,   Special grant for food-production <lb/> <hi rend="underline">schemes, &amp;c.</hi>    I enclose you copy of a note I had to-day from <lb/> Runciman promising to support our application for this <lb/> in the Cabinet. (This time last year when I saw him, as <lb/> Chairman of the National Food-Supply Committee of the <lb/> Cabinet, he promised me to do the same, but the <lb/> application was then deferred). I sent you con- <lb/> fidentially particulars of the application and of the <lb/> case for it. I think you ought to see Montagu <hi rend="underline">and</hi> <lb/> McKenna (I do not expect much out of the former without <lb/> the backing of the latter) and let them know Runciman's <lb/> view. Runciman is the member of the Cabinet who knows <lb/> most about the food-supply problem. Birrell is probably <lb/> the man who should bring it forward in the Cabinet, and <lb/> I have written him and also Russell a line telling them <lb/> of Runciman's support; but it is most important to <lb/> emphasise that this application is, and should be pressed <lb/> as, an <hi rend="underline">Imperial</hi> question, not as an Irish question. Also, <lb/> in  J.E. Redmond, Esq., M.P. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3627_img_3025_2"/>
            in view of all the precariousness attending the food- <lb/>supply problem, it is a question of some urgency.   Yours ever,   <hi rend="underline">T.P. Gill</hi> l
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3627_img_3025_3"/>
            <hi rend="underline">COPY.</hi>  BOARD OF TRADE, <lb/>WHITEHALL GARDENS, S.W.   10th April, 1916.   Dear Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 5th April, <lb/>Mr.Runciman has asked me to say that he will support <lb/>your proposal for a special grant for your <lb/>Department to save your food production schemes from <lb/>the effects of the shrinkage of your funds due to the <lb/>War.   Yours very truly,   (sgd.) R.W.Matthews.   T. P. Gill, Esq. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>