<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4254">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 4 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/90</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4254</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4254_img_3620_1"  type="Letter"  url="b92eb9f6f3a9c676ac4d2c7157e3d5f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4254_img_3620_2"  type="Letter"  url="ea8c6fa333c0c0b16784f337b5dcf240.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4254_img_3620_1"/>
             <seg type="del">pr.</seg>   Dec 4   My P.R.   Rather a sleepy b w as I was up all night detraining part of <lb/> our old Art<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. First train due in at 10 pm did not arrive till <lb/> 11.15 Last train did not finish till 9.15<hi rend="superscript">AM</hi> Raining hard <lb/> &amp; mud ! ! So that the b w fully realises how perfectly heroic the <lb/> "short legged" p r was in not taking a series of taxies when she was <lb/> <seg type="del">return</seg> caught so badly ! I am none the worse &amp; had a good sleep <lb/> from 10-45 till 12.30 &amp; feel quite fresh especially as I had a very <lb/> nice bath which Douglas got me — such a dirty b w before, but <lb/> quite fit for the company of a " respectable" p r now. The p r must <lb/> keep respectable for the b w's sake &amp; she surely knows that he would <lb/> like her to take a taxi to avoid getting really tired.   Douglas has returned looking well, &amp; happier for his journey &amp; <lb/> quite appreciative of the welcome at home, but he tells me that <lb/> he had a very stormy passage &amp; I dread what the p r was like, but <lb/> so glad she chose Larne under the circumstances. What a welcome the <lb/> p r would have got could she have taken Douglas' place. Perhaps she <lb/> could have taken his part rather well &amp; it would even have been an <lb/> economy in bedding if not in other kit ! This sounds most improper<seg type="del">,</seg>. <lb/> But the p r has other work to do at home which Douglas could not <lb/> do, &amp; the b w is proud to think how well she is doing it. She is <lb/> also keeping Mater happy &amp; the b w cannot feel jealous of that. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4254_img_3620_2"/>
             My last night's vigil was really <lb/> very good for me but I was quite annoyed when I heard that the Gen' had <lb/> "detailed" a G officer for it. It is A work &amp; tho' I should be as glad as <lb/> <seg type="del">Russel</seg>Richardson to take a turn for them voluntarily I don't like being <lb/> ordered to do it when I know that it is merely due to the impression <lb/> which old heavyweather Singleton has given the Gen' that we in G <lb/> do little whilst he is overwhelmed. As I came back this morning <lb/> at 9-45 AM &amp; saw Singleton on his way to the office my tenper <lb/> fairly rose &amp; the wrong man got it !    Last night Capt Hope the Staff Capt slept in my vacant bed. <lb/> He was nearly off his head yesterday. He &amp; the new GOC RA have not hit <lb/> it off, &amp; the latter had got so much on his nerves that he had a complete <lb/> painful breakdown begging me to save him. I got <seg type="del">Col</seg>him quieted &amp; <lb/> into bed &amp; got <seg type="unclear">Greig</seg> to see him &amp; he is now on his way home, as <lb/> happy as possible. It was the right thing to <seg type="unclear">invalid</seg> him, but the differ- <lb/>ence it made when he heard he was not to go back was the greatest <lb/> I have ever seen in any one.   As regards <seg type="unclear">concertinas</seg> etc I suppose the 107 Bde in the trenches <lb/> should have first call, but it depends on the gifts already made.   If one comes to HQ I expect Douglas would like it ! but I cannot <lb/> ask for any favouritism. There is too much of that !   Please let me know did Sir E actually go to Miss A's wedding or <lb/> was it merely invited guests &amp; not  actual  guests. I want to prevent any misunderstand <lb/>ing of this. I still suspect that K is giving up his old job for some other, but <lb/> wonder what that will be.   One letter went to Belfast yesterday.   Best love — nearly— to Mater <lb/> Your b w    Wilfrid BSpender   <seg type="unclear">Cleaver</seg> was 1 of my <lb/> supply Committee &amp; also the Ulster Div <lb/> clothing man &amp; I know him very well 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>