<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2629">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 8 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother. Maria Duffin (1854-1954) concerning Celia&#39;s daily life in the London hospital. Celia discusses her difficulties with her shifts and new accommodation, meeting with her sister Dorothy and the changes to pay expected for VADs working in the London hospital.

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/C/17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2629</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0733">3rd London General Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2629_img_2054_1"  type="Letter"  url="46e5d19886614164ed4f1a8a9246edbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2629_img_2054_2"  type="Letter"  url="28cf6799243768406c4d2b84030904e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2629_img_2054_3"  type="Letter"  url="962c2468ae948bd36687ca604b41d852.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2629_img_2054_1"/>
             Best love <lb/>If I can't come to you <lb/>you will have to come <lb/>and visit me -  Ever yours   <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi>    3<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> London General <lb/>Hospital   Dec: 8<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> 15.   Dearest Mamma   Many thanks for the glass and <lb/>the lovely warm gloves, but I wish you <lb/>had kept them for yourself. I am <lb/>delighted with them and glad to <lb/>have a looking glass again as the <lb/>charwoman in my house broke the <lb/>remains of mine.   I have been put on night-duty <lb/>again, much to my sorrow. I don't <lb/>know why, as lots of the nurses haven't <lb/>been on night at all yet, and I <lb/>have had all the bother of moving <lb/>my billetts and changing into another <lb/>house at 25 Nicosia Rd, where the <lb/>nurses are doing night work too.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2629_img_2054_2"/>
            Also I have lost the little room I had to <lb/>myself and now have to share with <lb/>another girl. Fortunately she is a lady <lb/>and seems nice, her brother, Capt: Josse is <lb/>the registrar here and she is a cousin of <lb/>Edmund Josse's.   I was sorry to leave my old ward, especially <lb/>as I am in an <seg type="unclear">enteric</seg> ward now and <lb/>the surgical work is much nicer. I <lb/>suppose I shall be on night duty <lb/>for some little time and will spend <lb/>Xmas day in bed! My day sister <lb/>was very nice when I was learning her <lb/>ward and I think was really sorry <lb/>I was going.   I missed my day off in consequence, <lb/>which had just been arranged so nicely <lb/>so that I could spend the day with Dorothy. <lb/>However I saw her for about an hour before <lb/>I went to bed. She was looking very well, <lb/>but her arrangement with Leslie <lb/><seg type="unclear">Horsburgh</seg> sounds very odd, and I <lb/>don't think she can be desperately in love <lb/>with him.   M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi> Lecky wrote me such a kind letter <lb/>asking me to go to the theatre with her <lb/>and Peggy, but I can go no place now.   What is the matter with Edmund ? He <lb/>seems to have been seedy for such a <lb/>long while now.   I don't know any of the nurses in this <lb/>house which is a little further away <lb/>from the hospital, and I think a <lb/>nicer house, but I don't think very <lb/>interesting people live in it.   My new ward is upstairs in the main <lb/>building instead of in the huts so is <lb/>much warmer at night which is an <lb/>advantage.   It is sad about Mr. Finlay's death, Mrs <lb/>Finlay will feel very lonely now with <lb/>only Babs at home.   It isn't at all possible to take a month's
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2629_img_2054_3"/>
            holiday as you suggest, if you go you are <lb/>not taken on again, I suppose if it were allowed <lb/>everybody would be rushing off. We are <lb/>now told that after this we are to <lb/>get at least £2 monthly allowance as <lb/>well as our pay, that is the extra money <lb/>over from our board, keep, etc; This <lb/>will be very nice indeed as I did not <lb/>expect it; and the £20 would have <lb/>been rather hard to do with, paying <lb/>for one's washing and a good many odd <lb/>meals out of it. I wonder what Emma <lb/>is drawing at Alexandria in the way of <lb/>pay. My new coat and hat are <lb/>very comfortable and  it's  a relief not to have <lb/>to wear that awkward cloak any more.   Our men have all got egg cups, but I <lb/>don't think the war office allows for them, <lb/>I think friends and the ward sister provide <lb/>them. It's time to give one of the <lb/>patients his 3 hourly feed. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>