<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5257">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 29, June, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell expresses gratitude for parcels received. He mentions it would be best not to send expensive books as he cannot carry them and leaves them in Y. M. C. A.&#39;s or gives them to fellow soldiers. William reports that a Captain Rose, who is from Clare, had said that a dead cat was nailed to a chapel door there with a note which read, &#34;To hell with Bishops, Priests, and Clergy&#34;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5257</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-06-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5257_img_None_1"  url="7df1d16bd71cb9c714c21c45f1f11375.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5257_img_None_2"  url="2dc68782a983f87171b988200d2640a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5257_img_None_3"  url="099652523de42d0a532de8a7f0106cc1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5257_img_None_4"  url="ee836d586d50b9dcfe93ea28add5f060.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5257_img_0_1"/>
              29 June 1917    My dearest Mamy   A thousand thanks for that most<lb/>beautiful parcel which came in perfect<lb/>order yesterday afternoon. You are<lb/>really so awfully good and always<lb/>send just the right thing. The cake<lb/>is particularly delicious as we never<lb/>by any chance can get anything in that line at all. Also the salad<lb/>dressing. It is so good that I feel like eating it without the salad.  We get quite a lot of fresh<lb/>vegetables etc here and as many<lb/>strawberries as we can possibly<lb/>eat. They are beauties too.  This is a very nice town indeed<lb/>and all the people are very nice<lb/>They are always ready to do anything<lb/>they can for us.  We had a very heavy thunderstorm<lb/>yesterday and the heaviest rain    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5257_img_0_2"/>
             that I have seen for a very long<lb/>time. It ran down the street in a<lb/>regular river.  Please tell Daddy not to be in<lb/>any hurry about <seg type="del">the</seg> getting the<lb/>knife I mentioned. My other one<lb/>turned up and will do to carry on<lb/>with. Just whenever he happens to<lb/>be in Dublin he might get one.  The one I have is made of such<lb/>bad material that it is not much<lb/>use but will do <seg type="del">it</seg> to carry on<lb/>with.  I am saying very little <hi rend="underline">about</hi> this<lb/>billet of mine as it is streets<lb/>better than every one else. The C.O's<lb/>is rotten compared to it. It is<lb/>well he does not know that. However<lb/>he is not likely to find out as he<lb/>lives some distance away. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5257_img_0_3"/>
             The book <seg type="unclear">'Beauty'</seg> is splendid. I<lb/>am half way thro' as I read it<lb/>yesterday while the thunderstorm was<lb/>on. It will go the rounds when I<lb/>have finished it as they all do.  The only thing is it is too good to<lb/>send out here. Don't send expensive<lb/>ones as I can't cart them about with<lb/>me. I sometimes leave them in at<lb/>some Y.M.C.A. when I have read<lb/>them. I think that a good idea.  I was delighted to get Miss Cimm's<lb/>letter and will write to her soon. I<lb/>hope you have her still.  The full glove was most acceptable.<lb/>The extra polish this morning is quite<lb/>noticable I am sure.  My new servant is very good +<lb/>looks after me well.  What is Jack's address? I really<lb/>must write to him and while I am<lb/>here I will have time. also you<lb/>might send me Lewis' address. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5257_img_0_4"/>
             I do not think he can be near<lb/>here but of course I do not know.  I see there are nice rows in<lb/>Cork and Clare. I heard yesterday<lb/>from Capt. Rose who comes from<lb/>Clare that last Sunday they  posted <lb/>mailed a dead cat to the chapel door<lb/>and stuck up a notice on it To hell<lb/>with Bishops Priests + Clergy.  I saw accounts of riots lately in<lb/>the Times but I am sure they suppress<lb/>most of it. The convention will be very<lb/>funny if ever they meet. I am sure<lb/>all will go armed with rotten eggs<lb/>if not revolvers.  No news so will shut up   With best love to all from<lb/>Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  Won't write tommorrow Nothing to write about 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>