<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3690">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Colonel Sir William Hutchinson Poë to John Redmond, 22 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Hutchinson Poë </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Hutchinson Poë (1848-1934) to John Redmond (1856-1918) inquiring about the current state of affairs regarding the settlement of Home Rule and the progress of talks with Lloyd George. Poe questions the utility of southern and western Unionists in bringing about a rapprochement between Nationalists and Unionists and questions the future state of Ireland should the talks break down. Ultimately, Poe believes that Unionists are the key to reconciliation and requests that Redmond would back him in any attempts to facilitate reconciliation. 

Colonel Sir William Hutchinson Poë was a politician and solider. In 1915 to 1916 he served in Egypt in the First World War, and from 1916 to 1919 with the Red Cross in France. Following independence he served as a Senator of the Irish Free State.

John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers, Collection List No. 118; MS 197/5/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3690</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0855">William Hutchinson Poë </persName>
              <date>1916-06-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1529">Heywood, Ballinakill, Queens Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_1"  type="Letter"  url="cd845e64875355cd8b99decde894f4e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_2"  type="Letter"  url="a2d6bc21abda752fd7c86086a6ebfac6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_3"  type="Letter"  url="5dcad7dd0f179158121662759e65031a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_4"  type="Letter"  url="3bdcf8d3cd15e91e5d61a139d60c077c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_5"  type="Letter"  url="29f902167fbafd1c77e2a1e01b665859.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_6"  type="Letter"  url="f725ad5e96e900199eb8e94617efa7e5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_7"  type="Letter"  url="9e5132450be901d0c42a3dc14e3d91c1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_8"  type="Letter"  url="bb071875384f504fe056449e577c30e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3690_img_3082_9"  type="Letter"  url="fe04a701ada9eeff15649678131bcbb8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_1"/>
              Private<lb/>&amp; Confidential    TELEGRAMS,<lb/>BALLINAKILL.<lb/>STATION, ABBEYLEIX.    Heywood<lb/>Ballinakill,<lb/>Queens Co.    22nd June 1916   Dear Mr. Redmond, <lb/>I hope you will<lb/>forgive me for troubling<lb/>you with a letter at a time<lb/>when I feel sure your<lb/>mind and energies must<lb/>be fully occupied in<lb/>connection with a settlement<lb/>of the Home Rule Question<lb/>My execuse for doing so<lb/>is, that during the last<lb/>few days, judging by what 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_2"/>
             one reads in the papers-<lb/>there appears some danger<lb/>of the negotiations intiated<lb/>by <seg type="unclear">David</seg> lloyd George falling<lb/>through, in which case<lb/>I am anxious to know,<lb/>whether in your opinion<lb/>the intervention of an<lb/>influential body of Unionists<lb/>of the South and West of Ireland,<lb/>might not possibly avail<lb/>to bring about a repproache-<lb/>-ment between the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_3"/>
             nationalist Party and Ulster,<lb/>with a view to effecting<lb/>such a setllement as would<lb/>enable Ulster, from the<lb/>first, to throw in her lot<lb/>with the rest of the country.  Should unfortunately, W.<lb/>Llyod George's proposals -from<lb/>one cause or another-not<lb/>materialise, it seems to<lb/>me that we shall be face<lb/>to face with a situation<lb/>of the upmost gravity,<lb/>for while few may be<lb/>found to evince much<lb/>upset of the abandonmnet 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_4"/>
             of proposals, which in them-<lb/>-selves afford little satisfaction<lb/>to any party in Ireland, the<lb/>unfeasibility of reverting to<lb/>the status-quo-ante, and<lb/>the prospect of the sole<lb/>alternative, viz, a prolonged<lb/>regime of martial law,<lb/>cannot but fill the whole<lb/>country with dismay.  Whatever the necessity for a<lb/>settlement at this juncture<lb/>may be, that necessity will<lb/>be still more insistent in<lb/>the event of the present<lb/>negotiations failing, for<lb/>the forces of disloyalty and<lb/>rebellion,    
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_5"/>
             rebellion, are in such a case<lb/>bound to re-assert themselves<lb/>with increasing vigour, in<lb/>an endeavour to still further<lb/>alienate the good-will and<lb/>allegiance of the loyal<lb/>nationalists, and to embitter<lb/>our relations with the Empire.  In these circumstances, I<lb/>believe every Unionist,<lb/>who has the country's interest<lb/>at heart would be prepared<lb/>to subordinate his own<lb/>particular views, and 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_6"/>
             to exert all his influence<lb/>in support of a policy of<lb/>reconciliation and co.operation<lb/>between the two, hithero,<lb/>opposing political parties<lb/>for he would realise that<lb/>only by a combination of<lb/>the best elements in a<lb/>united Ireland can we<lb/>hope to combat the spirit<lb/>of disaffection, unrest,<lb/>and disloyalty which now<lb/>threatens to destroy our 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_7"/>
             Country, and to wreck<lb/>the aspirations of those<lb/>who, like yourself, have<lb/>so long laboured for the<lb/>Welfare of Ireland.  Should you, as I hope,<lb/>agree with me in thinking<lb/>that some good might<lb/>result from a movement<lb/>such as I suggest, it would<lb/>greatly facilitate my task<lb/>in approaching leading<lb/>Unionists, if you would 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_8"/>
             authorise me to say, that you<lb/>are not unfavourable to<lb/>such a proposition, for without<lb/>some such indication of your<lb/>views, many men might shrink<lb/>from coming forward, and<lb/>exposing themselves perhaps,<lb/>to rebuff.  I need scarcely<lb/>say, there is no idea of<lb/>making any communication<lb/>to the press asregards this<lb/>matter, and the negotiations<lb/>between myself and unionists<lb/>would be of an entirely con-<lb/>fidential nature; no action<lb/>would of course, be taken<lb/>without your consent,<lb/>  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_3690_img_3082_9"/>
             for, unless I was in a<lb/>position to show you that<lb/>we had an influential and<lb/>representative body of<lb/>unionist opinion in<lb/>support of my proposals.   Believe me,<lb/>Dear Mr. Redmond,<lb/>Yours very sincerly<lb/>Hutchinson Poe.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>