<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0585">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J. E. Devlin to Robert Chalmers, 10 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J. E. Devlin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from J. E. Devlin, Assistant Secretary, Local Government Board, to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) returning the audited accounts fro the Prosecutor and Witness Expenses submitted by Waterford County Council. A handwritten note added by the C.S.O. gives instructions for payment.J. E. Devlin was an Assistant Secretary for the Local Government Board. Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13777</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/585</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0820">J. E. Devlin</persName>
              <date>1916-08-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0585_img_1988_1"  type="Letter"  url="2eebea7f67d530c57416ee67bdbd5415.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0585_img_1988_1"/>
             <seg type="head">CERTIFIED PROSECUTORS' AND WITNESSES' EXPENSES.</seg>   LOCAL GOVERNMENT BOARD  DUBLIN,    10 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> August, 1916.    Sir,   I am directed by the Local Government Board for Ireland to send <lb/> back herewith, duly certified by the Auditor, Mr. DB Sheehan <lb/> the return of the Expenses of Prosecutors and Witnesses n the County Borough <lb/> of Waterford for the <seg type="del">half</seg> year ended the 31 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi><lb/> of March, 1916.   The documents which accompanied the Return are also enclosed. <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,  <lb/> J.E. Devlin <lb/> Assistant Secretary.   To  The Under Secretary,  &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.,  Dublin Castle.  </seg> I Order Payment <lb/> II Send N.R. to <seg type="unclear">Bons</seg> Treasurer <lb/> III <seg type="unclear">Afc.</seg> for V. Box <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>