<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4498">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 27 March 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis M. Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw to Father Provincial regarding economic issues.

Francis M. Shaw worked in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. He was ordained on 31st July 1916 at Milltown Park in Dublin and in 1917 was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia, possibly due to his nationalistic views.

Fr. Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives </repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4498</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1425">Francis M. Shaw</persName>
              <date>1918-03-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2129">Mesopotamia </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr. Thomas V. Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4498_img_3842_1"  type="Letter"  url="85fd562418d4ba442e4b9966184852d1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4498_img_3842_1"/>
             27 March 1918.   16 Casualty Clearing Sta. <lb/>Mesop. Exped. Force.   Dear F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Provincial, <lb/> P.C.   Your Reverence's last letter came, with Ords, and <lb/>a notice <sic>ofthe</sic> death <sic>of<seg type="unclear">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></seg></sic> Carbery, just after I had posted <lb/>my last mail. The province seems <sic>tobe</sic> losing a <lb/>large number lately. Thanks very much for <lb/>the help you sent <sic>tomy</sic> sister's. I wrote to my eldest <lb/>brother Jack (he is in the National Bank, Ennistymon) to <lb/>tell him that they were not well off enough <sic>tobe</sic> able <lb/>to "carry on" with much comfort during these hard <lb/>times. I hope our chaplains in France will <lb/>be safe during this tremendous push that has just <lb/>started. The Lord will have to take special care of <lb/>some <sic>ofthem</sic> if they are <sic>tocome</sic> out fit.   Sometimes out here I have to do battle ( I, a Jesuit) <lb/>in defence <sic>ofthe</sic> principle that wrong must not be done <lb/>the good may come <sic>ofit</sic>. It is wonderful what lose <lb/>thinking there is, and loser grasp of even fundamental <lb/>morality among some <sic>ofthe</sic> officers. I think the lose <lb/>thinking is almost universal. They <sic>cant</sic> see that if <lb/>German air-raids are wrong, the English retaliation <lb/>in kind is wrong also. Among the offenders, are <lb/>some four step-brothers <sic>ofthe</sic> Establishment.   I am baptizing a Hindu on Easter Sunday, and there are <lb/>two or three more on the road.   Your Reverence's sincerely in Christ,   Francis M. Shaw S.J. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>