<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0632">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Helen Duffin to Celia Duffin, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Helen Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this four page letter, Helen Duffin is writing to her sister Celia who is ill and who cannot be with the family for Christmas. Helen tells Celia about an &#39;odd&#39; incident she had with an unexpected visitor to her office: a little man with a &#39;pale face&#39; and a &#39;fuz of red hair&#39; who is looking for some contributions to a poetry book for which Lavery (possibly John Lavery, the painter) is also providing a drawing. The man has requested that Celia provide a poem for the volume and their sister Ruth is also sending him one. At the end of the letter Helen encloses a humorous sketch.Helen (b.1891) and Celia Duffin (b. 1888) are two of the Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. At the age of sixteen, all seven Duffin girls attended Cheltenham Ladies College in Gloucestershire, England. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#39;Escape Poem&#39; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell &amp;amp; Co. Ltd in 1913.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/C, Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/C</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/632</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0952">Helen Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0632_img_2077_1"  type="Letter"  url="6a890762f0bb21d93c50cba2cfb5179f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0632_img_2077_2"  type="Letter"  url="0133bfbdd7106fdef01fe80443bc5434.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0632_img_2077_3"  type="Letter"  url="2e81cb018283c41d418b31fe5bb59e1a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0632_img_2077_4"  type="Letter"  url="3b1695f4a0bd9bbfb2d07dafcd439eb7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0632_img_2077_1"/>
                DUNOWEN,  BELFAST.    22.12.15.   My dear Celia,   It is folly to wish you<lb/> a Merry Christmas if you are<lb/> going to spend it in bed,<lb/> but I don't want only to<lb/> wish you a 'comfortable' <lb/>Christmas! I wish you could <lb/>walk home for a few days.  This morning in the office<lb/> I was so amused — the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0632_img_2077_2"/>
              office boy walked in and<lb/> asked if I would see Mr.<lb/>Gregory, the architect. I could <lb/>not think who he was at <lb/>first, but said I would see<lb/> him &amp; then the oddest<lb/> little man walked in<lb/> &amp; introduced himself as<lb/> 'Padraig Gregory' from the <lb/>office opposite! He has<lb/> a little pale face &amp;<cb/> has a fuz of red hair — do<lb/> you know his look? He <lb/>asked if I were Ruth or<lb/> Edith &amp; I denied being<lb/> either &amp; then he went on<lb/> to explain that he was<lb/> editing a volume of poetry<lb/> for the <seg type="del">St</seg> Hospital (St. <lb/>Dunstans) for blind soldiers<lb/> &amp; wanted you to contribute.<lb/> All the <hi rend="underline">best</hi> Ulster people<lb/> are to be represented &amp; <lb/> and Lavery is doing a drawing.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0632_img_2077_3"/>
              Ruth says she will send <lb/>him 'something'. I had not<lb/> time to read 'The <seg type="unclear">dog</seg> Collection', but it looked<lb/> very fine. You are getting<lb/> quite famous. We feel <lb/>quite a crowd now &amp; Ruth<lb/> comes to-morrow. Poor D is<lb/> very depressed. I am so<lb/> glad you have got a nice<lb/> girl in your room. We <lb/>had a letter from Harry<lb/> to-day (enclosed) — please return<lb/> to us. <seg type="closer"> Good Luck old thing,<lb/> Yrs, <lb/> Helen </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0632_img_2077_4"/>
              D2109/9/4/C  You haven't got a man!<lb/> Hand drawing of a lady wearing a hat sitting on a tilted back chair with her feet on desk with a speech bubble coming out of her mouth and sheets of paper thrown on the floor Miss Perry giving me dictation in<lb/> the office. Desperate - at the rate of<lb/> an hour. <seg type="closer"> Ever yours, <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Helen</hi> .</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>