<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1786">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Bertram Windle to Augustine Birrell, 30 March 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Bertram Coghill Alan Windle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Sir Bertram Coghill Alan Windle (1858–1929) to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933).
Windle was a scholar and university president in Cork. . He  came up against Sinn Féin resistance on numerous occasions as he was accused of  trying to consolidate pro-British, pro-unionist control of University College Cork. Alfred O&#39;Rahilly (1884–1969) was one of the men involved in mobilizing anti-Windle opinion for personal and political reasons.
Birrell was the chief secretary for Ireland. He was appointed chief secretary in January 1907. In 1916 Birrell resigned as he willingly accepted the political responsibility for the outbreak of the Rising in 1916.
The letter contains Windle&#39;s endorsement of John Robert O&#39;Connell for the position of chief crown solicitor, stating that he is a good lawyer and the hardest worker.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1786</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1132">Bertram Coghill Alan Windle</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0872">Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1929</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1786_img_1241_1"  type="Letter"  url="95051b512e0b06c6f5ed60c6b88b0cd1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1786_img_1241_2"  type="Letter"  url="2a0923363c1cde20d3f00b1933e72757.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1786_img_1241_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>  LISTARKIN,<lb/>UNION HALL,<lb/>Co. Cork. <lb/><lb/> March 30. 1916.    Dear Mr Birrell,   I have fled to my cottage here,<lb/>my place refuge &amp; a little one from the<lb/>ravages of influenza which has just had<lb/>my wife &amp; myself in its clutches. It is<lb/>lovely spring, like weather in this para.<lb/>dise &amp; one reads with astonishment of<lb/>the blizzards in England. But even<lb/>here the rumours of the world pene-<lb/>trate &amp; hear that my friend &amp; bene-<lb/>factor Sir J.R. O'Connell is a candi-<lb/>date for the position of Chief Crown<lb/>Solicitor. You will let me, I hope, take<lb/>the liberty of urging his claims seeing<lb/>how much I have seen of him on all<lb/>sides &amp; especially perhaps the legal. He 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1786_img_1241_2"/>
             is the hardest worker &amp; the most dogged<lb/>devil I ever met &amp; nothing can turn him<lb/>from his end nor is the money coined I<lb/>am sure which could buy him. I was<lb/>with him in the troublesome legal compli—<lb/>cations over the purchase of the Hostel, nor<lb/>(thanks to him) a triumphant success &amp; no—<lb/>thing but his skill &amp; determination<lb/>could have pulled the thing through as<lb/>it was pulled. I need as well repeat<lb/>that he has done more than any man<lb/>to push on the Cork College &amp; has got for it<lb/>somewhere between £50000 &amp;£60000 tho'<lb/>I think that will appeal to you but I<lb/>urge his claims on the lines they <seg type="unclear">should</seg><lb/>   <seg type="unclear"></seg>these of being a good<lb/>lawyer &amp; an absolutely honest &amp; fear.<lb/>less man. Don't reply &amp; don't forward    Yours sincerely   Bertram Windle     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>