<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2245">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to John Edward Fowler Sclater, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924). Montgomery was a lawyer and politician. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter is addressed to John Edward Fowler Sclater (1862-1918), a land agent in County Down. 
The letter concerns a letter, previously written by Montgomery, that Montgomery&#39;s associates have urged him to send into the &#39;Times&#39;. Montgomery has decided to keep the letter private but advises anyone likely to be involved in the &#39;Lloyd George conversations&#39; (talks to reach a settlement on the Irish question) to read it. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2245</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Edward Fowler Sclater</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2245_img_1689_1"  type="Letter"  url="937412ba38454d9b8164f32f50b354f4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2245_img_1689_1"/>
            <lb/>Copy  3rd June,1916.   My dear Sclater ,  I wrote the enclosed letter about ten days ago <lb/>more to blow off steam than anything else. One or two <lb/> leading Unionists in Dublin were very anxious I should get <lb/> it into the "Times". I came to the conclusion, however, <lb/> that as the game now stands it would not be good tactics <lb/>to publish it. I was, however, strongly advised to press <lb/> the contents upon anyone likely to be engaged in the Lloyd <lb/> George conversations. I have sent, copies to Carson and <lb/> Long and one or two to Bates. The letter may perhaps <lb/>serve as a starting point for any discussions we may have <lb/> on Tuesday.   Yours very truly 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>