<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0479">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from D. Mullally to the Under-Secretary, 21 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Denis Mullally</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Denis Mullally, Clerk of Bray Urban District Council to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), Under-Secretary for Ireland, asking for the consent of Lord Wimborne (1873-1938), the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, to the payment of a pension to Thomas D. Scraggs (b. 1859), the former Harbour Master for Bray, who had to retire on health grounds. The grant has already been sanctioned by the Bray Urban District Council and Mullally commends the Scragg&#39;s excellent service record. A copy of the Scraggs&#39; letter of resignation is enclosed.Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne, was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/12534/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/479</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0432">Denis Mullally</persName>
              <date>1916-07-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0327">Bray Urban District Council, Town Hall, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0479_img_1838_1"  type="Letter"  url="94b132ef53b320f420beb888b682c666.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0479_img_1838_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="7dc81de6d67f9aa9c7a0866d00021e25.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0479_img_1838_1"/>
                Bray Urban District Council  Town Hall,  BRAY    21st July1916   Sir,   In accordance with the provision of the Local <lb/> Officers Superannuation (Ireland) Act 1869, I am <lb/> directed by bray Urban District Council to ask the <lb/> consent of the Lord Lieutenant to the grant of a <lb/> pension of 13s 4d per week to Mr Thomas Scraggs, late <lb/> Harbour Master for Bray,   Inquire the <lb/> date of birth of Mr <lb/> Scraggs   The grant was sanctioned at two <sic>meetingsof</sic> the <lb/> council, held on the 6th June 1916 and 18th July 1916. <lb/> respectively,   Mr Scraggs was appointed Harbour Master on the <lb/> 22nd March 1897 and since that time carried out his <lb/> duties in a thoroughly efficient manner, and was in <lb/> every way a loyal servant of the Council. <lb/> His salary on retirement was £2 per week and the <lb/> grant made by Council is, therefore, <hi rend="underline">one-third</hi> of <lb/> that amount.   Mr Scraggs was obliged to retire from Council's <lb/> employment owing to failing health a copy of letter <lb/> resigning his position is sent herewith.   I am to say that the Council would greatly appreciate <lb/> the favour of an early reply.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Sir, <lb/> Your obedient servant   D Mullally  Clerk to the Council <lb/>  The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle,  Dublin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0479_img_1838_2"/>
                Bray Urban District Council  Town Hall.  Bray    21st July 1916   Gentlemen    Owing to failing health I respectfully beg <lb/> to tender my resignation as Harbour Master to your <lb/> Board    I have been engaged at the harbour for twenty <lb/> five years. five years during its construction, and <lb/> upwards of twenty years as Harbour Master <lb/> that with a previous 25 years of a very strenuous <lb/> life I am not able to give the same attention as I <lb/> have hitherto given. I have never spared <lb/> myself, night or day, to make it as successful as I <lb/> could.    I am glad to be able to say that the income <lb/> from the harbour has increased yearly. the first <lb/> year the total income was only £260. Last year <lb/> it reached £968 .2 .9    Trusting you will consider favourably <lb/> my past services.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Gentlemen <lb/> Your obedient servant   ( sd )  T. D. Scraggs.  Harbour Master. <lb/> To the Chairman and Members <lb/> Bray Urban District Council </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>