<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3685">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur Ferrall to The Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 7 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Thomas Ferrall</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Arthur Thomas Ferrall on behalf of  the Pharmaceutical Society of Ireland to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) regarding the terms of sale of carbolic preparations in Ireland.  </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T56-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3685</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0633">Arthur Thomas Ferrall</persName>
              <date>1916-02-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1566">67 Lower Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3685_img_3078_1"  type="Letter"  url="bb34eee28e98caeebddd62c41b161032.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3685_img_3078_2"  type="Letter"  url="4e2eb4b477c235264cecd463ee042edb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3685_img_3078_1"/>
             The Pharmaceutical Society of Ireland, <lb/>67,Lower Mount Street   Dublin 3rd February, 1916.   Dear Sir,   I learn, through your courtesy, that you have received <lb/>a communication from the Under Secretary, Dublin Castle, on <lb/>the subject of the sale of carbolic preparation for agri- <lb/>cultural and horticultural purposes, and that same will be <lb/>considered by your Council tomorrow. I have also received <lb/>a letter from the Under Secretary on the same subject, which <lb/>will be considered by my Council on the 8th instant.   Last August a letter was received from the Under Secre- <lb/>tary, enclosing copy of one from Messrs. Wm Cooper &amp; Nephews <lb/>urging the Government to take steps to nullify any action my <lb/>Council might feel bound to take against unregistered sellers <lb/>of their preparations. The letter now received, enclosing <lb/>copy of one from the Department of Agriculture and Technical <lb/>Instruction for Ireland, states that His Excellency is advis- <lb/>ed that the object desired by Messrs. Cooper and Nephews may <lb/>be attained by making an Order in Council under Section 2 (1) <lb/>of the Poisons and Pharmacy Act, 1908.   I beg to submit the following observations for the kind <lb/>consideration of your Council:-    (a) The agitation has been started by Messrs. Cooper, a <lb/>powerful English firm of manufacturers, who have probably <lb/>found that the technical knowledge of the Chemists enable the <lb/>latter to prepare and supply to their customers a similar <lb/>article on better terms.   To/ <lb/>The Registrar of <lb/>The Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, <lb/>Kildare Street, <lb/>Dublin.   Macd.C. <lb/>4.II.16 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3685_img_3078_2"/>
             (b) Messrs. Cooper naturally would like to secure as <lb/>large an output as possible for their preparations; no doubt <lb/>preferably amongst those lacking the technical skill to com- <lb/>pete with them.   (c) From the evidence which has come before my Council, <lb/>it is clear that most of the County Councils have used no <lb/>discrimination in the issue of Licenses.   (d) Several instances of gross carelessness in the hand- <lb/>ling by Licensees of poisonous preparations - such as storing <lb/>them in close proximity to foodstuffs - have occurred, and <lb/>prosecutions in consequence have been instituted by my Coun- <lb/>cil. To increase the number of poisonous preparations which <lb/>may be sold by such persons would accentuate the already ser- <lb/>ious danger to the public.   (e) Owing to the number of Chemists' shops throughout <lb/>the country, there would be little or no public inconvenience <lb/>by confining the sale of such preparations to those who, by <lb/>training and examination, are most competent to deal with <lb/>them.   Hoping that the foregoing observations may commend them- <lb/>selves to your Council, and receive their kind support,   I am, dear Sir, <lb/>Yours faithfully,   Arthur J. Ferrall  <lb/>Registrar.  MacdC <lb/>4.II.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>