<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5550">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 19 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancee Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June and the letters were written between them during that period. He lived in Dublin, she lived in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. He tells how he &#34;had his eye on her&#34; for a long time but waited until she was old enough. Throughout the series of letters you can see how their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters and how her confidence grows.
The series is not complete; it is interrupted by visits to each other’s homes and by obviously missing letters. They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child, my father. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him: this explains their survival. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats, so that she ended up quite comfortable off!
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him, trying to demand he be carried in to meetings. 
Neither May nor James were politically active though, like many in the Civil Service, James was obviously somewhat activated, learning Irish, probably Gaelic League, and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in it. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
The letter refers to spring weather, Tim and their latest plan to see each other.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5550</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-02-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0273">Togherstown, Co Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5550_img_646_1"  type="Letter"  url="cdecc921839b5a7702e261be645bbd34.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5550_img_646_2"  type="Letter"  url="535edc9ff1c326ae8a63be112fe18db2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5550_img_646_3"  type="Letter"  url="58d37aacc59da3feb372fabc6ef78d68.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5550_img_646_4"  type="Envelope"  url="4bc3778779cd5fc0e3e0b8b2efb571d5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5550_img_646_1"/>
            <!-- Writing on the side of the page --> got acquainted with Christy going along on the train to<lb/>Clara, T would have gone further only the big man was<lb/>charmed with the child. I<lb/>am sure Tim did not half<lb/>like being called a child.<lb/>I have no other news so I will<lb/>say good bye with my very<lb/>best love. It won’t be long now<lb/>until you are down. I hope<lb/>this weather will continue,<lb/>I feel this day doing me good.  Warmest love to dear<lb/>James from his loving<lb/>big   <hi rend="underline">May</hi>    Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea     Feb 19 1916    My dearest James,   I was very glad<lb/>to get your letter this morning<lb/>early in comparison with<lb/>other mornings as Mother,<lb/>Daddy &amp; Nano &amp; Mrs Seery<lb/>were at mass. don’t think 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5550_img_646_2"/>
             by that I am losing my bit<lb/>of religion for I had to stay<lb/>at home to mind my brother<lb/>that’s the way I’ll be staying at<lb/>home to mind somebody<lb/>else very soon. Who is that<lb/>unfortunate somebody? While<lb/>I talk of religion Nora was<lb/>inquiring to Mrs S. about<lb/>a prayer book she lost perhaps<lb/>you would have it in the pocket<lb/>of your over coat I might have<lb/>had it the first Sunday I was<lb/>up It was your Mother’s I had  <lb/>the last Sunday I hope she will get<lb/>it, rather soon to blacken my<lb/>character you know.  This is a glorious day real spring<lb/>not one about the place all gone<lb/>to a ploughing match Joe Finn<lb/>is taking part he was all excited<lb/>had his boots polished, nothing else<lb/>he expects to win but if he doesn’t<lb/>he has lost his days hire &amp; 2/6 fee<lb/>that will be awful I hope he’ll get<lb/>something anyway. Christy is<lb/>selling cattle to day, he is gone<lb/>off to see Seery’s sold so we don’t<lb/>know what has he got or did he<lb/>sell at all.    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5550_img_646_3"/>
             I might be in Mullingar next<lb/>Sat. I could wait for your train<lb/>that will be grand I never told<lb/>Mrs Seery when you intended<lb/>coming but I will tonight if<lb/>she comes up. She (Mrs S) had<lb/>the Misses Kelly down on Wed.<lb/>Pauline Aggie &amp; Rose, the latter<lb/>is going to some job in England<lb/>crying how Jim listed etc. he<lb/>sold all her rings while he was<lb/>with her even the wedding of course<lb/>they don’t intend going near<lb/>the bride Mrs Kiernan says she<lb/>won’t either. This Kerry jobber only <!-- continued on Page 1--> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5550_img_646_4"/>
             JE Finn Esq <lb/>39 Belgrave Sq <lb/>Rathmines <lb/>Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>