<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4044">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hanoria Shanahan to the Lord Lieutenant, Lord Wimborne, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hanoria Shanahan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A handwritten petition from Nora (Hanoria) Shanahan for an extension to a lease to continue a licensed premises in Portmagee, Co. Kerry for a further number of months beyond April 1916.

This petition is a follow up to an initial request in January (NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-646) that was granted.  NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-14211 and 1644 also refer.

Lord Wimborne (1873 –1939) was Lord Lieutenant, a largely ceremonial role, from 1915 until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers 1916, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-5526a</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4044</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1261">Hanoria Shanahan</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1344">Portmagee, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4044_img_3426_1"  type="Letter"  url="ff2082969c9d009243f414111c6d29e2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4044_img_3426_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Memorial.</hi>  To His Excellency <lb/>Lord Wimborne <lb/>Lord Lieutenant <lb/>of Ireland.   Your Excellency:   I thank you from my <lb/>heart for the concession favour of carrying on a public <lb/>business <sic>till</sic> the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April, pending the refurbishment of my house.   I pray your clemency an extension until August or <lb/>the middle of September next for the following reasons.   1. Owing to the winter being on, funds not available <lb/>and materials unnecessarily high the building <lb/>could not be proceeded with.   2 Tradesmen being scarce in this locality, could <lb/>not afford to bring them from the city, therefore was <lb/>compelled up to the present time to wait on local tradesmen.    3 Owing to my back premises or stores being destroyed <lb/>by fire I have nowhere to retain my little stock, <lb/>therefore crave permission to retain it in the occupied <lb/>house, and to proceed with my business therein until <lb/>my house which is to be commenced immediately, <lb/>is rebuilt.    I ask the Almighty to grant you your favours, <lb/>to assist you in your need, and to grant you long <lb/>life and happiness in our midst is the humble prayer <lb/>of a helpless widow and her orphan children.   Nora Shanahan 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>