<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0628">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from R. Hickey to James Ryan, 26 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>R. Hickey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from R. Hickey to James Ryan (1891-1970) during Ryan&#39;s imprisonment in England. Hickey expresses his surprise not only at Ryan&#39;s arrest but his deportation. Hickey assumes a mistake has been made and that Ryan was simply treating the wounded: he says he thinks Ryan&#39;s politics &#39;have been &amp;amp; are — none&#39;. Hickey passes on news of Ryan&#39;s family and acquaintances, and asks if he is allowed to send cigarettes or tobacco to Ryan in prison.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch, and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>James Ryan Papers, P88 16 001</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/628</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0816">R. Hickey</persName>
              <date>1916-05-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1768">Coombe Hospital, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0628_img_207_1"  type="Letter"  url="b35ada46eb8b7af0b13b2ad0a7f8ac2b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0628_img_207_2"  type="Letter"  url="f4ac482c7e156c738dd17cfee9d2ebff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0628_img_207_3"  type="Letter"  url="4bf7004efbef063336fe84a8a553015f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0628_img_207_4"  type="Letter"  url="403a46101aeab5e8310aea7a8edcbc85.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0628_img_207_1"/>
                Coombe Hospital  Dublin    26<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> May '16   My dear James,   I cannot say how<lb/> very much surprised I was when<lb/> I came back after the vac. to find<lb/> that you were not only arrested <seg type="del">by</seg><lb/> but deported for I ought to know<lb/> you as well as anyâone &amp; I always<lb/> thought nay I am sure that your<lb/> politics have been &amp; are â none.<lb/> Did you start dressing the wounded<lb/> or what? that you <seg type="del">should</seg> were arrested  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0628_img_207_2"/>
              If you can read up your surgery<lb/> &amp; medicine there, you will be alâ<lb/> right because it should be a topping<lb/> place to work but all the same I <lb/> am sure you must think bad of it<lb/> under the circumstances for I am<lb/> quite confident that there has been<lb/> a terrific blunder someâwhere.<lb/> I am in the Coombe now since<lb/> last Monday &amp; have done three<lb/> cases. I like it fairly well but<lb/> would like it better if you were<lb/> there to come with me on first few<lb/> cases for I am not too sure yet &amp;<lb/> just a little bit nervous.  I   over at 19 after all<lb/> are in fairly good form â <seg type="unclear">Min I</seg>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0628_img_207_3"/>
              think has gone down to country toâ<lb/> day. I saw Mick the day I was<lb/> coming back &amp; he was telling me<lb/><seg type="del">that</seg> the boss, your mother &amp; all at<lb/> home are quite well.  I am taking advantage of you, whilst<lb/> you are away &amp; am using all the<lb/> instruments I can find belonging to<lb/> you about house, including the little<lb/> bag. I also have your midwifery<lb/> but have never looked at it yet.<lb/> I you want it anytime let me know<lb/> &amp; I shall send it on  I saw your razor today &amp; it reminded<lb/> me that you may be bad off for a<lb/> good shave so I am taking it to get<lb/> new blades &amp; you can write me as<lb/> soon as you can to say whether it would<lb/> be likely to go astray or if you will be  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0628_img_207_4"/>
              sure to get it because it would be<lb/> a little too valuable to lose. Also<lb/> say whether I can send you cigarettes<lb/> tobacco or anyâthing. <seg type="del">I shall</seg>Write<lb/> soon while I have a little money &amp;<lb/> I shall be only too pleased to send on<lb/> anything you may require.  Leo Doyle, McNamara, John Healy<lb/> are also in Coombe now, the<lb/> former is often asking about you.  There is nothing else I am sure you<lb/> haven't heard of for I am sure<lb/> you are well versed in the City's<lb/> doings from lady friends  Sincerely hoping that you will soon<lb/> back here to medicine again &amp;<lb/> hoping that you are keeping quite<lb/> fit. <seg type="closer"> Yrs V. Sincerely  R. Hickey. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>