<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0530">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to Bridget McLoughlin, 15 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Suffield Mylius</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941) to Bridget McLoughlin and concerns the death of her son Detective Sergeant Matthew McLoughlin (1879 -1916). This series of correspondence refers to the granting of relief to Mrs McLoughlin as a result of her son&#39;s death and her dependence upon him. The first of these letters, sent by Magill, states that the chief secretary, Henry Edward Duke (1855-1939), hopes to be able to render Mrs McLoughlin some assistance. This letter also raises the concerns of the chief commissioner of the Dublin Metropolitan Police Force, Walter Edgeworth Johnstone (1863 – 1937), regarding Mrs McLoughlin’s situation. The letter explains how the entirety of Sergeant McLoughlin’s allowance under the Police Act has been given to his widow and child with no provision for his mother whom he also supported. In the letter he notes that Mrs McLoughlin received the sum of £5 from a Metropolitan Police Private Fund but that the resources of this fund are limited and therefore further assistance from elsewhere is required.The enclosed letter was sent by the secretary of the Prince of Wales’ National Relief Fund, . This fund was established with Edward, Prince of Wales, as treasurer, to help the families of serving men and those suffering from &#39;industrial distress” during the First World War. Andrew Philip Magill was the private secretary to the chief secretary of Ireland. Magill was a civil servant and held the position of private secretary for successive chief secretaries of Ireland until his transfer to the Northern Irish Civil Service in 1921.Matthew McLoughlin was one of the thirteen members of Lord Kitchener&#39;s (1850-1916) staff who died in the sinking of the HMS Hampshire on the 5 June 1916 just west of the Orkney Islands in Scotland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13426</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/530</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0510">Suffield Mylius</persName>
              <date>1916-08-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1483">Irish Office, Old Queen St., London SW, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Bridget McLoughlin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1728">Foilnadrough, Kilcommon, Thurles, Tipperary, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0530_img_1908_1"  type="Letter"  url="8a3dcef4a2fb2c89babe467fb87893d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0530_img_1908_2"  type="Letter"  url="01dbbcdca5c6a0fe8af4acfcbbd75263.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0530_img_1908_3"  type="Letter"  url="2f145d7255195e6a78806bb0d257282f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0530_img_1908_1"/>
              Copy    15th August, 1916.   Dear Madam,   With reference to your letter addressed to the <lb/> 'Officer in Charge, War Allowance Department, London,' <lb/> relative to the death of your son, Detective Sergeant <lb/> Matthew McLoughlin, I am desired by the Chief Secretary <lb/> to inform you that he has made enquiries into the <lb/> matter, and he understands that the Commissioner of the <lb/> Metropolitan Police has had your case under consideration, <lb/> and the Chief Secretary hopes that it may be possible <lb/> to render you some assistance in view of the particular <lb/> circumstances of your son's death.  The letters received fro you which were sent to <lb/> you by your son are returned herewith. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  (Sd) APM   Mrs. M. McLoughlin,  Foilnadrough,  Kilcommon,  Thurles.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0530_img_1908_2"/>
              <hi rend="underline">COPY</hi>  G.R.116843/4.    4th August, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Commissioner of Police of the <lb/> Metropolis to bring to your notice the case of Mrs. Bridget <lb/> MCLoughlin of Foilnadrough, Kilcommon, Thurles, Ireland, the <lb/> mother of the late Detective Sergeant Matthew McLOUGHLIN <lb/> who lost his life whilst en route to Russia on board H.M.S. <lb/> Hampshire when on protection duty with the late Lord Kitchener, <lb/>Secretary of State for War.  Sergeant McLoughlin's widow and child are receiving the <lb/> maximum allowance that can be given under the Police Act. <lb/> This Act, however, makes no provision for dependants other <lb/> than the widow and children, and consequently no assistance <lb/> from this source is available for Sergeant McLoughlin's <lb/> mother, who up to the time of her son's death had been in a <lb/> great measure dutifully <sic>suported</sic> by him, being in very poor <lb/> circumstances.  Copies of her letters to this office, together with one <lb/> from the Parish Priest at Kilcommon, are enclosed herewith <lb/> for your perusal. From these it will be seen that a grant of <lb/> Â£5 for immediate necessities has been made to Mrs McLoughlin <lb/> from a Metropolitan Police Private Fund. As the resources of <lb/> this Fund are on a strictly limited scale the Commissioner <lb/> desires to bring the facts to your notice in the hope that <lb/> it may be deemed right to render assistance to Mrs McLoughlin <lb/> from the Prince of Wales' National Relief Fund in view of the <lb/> particular circumstances of his death.  The Secretary, <lb/>The Prince of Wales' National Relief Fund, <lb/>Belgrave Square, <lb/>S.W.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0530_img_1908_3"/>
              It may be added, that inasmuch as the late Sergeant McLoughlin <lb/> was not in the pay of either the Admiralty or the War Office, the <lb/> Commissioner fears that there is little likelihood of either Department <lb/> having the power to make any grant to his widowed mother. <seg type="closer"> I am,  Sir,  Your obedient Servant,  (s.d.) Suffield Mylius. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>