<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1745">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Chadwick (Bishop of Derry and Raphoe) to Sir James Dougherty, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Chadwick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Sir James Dougherty (1844-1934), presbyterian minister, academic and politician. Dougherty was the MP for Derry in 1916 having retired as under-secretary for Ireland in 1914. The writer of the letter is recommending Harry T. Gallagher for the vacant position of chief Crown solicitor following the death of Malachy Kelly (1851-1916). The letter praises both Harry T. Gallagher and his father. Both were active in the recruitment campaign for the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5554/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1745</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0161">George Chadwick</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir James Dougherty</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1745_img_1202_1"  type="Letter"  url="4e073d33c221e480d62c1e4325f4aa9f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1745_img_1202_1"/>
             Handed to me by Sir James Dougherty<lb/>Seen by C. Sec. A.P.M. 31/3/16.   BISHOP'S HOUSE,<lb/>DERRY    March.29.1916    Add to application.<lb/><seg type="unclear">C.h. </seg>   3:4:16   My dear Sir James.   As Mr. Harry Gallagher Solicitor is a<lb/>candidate for the post of Chief Crown Solicitor rendered vacant<lb/>by the death of Sir Malachy Keely I should like you<lb/>to put his claims before the Chief Secretary and urge<lb/>them as strongly as you are able.  It is quite unnecessary to remind you that Mr Gallagher’s<lb/>father &amp; himself, more than any others, deserve the<lb/>credit of retaining North Tyrone as a Liberal seat.<lb/>Their services have always been given ungrudgingly without<lb/>seeking any reward. The same can be said of<lb/>both in regard to the Recruiting Campaign. In<lb/>fact Mr Harry Gallagher went so far on more than<lb/>one of the Recruiting platforms that he has injured<lb/>his business thereby. If loyal service merits<lb/>a reward I would say that Mr Gallagher’s<lb/>application should receive favourable consideration.   I am Sincerely Yrs    +. Chadwick<seg type="unclear">yh</seg>  <!-- George Chadwick was Bishop of Derry and Raphoe in 1916 --> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>