<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3476">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Postcard from George D. Roche to Nancy McCarthy, 2 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George D. Roche</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a postcard from George D. Roche to his niece Nancy congratulating her on passing her Inter Exam. A French priest who works as an interpreter has joined them, along with Fr. Bleasdale “and nobody gets a look in now with the pair of them”. He remarks they are kept busy. 

Nancy McCarthy was a well-practiced letter-writer, and her collection of correspondence spans eighty years. This postcard is one of seven included in the Letters of 1916 collection written to Nancy by her uncle, George D. Roche, on active service with the 7th London regiment during World War I.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>UCC Library Special Collections and Archives</repository>
                  <collection>The Nancy McCarthy Collection, BL/PP/NMC/608</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3476</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0611">George D. Roche</persName>
              <date>1916-09-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Nancy McCarthy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0711">The Convent, Mountrath, Queen's County, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3476_img_2885_1"  type="Letter"  url="9b9b2f2c84df32c12c02c7ae821d309d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3476_img_2885_2"  type="Letter"  url="62deb298cb70d4ad10bde38c17ce44d3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3476_img_2885_1"/>
             G. <seg type="unclear">Helong</seg>, 21, Rue St. Martin, Amiens Vise Paris n 118<lb/>Guevve 1914-1916<lb/>Intérieur de la Basilique - Le Maitre Autel<lb/>Interior of the Basilica - The Great Altar<lb/>Après le bombardement - After the bombardment 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3476_img_2885_2"/>
             BL/PP/NMC/608  CARTE POSTALE  Adresse   Miss Nancy McCarthy    Brigidine Convent<lb/>Mountrath<lb/>Ireland    Father Bleasdale says he is going<lb/>to write to you. So lookout for squalls!    France<lb/>2/9/16     My dear Nancy   Correspondance  Congratulations on passing your Inter<lb/>Exam. I'd leave Father Bleasdale<lb/>alone but there are two of them now!<lb/>I've got a French priest to look<lb/>after as well — he is attached to<lb/>us as interpreter and nobody<lb/>gets a look in now with the pair<lb/>of them. Hope you have quite<lb/>recovered from your camping out<lb/>adventure. Haven't got time to do<lb/>so here as we are at it nearly<lb/>all the time  Best of luck and<lb/>love from Uncle George  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>