<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3488">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Dillon to John Redmond, 29 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Dillon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from John Dillon (1851-1927) to John Redmond (1856-1918). Dillon writes to Redmond about a summons they received from Herbert Henry Asquith, the British Prime Minister. Dillon is clearly angered at the vagueness of the request and decides he will not travel until the next week.

John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. John Dillon was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. Dillon issued a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 where he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Dillon would succeed John Redmond as leader of the Home Rule party in 1918. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 15,182/23/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3488</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date>1916-06-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1834">2 North Great George&#39;s Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_1"  type="Letter"  url="9175de0b70bfad67c9f1dda2ab42112e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_2"  type="Letter"  url="4294d97c273920d62fca4e667fc11be2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_3"  type="Letter"  url="330717c97e73786ce6576b741c237381.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_4"  type="Letter"  url="bae564bd8a844d808ca6bc61fab91ab0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_5"  type="Letter"  url="90ce66be5ccebcddd3ba233bfa884bcd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_6"  type="Letter"  url="6445f61a85c68b8bae00e3360420c412.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_7"  type="Letter"  url="8526aad50f69a82fd1b37c62bec313a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3488_img_2896_8"  type="Letter"  url="22cec2e3214615e96c81b2ddcdb19d0f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_1"/>
             2, North G<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. George's Street,<lb/>Dublin.   <lb/>Monday<lb/>29 June 1916    My dear Redmond   You have — I assume —<lb/>received a <seg type="del">me</seg>line from<lb/>Bonham Carter asking<lb/>you to cross tonight.  The message reached me<lb/>about 6 <hi rend="superscript">o'c</hi> — and I<lb/>replied that it was 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_2"/>
             <lb/>not possible for me to<lb/>cross tonight.  I do not like the look<lb/>of things at all —<lb/>and I have no doubt<lb/>that this somewhat<lb/>persumptuous summons<lb/>is further purpose<lb/>of demanding some<lb/>large concession from<lb/>us — to enable 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_3"/>
             the P.M. to keep<lb/>the Cabinet together.<lb/>I am not disposed to<lb/>go before Tuesday<lb/>morning.  I confess I resent<lb/>being summoned over<lb/>in this peremptory<lb/>fashion without a<lb/>word of explanation.<lb/>Since these negotiations 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_4"/>
             commenced the P.M.<lb/>has not communicated<lb/>with us directly or<lb/>indirectly — and now<lb/>that the Tories have<lb/>kicked — that we<lb/>should be suddenly<lb/>summoned without a<lb/>hint of what we<lb/>are required for is<lb/>more than I am<lb/>prepared to stomach  MS 15.182/23/4(1) 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_5"/>
             As for representation of <lb/> Southern Unionists in the <lb/>Senate — George knows <lb/> we are prepared to <lb/> agree to any reasonable <lb/> proposal in this direction — <lb/> And it does not <lb/> need to drag us to <lb/>London to discuss that <lb/>matter — A letter would
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_6"/>
             do.  As at present advised—<lb/>and unless some fresh<lb/>information change my<lb/>mind — I shall not<lb/>cross till Tuesday.  Yours Sincerely   John Dillon       I read the article in<lb/>the D. Mail — It is  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_7"/>
             extremely good.  If Asquith had<lb/>any back bone —<lb/>and if Carson means<lb/>honestly — the settlement<lb/>could be put this.  But I confess<lb/>that the <seg type="unclear">London</seg> <!-- maybe this refers to a column in the newspaper --> in this<lb/>days Belfast news-letter<lb/>makes me suspect<lb/>that Carson is 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3488_img_2896_8"/>
             playing a double game<lb/>and if he is — the<lb/>settlement <hi rend="underline">cannot</hi><lb/>go through.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>