<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3749">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jo Sterdman to Samuel Davidson, 4 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jo Sterdman</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter of condolence from Jo Sterdman to Samuel Cleland Davidson (1846-1921). Sterdman writes an account of James Davidson&#39;s actions during the battle of the Somme. He lost his life while returning, wounded, across No Man&#39;s land for aid. The letter finishes, ‘I am sorry I am unable to write you a good letter but even yet I am not myself after what I have come through this last 10 days, and the tears are rolling down the face of your friend and his friend’.

This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.

Sir Samuel Cleland Davidson was an Irish inventor and founder of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast. During the First World War the Sirocco Engineering Works manufactured and exported equipment for cooling, drying, dust collecting, heating, ventilating, pneumatic conveyance for the Royal and Merchant Navy. 

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>PRONI-D3642-B-8-61</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3749</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0740">Jo Sterdman</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1121">SeaCourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3749_img_3136_1"  type="Letter"  url="8914f62b5b41e097c8bd47d87f7f8bfc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3749_img_3136_2"  type="Letter"  url="9b4475216bd2a464105b29aeffde24db.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3749_img_3136_3"  type="Letter"  url="daa0b301d7adcda5d7925d1d4abf69e9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3749_img_3136_4"  type="NULL"  url="27de6507a3d27e60d0614954e5a0f909.JPG"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3749_img_3136_5"  type="NULL"  url="fcc5ba934b92eda380c7feb7b618386e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3749_img_3136_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline"> 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July '16 </hi>  Dear Mr Davidson   It is with the deepest <lb/>regret and sorrow I start this <lb/>letter to you, and cannot express <lb/>in words what I feel about <lb/>poor Jim, he always was so <lb/>good &amp; kind to me. All I <lb/>can say in my poor way is <lb/>that he died as he live a <lb/>grand man, ad is for ever <lb/>graded as one of "<sic>Brittians</sic> <lb/>greatest Hero's." I am sure <lb/>you know by now what he <lb/>did, but I must tell you in <lb/>my own words. He went <lb/>across with the first and <lb/>although getting casualties in his
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3749_img_3136_2"/>
            team took the German 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> <lb/>and second lines, with the <lb/>help of a few men made an <lb/>emplacement in the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> line <lb/>and although wounded started <lb/>to work, one by one his men <lb/>fell until he had no one <lb/>but himself, and did he stop <lb/>No!!! he worked on with his <lb/>gun "singlehanded" although <lb/>wounded through the leg. <lb/>His ammunition ran out did <lb/>he give in, those who know <lb/>Jim well know the answer <lb/> No !!!. He took bombs from <lb/>the men round him and <sic>through</sic> them till his strength <lb/>gave out. Some men
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3749_img_3136_3"/>
            carried him to a dug out <lb/>in the German front line <seg type="del">untill</seg> <lb/><sic>untill</sic> the bearers would come <lb/>for him, Ah!!! there is the <lb/><sic>tradgity</sic>, the stretcher bearers <lb/>could not come. The ground <lb/>between our line and theirs <lb/>was <sic>sweped</sic> with <sic>murdreous</sic> <lb/><sic>m/c</sic> gun and shrapnel fire <lb/>which made it impossible <lb/>for the bearers, ammunitions carriers <lb/>or messengers to get across. <lb/>Many a good life was sacrificed <lb/>in trying to do this.   Our men after fighting for <lb/>hours were beaten back because <lb/> of shortage of ammunition and <lb/>men so when this word reached
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3749_img_3136_4"/>
            4/ <lb/>Jim he made his way out of <lb/>the dugout to try &amp; get back <lb/>to rally his men, what a <lb/>noble heart, — but found <lb/>he was unable to do anything <lb/>but crawl, <sic>therefor</sic> as no <lb/>help was <sic>coming</sic> <sic>accross</sic>he <lb/>tried to get back him self <lb/>and while crossing "nomans land" <lb/>was shot, I believe through the <lb/>head &amp; it is believed died <lb/>instantly in no pain. Was <lb/>not it a glorious ending <lb/>to a glorious life. I am sorry I <lb/>am unable to write you a good <lb/>letter but even yet I am not myself <lb/>after what I have come through this <lb/>last ten days, and the tears are rolling <lb/>down the face of your friend &amp; his friend.   <seg type="unclear">Jo</seg> Sterdman 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3749_img_3136_5"/>
             On Active Service   Written 21st Sent 26th June   Mrs. S.C. Davidson <lb/>Seacourt <lb/>Bangor <lb/>Co. Down <lb/>Ireland   JmDavidson   21-6-16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>