<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2630">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Adam Duffin, 9 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Maria Duffin (1854-1954) to her daughter, Celia (1888-1979). In this letter she urges Celia to contribute something to the Hospital magazine

Celia Duffin, born in 1888, was one of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She attended the Cheltenham Ladies College. She served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#34;&#34;Escape Poem&#34; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell &amp; Co. Ltd in 1929. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/C/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2630</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-12-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0784">Dunowen Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0733">3rd London General Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2630_img_2055_1"  type="Letter"  url="28c4d31bdc1e9d8b2c18e9a621cd4825.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2630_img_2055_2"  type="Letter"  url="97bbad4a321a4c71c06f6aa73658a816.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2630_img_2055_3"  type="Letter"  url="4ecacc4ebaa463f7002a0871af2ebe8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2630_img_2055_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/C   3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> London General Hospital    Dec. 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915    Dearest Papa   Thank you so much for your letter and for<lb/>the nice packet of sweets, it was good of you to<lb/>send them. When are you going to have some<lb/>business in London? I should like to have a<lb/>glimpse of you again. My seven months will<lb/>soon be up now and all those who are not<lb/>signing on again have to give in their names be-<lb/>fore the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of this month. I think they should<lb/>give us a holiday in between, but see no chance<lb/>of getting one. We are now to get at least<lb/>£2 a month, (probably more) government allowance<lb/>which is <seg type="unclear">over</seg> from our keep, as well as<lb/>an £20 pay, so I think we are very lucky<lb/>in that way, the advantage of being under<lb/>the war office, as I don't think ordinary  <lb/>in civil hospitals get any pay at all, or very<lb/>little.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2630_img_2055_2"/>
             I am rather sick at being put on night duty<lb/>again, especially as I had to change my<lb/>rooms and move into a night house where I<lb/>don't know any of the nurses. Fortunately<lb/>my stable companion, a Miss <seg type="unclear">Gosse</seg>, is a very<lb/>nice girl who has travelled about the<lb/>world a lot.  This ward is full of Australians and New<lb/>Zealanders, nice big men, but much more<lb/>free and easy than the British tommy,<lb/>some of them have lived in the wild all<lb/>their lives, and they are all looking for-<lb/>ward to seeing snow for the first time.<lb/>They make  me  laugh sometimes, They have such queer<lb/>expressions and ways of putting things; one<lb/>has just asked me to put the block of<lb/>wood in that hole, meaning that he<lb/>wanted the door shut. Dinkum is a<lb/>great expression with them all, meaning<lb/>yes, really. Two of them here are<lb/>maoris and can talk to each other in<lb/>some unknown tongue. I have awful<lb/>trouble in getting them up in the mornings, as<lb/>they must be dressed and their beds made<lb/>when the day nurses come on, unless they<lb/>are bed patients. They try all sorts of tricks,<lb/>and pretend the doctor has ordered them<lb/>back to bed. To-night when I came on duty,<lb/>one of them would creep out of bed and<lb/>switch all the lights out, so that I had to grope<lb/>my way up the ward in the dark, and when<lb/>I got back to my seat again, out they all<lb/>went again.  I am having my night off on Friday, so<lb/>I expect I shall go to Epsom and spend<lb/>the night there.  Have you been playing any golf lately? not<lb/>if the weather is anything like what we have<lb/>here, it has been raining a lot.  What do you think of the war news, it all<lb/>sounds rather depressing at present, but I<lb/>suppose we will struggle through in time.<lb/>The hospital is always warned when<lb/>zeppelins are expected, but they never seem 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2630_img_2055_3"/>
             to arrive. Is it true that the Arsenal at<lb/>St. Petersburg had a German manager and<lb/>that it was blown up when war was de-<lb/><seg type="unclear">cl</seg> and the Russians left with practically<lb/>no ammunition? One hears such a lot of<lb/>stories.  Emma seems to be enjoying the life at<lb/>Alexandria, perhaps we may be sent<lb/>abroad soon, but nobody knows any-<lb/>thing, and nobody seems to be able to give<lb/>you any information.  I cook myself funny meals to keep myself<lb/>awake; to-night I have an egg and<lb/>tomatoes, and last night I fried potatoes<lb/>and found they tasted much better<lb/>straight from the pan.  I hope you are keeping well this<lb/>winter and you throat isn't bothering you.<lb/>I have made horrid blots over this, but<lb/>I have to jump up every now and then.  Best love, dearest Papa,<lb/>Ever your own  Celia 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>