<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2020">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to Sir Neville Chamberlain, 24 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Andrew Philip Magill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941) the Private Secretary for the Chief Crown Secretary of Ireland, Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) to the Inspector General of the Royal Irish Constabulary, Sir Neville Chamberlain (1856-1944). In the letter Magill writes to the Inspector General to talk of the health of a Sergeant Ahearn, a police officer who was shot twice by Irish Volunteers on the 22 March 1916. The attack happened at when an anti-Sinn Féin demonstration took place in Tullamore, Co Offaly. Fourteen Irish Volunteers were besieged by a hostile mob in the local Sinn Féin hall. Believing they were inadequately protected by the police they fired revolvers to keep the mob away, and when the police moved in to disarm them resisted arrest, seriously wounding a Sergeant Ahearn. Magill wishes to express his sadness for his injury and declares that Mr. Birrell is appreciative of their sacrifice.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI; Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8125/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2020</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date>1916-03-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Neville Chamberlain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2020_img_1468_1"  type="Letter"  url="6e357e3f3b05212a1bcc06dfee71427a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2020_img_1468_1"/>
             MAR 24 16  <lb/>WIRED AT 1.26pm  Inspector General   Will you kindly convey to <lb/>County Inspector Crane and the <lb/> officers &amp; men under him Mr. Birrell's <lb/> regret that they, and especially Sergeant <lb/> Ahearn, should have been so <lb/> seriously injured in the recent <lb/> disturbance at Tullamore. Mr Birrell <lb/> appreciates fully the services which <lb/> they rendered &amp; the courage they <lb/> displayed on this occasion. He <lb/> hopes that Sergeant Ahearn is <lb/> progressing favourably &amp; will <lb/>soon be out of danger.   Magill 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>