<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3320">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Tomás Mac Curtain to Áine, 27 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Tomás Mac Curtain</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork Public Museum</repository>
                  <collection>T. Mac Curtain Collection, L1945.213 B7.7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3320</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0338">Tomás Mac Curtain</persName>
              <date>1916-09-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Áine</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1920</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3320_img_2733_1"  type="Letter"  url="97f9be4b093e9b36b6290a5a68a319c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3320_img_2733_2"  type="Letter"  url="cbdf840c1f54e1f8ea95a495a265cf2c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3320_img_2733_3"  type="Letter"  url="94e69308d625a5e77bf07e8d7a432be4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3320_img_2733_4"  type="Letter"  url="ee122aa321fc28d024d6b0a0bcdf75dd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3320_img_2733_1"/>
             Wednesday Sept <hi rend="underline">27.</hi> 1916   A. Áine Acroide—    Yours of 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> received to-day and it<lb/>was indeed a welcome visitor. I'm sure it must<lb/>be very tiring in that shop all day, of course<lb/>I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> it is. Do be very careful throughout<lb/>the winter and I'm very glad the Doctor has<lb/>put the bar on the theatres &amp; picture houses<lb/>in your case. The atmosphere of those places<lb/>is very bad, when a few thousand people get<lb/>packed in close together think of the effect<lb/>on the air. I'm sorry I'm not at home that<lb/>I could help to make the time pass for us<lb/>all together, but patience will do all that.<lb/>D.G. <seg type="del">I am delighted to hear of your success</seg><lb/><seg type="del">with Mr Rowe.</seg> It must have surprised you<lb/><hi rend="underline">very much</hi>. Annie, girl, spare as much as you<lb/>can, don't be too anxious to throw it around<lb/>it will undoubtedly come in useful later<lb/>I'm very very glad to hear it, indeed,<lb/><seg type="unclear">Re Siobán</seg>; I at first thought she was too young to<lb/>send away, but I quite agree that she is much<lb/>better off there during the winter and the<lb/>discipline of the place will be just the thing<lb/>for her. She is so full of spirit that I'm afraid 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3320_img_2733_2"/>
             2  Lizzie could never keep her under control, with<lb/>all the other cares she now has to contend<lb/>with. Yes, you are quite right and Im now<lb/>very glad she has been sent to the nuns<lb/>I've written to the Superioress (whom I met once)<lb/>about Siobán and have asked her to teach her<lb/>all the IRISH possible. Tomas Og must be a<lb/>bit on the heavy side when he hasnt yet succeeded<lb/>in guiding his own helm: <seg type="del">B</seg>Lizzie always pays<lb/>special attention to the bodily comfort and I<lb/>daresay our hope has not been neglected, and<lb/>therefore finds it had to carry his own weight<lb/>I've always thought that Lizzie was very practical in<lb/>that respect, really the most practical of you all. She<lb/>always paid special attention to sound wholesome<lb/>food, and I always admired that ideas as practical<lb/>commonsense. I dont know whether I've ever praised<lb/>her for it, but indeed I should have, but you<lb/>know its always the way with men (and women<lb/>too) they never say really the things the ought say<lb/>and at the right time; although as far as<lb/>Lizzie is concerned I think I did say<lb/>a <hi rend="underline">few things</hi> at the right time — ask her —<lb/>But, your pardon, good patient Annie for<lb/>bothering you with my domestic affairs, I'm<lb/>sure it doesn't interest you, but I'm 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3320_img_2733_3"/>
             3  inclined to allow myself ramble off into<lb/>side issues and I am sure you wont be too<lb/>angry toward me. You are still the patient<lb/>wise looking little Colleen I first got to really<lb/>know at Midleton Feis when you won the<lb/>medal, always serious looking, indeed you<lb/>didn't seem much elated by your success on<lb/>that occasion — anyway not at a distance.<lb/>You were quite cool — but I could see when<lb/>I met you coming out the gate that your<lb/>heart was jumping with excitement and<lb/>you were quite aglow with the pleasure<lb/>of winning. Undoubtedly we started a friendship<lb/>on that day a <seg type="foreign">Cáilin </seg> which will hold through life<lb/>and be a help to both in our difficulties along<lb/>the narrow way. Again through you, I met<lb/>Lizzie, and tis then only life for me began,<lb/>whether sorrow or joy, even heavy sorrow<lb/>loses its bitterness in perspective and when<lb/>that sorrow is shared by a loyal and true<lb/>partner, <seg type="del">you</seg> a person looks back upon it<lb/>more as a victory over adversity, and it<lb/>becomes tinged with a feeling of having borne up<lb/>well under trying difficulties and standing the<lb/>test — of being tried and not found wanting—<lb/>I only know how, after Lizzie (who certainly is splendid when 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3320_img_2733_4"/>
             4  trouble knocks at the door. ) much your help and<lb/>Hannas and Mary's (God rest her Soul) and Susies<lb/>Ma's in fact you all, have been to me in<lb/>some pretty serious difficulties which I have<lb/>been up against for the past eight years,<lb/>and greater than all the material assistance<lb/>was the powerful use you always made of<lb/>prayer on our behalf and I will always<lb/>bless you for that. Forgive me again for<lb/>rambling so much into my own affairs, but<lb/>the mood happens to be on me and I<lb/>like to say to you what really is in my<lb/>mind. Jerry and I will not forget the Novena<lb/>on Oct 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> and afterwards and we wont<lb/>forget the Little Flower. Many thanks for the<lb/>pictures, they are very appropriate — I mean<lb/>the lines. I enclose an Irish Hymn which<lb/>I am sure you will like. It came here from<lb/>Kerry and now goes back to Cork to you.<lb/>I'm very glad the school is doing so well<lb/>Rosies sketch is <seg type="del">  </seg> splendid and has gone<lb/>the rounds. I wonder how she likes the new name<lb/>I have given her — I am expecting a<lb/>word from L. any day . — Remind her—  I'm writing Hanna to know <seg type="del">  </seg> how I have offended<lb/>her, she hasn't sent me a line. —  Goodbye<lb/><seg type="foreign">A cara mo croide</seg>   Ó Tomas 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>