<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1946">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate English to Patrick English, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate English </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Kate English (b. 1855), and is addressed to her son Patrick English (1894-1970). After the Easter Rising of 1916 Patrick English was interned at Stafford Prison before he was later moved to Frongoch internment camp in Wales.

In the letter Kate states that she is surprised to learn that Patrick did not receive the money that she sent him to buy cigarettes. She states that she will send him some more money. She asks Patrick to write to her as soon as he receives this money. She writes, also, of her hope that he will soon be released. Kate goes on to state that she is happy with the new house she has moved into with her daughter Nellie. She also notes that Patrick&#39;s comrades are surprised he has not been released yet.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Private Collection, Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Patrick English Collection; English/1916/nd7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1946</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0694">Kate English </persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0146">Blackhorse Lane, Phoenix Park, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1946_img_1394_1"  type="Letter"  url="c4adce856b3fca643ec24e1895b61c2d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1946_img_1394_2"  type="Letter"  url="e95df22c054f910e7d126a5cd2a00d3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1946_img_1394_3"  type="Letter"  url="25cd09d722bc078ebe08b5f9633a8d5e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1946_img_1394_1"/>
             c/o 2 Ashtown Villa,<lb/>Black Horse. Road.<lb/>Phoenix Park.<lb/>Co. Dublin   My Dear Patrick,   I got your<lb/>second letter and was<lb/>surprised to hear that you<lb/>did not get the money<lb/>I sent you for  Ciggarettes .<lb/>I sent you one shilling<lb/>and I am sending you<lb/>another now. answer 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1946_img_1394_2"/>
             as soon as possible to<lb/>let me know if you<lb/><sic>recieved</sic> it. I hope<lb/>you will be soon home<lb/>as I am expecting you<lb/>every morning You<lb/>need not be <sic>worring</sic> about<lb/>me as I am splendid<lb/>I am quite happy with<lb/>Nellie it is a beautiful<lb/>house when you are<lb/>coming it is to this<lb/>house you are coming<lb/>it is beside Horans. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1946_img_1394_3"/>
            <lb/>3 <lb/>I know you will be <lb/>delighted with it. all your <lb/>comrades are more than <lb/>surprised to see you <lb/>are not home they <lb/>cannot understand it <lb/>I have no more to <lb/>say at present hoping <lb/>to hear from you soon <lb/>again. we all join sending <lb/>our best love Good Bye <lb/>with love and kisses <lb/>from mother <lb/>x x x x x x x x x x x x x x x x x
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>