<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4214">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Shaw to Martha Shaw, 29 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Samuel Shaw to his mother, Martha Shaw, informing her that John has returned safely and greatly enjoyed his holiday. Samuel also asks his mother to pass on the message that he will not stay in France a minute longer than necessary once the Germans have been defeated.

Samuel Henry Shaw (1896-1967) was a sergeant with the 10th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers. He volunteered for active service in September 1914. Before enlisting Samuel was a member of the Portstewart Company, Coleraine Battalion, North Derry Regiment, Ulster Volunteer Force. Samuel served in France, and was wounded during the Battle of the Somme in July 1916 and again in early 1917 and in 1918. Before the War he was employed as a ironmonger&#39;s assistant.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-36</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4214</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0493">Samuel Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-08-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Martha Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1027">Shorncliffe, Portstewart, Co. Derry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1967</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4214_img_3584_1"  type="Letter"  url="24810f2f1817ce026e0e9915fc2ae5bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4214_img_3584_2"  type="Letter"  url="f2b819b073bac8936102077b19de6ce3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4214_img_3584_1"/>
             B.E. Force   29 Aug. 16   My Dear <lb/>Mother   Just a few lines to let you <lb/>know I received your letter &amp;parcel all right. <lb/>John has got back here again. I was <lb/>speaking to him yesterday, he enjoyed <lb/>his holiday very much. I am glad to <lb/>know that you are all well and in the <lb/>best of health. Tell Mrs Mc Aulery that <lb/>we wont stay a minute longer in France <lb/>than we can help after the Germans <lb/>are beaten. I hope the fishing is still <lb/>good. I think this is all at present. With <lb/>love to all.  <lb/> I remain <lb/>Your Loving Son   <hi rend="underline">Sammie</hi> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4214_img_3584_2"/>
             Mrs Jas Shaw <lb/>Shore cliffe <lb/>Portstewart <lb/>Co. Derry   <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>