<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4277">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 9 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/214</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4277</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4277_img_3641_1"  type="Letter"  url="96df9c723f7d3f5ef6dcc328e4e7ba9a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4277_img_3641_2"  type="Letter"  url="237015877e6ad48d60c3928c5e55c843.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4277_img_3641_1"/>
             April 9<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">th</seg></hi>.   My p r   Your most thrilling letter was brought by Douglas <lb/>early this morning &amp; has been reread over &amp; over again but <lb/> will be burnt probably tomorrow !    I a little wish Ed had not asked for that interview <lb/> it is just the line I want not to take. I know what <lb/> it is in a small way having people anxious to see you at <lb/> all hours but only on the smallest scale compared.    I don't think I should press for it for him next time <lb/> he is up. It really is not fair, tho' I suppose he would say <lb/> it is part of his business. So it is I see, but somehow I'd <lb/> rather be the other way &amp; not get on.    Mater's 25 shall go towards the p r. It is good for her.    I can hardly wait for your most wildly exciting packets to <lb/> hatch out &amp; feel inclined to bust too watching the Morning post <lb/> &amp; Squiffy's attempts to get Sir E into a false position. I <lb/> see the traps set for him now, but am disappointed at <lb/>Bonar Law who shows that tho' a most sincere patriot he <lb/> is not a really great man in the widest sense. A good adminis-<lb/>trator but out of touch with the great <seg type="unclear">events</seg> which call <lb/> for greatness.   I'm afraid the summing up of K is correct &amp; it will 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4277_img_3641_2"/>
            <lb/>be difficult for Sir E to find his collegues perhaps if he does come <lb/> in, but the main thing is the Great man at the top <lb/> with large ideas, &amp; there are plenty of good administrators <lb/> Craig etc   I will try to get a definite decision about my leave <lb/> tomorrow but I hardly think it will be possible for me <lb/> to go now &amp; I shall not press it, much tho' I long to see <lb/> my p r again.    I do hope she is alright again. Douglas did <lb/> not get much time at home &amp; so far I have had little <lb/> chance of talking to him. I want to hear about your eyes.   I think Place will stand up to the GOC &amp; rather look forward <lb/> to the results. Former is <seg type="del">tryin</seg>taking up many of my suggestions <lb/> which were badly sat upon perviously.   I don't think there would be any difficulty in your <lb/> sharing a houes. If I came home on leave I should probably not <lb/> stop with you — in the suburbs ! — more than one night, the remainder <lb/> would London or Oxford or Broads. In fact if you still hanker after <lb/> a country house &amp; won't feel it makes you too tired travelling I think <lb/> a companion might be wise if you started right off on the lines that <lb/> you do not attempt to <seg type="unclear">entertain</seg> the other.   I like to think of the p r with her Duchess &amp; her big man, <lb/> it seems quite right somehow.   Let me know about your eyes    Your b w     Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>