<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5899">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lance Corporal P. Lynch to Lady Clonbrock, 25 September, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Lance Corporal P. Lynch</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Lance Corporal P. Lynch of the 5th Connaught Rangers, a prisoner of war in Bulgaria, to Lady Clonbrock, Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), (1839-1928), wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock, (1834-1917).
Lady Clonbrock was one of a number of ladies who were members of the Irish Womens Association. Formed in London in the Spring of 1915, the IWA.&#39;s purpose was to provide food and comforts for prisoners of War belonging to Irish Regiments. 
The writer is responding to a postcard he has received from Lady Clonbrock in which she requested his regimental details, which he supplies here. He says that he hasn&#39;t been receiving any parcels and this is his reason for writing to her.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5899</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1517">Lance Corporal P. Lynch</persName>
              <date>1916-09-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0917">Philipopolis, Bulgaria.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5899_img_994_1"  type="Letter"  url="d275b8a93aaff5c5bae6d6b335fc580f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5899_img_994_2"  type="Letter"  url="681f85a5571a6c0f11fa070adddad377.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5899_img_994_1"/>
             25/9/16   Lcpl P. Lynch No. 10207 <lb/>5th Connaught Rangers, British Prisoner War <lb/>Philipopolis <lb/>Bulgaria   Dear Madam   In reply to your P.C. dated 4 instant <lb/>I am sorry to put you to <lb/> so much trouble but as I <lb/>have not <sic>being</sic>receiving <lb/> any <sic>parcles</sic> I took the <lb/> <sic>privilage</sic> of writing. <lb/>I am letting you know to <lb/>which regiment I belong
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5899_img_994_2"/>
            as you asked me in <lb/>your Post Card.   Thanking  you  for taking <lb/>so much interest in me.  <lb/>I remain yours  Sincerely   Lcpl Lynch 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>