<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0352">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Phyllis Ryan to James Ryan, 19 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Phyllis Ryan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Philomena Ryan (1895-1983) to James Ryan (1891-1970). Philomena writes to James enquiring as to his well being and what he requires now that Irish prisoners are able to receive post. She describes the lonely conditions at home and the continued incarceration of friends. She informs James that letters will be sent to him more regularly from now on.Philomena Frances Kelly, neé Ryan, was the sister of James Ryan. She served as a messenger for the GPO garrison during the Easter Rising. She later married future president of the free-state Seán T. Ó Ceallaigh. James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>, IE UCDA P88</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/352</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1444">Phyllis Ryan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1357">19 Ranelagh Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0352_img_159_1"  type="Letter"  url="aa08a1bd6ffa6f2161af3998486f2d2f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0352_img_159_2"  type="Letter"  url="5c4d90e0b4e61238f8ca3e0523dbaf24.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0352_img_159_1"/>
                19 Ranelagh Rd.    19-5-'16.   My dearest Jim,   We hear from your Commandant this<lb/> morning that one is allowed to send you food &amp; clothing,<lb/> and you are allowed to write and receive letters, so<lb/> we shall try at once. We had written to you a few<lb/> times already, but not sending it in case of the<lb/> Chief Postal Censor perhaps you never got it. How are you<lb/> all getting on there. Write and tell us exactly what you<lb/> want. Are you allowed to have money. What in the<lb/> way of food would you like best? We could send<lb/> even cooked ham or that sort of thing if you like.<lb/> Just tell us as soon as you can, since you are allowed<lb/> to write. Could we send you newspapers I wonder.  Well we are all getting on well here, although very<lb/> lonely for everyone. Kate &amp; and Nell are both in Mountjoy.<lb/> We see them every day for a short time. They have no<lb/> idea of what they are being kept for or for how long.<lb/> Miss <seg type="unclear">Deagani</seg> and Slayer are doing Kits work in the<lb/> university and Cadigan is doing Nells in Wexford. Chris<lb/> &amp; Ag. are both at home, having good times I think.<lb/> They are all as usual like Mick &amp; and Jack and all. Even<lb/> Mother is improving a lot I think, and not in    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0352_img_159_2"/>
               about us all. Min and myself are here as usual.<lb/> Nancy Power is staying with us. We have a tremendous lot<lb/> of visitors in notwithstanding all that are gone. Of<lb/> course nearly all are women or priests. I am trying<lb/> to think about my exam, at least wondering when I<lb/> am going to begin. Everyone keeps asking for you.<lb/> We see all our friends through barbed wire in Richmond<lb/> Barracks on three days of the week. Dinny &amp; and Sean C<lb/> and all that crowdâ, but nearly everyone is in England<lb/> now. Fr. Paul is going to try and see you some day.   We are just sending clothes today. We shall send<lb/> some food later on. Can you have cigarettes or<lb/> perhaps your pipe and tobacco. Let us know as<lb/> soon as you can what you want.   We shall write often now, and get other people to<lb/> write. <seg type="unclear">Marie</seg> wrote to you too. Did you ever<lb/> get her letter.   Goodbye. If we don't send parcel we shall<lb/> write very soon again.  <seg type="closer"> Love from everyone and good luck. <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Phyllis.</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>