<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0782">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender asks Lillian to advise the aunt of a man who has been reported wounded on how to contact him. He asks her not to overwork herself, though he takes pleasure in the idea of Lillian &#39;ordering Duchesses and Countesses around like kitchen maids&#39;. Spender expresses sympathy that Lillian is missing her usual summer trip to the sea, inquires about the weather, and confesses that he is accomplishing.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund. This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. g very little in his own work.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/370</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/782</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0782_img_2317_1"  type="Letter"  url="fcf73babd7b0938e0ea5876bf513f18c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0782_img_2317_2"  type="NULL"  url="110ccd3acfe3949145dc1d7be77527d4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0782_img_2317_1"/>
                July 31    I'm so glad you take taxis <lb/>when it saves you. <seg type="del">not</seg>. I much <lb/>approve tho I should not like you <lb/>to take joy rides now.  I have briefly told you of <lb/>my questions so your letter poured <lb/>off oil   Jessie's nephew was reported <lb/>as <seg type="del">missin</seg> wounded &amp; she has not <lb/>heard of him for weeks. Could you <lb/>let her know what to do.  I'm afraid I am rather trouble <lb/>some to a poor overworked pr but <lb/>she must cut down her letters to <lb/>the bw   I like to think of you ordering <lb/>Duchesses &amp; Countesses about like <lb/>kitchen maids. I wish I could <lb/>peep in &amp; watch you really at <lb/>work without you knowing it.  Very good of you to send parcel <lb/>to Rex like that. Perhaps a long <lb/>  once every fortnight &amp;  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0782_img_2317_2"/>
              one from Mater would be easier <lb/>than 2 <hi rend="superscript">le</hi> a week between you  Rex wants to pay but of <lb/>course we shan't allow that.  Is your work getting any <lb/>less now. I think it ought <lb/>to be a bit better now &amp; in <lb/>this hot weather I feel very <lb/>sorry for the pr who wants <lb/>her annual bath — sea bath <lb/>so badly. You ought most <lb/>certainly to get off in September <lb/>somewhere.  I shan't be able to prattle <lb/>on like this when <seg type="del">you</seg> I <lb/>once get settled down to work <lb/>At present I am rather at a <lb/>loose end in work &amp; wish to <lb/>be tactful as the G S O is older <lb/>than I am  Must stop now <seg type="closer"> Your b w  WBSpender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>