<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2356">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from S.C Harrison to Sir Matthew Nathan, 5 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>S.C. Harrison</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from S.C. Harrison to Sir Matthew Nathan. Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). was  the under-secretary to the Chief Crown Secretary of Ireland Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Nathan was under-secretary until the 1916 Rising after which he offered his resignation. 

Harrison is writing to Nathan about the making of linen in Belfast and how there are women employed in the making of linen.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP KB, 1916/7443/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2356</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0115">S.C. Harrison</persName>
              <date>1916-03-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1390">36, Upper Fitzwilliam Street, Dublin, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName >None</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2356_img_1802_1"  type="Letter"  url="c99337646ca89986a7f2ea6ff73e9945.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2356_img_1802_2"  type="Letter"  url="ae004271138eae5702dc1afb14d10292.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2356_img_1802_1"/>
             36, Upper Fitzwilliam Street    5<hi rend="superscript">th March, 1916.</hi>   Dear Sir Matthew    I shall be glad to know <lb/> if you have investigated my statements <lb/> as to the conditions of employment in the <lb/> linen factories &amp; mills in Belfast yet? <lb/> The time is getting on, while these poor <lb/> women slave for 6/2.5 a week I <lb/> hear their well off sisters are being given <lb/> the munition work at 16/- -I have not <lb/> had the opportunity of checking this fact <lb/> figure - But I was shocked <lb/> to hear that the direction of munition <lb/> work in Belfast has been handed over <lb/> to W Alexander M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dowell officially, - <lb/> the representative of the employers in the <lb/> linen trade - without anyone to represent
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2356_img_1802_2"/>
            labour associated with him. This -<lb/> ought not to be -    If you would just invited my <lb/> official informants,- Miss M Galway <lb/> Avenue Hall, Garfield Street,<lb/> W Wm. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dowell, 11 Dover Street <lb/> Shankill Road, <lb/> &amp; Mr D. Gordon, Engineer's Hall College <lb/> Street Belfast, to come &amp; give you <lb/> their evidence, you would soon find <lb/> what cruel injustice is being worked <lb/> by the foot- putting such powers into <lb/> the hands of those interested in keeping <lb/> down women's wages . There is no <lb/> other explanation of such a measure as <lb/> introducing well off women into factory <lb/> life in Belfast now where so large a <lb/> number of women are on short time &amp; <lb/> earning pitifully insufficient wages if the <lb/> prices were normal, but starvation wages with <lb/> high war prices -    Yours Sincerely  <hi rend="underline">S. C. Harrison</hi>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>