<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0764">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 2 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfred Bliss Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender (1880-1968). Wilfrid expresses his pride and sadness at the men of Ulster &#39;sacrificing their lives by the thousands&#39; with no apparent result, due to the failure of the (non-Ulster) divisions on their right and left. He characterises this doing of &#39;the most splendid things with no results&#39; as the usual fate of the Ulsterman. This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/346</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/764</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0764_img_2296_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc8dabdd91f86fd02750ae0733eedaf4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0764_img_2296_2"  type="Letter"  url="236a5f1156dca8fd578b759bd1d78ad8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0764_img_2296_1"/>
              July /16    july 1916   My pr   I am a proud but sad—<lb/> dend man. I have seen our <lb/> attack as no other man <lb/> in this world could Do. I believe<lb/> I have seen them win through <lb/><seg type="unclear">an inferno</seg> which other <lb/><seg type="unclear">troops failing</seg> ours<lb/> got through. I have seen <lb/> their advance as if in <lb/> drill on parade winning the <lb/> admiration of the next corps<lb/> staff &amp;  of all who saw them . I know our men <lb/> are sacrificing their lives by  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0764_img_2296_2"/>
              the thousand. I know that <lb/> their cause is probably in vain owing <lb/> to the failure on our right &amp; left. <lb/> It seems to be the fate of the Ulsterman <lb/> to do the most splendid things with <lb/> no results. I am not going in to <lb/> the question of our losses which run  very <lb/> heavy. I know you will do all you can. Don't spurn any <seg type="unclear">experts who'll<lb/> save you  for your work  a little in your work.</seg><lb/><sic>Probly</sic> Capt  Bruce's sister may come<lb/> &amp; help. I don't intend to write<lb/> of what I saw,but you can tell<lb/><seg type="unclear">Sredward</seg> that I think half our<lb/> men deserve VCs &amp; Crosses but <lb/> will not get them of course. <seg type="closer"> Always your bw <lb/> Wilfred Spender .</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>