<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1841">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John O'Brien to Anna O'Rahilly, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John O&#39;Brien</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by John O&#39;Brien to Anna O&#39;Rahilly (d.1958). In the letter O&#39;Brien thanks Anna for sending him to Lady Albinia Broderick (1861-1955), also known as &#39;Gobnait Ní Bhruadair&#39;. Lady Broderick was a republican and supporter of the 1916 Rising; she joined both Cumann na mBan and Sinn Féin. O&#39;Brien also speaks about what an honour it was to have known Michael. O&#39;Brien then asks Anna if she could secure some money from the National Aid Association, set up to provide aid to dependants of those connected to the Rising, on his behalf to cover some expenses.

Anna was the sister of  Michael &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill (1867-1945) and Bulmer Hobson (1883-1969) who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/239/6/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1841</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1227">John O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0045">Ballincoona, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1841_img_1296_1"  type="Letter"  url="d32401110d17123909fd4a76d51ad478.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1841_img_1296_2"  type="Letter"  url="7c6c0ac0ff0959df433797d1d0845b66.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1841_img_1296_3"  type="Letter"  url="fd88064e970de619ca40fdcdbcd1a329.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1841_img_1296_4"  type="Letter"  url="7a925b4d68a4d0ea0adc5872d27c2b66.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1841_img_1296_1"/>
             Ballincoona <lb/>Caher Daniel <lb/>Co. Kerry   Dear Miss O'Rahilly   I don't know how <lb/>to thank you for sending <lb/>me not only to such a <lb/>nice place &amp;&amp; country and <lb/> its homely people But also <lb/> for the honour that you <lb/> have bestowed on me <lb/> In placing me under the care <lb/> of such a splendid Lady <lb/>as the Hon A Broderick
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1841_img_1296_2"/>
            <lb/>I almost feel a different <lb/>person since I came here <lb/> and improving every day. <lb/>I must not forget to tell <lb/> you how much I feel the <lb/>honour of knowing your <lb/>Brother (R.I.P.) I know that it <lb/>is hard to <sic>loose</sic> ones Brother <lb/>but I am quite sure that <lb/>you are the proudest sister <lb/>to have such a brother as <lb/>you had I hope you will <lb/>excuse me for intruding <lb/>on such a sacred subject <lb/>but I am quite sure that <lb/>you will understand me.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1841_img_1296_3"/>
            <lb/>Because I feel the honour <lb/>so much that I could not <lb/>help saying what I have <lb/>said. Mr Gannon wishes me <lb/>to also thank you he is <lb/>delighted with the place <lb/>and Lady Broderick.   Dear Miss I am run of <seg type="unclear">our</seg> <lb/>money, and I do not want <lb/>the Lady know, for she is <lb/>really too good to us down <lb/>here so if you can, get from <lb/>the National Aid just a little <lb/>for expenses I should be very <lb/>thankful to you. Of course I <lb/>should have had plenty
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1841_img_1296_4"/>
            <lb/>to last me for my time here <lb/>out of what you generously <lb/> gave me in the offices, only <lb/>I had to pay my hotel Bill <lb/>in Dublin before I came away <lb/>I hope you will excuse my <lb/>being so forward. But somehow <lb/>I would sooner ask through <lb/>you than apply to the office. <lb/>I think I have said as much <lb/>as time permits me at present <lb/>so I will conclude and I <lb/>again thank you. I remain    Yours sincerely   John <hi rend="underline">O</hi> Brien 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>