<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3542">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Lansbury to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 19 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Lansbury</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from George Lansbury (1859-1940) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), George communicates his sadness regarding the death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. George offers her his help and expresses his solidarity.

George Lansbury was a British politician who held socialist views and advocated for social justice, disarmament, and women&#39;s suffrage. He held various elected offices and was the editor of the Daily Herald, which he helped to establish. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3542</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1474">George Lansbury</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0962">21 Tudor Street, London, U.K.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1940</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3542_img_2946_1"  type="Letter"  url="3b8380b0c2b1141e966b5649f44ffd88.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3542_img_2946_1"/>
             THE LIMIT PRINTINIG AND<lb/>PUBLISHING CO., LTD.  TELEPHONE<lb/>CENTRAL <seg type="unclear">8991</seg>  THE HERALD<lb/>(The National Labour Weeekly)  EVERY SATURDAY. 21, TUDOR STREET, LONDON, E.C.   19-5-16    My dear Mrs. Sheehy Skewington,    I have just received your letter &amp; my heart is<lb/>  sad <seg type="unclear"></seg>for you &amp; your darling boy. May God in His<lb/>mercy bless &amp; preserve you.     The shocking brutality makes me blush for<lb/>very shame. But  we English are not all like that . Your<lb/>dear husbands sacrifice will bring us together with your<lb/>people &amp; somehow a real peace will get established.    Will you do us the favour here of always feeling we<lb/>are all your friends &amp; all of us want to help you in any way<lb/>possible, as please always write us if you think we can be<lb/>of the least service.  My wife joins in sending our united love<lb/>&amp;so does John  Gerald  <seg type="unclear">every well</seg><lb/>Mr P.  , W.H.  &amp; in fact all our staff         Always George Lansbury  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>