<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3485">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. MacSwiney to Tomás Mac Curtain, 27 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Áine MacSwiney (TBC)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter possibly written by Áine MacSwiney (sister of Terence MacSwiney 1879–1920). The letter is concerned with arrangements for a solicitor who is prepared to represent MacCurtain and the other men. 

Tomás MacCurtain (1884–1920), republican, was born Thomas Curtin in Ballyknockane, Co. Cork, on 20 March 1884. MacCurtain was a founder member of the Cork executive of the Irish Volunteers, and in the time leading up to the 1916 Rising, he travelled the county organising new Volunteer units. MacCurtain was arrested in Cork in May 1916, and sent to Dublin before being deported to Wakefield prison on 30 May. On 10 June he was moved to Frongoch in north Wales and on 11 July to Reading gaol, where he remained until his release in December 1916. He continued to lead the Cork Volunteers despite being imprisoned on other occasions in 1917. On 30 January 1920 he became the first Sinn Féin lord mayor of Cork. On 20 March 1920,  MacCurtain was shot dead in his bedroom a major escalation in the spiral of violence that marked the last year of the war of independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork Public Museum</repository>
                  <collection>T. Mac Curtain Collection, L1966.174 D9.7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3485</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0666">Áine MacSwiney (TBC)</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0294">Russell Hotel, St Stephen&#39;s Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0338">Tomás Mac Curtain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3485_img_2893_1"  type="Letter"  url="9947e3bc7c9e6e38251c9ecb907a8b0e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3485_img_2893_2"  type="Letter"  url="93bb781ce8463861df764566e38d6df6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3485_img_2893_3"  type="Letter"  url="297d503bad2cf35377f4230a92465155.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3485_img_2893_1"/>
             Hotel Russell<lb/>St Stephen's Green<lb/>Dublin    27-5-16    Dear Mr Curtin   After having left<lb/>you this morning, I called<lb/>on Mr Corrigan, the Solicitor,<lb/>&amp; asked him to act for<lb/>the men. I wished to know<lb/>if he would be available<lb/>when needed. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3485_img_2893_2"/>
             He is quite ready, but says<lb/>he cannot go to interview<lb/>the men unless he gets a<lb/>written request from each<lb/>one separately. I told him<lb/>we had heard there was<lb/>always a Summary first, &amp;<lb/>that counsel could be engaged<lb/>between that &amp; the trial. He<lb/>said that was so, but that<lb/>he naturally wanted to know<lb/>&amp; prepare his cases, &amp; that<lb/>anyone who wanted him  <lb/>should engage him at once.<lb/>He asked me to write to<lb/>you tonight, &amp; get you to<lb/>pass word round to the men<lb/>to write to him immediately  Will you please do so. Should<lb/>any be departed without trial,<lb/>or released, no harm will have<lb/>been done, &amp; those to be tried<lb/>would make a great mistake<lb/>by delaying. There is no reason<lb/>for delay, every reason for<lb/>having some definite<lb/>arrangement  I have asked <seg type="unclear">Jeremy</seg> to<lb/>write also. You can decide<lb/>with Mr Corrigan about the<lb/>Counsel 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3485_img_2893_3"/>
             L1966:174  On Monday. I can tell you<lb/>more about the interview.<lb/>This is just a hurried line<lb/>to ask you to get the men<lb/>to write at once. Please<lb/>tell them all from us to<lb/>be of good cheer (which we<lb/>know they will) &amp; to keep in<lb/>good form all round.   With kind regards,<lb/>Believe me<lb/>Sincerely yours,<lb/>A. MacSwiney.   L.<lb/>330<lb/>YI 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>