<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1246">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 21 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) regarding their everyday activities. James discusses the misconduct of Brother Long and the necessity of writing to Mrs Seery. Before signing off he reassures May of his love for her.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1246</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-01-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1661">National Health Insurance Commission, Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1246_img_435_1"  type="Letter"  url="fff5dcfda10680cb618a17fd9b9de110.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1246_img_435_2"  type="Letter"  url="cd7d5d394d423509b504e53406f2be3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1246_img_435_3"  type="Letter"  url="451db6ac76bbe4812bd8aee2bc6c1fa3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1246_img_435_1"/>
                NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION (IRELAND),  PEMBROKE HOUSE,  UPPER MOUNT STREET,    21 January, 1916.   My darling May,   I have a minute or two <lb/>to spare so I had better drop you <lb/>a line. I got your letter yesterday <lb/>but could not manage to find <lb/>time yesterday to reply and shall <lb/> have very little time now either <lb/> so you must let me down light <lb/>if I can't write much.  I was very sorry indeed to hear <lb/>of the cold and that it was so very  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1246_img_435_2"/>
              near having the lamentable result of <lb/>producing blossoms on your nose and <lb/> lips. What on earth would I do if <lb/> that happened and I looking forward <lb/>so anxiously to see you and — with <lb/> pluck — to kiss you in a few days. <lb/> However all's well that end's well and I <lb/>will pray for Corbett until my dying <lb/>day if his ointment cures the complaint <lb/> in time.  I was very jealous to hear about <lb/>Brother Long's conduct. I begin to see <lb/> that if a man has only cheek enough <lb/> he can do anything so you'd better look <cb/> out for trouble when I see you. By <lb/> the way while I think of it, I don't see <lb/>why you only received my letter on the <lb/>19th. I wrote to you on Sunday last <lb/> the 16th in time for post so you <lb/> should have had my letter on Monday <lb/> or <hi rend="underline">Tuesday at the very latest</hi>. I expect <lb/>the bould Paddie is neglecting his duties.  Mrs Seery's message is a rebuke to <lb/>me for not writing. If I can manage <lb/> a moment at all I will write to her <lb/> today but tell her in any case I <lb/>bear her in mind even though I don't <lb/> write. I'll have to keep her on my hands <lb/>for another few months anyhow. I was  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1246_img_435_3"/>
              glad to hear of Josephine's and M. for <lb/>Wynne's congratulations. I accept them for <lb/>myself anyhow — in your case I'm not <lb/> so sure but it should be sympathy <lb/>that should be offered you. That reminds <lb/>me that it's rather a shame for you to <lb/> be 'pulling my leg' about the plain country <lb/>girl and her worthlessness. Don't you <lb/>know very well that you're about a <lb/>million times too good for a chap like me. <lb/> As I hope for mercy, I can tell you that I <lb/>have asked God's pardon every day since you <lb/>promised me for having cheated you into <lb/>marriage with me. As I'm writing this in the <lb/> office you won't I suppose suspect me of not <lb/>being quite sober so I can say again that I love <lb/>you, May, and will, I hope, till the end. <seg type="closer"> Always your loving  <hi rend="underline">James</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>