<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5123">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 16, August, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Discusses Gernamy&#39;s push for peace. Fresh vegetables are plentiful.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5123</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-08-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5123_img_None_1"  url="c5bec205be9c74c29e95153857bb8d8d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5123_img_None_2"  url="a5c1e94ffdf3bb26f02ba669cc33822a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5123_img_0_1"/>
              I had a long epistle from Uncle Rob<lb/>3 days ago. <lb/> 16 August 1917    My dearest Daddy <lb/>No news but just a line as usual<lb/>to tell you all is well.  The weather is splendid again which<lb/>is a great blessing.  Apparently you have been getting<lb/>my letters very irregularly lately. That<lb/>was on account of my being away<lb/>from the batallion. <sic>Isee</sic> the old Pope<lb/>is talking of a German Peace again.<lb/>Germany is apparently working very<lb/>hard for peace now &amp; I should say<lb/>must be on her last legs. She will<lb/>get no peace till she come on her<lb/>knees &amp; begs for it. She knows<lb/>now that she as not a chance and<lb/>has got the wind up badly over this<lb/>push. <sic>Isee</sic> by the official German<lb/>wireless that they are preparing the<lb/>people for a great defeat. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5123_img_0_2"/>
             I met my namesake today. The<lb/>international football player. He<lb/>is a Lieut. Col in the R.A.M.E and is<lb/>near here.<sic> Iwas</sic> very glad to<lb/>get the opportunity of talking to him.  Our poor Doctor was killed last<lb/>week in the show.  We have nothing to do here &amp;<lb/>will be some time doing it I think.  The people here are very<lb/>decent and obli d ging.  The book which <seg type="unclear">Min</seg> sent came<lb/>a few days ago and I was<lb/>delighted to get it.<sic> Ihave</sic> lots of<lb/>time for reading here. We get<lb/>beautiful plums and tomatoes here<lb/>now &amp; any amount of fresh<lb/>vegetables.  No news but with very best<lb/>love to all.   Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>