<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2138">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegram from the Managing Editor, Central News to the Secretary, Dublin Castle, 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Managing Editor, Central News</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a telegram from the managing editor of the London Central News Agency to the secretary in Dublin Castle appealing against a decision to publish exclusive reports on events concerning Dublin affairs through the Press Association instead of Central News.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary’s Office Registered papers, CSO RP/1916/8640/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2138</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0980">Managing Editor, Central News</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Secretary, Dublin Castle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2138_img_1588_1"  type="Letter"  url="5b520dc3b88ed62a6da4545dd87083db.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2138_img_1588_2"  type="Letter"  url="88769a00f4482c25b2e3090d25f9b497.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2138_img_1588_1"/>
             XXX SECRETARY OF DUBLIN CASTLE DUBLIN   OUR SPECIAL CORRESPONDENT IN DUBLIN MR FITZPATRICK STATES HE HAS BEEN <lb/>INFORMED THAT FURTHER OFFICIAL COMMUNIQUES RE DUBLIN AFFAIRS WILL BE MADE <lb/>EXCLUSIVELY THROUGH PRESS ASSOCIATION CORRESPONDENT WE PRESUME THERE HAS <lb/>BEEN SOME MISUNDERSTANDING THE CENTRAL NEWS IS THE LARGEST HOME AND <lb/>FOREIGN NEWS AGENCY IN THE WORLD IF YOU REQUIRE ANY INFORMATION AS TO OUR
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2138_img_1588_2"/>
            (2) SECRETARY THE CASTLE DUBLIN <lb/>STANDING WE REFER YOU TO ANY OR ALL EDITORS OF DUBLIN NEWSPAPERS <lb/>MANAGING XXXXXXXXX EDITOR CENTRAL NEWS 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>