<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0693">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Clara Davidson, 27 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from James Davidson to his parents, he recounts the effect of an acute ear infection on his work and the organisation of the Machine Gun Company. He also reports the rumour of an imminent move to the trenches. This letter is part of a large correspondence from Davidson to his parents. Captain James Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/693</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">S.C. Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0693_img_2185_1"  type="Letter"  url="2668f4c3715856c3be3ed0724df7e0f3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0693_img_2185_2"  type="Letter"  url="04a3f5c7fa95e197b9824309c8edd7c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0693_img_2185_3"  type="Envelope"  url="be726d2b40323945cda6119cc0774d7a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0693_img_2185_1"/>
                27/1/16   My dearest Mother   — I have not written for<lb/> some days as I have had such a lot to do<lb/> &amp; think about &amp; now it is very late so<lb/> must make a very wee line do. Give<lb/> R. my love &amp; best thanks for her 2 letters &amp;<lb/> I had one from you today. Was so sorry<lb/> Mother dear that you had been poorly — hope<lb/> you have since been keeping better. The<lb/> weather at this time of year is very trying<lb/> for everyone. My throat though still<lb/> troublesome is better than it was a few days<lb/> ago. The inflammation got into my ear<lb/> &amp; as I could not lie up owing to having to<lb/> make all arrangements for the Machine Gun<lb/> Company. I became quite deaf with the right<lb/> ear &amp; felt perfectly wretched. Thank<lb/> goodness it is rather better now but even<lb/> when there is not much the matter it adds very<lb/> considerably to the burden of ones work.<lb/> Well the Machine Gun Company has been formed. <lb/> The Units arrived yest. &amp; by degrees things are<lb/> getting straightened out but there is so<lb/> much to be done in starting all the organisation<lb/> that sometimes it seems as if I should never<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0693_img_2185_2"/>
              get to the end of it. The other officers however<lb/> are working for all they are worth &amp; Dermot<lb/> Neill who is my Adjutant is splendid.  If we only get a few weeks to settle down<lb/> we shall be all right but there are strong<lb/> rumours going round of a move to the trenches<lb/> at an early date. Would you please<lb/> tell Furey when sending parcels to me not<lb/> to put 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Royal Irish Rifles on the address.<lb/> I enclose the label that was on the last one<lb/> &amp; of course it went to the Batt &amp; then had<lb/> to be forwarded. My address is now<lb/> Machine Gun Company, 108<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Infantry Brigade<lb/> 36<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division B. E. F. Would you please<lb/> tell them this in the Works. <seg type="closer"> With fondest love to all<lb/> Your loving son <lb/> James </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0693_img_2185_3"/>
              On Active Service<lb/> rcd 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Feb /16  Mrs S C Davidson<lb/>  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland    recd 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Feb /16<lb/> J Davidson<lb/> 27/1/16  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>