<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0515">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Local Government Board (LGB) to Cecil Pim, 11 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Local Government Board</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from the Local Government Board (LGB) to Cecil Pim of the Greenmount Spinning Company, requesting information on the reasons behind imposing &#39;short time&#39; hours on the employees in a number of Belfast linen mills, and whether it is due to shortage of raw materials or coal. The writer poses these questions to Pim so as to be &#39;prepared to meet demands which may arise for the relief of distress...&#39;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7443/14/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/515</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0699">Local Government Board</persName>
              <date>1916-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1501">Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1170">Cecil Pim</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1010">Greenmount Spinning Company, Harold's Cross, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0515_img_1887_1"  type="Letter"  url="d0834110a377e958a1fc27231ef810a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0515_img_1887_2"  type="Letter"  url="12d9b1e4441357411e91f7fcc608fb10.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0515_img_1887_1"/>
                Local Government Board,   Dublin.    11th March, 1916.   Dear Mr. Pim,   You have been good enough on previous occasions to <lb/> give me the benefit of your knowledge as to the conditions <lb/> prevailing in the linen trade in Belfast and I fell sure that <lb/> you will not object to doing so again. Such information as <lb/> you can give me will of course be confidential.   Some months ago as far as I can ascertain 'short time' <lb/> was imposed upon a number of Belfast Mills owing to the <lb/> difficulty and uncertainty as to the supply of raw materials. <lb/> Am I right in thinking that these difficulties have not been <lb/> so great as was anticipated and that by some means or other <lb/> the spinning and weaving trades are managing to get a <lb/> reasonably good supply of flax and yarn? If this is so at <lb/> the moment I suppose we may reasonably conclude that that <lb/> supply of raw material will somehow or other continue to be <lb/> sufficient to keep the mills going without recourse to short <lb/> time.'   Upon the other hand I hear that there is great <lb/> difficulty experienced in getting sufficient supplies of coal <lb/> in Belfast and that owing to a shortage in coal rather than a <lb/> shortage in material 'short time' prevails and may continue.   I am asking you these questions because as you know <lb/> we have to be prepared to meet demands which may arise for the <lb/> relief of distress as a consequence either of shortage in raw <lb/> material/  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0515_img_1887_2"/>
              material, coal or from any other cause. <lb/> With apologies for troubling you again.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,   Cecil Pim, Esq.,  c/o Greenmount Spinning Company,  Harold's Cross,  DUBLIN.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>