<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0149">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Patrick Farrell to Lord Wimborne, 27 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Patrick Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from James Patrick Farrell (1865-1921), MP for North Longford, to the desk of the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939). James Patrick Farrell (1865-1921) was an MP in West Cavan after the 1895 by-election and then North Longford from 1900 until 1918 general elections. Farrell was also founder, owner and editor of the Longford Leader newspaper.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/6258/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/149</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0110">James Patrick Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0610">Longford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0149_img_1271_1"  type="Letter"  url="a9e86d9f0ed44b8901a3566f13b38f47.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0149_img_1271_1"/>
                Longdord    March, 27th 1916  <lb/>To the Right Hon. Lord Wimbourne, <lb/>Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, <lb/>Dublin.  My Dear Lord Wimbourne -:   Pardon the liberty I take as <lb/>an old Parliamentary Colleague of Your Excellency in <lb/>the House of Commons, to recommend to your favourable <lb/>notice the application of Mr. Thomas W. Delany, Crown <lb/>Solicitor of the County of Longford, for the position <lb/>of Chief Crown Solicitor for Ireland, rendered vacant <lb/>by the death of Sir Malachy Kelly. I am sure that <lb/>amongst  t he profession in Ireland,there are many able <lb/>Solicitors well fitted to discharge the duties of <lb/>Chief Crown Solicitor, but I respectfully say that in <lb/>my opinion not one of them can equal either in tact <lb/>or ability, the gentleman whose name I have the honour <lb/>to submit to Your Excellency. Mr. Delany has a record <lb/>of public service here which few men of his class in <lb/>Ireland can <seg type="del">say</seg>show. He has in addition since the War began, <lb/>whole-heartedly thrown himself into the work of <lb/> securing recruits for the Irish Regiments. He is Vice-   letter incomplete  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>