<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1222">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nicholas Nally to the Lord Lieutenant, 17 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nicholas Nally</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Nicholas Nally, a petty sessions officer in Tipperary, to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Lord Wimborne, describing the case of Richard Carroll. The defendant, Carroll, was sentenced to six months&#39; hard labour for assaulting his wife. Nally reports that the Justices had wished to impose a higher sentence than was permitted on Carroll. The wife had her tongue bitten through and the hair off her body singed by a candle and Nally adds that it would be best if she and her relatives were kept out of contact with Carroll. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne (1873-1939) was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>CSO RP/1916/6834/3/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1222</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0396">Nicholas Nally</persName>
              <date>1916-05-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0442">Templemore, County Tipperary, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1222_img_408_1"  type="Letter"  url="dedb23901df4da30404bb6928c985d26.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1222_img_408_1"/>
                Petty Sessions Office  Templemore    17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916   <hi rend="underline">To His Excellency the Lord Lieutenant</hi><lb/> May it please your Excellency—   I am directed by the Justices to state<lb/> that the petitioner was convicted of an<lb/> aggravated assault upon his wife,<lb/> he blackened her eyes, bit her tongue<lb/> through, burnt the hair off her body<lb/> with a candle, he was sober at the<lb/> time but acted more like a wild beast<lb/><seg type="del">that </seg> than a human being, and at the<lb/> time of his conviction the Justices present<lb/> told him that they regretted it was not<lb/> in their power to inflict a heavier<lb/> sentence. According to the wife's evidence<lb/> and that of her relations this was not<lb/> the only occasion upon which he ill treated<lb/> her and they would therefore consider<lb/> it better for the petitioner's wife and<lb/> family to keep him away from them<lb/> for as long a period as possible-<lb/> No fine was imposed <seg type="closer"> I am<lb/> your <sic>Excellencys</sic><lb/> Most obedient Servant  Nich. Nally<lb/> C.P.S. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>