<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3896">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 24 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-46</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3896</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-03-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1820">8th Royal Irish Fusiliers, British Expeditionary Force, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2113">Melrose, Dalkey, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3896_img_3274_1"  type="Letter"  url="3eebf4c6913cfc5b07c93fb4539dc7f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3896_img_3274_2"  type="Letter"  url="d8ce76c5094182c92c46e5c7c2bc4f1c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3896_img_3274_1"/>
             Please ask Linn to thank Nellie for her letter received yesterday.   8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Royal Irish Fusiliers, <lb/>B. E. Force <lb/>France.  <lb/> 24 March 1916.   My dear Father,   Unless I chance upon my imagination I <lb/>am afraid this letter will prove rather uninteresting, <lb/>as I have little news to give you, no thrilling "hairs-breath" <lb/>escapes to account, (possibly because I have had my few <lb/>remaining locks cut recently), nor can I ever say that <lb/>thanks to a magnificent piece of horsemanship I <lb/>escaped a happy dispatch to a better world by jumping <lb/>over a passing shell. I must only fall back upon a <lb/>description of my day's work last Sunday, which <lb/>will show you that, at times at least, I am kept <lb/>pretty much on the go.   I started at seven in the morning by giving Holy <lb/>Communion to the men whose confessions I had heard <lb/>the previous evening, a goodly number I am <lb/>glad to say. This was followed by a number of <lb/>confessions in French for the townspeople and <lb/>some French soldiers — I am quite ready to face <lb/>any language at the present moment. This brought <lb/>me up to nine when my own <seg type="unclear">Last Mass Parade</seg>. <lb/>By chance the whole regiment were in the village
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3896_img_3274_2"/>
            <lb/>which meant of course that the church would <lb/>not hold them, so I had arranged for Mass <lb/> in the open. The spot I selected was a large <lb/>courtyard in front of the school&amp; whereby hangs <lb/>a tale. Armed with the Mayor's permission I <lb/>approached the schoolmaster for his sanction <lb/>and, I must say, found him most obliging <lb/>and very gracious, even helping to get things <lb/>ready. It was only afterwards that I discovered <lb/>that this man was a red-hot anti-clerical, <lb/>anti anything that was good in fact, quite <lb/>a bad lot, so that my request was about <lb/>the same as asking the Grand Master of <lb/>the Orange Lodge in Belfast for permission <lb/>to have Mass in his hall. He was so staggered <lb/>I suppose, by my innocent request he could <lb/>not find words to refuse, but the good folk <lb/>of the town are wild with delight and immensely <lb/>tickled by the idea of Mass in the porch of <lb/>his school above all people; needless to say <lb/>they have <seg type="unclear">rulled</seg>it into him well.   I had never celebrated Mass in the open air <lb/>before and I think the men were as much <lb/>impressed as I was. It was a glorious morning, <lb/>with just a sufficient spice of danger to <lb/>give the necessary warlike touch to the <lb/>picture by the presence of a German <seg type="unclear">airoplane</seg> <lb/>scouting near at hand. I was a nice bit <lb/>anxious lest a local might come down in
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>