<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0874">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of letter from Henry A. Robinson to Thomas Nally, 2 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry A. Robinson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a typescript copy of the handwritten letter from Henry Robinson (1857-1927) to Thomas Nally. Robinson states that he has read his play, the Spancel of Death, remarking that it is &#39;powerful&#39; and &#39;held me spell bound&#39;. He points out an historical inaccuracy in the play but concludes that the play will be a great success if staged. Sir Henry Augustus Robinson was an Irish public servant. He was primarily responsible for the drafting and implementation of the local government act of 1898, and shortly before the bill became law was appointed vice-president of the Local Government Board. Thomas Nally was an Irish playwright and colleague of WB Yeats. His work, the Spancel of Death, was due to open on Easter Tuesday 1916, the play was cancelled due to the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Thomas Nally Papers, MS 36,213/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/874</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1440">Henry A. Robinson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0210">Lisnacarrig, Foxrock, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1110">Thomas Nally</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0874_img_244_1"  type="Letter"  url="aa41a3b61a51ea8b54595f9cceed7f22.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0874_img_244_2"  type="Letter"  url="96acedeb01869b062b6df3766ef6f4f3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0874_img_244_1"/>
              COPY<lb/> of letter received from<lb/> Rt. Hon. Sir Henry A. Robinson, Bart., P.C., K.C.B.,<lb/> Vice—Chairman, Local Government Board,<lb/><lb/>re <lb/><hi rend="underline">'THE SPANCEL OF DEATH.'</hi><lb/> Note: Sir Henry A. Robinson expressed a wish to read the Play,<lb/> as his wife, Lady Robinson [<hi rend="underline">nee</hi> Miss Harriet Lynch—Blosse]<lb/> is one of the present—day representatives of the Lynch—<lb/> Blosse family, to affect one of the early members of which<lb/> [Sir Harry] the spell was performed.]    'Lisnacarrig,  Foxrock,  Co. Dublin,    2nd April, 1916.   'My <sic>sear</sic> Sir,   I have read your play and think it is the most<lb/> powerful and dramatic thing I have ever read. It held me spell—<lb/> bound.  I wonder if the Abbey people have any women in their<lb/> Company capable of doing justice to the part of Sibby Cottle?<lb/> It would need a Maire O'Neill.  My wife remembers Biddy Holian, — the last of the<lb/><sic>witche's</sic> race, and she had a bad name — an inheritance, I suppose,<lb/> from Judy.  Old Sir Harry Lynch—Blosse's evil reputation is a <lb/> tradition in the family even now; and my wife tells me that when<lb/> her father's generation suffered from gout, or other ailment, or<lb/> misfortune, they always regarded it as a visitations for the sins<lb/> of Sir Harry.  There is one little mistake you make which is a pity<lb/> in a story which is otherwise historically accurate. You make  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0874_img_244_2"/>
              Lord Oranmore the person who is arranging the marriage with<lb/> Altamount's daughter. Now, the Oranmore peerage was only created<lb/> in 1836, and Sir Harry's period was nearly 100 years earlier.  The play will create a great sensation if properly<lb/> staged. The dialogue is so natural that I can almost hear the<cb/> people speaking.  Wishing you every luch with it, and with many thanks for<lb/> your courtesy in letting me see it, <seg type="closer"> I remain,<lb/> Yours sncy,  H.A. Robinson. </seg> I omitted to mention that my wife doesn't see any reason why <lb/> any of her family should object to the play. I will register it<lb/> and send it back to—morrow.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>