<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2379">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David Augustin Quaid to the Lords Justices (Ireland), 24 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David Augustin Quaid</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from David Augustin Quaid, a Dublin solicitor, to the Lords Justices (Ireland), applying for the vacant position of Clerk of Crown and Peace for County Westmeath, stating that the Incorporated Law Society and Major General Sir Lovick Bransby Friend (1856-1944), removed as Commander-in-Chief, Ireland following the 1916 Easter Rising, would provide testimony in support of his candidacy. 

He mentions two examples of how he made unpopular decisions - removing Professor Kuno Meyer (1858–1919) from the Freeman Roll of Dublin City in 1915 for his pro-German views, and preventing the laying of a commemorative slab on Batchelor&#39;s Walk (in memory of the Howth gun-running incident of 1914).  These actions led to Quaid having to carry a weapon because of threats received.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5615/10763</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2379</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1099">David Augustin Quaid</persName>
              <date>1916-06-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0708">9 &amp;amp; 10 Eustace Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lords Justices for Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2379_img_1823_1"  type="Letter"  url="2428dc956f5bec1e836d0cb4e489e2bb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2379_img_1823_2"  type="Letter"  url="1e64aa27184f9d78fe21eaae06605dd8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2379_img_1823_1"/>
              Offices: 9 &amp; 10 Eustace Street, <lb/>Dublin,    24th June 1916    May it please Your Excellencies,   May I be permitted to place myself before Your Excellencies <lb/> as a candidate for the Clerkship of the Crown and Peace for the County of <lb/>Westmeath now vacant.   I have been for 18 years a practising Solicitor, and as such would <lb/> refer Your Excellencies to the Incorporated Law Society, the secretary <lb/> and Registrar of which will answer any inquiries.   Being in the public life of this city as an Alderman of the <lb/> Corporation, I have had from time to time to take steps in my public <lb/> capacity in the interests of the State, as for instance notwithstanding <lb/> methods of intimidation adopted towards me and unpopularity incurred <lb/> in some ranges of public opinion, I felt it my duty to remove from the <lb/> Freemen Roll of this city a dangerous Spy Professor Kuno Meyer, who was <lb/> engaged in espionage for 18 years in Liverpool, and, subsequently at the <lb/> insistence of the Military Authority, I succeeded in defeating the projected <lb/> laying down of a commemorative slab on Bachelors Walk by disaffected <lb/> persons which it was intended, should mark the site of casualties there <lb/> on the day of the Howth Gun Running affair To accomplish this I had <lb/> to get rescinded a resolution of the Paving Committee of the Dublin <lb/> Corporation authorising the laying down of the stone.   In consequence of my action which so far as Professor Kuno Meyer
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2379_img_1823_2"/>
            was concerned, deprived him of power to suggest In the States <lb/> that he was a Freeman of Dublin, notwithstanding his attitude, and, so far <lb/> as the Bachelors Walk incident was concerned, prevented riot and bloodshed, <lb/> I received many threatening letters as a result of which I had to apply <lb/> to the Chief Commissioner of Police for permission to carry a revolver <lb/> for my own protection.   As to the assistance I may have given the Military Authorities, I <lb/>would refer Your Excellencies to Major General Friend C. B. lately in <lb/>the Irish Command, who indeed was good enough to personally appreciate my <lb/>action more than once by his letters.   I place my application before the Executive Government, trusting <lb/> that it may see its way to favourably consider it, my professional inter— <lb/> having, unfortunately, in the state of public opinion in this City <lb/> been detrimentally affected.     I am <lb/> Your Excellencies obedient servant,   David A Quaid    Their Excellency's the Lords Justices in the Government of Ireland, <lb/> Dublin Castle. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>