<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6708">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frank P. Walsh to all State Chairmen and City Chairmen, 30  December 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frank P. Walsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Frank P. Walsh (1864-1939), was an American lawyer and political reformer. He was one of the chief architects of the legislative struggle against industrial exploitation of children and an advocate of Irish and anti-imperialist causes. He also fought for civil liberties and was a labour partisan and staunch New Dealer. Walsh was a member of the Irish-American delegation (along with Michael J. Ryan and Edward F. Dunne) who were appointed to represent Ireland at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919. On 10 April 1919 the delegation arrived in Paris. The men returned to America in July 1919 where Walsh began working with the Dail External Loan (Bond Drive).
In this letter, State and City chairmen are urged to avail of local picture houses, to display notices regarding the bond drive for the public to see. Chairmen are also advised to circulate literature regarding the work of the drive to those who may be called upon to work in the drive in January. Doing so may help those being called upon to understand the intricate workings of the bond certificates such as payment options. As well as this, being familiar with the literature on the bond drive may enable workers to canvas for the republic in a positive way. By having those involved in the drive familiar with the campaign, Walsh suggests, the people would be more willing to work within the bond drive.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>William Bourke Cockran Papers, Box 13, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6708</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0925">Frank P. Walsh</persName>
              <date>1919-12-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1646">New York</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">State Chiarmen; City Chairmen</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6708_img_None_1"  url="phpSOylF0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6708_img_0_1"/>
             American Commission on Irish Independence<lb/>Frank P. Walsh Chairman   411 Fifth Avenue<lb/>New York    December 30, 1919   To:<lb/>State Chairmen:<lb/>City Chairmen:  <hi rend="underline">Re- Moving Picture Publicity</hi>: No doubt you have had it in<lb/>mind to make use of the good offices of moving picture places in your<lb/>city, during the week of the Bond-Certificate Campaign. As a rule,<lb/>the managers of these popular places are quite willing to cultivate<lb/>the good will of their patrons by displaying, without charge, a notice,<lb/>which, while it involves no sacrifice of time, constitutes a very valu-<lb/>able reminder. We would suggest that the arrangements for this useful<lb/>free publicity ought to be made well in advance, and as soon as possible,<lb/>as there will be many visitors of pressing detail to attend to once the<lb/>campaign begins.  <hi rend="underline">Advance Literature</hi>: We have had several suggestions that<lb/>persons who will eventually be called upon by team workers might be in<lb/>a more receptive mood if they had already had the chance to read and<lb/>ponder the enclosed address by President De Valera, which would be sent<lb/>to them by mail a week or so in advance of their being called upon.<lb/>State Chairmen are invited to consider this suggestion with their City<lb/>and County Chairmen, and, if they think well of it, to proceed with the<lb/>necessary printing of the quantities they consider essential, without<lb/>waste.<lb/>- - - - - - - - - - - - - - -  To the Chairmen: At the turn of the year, I take the oppor-<lb/>tunity of expressing to all State, County and City Chairnmen the ap-<lb/>preciatin of all at Headquarters for their splendid and most encour-<lb/>aging co-operation. Thanks to what they have already accomplished, we<lb/>now know that a campaign, covering all our principal cities, with<lb/>every prospect of a splendid succss, is assured for the week of Janu-<lb/>ary 17th-26th. President De Valera joins with me in this expression,<lb/>and in wishing you a Happy and Prosperous New Year.  Very truly yours,   Frank P. Walsh<lb/>Chairman  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>