<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0111">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">A letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 27 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Helena Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin in Dublin. Marie is writing home to tell her mother the news from the front and to hear about the news back home. In this letter Marie asks her mother to send her out some gloves, a scarf and a coat. She writes that her six months are nearly over and that she hopes to be returning home soon. Marie focuses on the family news that she has heard and gives advice to her mother about the health of her relations.Marie Martin, later, known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39; was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/1/69, B/F/1/69</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/111</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0618">Marie Helena Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-10-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_1"  type="Letter"  url="9ead6951366e43a6d4f90eac4da045dd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_2"  type="Letter"  url="320e4f6912aa8c0bb0b05eee438ec393.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_3"  type="Letter"  url="f8219129b6d5b8e45d2819dbf3c3249a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_4"  type="Letter"  url="68948663d4264052935d18ea91cca2c8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_5"  type="Letter"  url="0268e5ebec5a0068526da2d9e4fdabb2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_6"  type="Letter"  url="d3d586b226b265702b34e7fe8e313e43.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_7"  type="Letter"  url="7388bcd3123b62c220cb86cf1e933217.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0111_img_1194_8"  type="Letter"  url="2513d2b1ece068e75c9422e98999ac02.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_1"/>
              B/F/1/70    27-10-16   My very dearest Mother,   A 1000 thanks for the very <lb/> nice letter of the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> enclosing Tommys <lb/>letter. you have no idea how it <sic>cheer</sic><lb/> me up to hear of him as it seemed <lb/>ages— what an absolute brick he is <lb/> never seems to grumble at any thing <lb/>&amp; every is going through more things <lb/> he is. I think they must be having <lb/>a very trying time of it out there <lb/> they are so queerly situated with Greece <lb/>&amp; the fighting <sic>seem</sic> bad enough at <lb/> times. I really think we are doing <lb/>very well now, the news from here is <lb/> very good &amp; they are expecting to hear <lb/>great things in a day or two— <lb/> I must also thank you for the regular <lb/>P.C. with news of Uncle Frank I was <lb/> so glad to hear last night he had <lb/>been up for a bit &amp; sincerely hope  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_2"/>
              he was none the worse after it. I hope <lb/> Aunt Maysie will not knock her self <lb/>up as I do not think she has been <lb/> very strong lately either— I hope he <lb/>likes his two nurses as I find it makes <lb/> a great difference to the welfare of <lb/>the patient. I am sorry to hear Granny <lb/> has been hard up again, &amp; poor <lb/>Aunt Sissy, I wonder if she would try the <seg type="unclear">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></seg> I sent to Uncle Frank <lb/>It seems so terrible if she could be <lb/>cured not to give herself every chance <lb/>Oh I had such a nice long letter <lb/> from Aunt Eveleen, it pleased me more <lb/>than any thingas she told me how <lb/> you were looking etc &amp; since I came out <lb/>here I have heard from very few of the <lb/> relation Of course I never have time to <lb/>write so cannot expect them to write but <lb/> she gave me all the family news in great <lb/>form— She also sent me a ripping cake. <lb/>I want you the next time Dr. Beatty <lb/>goes to Greenbank to ask him for a  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_3"/>
              real good cure for chilblains as I <lb/> have them very badly on my feet <lb/>even up the shins of my legs &amp; they <lb/> are just coming on my hands— We <lb/>have had some very cold &amp; wet days. <lb/> &amp; with skin cases one is continually <lb/>washing &amp; dabbling <sic>is</sic> some lotion <lb/> or other. I went in the other day to <lb/>B.— &amp; bought myself a dear little <lb/>oil stove which warms the room <lb/>beautiful I am <sic>a</sic> present sitting <lb/> beside it &amp; feel quite cosy. the only <lb/>thing is I think they are inclined <lb/> to give you a headach— <lb/>I am enclosing you £2-0-0 &amp; would be so <lb/> pleased if you would pay for a pr of <lb/>Shoes I had sent out to me here— <lb/> Also the next time you are in town <lb/>will you get me a very warm pair <lb/> of Fur gloves it does not matter how <lb/>clumsy they look so long as they  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_4"/>
              are warm easily put on &amp; off— Also <lb/> a navy blue silk scarf &amp; one of those <lb/><sic>Shetlan</sic> jackets that I could wear under <lb/> my <sic>overal</sic> but over my dress if you <lb/>can get one in sax blue all the better— <lb/>I am sending you an other £-1.0-0 <lb/> as you will not have quite enough <lb/>&amp; if you have 12/-6 over will you <lb/> send it into <seg type="unclear">Arnotts</seg> for 3 aprons they <lb/>send out to me at the beginning— <lb/> Should you have paid for any of these <lb/>things just keep the money instead <lb/> Hoping this is not giving you a great <lb/>deal of trouble— <lb/> What <sic>a bout apresent</sic> for Charlie <lb/> O'Kelley I will let you know in a <lb/>week or two if I can get some little <lb/> thing out here for them— <lb/>I &amp; Miss Paul gave our men a tea <lb/> party yesterday afternoon it was <lb/>rather a undertaking as we happened  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_5"/>
              to fill up on Thursday morning at <lb/> 5 A.M. &amp; just one very bad case of <lb/>Erysipelas among the lot which gave <lb/> me <sic>avery</sic> anxious day as he was <lb/>put on the D.I. list &amp; needed <sic>agreat</sic><lb/> deal of watching but I am glad to <lb/>say he was <sic>transfered</sic> to a room <lb/> to him self at 4 O'ck which left me <lb/>much freer for the tea which was <lb/> a great success but is a thing <lb/>that can only be done very seldom <lb/> as it cost a fair sum—as you will <lb/>know— however it is better spent that <lb/> way than wasted on trash for one <lb/>self &amp; they do enjoy it &amp; deserve it <lb/> I have such a nice lot of men who <lb/>do so much for me— you see in <lb/> skin wards we only have one orderly <lb/>&amp; he has to do all the dressing we <lb/> cannot do, like Seabees all over— <lb/>so that means the Sister in Charge has to  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_6"/>
              get the patients to do all the ward <lb/> work as well as the kitchen, it is <lb/>really much <seg type="del">for</seg> more difficult for <lb/> us but I have been extremely lucky <lb/>&amp; have 4 <seg type="unclear">topping</seg> men, one is just <lb/> like a father to us, one does feel such <lb/>a brute some times when one thinks <lb/> of all they do for us and how little we <lb/>can really do in return— <lb/> I have not heard from Gerald Cutify <lb/>so do not know where he is I <lb/> wonder if he has been home in the <lb/>mean time— Please give every one <lb/> my fondest love also Nana &amp; tell <lb/>her I shall try &amp; write very soon I <lb/> am ashamed to think I have <lb/>never written — how is she working <lb/> on — by the way did Nidia K— <lb/>ever turn up to see you was it <lb/> not funny how I managed to <lb/>get over— they have teased me so <lb/> much here because I am such  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_7"/>
              a bad walker. I thought I would <lb/> have a try &amp; succeeded but I did <lb/>suffer for it the stiffness was something <lb/> terrible however it did me no <lb/>real harm &amp; I walked over 15 <lb/> miles— I hope her mother is better <lb/>My six months are very nearly over <lb/> &amp; am expecting every day now to <lb/>be asked to resign and will get what <lb/> for from the Matron it will be <lb/>nearly as bad as Granny's <seg type="unclear">intirocen</seg><lb/> &amp; one has to give such a long reason <lb/>for resigning, however I am coming <lb/> home &amp; looking forward to it to &amp; <lb/>perhaps after Xmas Ethel would <lb/> like to come away for a bit— <lb/>I feel sure it will do her good <lb/> she has had the hardest part all <lb/>the time &amp; I feel that I have <lb/> done a little &amp; can always find <lb/>some work at home—  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0111_img_1194_8"/>
              I am longing to be at home <lb/> with you all again <lb/> How is Uncle Charlie these times <lb/> I have not heard from him <lb/> for ages I shall write to <lb/> him in a day or two <lb/> Fondest love dearest Mother <lb/> and Cheer Oh. I think the war will <lb/> soon be over— <seg type="closer"> Your most loving and ever <lb/> grateful daughter   Marie </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>