<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0421">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from B. B. Cubitt, War Office, to Sir Matthew Nathan, 2 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Bertram B. Cubitt</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Bertram B. Cubitt (1862-1942), assistant under-secretary of State at the War Office to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), under-secretary for Ireland. A Mrs. E. Morgan has been tried for illegally drawing Army Separation Allowance and is now required to make restitution. This letter concerns a sum of £5 already recovered and the writer requests that this amount be remitted to the Regimental Paymaster in Dublin. For reference purposes, he supplies details regarding the soldier concerned in this case. A handwritten note in the margin, by assistant under-secretary for Ireland, Sir Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926), gives further accounting instructions.Cubitt was originally appointed to the War Office in 1886 and was under-secretary of state from 1914 until his retirement in 1926. Nathan was appointed under-secretary in 1914 but resigned after the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/20438</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/421</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0807">Bertram B. Cubitt</persName>
              <date>1915-12-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0372">War Office, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0421_img_1716_1"  type="Letter"  url="48ab536ef63883828a32782fc13d2213.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0421_img_1716_1"/>
              M.A <lb/>Any further communication on this <lb/> subject should be addressed toâ <lb/> The Secretary, <lb/> War Office, <lb/> London S.W., <lb/> and the following number quoted. <lb/>46/M/629. Accounts 3.    War Office,  London, S.W.     2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> December, 1915.   Sir,   With reference to your letter N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>18367 of the <lb/> 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> November, I am commanded by Army council to <lb/> request that you will be so good so to remit to the <lb/> Regimental Paymaster, Dublin, the sum of Â£5 recovered <lb/>from Mrs E. Morgan in respect of Separation Allowance <lb/> irregularly drawn by her.  The official description of the soldier <lb/>concerned is N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. 6926 Private J.Morgan, 4th Royal Irish <lb/> Rifles and it would assist the Regimental Paymaster <lb/> in dealing with the case if these particulars are <lb/> embodied in your letter. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   B B Cubitt </seg> Request Mr Moorehead <lb/> C.S. to forward cheque, <lb/> payable to the <lb/> Regimental Paymaster <lb/> Dublin, for Â£5 <lb/> plus any sums <lb/> since paid in <lb/> by Mrs Morgan. <lb/> Inquire as to person <lb/> nominated to receive <lb/> her weekly payments <lb/> of 10/- <lb/>4/12/15  The Under Secretary, Dublin Castle, DUBLIN.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>