<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3617">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Russell Williams to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 10 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Russell Williams</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Thomas Russell Williams (1869 – 1926) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) expressing condolences in regards to the death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. He writes of his respect for Francis and his fond memories of their time together.

Thomas Russell Williams was a British socialist politician and member of the Labour Party.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3617</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0442">Thomas Russell Williams</persName>
              <date>1916-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1192">33 Victoria Terrace, Leeds, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3617_img_3016_1"  type="Letter"  url="005ae17a42e6ed520d05589e7d836fda.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3617_img_3016_1"/>
             33 Victoria Terrace<lb/>Leeds.   <hi rend="underline">10 3 16</hi>    Dear M<hi rend="underline">rs </hi>Sheehy Skeffington.   From the bottom of my heart I<lb/>offer you sympathy in this hour of your<lb/>terrible trial. It must be nearly ten years<lb/>since I met you <seg type="del">and</seg>and your brave<lb/>husband in your own home; but I have<lb/>always cherished the memory of that visit<lb/>and have read with <seg type="unclear">avidity</seg>whatever<lb/>I have seen regarding his activities.  The lengthening list of Irish martyrs<lb/>includes none whose vision was<lb/>clearer regarding our unfortunate<lb/>country's needs.   Yours sincerely <lb/><hi rend="underline">T Russell Williams</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>