<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2963">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 13 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lillian in which he  discusses a flat which Lillian has moved into. He writes about the accomplishments of his Division, the problems faced by it, and the internal politics of its leadership. Spender expresses the hope that he will be granted leave to return home around Christmas, and mentions his anxiety at the possibility that his brother Rex will soon be sent to the front.

This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender  née Dean, (1880-1968)The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.

Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1916 served at Advanced General Headquarters, his duties mainly involving the writing of reports for the cabinet, for the Press, and for posterity. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund during the war, and a member of the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/101</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2963</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2963_img_2369_1"  type="Letter"  url="043094d66c34605759f0951fe32f622c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2963_img_2369_2"  type="Letter"  url="a651015a0e4ee828d0d5a0ce2b4a62e0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2963_img_2369_1"/>
              I must send <lb/>Rex a line or <lb/>two. I'm so <lb/>glad to hear of <lb/>Julie's renewed <lb/>health &amp; wish <lb/>she could have <lb/>paid "us" a visit, <lb/>a pleasure deferred to <lb/>when and where?   I have <lb/>heard from <lb/>Coachman <lb/>rather a miserable <lb/>bitter poor fellow.   Good bye to my pr <lb/>from the bw <lb/>who is always hers   You can strike the <lb/>3 Trench Mortar <lb/>battalion out of <lb/>your list for <lb/>comforts    13 Dec   My pr   I expect to hear that there is a rather aggrieved little pr <lb/>at having nothing to feed upon except some buff leaves &amp; a 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> <lb/>hand roll - rather stale sent via Mater - especially as she sent <lb/>3 on one day to feed a hungry wolf. Well he was busy <lb/>foraging, &amp; tho' he would gladly have written more after being <lb/>up all night, he really couldn't find the time.   I am most eager to hear about the result of the flat <lb/>whether the pr has succumbed &amp; given up 5 little guinea pigs, <lb/>or whether her attractions &amp; persuasions have got a reduction to 4 1/2 <lb/>or perhaps even 4 gns?? Any-how I shall expect a very very <lb/>good letter pr if it is 4 or over. Letter just came telling of your <lb/>distractions about the flat. I hope you have settled as of course the <lb/>bw does not want you to worry yourself to death trying to save <lb/>a few shillings. I agree with you that you must be near your <lb/>work &amp; you had better get a house than a flat if it is one you <lb/>can manage so easily. You had better make certain that the option <lb/>of leaving rests with you ie that they cannot turn you out <lb/>or demand higher rent 'in the season". The agents might have <lb/>agreed to a reduction in rent after so many weeks occupation.   The enclosed from Rex makes me anxious especially if it <lb/> means his going to the 107 Bde now in the trenches tho' I under
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2963_img_2369_2"/>
            stand the details are often <lb/>kept at Havre for some time, &amp; by then the 107 Bde may be back.   I asked the Brigade Major of the attached Regular Bde what <lb/>he thought of the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, which have been attached to him &amp; <lb/>he replied that the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> was a first class battalion, but the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>had no officers worth anything and very few <seg type="del">men</seg>  NCOs , &amp; that tho' the <lb/>men seemed a good lot, they were little more than a rabble now <lb/>This after 15 months is pretty disheartening, &amp; is a fair condem— <lb/>nation of Gen H..W who however in other respects has shown <lb/>himself quite a useful Brigadier <seg type="unclear">Kene</seg> &amp; very active, but he is a <lb/>clever chap &amp; plays up to our Gen's whims in a way which <lb/>I suppose exemplifies the "good politician" of the past, but please <lb/>heaven not the type of the future.   Henry hopes to get leave for Xmas so if things go well I <lb/>may get away by the End of January. He is being sent <lb/>partly on duty.    R &amp; I <seg type="del">We</seg> had a great success yesterday. Comyn came in &amp; asked <lb/>if R &amp; I would help with the entertainment as A was so busy. I <lb/>said we should be delighted if Singleton took a turn. C hesitated <lb/>&amp; said he was very busy but that he C would take a turn. I <lb/>absolutely refused on those conditions &amp; pointed out that old S was <lb/>in the office less than any of us, had <seg type="unclear">Cursons</seg> to help for him, <lb/>&amp; finally that at the beginning of the war I had done DAA <lb/>for 2 months for 40000 men without any one's help &amp; also <lb/>without a DAQMG. This clinched the matter &amp; old heavy weather <lb/>was up from 11 till 8 AM this morning so the ice is <seg type="del">p</seg> broken &amp; all <lb/>is now well. S will try &amp; get back at me probably but that does not <lb/>matter, &amp; C is probably glad to have had my ultimatum to stiffen his hands.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>