<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4614">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to Henry Duke, 5 June 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941) had a varied career in the Irish civil service; he moved to the Ministry of Home Affairs in Northern Ireland before resigning prematurely in 1925. As private secretary to Augustine Birrell, the Chief Secretary whose resignation was prompted by the 1916 Rising, Magill was well placed to observe the often bizarre workings of the pre-revolutionary Irish administration. His subsequent postings in Dublin and Belfast likewise made him an invaluable witness of conflicts associated with revolution and partition.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-234</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4614</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1917-06-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Henry Duke</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4614_img_3954_1"  type="Letter"  url="c992fadac0fef58574b4e4b907dd7d70.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4614_img_3954_2"  type="Letter"  url="0c741cbb11d165d08812cc08bd9ebae8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4614_img_3954_3"  type="Letter"  url="93f74ce7678939a406586ca0bbefbf4e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4614_img_3954_1"/>
             5th JUNE 17   To, <lb/>the Right Hon. <lb/>The Chief Secretary for Ireland, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   Sir,   I am directed by the President and Fellows of <lb/>the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to send <lb/>you the enclosed copy of a resolution which was <lb/>passed, <seg type="foreign">nomine contradicente</seg>, at the monthly <lb/>business meeting of the College held on Friday the <lb/>1st instant.   I have the honour to be <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4614_img_3954_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Copy of Resolution.</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Resolved</hi>: "That the Royal College of Physicians of <lb/>Ireland have observed that in the House of Commons on <lb/>April 19, 1917, the Right Hon. The Chief Secretary for <lb/>Ireland, speaking about Summer time, stated that he <lb/>desired to obtain the opinion which non in Ireland in <lb/>practical business have formed on the subject; and <sic>tha</sic> <lb/>if he came to the conclusion that before the time of <lb/>harvest some action should be taken, he would submit a <lb/>proposal to the Government.   The President and Fellows desire to express <lb/>their conviction that Summer time is of the greatest <lb/>value to the health of the community. They feel that <lb/>for all workers, and especially for those dwelling in <lb/>towns or whose occupation is carried on indoors, to <lb/>have an hour's extra daylight in the evenings after <lb/>their work is done is of the very greatest advantage. <lb/>The President and Fellows believe that the system of
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4614_img_3954_3"/>
            the cultivation of Allotments by artisans and other <lb/>workers and their families is a very important <lb/>means, not only of providing food but also of pro- <lb/>viding health; they trust that this system will be <lb/> developed to its utmost, and they feel that for this <lb/> allotment work Summer time is most valuable.    The President and Fellows of the Royal College <lb/>of Physicians of Ireland therefore trust that the <lb/>Summer<seg type="del">e</seg> time Act will be made permanent, so as to <lb/> come into force automatically every year." 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>