<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4523">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 24 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis M. Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw to Father Provincial regarding Francis M. Shaw&#39;s delayed letter and his future meeting with Father Frank Browne and Father Fitzgibbon. Also he writes that he was not in the front line of the battle.

Francis M. Shaw worked in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. He was ordained on 31st July 1916 at Milltown Park in Dublin and in 1917 was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia, possibly due to his nationalistic views.

Fr. Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/7-8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4523</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1425">Francis M. Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-07-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1941">Paris, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr. Thomas V. Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4523_img_3866_1"  type="Letter"  url="44368fd51fdc5c26a44195a2a6aba24d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4523_img_3866_2"  type="Letter"  url="7e4710168b52748599785d29fc407607.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4523_img_3866_1"/>
             24 July 1916   Dear F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Provincial, <lb/>P.C.   I forget whether I have written to your Reverence since <lb/>I became a military Chaplain, There is really very little to <lb/>report. Today my unit was transferred to an entirely different <lb/>sphere of action. As things are as present I run a very good <lb/>chance of being able to meet Fathers Frank Browne and <lb/>Fitzgibbon. But orders change at such short notice, one can <lb/>never count on things turning out in any particular way. I find <lb/>from a letter from Milltown, that F<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">r</hi></hi> Roche and myself must have <lb/>been rather near neighbours during the last three weeks. I <lb/>have already been often under shell fire, but have not <lb/>had any really alarming experiences. I buried two men <lb/>in the dead of night, in the interval between some enemy <lb/>arrivals, one of which actually fell in the cemetery. The <lb/>others were just close enough to be joked about. I have <lb/>not been yet in the actual trenches — I was in our H.Q. <lb/>— a dug-out; about 300 yards from the front line, but <lb/>the water was over knee-deep in the trenches beyond, and <lb/>I did not go on. Then we came out of the line and I had <lb/>no need to go a-trenching. I need hardly tell you I don't <lb/>go out of my way to collect bits of German lead or shrapnel. <lb/>if they come in the course of the game, that is the Lord's <lb/>look-out. Before my arrival in these parts I met <lb/>Fr Graham S.J. marching through a village with his division. <lb/>He got sub-deaconate and deaconate last year at Milltown. <lb/>Fr. Strickland S.J. (One of the Italian Provinces) is in my division, <lb/>but is giving up. He is well on in years; and twenty-two <lb/>months at the front are telling on him.   I have heard some interesting news of the Province from
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4523_img_3866_2"/>
            Milltown. I imagine the selections for the team to <lb/>tour in Australia gave matter fro harmless conversation. <lb/>I hope your Reverence will send out the new <lb/>status, as everything concerning the Province is of <lb/>great interest here.   I met a wounded lad in hospital (field ambulance) <lb/>about ten days ago, from no.6 up. Gardiner St. I forgot <lb/>his name for the moment - I think it was Evans. - <lb/>he was only slightly hurt. There are crowds of <lb/>Irish lads with other units I come in contact with <lb/>constantly, and I sometimes envy their Padres. <lb/>I enclose a note for F<hi rend="underline">r</hi> Farley with no of masses <lb/>I said for him during July. I shall send on <lb/>a cheque for the the £12, advanced by you for <lb/>outfit purposes.   I hope your Reverence's prayers will not be <lb/>wanting <seg type="del">to me</seg> that I may "carry on" in the <lb/>right way, &amp; help to win some souls for God.   Yours very sincerely in Christ,   Francis M. Shaw S.J.   P.S/ In my last billet (on the way up here) I found myself in a <lb/>convent. The two nuns who were there learned from the <lb/>interpreter that I was S.J. and when I arrived I was put into <lb/>"<seg type="foreign">dortoir</seg>St. Ignace." Next door was "<seg type="foreign">Dortoir</seg> St. Augustus." 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>