<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4119">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Last page of this letter is missing (possibly not photographed). Assuming it is from Emma Duffin (1883 - 1979) to her mother, Maria Duffin (1854-1954) as it is sent from Egypt where Emma was serving as a V.A.D. at the time.

Emma was the fourth daughter and fifth child of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She was educated at Cheltenham Ladies College. Emma served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. She served initially in Egypt and was transferred to northern France just before the Battle of Somme, where she remained to the Armistice in 1918. On her return to Belfast, Emma worked as an illustrator of cards and books, including children’s stories written by her sister Ruth. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4119</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1134">Emma Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1413">Khedivial Hotel, Alexandria, Egypt</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4119_img_3495_1"  type="Letter"  url="b30b750a3d77197cdd961769ad981d4c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4119_img_3495_2"  type="Letter"  url="46ef9591a8bf60d0128e00a3312e2c72.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4119_img_3495_3"  type="Letter"  url="be5009705b06e499d1e7902909cb8c04.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4119_img_3495_4"  type="Letter"  url="6fb946ff53a91a8473e7cd8476a03138.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4119_img_3495_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/B   Khedivial Hotel Alexandria    Nov. 22/15    My dearest Mamma   Your letter with the great news about <seg type="unclear">Drosie</seg><lb/>&amp; me from her herself arrived on the 20<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>. I am sure it is<lb/>the best thing that could happen to her, &amp; it sounds very nice. I was<lb/>glad to <seg type="unclear"></seg>  details for she gave me really were. I know how<lb/>anxious you &amp; Papa will be until you see him. I hate to think<lb/>they may be married before I get home, as indeed they most<lb/>likely will be, for all being well I have 5 months in front of me<lb/>still. I try   hardly say, <seg type="del">where</seg>some me to share the news<lb/>with, let me know when I may tell Molly! Let me have more<lb/>details when you can, I presume he is not well off, but no one can<lb/>expect the that after this war. I am awfully glad about it,<lb/>but we will all miss him a lot, won't we? I am very happy<lb/>but there is no cause for your suspicions, the only me I have<lb/>met so far have all been married! Yesterday we got<lb/>paid £15 up till the end of October all expenses of board etc.<lb/>having been deducted, so that is pocket money to do what we like with<lb/>we nearly fainted with surprise, but it appears we get colonial<lb/>allowance for active service of 3/— a day, and various other allowances<lb/>too, this includes our time on the boat so we will not get<lb/>quite so much next time but as far as I can see we will have<lb/>about £10 a month free, so Papa's £10 will certainly not be   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4119_img_3495_2"/>
             D2109/9/4/B  <hi rend="underline">2</hi>  required. I am awfully glad about it, for though I<lb/>don't mean to spend it all, still it is a pity not to have some<lb/>cash to go about to see things &amp; buy things which we might never<lb/>have the chance of seeing &amp; buying again. I must also<lb/>acknowledge your £20, it is really splendid to have that, we went<lb/>out straight away &amp; bought some books &amp; papers, flowers &amp;<lb/>sweets, &amp; the men were delighted. The Australians love, what<lb/>they Call lollys, any form of sweets &amp; they all delight in<lb/>having flowers. Tell Mrs. <seg type="unclear">Heyn</seg> I will spend her £1 on flowers<lb/>and I know it will give the greatest pleasure to them. They are<lb/>such fine men, great handsome fellows, &amp; such nice manners they nearly<lb/>all tell you they have never been ill in their lives &amp; it is difficult<lb/>to persuade them they must stay in bed. One of them is nearly mad<lb/>with delight because he is going to England, he has asked me again<lb/>&amp; again to persuade the doctor to send him, &amp; <seg type="del">I</seg>now is firmly con—<lb/>vinced that it was my doing, especially as Capt. Connor's familiar<lb/>Irish manner makes them think that I am very great with him.<lb/>I have just enticed our chambermaid on to the roof to take his<lb/>photograph, unfortunately the minute he saw the camera, with<lb/>mutterings &amp; of gesticulations he fled to return in 2 minutes dressed in<lb/>his best clothes, red fez &amp; all. I am afraid he will never allow<lb/>me to take him in his housemaid's apron! I wish I could<lb/>describe all the things I see here. A funeral has just gone<lb/>by below my window, the women wailing, &amp; the men chanting, the coffin 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4119_img_3495_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">3</hi>   has a little thing like a stove pipe in the end in which sits <lb/>the dead man's Fez, or when it is a girl a white veil &amp; wreath <lb/>of flowers. The children here are sweet, such wonderful <lb/>velvety brown eyes &amp; such lashes, the better class children wear chiefly <lb/>European clothes with the inevitable red Fez for the little boys, but <lb/>the poor children wear bright picturesque clothes, are always dirty <lb/>but look jolly &amp; well fed. The women carry their babies stride <lb/><seg type="unclear">legs</seg>on their hips or their shoulders, &amp; spring along often with a <lb/>big bundle on their heads as well, but they have awful <seg type="unclear">hijabs</seg> and <lb/>generally hideous feet and ankles which they have no modesty <lb/>about <seg type="del">covering</seg> displaying. At night when we are waiting <lb/>for the mule wagon, I see such pictures sometimes, a man in <lb/>a white turban &amp; a lovely green <seg type="foreign">eau de nil</seg> garment rides past on <lb/>a pure white mule with the moon behind him and a perfect <lb/>sky, a woman all in black, <seg type="del">with</seg>veiled, follows presently on <lb/>a dark mule, <seg type="del">and</seg>old man the colour of old mahogany goes <lb/>all bent up with a <seg type="del">gourd</seg>skin water bag on his back, &amp; a little brass <lb/>mug to give drinks, to children a boy &amp; a girl, on donkeys <lb/>with pa<seg type="del">nniers</seg> &amp; big shining tin water jars on each side, it is <lb/>like living pictures, I never get tired of watching them. If <lb/>I had only Ruth's gift of writing, I could write not one but <lb/>20 articles, I think of you shivering round the fire <lb/>when I am basking in the sun! Think not a drop of rain <lb/>since we came! I am as usual bursting with <lb/>health &amp; that reminds me, you asked about Celia! Well <lb/>firstly I'm afraid she hasn't a chance for a new lot of V.A.D.s <lb/>came lately. I think if anything they have more than they <lb/>want, here anyway. It is very difficult to say, undoubtedly <lb/>it doesn't suit some people, &amp; a fair amount leave some home <lb/>and one or two were very ill with enteric &amp; dysentery, two died <lb/>the first week we were here, on the other hand if it suits you 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4119_img_3495_4"/>
             <hi rend="underline">4</hi>  you are very well, it is not too hot now at all and as far as hard<lb/>work goes, she has stood that for 6 months already. It certainly<lb/>is the chance of a lifetime <seg type="unclear">well</seg> this peace. I think a lot of illness<lb/>though of course by no means all, is due to carelessness, one girl who<lb/>sat by me at latte the other day, said gaily Oh I forgot to wash my<lb/>hands since I left hospital, &amp; it transpire that she had been<lb/>bathing enteric patients back, this I think not only disgusting<lb/>but madness. She has been ill, not I must admit with enteric, but<lb/><seg type="del">dyre</seg> diahoerrea which has been so bad that she goes home to—<lb/>morrow, still if she was as careless as I have that what can she expect.<lb/>I have come to the conclusion that nursing like every other walk<lb/>of life is a case of common sense. Sister <seg type="unclear">Sargeant</seg><lb/>who was the night superintendent sister, &amp; whom I did not like<lb/>told one of my friends, that she had a great admiration for<lb/>me &amp; that she had to write a report of us as well as our own<lb/>sisters, &amp; according to herself she gave me a most glowing one. I<lb/>would love to see it! I thought her &amp; soon latter eat! She<lb/>has now been  with 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> hospital where she   Behand<lb/>It was she who asked me if I have engaged to him, I think I<lb/>told you about it!    By the way, yesterday I went to see one of my friends Nell Ryland,<lb/>such a nice girl who was had jaundice, she asked me if I<lb/>   could order her a tea service, the same as the one you gave me<lb/>for her sister in France, I said I knew you could do it with<lb/>pleasure if they were who had. Could you please, get me,<lb/>not a basket but one the same as mine, it is so convenient<lb/>tell Mitchell to send it to<lb/>Miss C. W. Ryland<lb/>V.A.D.<lb/>13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> General Hospital<lb/>B.E.F.<lb/>Nr. Boulogne France.     Nell was most anxious to send the money, but I could not<lb/>remember the exact price, so will you pay for it &amp; let me 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>