<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4251">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 3 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his family. Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/88</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4251</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4251_img_3618_1"  type="Letter"  url="02a2806e81e1b8bff4fe215aaa248da6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4251_img_3618_2"  type="Letter"  url="8425b328783b603419b8267fbb39c05a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4251_img_3618_1"/>
             Please return to Lil finally. <lb/> <lb/><seg type="del">Mater</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Edmund</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Mabel</seg> <lb/>Rex   3 Dec. 15.   My dear folks   We are now settled in our new Chateau &amp; so <lb/> I expect we shall not stay much longer. In fact we already <lb/> have the feeling of more work  in the air which usually presages a move   We are on a big river  <seg type="del">of Fr</seg> , but like most French rivers it is not <lb/> very beautiful. The chateau is rather fine with 2 big bastions <lb/> of white stone many centuries old &amp; marked with many stone <lb/> bullet holes, but the French neither then nor later have <lb/> learnt how to build houses, &amp; the interior is gloomy, when it <lb/> could have been so fine. The walls of white stone have been <lb/> covered with cheap red canvas outlined with dark blue, with <lb/> fine wood panelling on the walls &amp; the ceiling. One of course <lb/> has no passage &amp; has to go through most of the rooms to <lb/> get anywhere, but my little loft up high is luckily to itself, <lb/> a great relief when one likes to be asleep before midnight.   The weather has been really bad &amp; the poor chaps in the <lb/> trenches must really be having a terrible time from what I <lb/> saw of them before. I expect we shall have to relieve them soon, <lb/> but I count every day that passes as a day gained towards next <lb/> summer.   I have just heard that Lily is to go on a mission to Belfast <lb/> It really is rather an honour to have been chosen, but perfectly heroic
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4251_img_3618_2"/>
            on her part — poor sailor that she is — to undertake it. I do hope <lb/> that she may get a glimps at <lb/> Rex, tho' I expect that her movements make plans very uncertain.   I hope to get time to see Gen' Rimington of the Indian Cav<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> <lb/>Corps who has sent me a warm pressing invitation to lunch or dinner. <lb/> He is a strong Ulsterman which accounts for his kindness as I <lb/> have never met him.   I hope Douglas has brought back good news of his wife &amp; <lb/> that he has turned up at 24 again. He wrote me a line show- <lb/>ing that he had really appreciated Mater's hospitality &amp; Jessie's <lb/> kindness.    I thought that we should lose  Capt Richardson — the GSO 3— <lb/> with whom I have now been working so cordially for 6 months, but <lb/> he has decided not to go in for a special course in spite of my <lb/> strong advice. that he should.   I know you won't like Lily going off to Ireland but it <lb/> is certainly a case of duty call &amp; I hope she may prove as <lb/> good <seg type="del">an ambassad</seg> <seg type="del">a kind o</seg>  a traveller as did Mater &amp; Jess at this <lb/> time last year. Was it only last year?   Mater has been most good in writing but many <lb/> letters of the others do not now reach me.   I see Lord K is back in London. I hope he will <lb/> take over again at the War Office tho' no one expected this.   Best love    Wilfrid . B Spender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>