<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0329">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Colonel Henry Gerard Kennard to the Under-Secretary for Ireland, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Gerard Kennard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Colonel Henry Gerard Kennard (b. 1871), the commander of the Dublin garrison in 1916. The letter was addressed to the under-secretary for Ireland. This position was previously held by Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). However, in May 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. He was soon replaced by Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). In this letter Kennard informs the under-secretary that he is forwarding him the 13th list of casualties incurred in connection with the Sinn Féin insurrection.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/8286/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/329</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1313">Henry Gerard Kennard</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0679">Lower Castle Yard, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0341">Upper Castle Yard, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0329_img_1553_1"  type="Letter"  url="cfca4ea02764cd953786e8c2199fdeff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0329_img_1553_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="966aed4573498d3e2a8fd94dc580ee99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0329_img_1553_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="646c6551d809edd3348599f01b61f5df.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0329_img_1553_1"/>
             <seg type="head">Subject;- Sinn Fein Insurrection.<lb/> D.G.C.R No. 45/16. </seg>   The Under Secretary for Ireland,  Upper Castle Yard,  Dublin.   Sir,   I have the honor to forward herewith the 13th<lb/> list of Casualties incurred in connection with the<lb/> Sein Fein Insurrection. <seg type="closer"> I have the honor to be, <lb/> Sir, <lb/> Your obedient servant,  <hi rend="underline">H.G Kennard Colonel</hi> , <lb/> Commanding Troops, Dublin.<lb/>  Lr. Castle Yard,  Dublin.    13. 5. 1916.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0329_img_1553_2"/>
               King George V. Hospital. Dublin. address  May 11th 1916.  date  paragraph  To. A.D.M.S,  paragraph  Dublin District.  paragraph  The undernoted casualties have not been previously reported to you: paragraph  Pte. Fox S.Staffs. Killed. paragraph  3370 Sibley A. 2/7 Sher.For. paragraph  2793 Barks G.W paragraph  2420 Cpl. Hoyle C.  paragraph  5605 Pte. Holbrook A. paragraph  2853 or 28537 Kitchen H.T. 2/8 paragraph  3080 OR 30807 Gross T. 2/7 paragraph  4136 Holland T. 2/8 paragraph  4809 Jepps P. 2/7  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0329_img_1553_3"/>
              7155 A. D. M. S. D. D. <lb/> Sergeant Fletcher 6th South Staffords. ( DEAD ).<lb/> Private Barrett, 6th South Staffords ( DEAD ).   These men were buried in the grounds of the Parochial <lb/> Hall, Northumberland Road, Ballsbridge.  <seg type="unclear">Wpm, acknowledge<lb/> Lt. col. br.am.s</seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>