<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5502">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M.P. Kehoe to Sir Roger Casement, 10 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M.P. Kehoe</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from M.P. Kehoe, to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written during Casement&#39;s eighteen month stay in Germany, where he was attempting to gain German support for an Irish rebellion against British rule. The letter refers to Casement&#39;s attempts to create an Irish Brigade of Irish-born British army soldiers who were then held as prisoners of war in German camps. It was the camp at Linberg, in the Lahn valley, that was designated for the project. Kehoe writes mainly about the attempts to convince men to join the brigade and mentions some of the men who had already joined. He describes the work as &#39;slow &amp; tedious&#39;. The project was ultimately unsuccessful and only fifty-six men signed up.
Casement was later arrested in County Kerry having returned to Ireland in a submarine to try and prevent the Easter Rising from taking place as he felt German support was insufficient. He was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,085 /21</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5502</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0288">M.P. Kehoe</persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0826">Hotel zur Alton Post, Limberg, Lahn, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0840">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5502_img_534_1"  type="Letter"  url="ba56eed8df2231ca0bfa4cf1876fb92d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5502_img_534_2"  type="Letter"  url="604ad2bdb1c30c9b01f670efa1fe18b0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5502_img_534_3"  type="Letter"  url="62346d07e5b9069d60a8c2da1e809f89.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5502_img_534_1"/>
             <seg type="foreign">Hotel zur Alten Post<lb/>Bezitzer :<lb/>Ernst Bielefeld<lb/>Dampfheizung :-: Elektrisch Licht.<lb/>Weingrosshandlung<lb/>Fernruf Nr.17<lb/>Postscheckkonto<lb/>Frankfurt a. M. Nr. 8742</seg>   Limburg (Lahn),   den 10<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>Nov 1915 <lb/><lb/>To. Sir Roger Casement   Dear Sir Roger,   I reached Limburg safely yesterday<lb/>morning but did not start any work until this morning<lb/>when I reached Camp I found a man of my Regt. waiting<lb/>to see me. He was working with Wilson on some farm<lb/>he joined, &amp; also another man Munsters, I think he belongs to<lb/>who was with Wilson on Farm he is waiting answer to his<lb/>letter he wrote Wilson through us &amp; Underofficer Hahn, when<lb/>he receives his answer he will decide. The men who join<lb/>are separated from others into a Barrack where German<lb/>speaking Russians are &amp; who have volunteered to fight<lb/>with Germany it was proposed by Authorities here &amp;<lb/>accepted by Capt.M. because the men I am sure after<lb/>hearing what we have to say to them &amp; the system Mr. M.<lb/>has adopted, requires consideration &amp; he gives them<lb/>ample time , to-day one young fellow, <seg type="unclear">Comm Rgt</seg> just<lb/>went to his Coy Officer &amp; said he wanted to join Irish Bde<lb/>&amp; was brought up to Barracks set apart for Bde.  Up to now Mr. M. said after interviewing about 250 or so<lb/>he said 12 to 15 were likely candidates. It was only to-day<lb/>Barrack was set aside, &amp; to-day first man came on his own. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5502_img_534_2"/>
             but I got another man to join him, so I think we will<lb/>have luck, although it will be slow &amp; tedious work.<lb/>It is an individual method Mr. M. has, &amp; between the<lb/>number of interviews &amp; the men I have on list from<lb/><seg type="unclear">new</seg> in Zossen &amp; those I know myself we will see<lb/>about 70 or so per day. Besides men are returning from<lb/>farms every day since 1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> Nov. I've heard that the men<lb/>must be sent back to Camp after 1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> Nov. &amp; any of those<lb/>kept at work must have special allowance.<lb/>My first day here brought luck, the first two actually<lb/>joined &amp; three others I am sure will come too.  I have got a Mantle &amp; Sword given me here from<lb/>Authorities. The men in Camp have taken a different<lb/>attitude towards us this time, they listen attentively,<lb/>quietly &amp; are never insulting, it is much easier to work<lb/>with them. Srgts Beverly &amp; O'Toole wish to be<lb/>remembered to you. hoping you are quite well  I remain<lb/>Your obedient servant<lb/>M.P.Kehoe 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5502_img_534_3"/>
             Kehoe<lb/>from<lb/>Limburg   <hi rend="underline">6 Nov 1915.</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>