<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4522">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Fitzgibbon to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 10 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Fitzgibbon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Fitzgibbon to Fr. Nolan regarding John Fitzgibbon&#39;s place changes and the Catholics who met. 

Fr John Fitzgibbon SJ (1882-1918). His adopted name was Jack. His father, John Fitzgibbon, was a successful draper and subsequent Member of Parliament (PM) the time period 1910-1918. His brother, Michael Fitzgibbon, was captain in the Royal Dublin Fusiliers and was killed in the Battle of Gallipoli.  Jack was ordained a priest on 31st July, 1915. Subsequently, he served in the 6th Division of the British Army, and enlisting shortly after the death of his brother. He was promoted to senior chaplain in 1917, and in the same year he was gassed at Loos on 5th September and was awarded the military cross. Next year, on 18th September, Jack was killed in action by an artillery shell at Attilly and buried at Trefcon, St. Quentin, Picardie.

Father Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives </repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4522</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0632">John Fitzgibbon</persName>
              <date>1916-04-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V. Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1918</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4522_img_3865_1"  type="Letter"  url="1ede3bd517a1d4f91a959f7b0115e644.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4522_img_3865_1"/>
             10/4/16   Dear Fr Nolan_ <lb/>P.C.   I should have written some <lb/>days ago, but I have been moving + moving. As <lb/>you know my address now is the 16th Field Ambulance <lb/>B.E.F. France:- as the man whose place I was <lb/>taking at the 23rd turned up about a fortnight <lb/>ago. So, now, I am permanently attached too the <lb/>16th which includes about twenty two different <lb/>sections scattered all over the country, with a <lb/>few Catholics in each. The total number of <lb/>Catholics in the whole Brigade would not exceed <lb/>500, + still the senior chaplain told me that <lb/>if I am able to get around to them all in a <lb/>month, I shall have done good work. <lb/>Consequently my horse got plenty to do + when he <lb/>is tired, I get another one from one of the officers <lb/>who are most obliging + extremely kind to me. <lb/>We are at present resting and not far from <lb/>the sea, under canvas; but we are to be on the <lb/>move again in a few days, back to the trenches. <lb/>It took us only a night + day to come here, having <lb/>trained portion of the way: but we have just heard <lb/>that we are to march back the whole way and <lb/>take three days to do it.   Except for the night I was in the train before <lb/>joining the 16th. I never had to miss saying Mass <lb/>on the last march I was able to fall out + say Mass <lb/>in a small village + then join the troops later. <lb/>Most of my fellow officers are Irish, but are <lb/>protestants. the men are mostly English but of Irish <lb/>extraction.   Thank God everything is going well as far as I can <lb/>judge and I am certainly nothing the worse of the <lb/>month out here. Hoping you are quite well.   Yours very sincerely in Xt.    Jack Fitzgibbon, S.J.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>