<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6663">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from WB Yeats to Harold Edward Monro, 10 June 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.B. Yeats</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 7. Folder: Letters L-O</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6663</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date>1920-06-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1373">4 Broad Street, Oxford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harold Monro</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6663_img_None_1"  url="phpyQuW9i.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6663_img_None_2"  url="phpX739dv.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6663_img_0_1"/>
              4 Broad St<lb/>Oxford    June 10 1921   <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">Private</hi></hi>   Dear Monro   I have been a long time answering<lb/>your letter of April 22. I stayed in London<lb/>a very short time or I would have been<lb/>to see you. I gave a lecture or two<lb/>&amp; returned home. I wish I could have been<lb/>in London long enough to have given<lb/>your paper a reading.  You tell me that certain of my<lb/>books are unobttainable. The truth is<lb/>that Macmillan &amp; I are disputing<lb/>on the question. He signed an agreement<lb/>to re-issue all my work in a certain<lb/>form &amp; now their printing has got so much<lb/>more expensive, wants some other arrangement.<lb/>He keeps evading the point. I want to get<lb/>out a uniform edition of all my poems<lb/>&amp; prose. If that should be impossible<lb/>I have a compromise in my head which<lb/><seg type="unclear">warants some negotiation with business</seg>    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6663_img_0_2"/>
             One of my few  upsets  at leaving London<lb/>is that I cannot any longer look in<lb/>occasionally at TThe Poetry Bookshop &amp;<lb/>find what is being written.   Yours<lb/>W B Yeats  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>