<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0260">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from C. J. Hyder to Sir Matthew Nathan, 8 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles John Hyder</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Charles John Hyde (b. 1862), the manager of W &amp;amp; A Gilbey Ltd. to Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), Undersecretary for Ireland. Mathew Nathan had become undersecretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell (1850–1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned as undersecretary due to his misjudgement and failure to stop the Rising. The letter states that Hyde received a letter from Lord Blythe (d. 1925) the director of W &amp;amp; A Gilbey Ltd, a wine importers and distillers. The letter stated that he offered the government room in the company for postal services due to the disturbance of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5611/7970/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/260</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1208">Charles John Hyder</persName>
              <date>1916-05-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0260_img_1445_1"  type="Letter"  url="d22c2c880c8d8474dd77b0592f36652d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0260_img_1445_1"/>
                W. &amp; A. Gilbey. Ltd  Wine Importers &amp; Distillers  DUBLIN    8th May, 1916.   Sir,   Our Lord Blyth writes us a letter dated the 3rd ins, received <lb/> this morning, to say that he had offered the Government the use of the <lb/> upper portion of our house here, if required, for Postal or other service <lb/> during the present crisis.  At Lord Blyths' request we write to confirm this, as we can <lb/> give you the use of several large rooms, and will give you every facility <lb/> possible if you would think well of accepting our offer. <seg type="closer"> Yours respectfully,  P.Pro. W. &amp; A. Gilbey Ltd.<lb/> C. J. Hyder Manager<lb/>  Sir Matthew Natha, K.C.M.G.  DUBLIN CASTLE  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>