<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3482">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Angela "Witchie" to her uncle, Tomás Mac Curtain, 13 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Angela </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, Angela &#34;Witchie&#34; writes to her uncle with general news from Cork. She finds it lonely in Blackpool without him. She is enclosing a holy picture for his cell and is also sending one to MacSweeney (Terence?). 

Tomás MacCurtain (1884–1920), republican, was born Thomas Curtin in Ballyknockane, Co. Cork, on 20 March 1884. MacCurtain was a founder member of the Cork executive of the Irish Volunteers, and in the time leading up to the 1916 Rising, he travelled the county organising new Volunteer units. MacCurtain was arrested in Cork in May 1916, and sent to Dublin before being deported to Wakefield prison on 30 May. On 10 June he was moved to Frongoch in north Wales and on 11 July to Reading gaol, where he remained until his release in December 1916. He continued to lead the Cork Volunteers despite being imprisoned on other occasions in 1917. On 30 January 1920 he became the first Sinn Féin lord mayor of Cork. On 20 March 1920,  MacCurtain was shot dead in his bedroom a major escalation in the spiral of violence that marked the last year of the war of independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork Public Museum</repository>
                  <collection>T. Mac Curtain Collection, L1966.166 D9.7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3482</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0146">Angela </persName>
              <date>1916-07-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1324">2 Moorfield Terrace, South Douglas Road, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0338">Tomás Mac Curtain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1457">Reading Gaol, Berkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3482_img_2890_1"  type="Letter"  url="20df7fe1b66eb719839b0304c9f8beed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3482_img_2890_2"  type="Letter"  url="874bec09b26fe52bdd23254ea518fdec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3482_img_2890_1"/>
             2 Moorfield Terrace<lb/>South Douglas Rd.<lb/>Cork   (July)13-7-'16 <lb/><lb/> My darling Uncle Tom,   At last I got the chance<lb/>of writing to you. How are you getting<lb/>on now? I'm dying for you to come<lb/>home, as the place seems so lonely<lb/>without you. We do not like half<lb/>so much going to Blackpool since<lb/>you are gone. Because it is so lonely,<lb/>Siobhán is now in first <seg type="unclear">look.</seg> Patrick<lb/>is going to Sullivans Quay School &amp;<lb/>likes it very much. He learns Irish<lb/>there.  On Sunday we went to Kilcrea<lb/>to the O'Driscolls. We went down<lb/>on the 9.15 a.m. and got Mass at<lb/>10.15 in Kilcrea. Do you know a<lb/>boy named Bernard O'Driscoll?<lb/>He is related to the OD's in Kilcrea.<lb/>If he is there with you give him<lb/>best love from his family. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3482_img_2890_2"/>
             I am sending a little Holy Picture<lb/>to Mr MacSweeney and one to your<lb/>little self. I have no 'corncrakes'<lb/>around me now as I am in Moorfield.<lb/>I am going to Blackpool after dinner.  I have not much news this time.<lb/>I hope you will find a little<lb/>corner in your cell for the little picture.  We were out in Young's house<lb/>yesterday (Wednesday) with Aunt<lb/>Han. We were nearly sick from<lb/>eating gooseberries and red currants.<lb/>Of the latter we made a drink<lb/>by mashing the currants up in<lb/>sugar and goats milk. It was<lb/>lovely.  Best love from all here<lb/>and in Blackpool.<lb/><lb/> Goodbye now darling Witchie <lb/> xxxxxxYour ever lovingxxxx <lb/> xxxxxxx and grateful xxxxx <lb/> xxxxxxx<hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">Po. 1 Rotten</seg></hi> Cork xxxx <lb/>P.S. Love to Mr. MacSweeney 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>