<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4290">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William R. Young to Edward Carson, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Robert Young</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Robert Young (1856-1933) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. William Robert Young, linen merchant, politician and philanthropist, was a prominent Unionist. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4290</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1100">William Robert Young</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0869">34 Bedford Street, Belfast, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1933</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4290_img_3653_1"  type="Letter"  url="09fac722b3104c16cc048303f66fdb93.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4290_img_3653_2"  type="Letter"  url="2a08727262dda5e309a92e378cb603ea.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4290_img_3653_1"/>
             34 Bedford Street, <lb/> Belfast.   Nov. 12. 1915    My dear Sir Edward,   Thanks for your letter of the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/> <seg type="unclear">inst.</seg>; I have seen Bates and the papers <lb/> from General Nugent —- Many of the <lb/> suggestions —- indeed most - had already <lb/> formed part of the Winborne Scheme — <lb/> You can rely on your friends here <lb/> keeping a strict look out that no <lb/> injury is done us —    At least 3/4 of the recruits being got, <lb/> and they are coming in fairly well <lb/> are for the Ulster Division —    I enclose you cutting from Ballymena <lb/> Observer giving list of recruits in <lb/>Ballymena District last week — 54 in all. <lb/> 30 from Country &amp; 24 from Town — <lb/> An <seg type="del">anayli</seg>analysis of these figures <lb/> shows following results   Ulster Division 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>R.I.R. 28 <lb/> " " 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> " 2 <lb/>County Down Regt 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> " 6 <lb/> Ulster Division 9 R.I.F. <hi rend="underline">1</hi> <lb/> North Irish Horse — 3/<hi rend="underline">5</hi> 42 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4290_img_3653_2"/>
            <seg type="head">(2)</seg>  out of the balance of 12 <lb/> Seven Regiments 5 <lb/> R.S.A 1 <lb/> Army Service Corps 1 <lb/> Navy 1 <lb/> Home Service 2 <lb/> RIR (no battalion) 1 <lb/> Munsters' <hi rend="underline">1</hi> <lb/> 12    This I think shows that the interests <lb/> of the Ulster Division are being watched.   Dublin has played a low game — <lb/> but I think they have been outwitted, <lb/> and that recruiting in Ulster has so <lb/> far been entirely to the advantage of <lb/> the Ulster Division — They take an <lb/> awful lot of watching —   You must have had a hard and <lb/> anxious time of late. I congratulate <lb/> You on great services rendered to the <lb/> Empire.   Yours sincerely    William R Young 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>