<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0716">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 19 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother. James writes about waiting for deliveries of parcels and his concern that his letters home are not being delivered. As per his previous letter, he stresses his need for replacement boots and requests that any items of kit be sent as soon as possible. He also mentions the conditions of the trenches and considerable shelling and fighting in nearby sections.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/30</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/716</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clara Mary Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0716_img_2217_1"  type="Letter"  url="ca77ffece53a558a7dd5d2b4ada5adba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0716_img_2217_2"  type="Letter"  url="eed9054dfa5e85ceb93da3753a6dda0e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0716_img_2217_3"  type="Letter"  url="fa809b791cbebae575878c8bfb881a4d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0716_img_2217_4"  type="Envelope"  url="c3c3561d1e63a231ead1ea32300f1175.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0716_img_2217_1"/>
                19/2/16   My dearest Mother    — I got your <lb/> letter of 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yest &amp; was surprised <lb/> to hear that you had not received <lb/> any letters from me since <lb/> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. I wrote on 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> &amp; 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> then to <lb/>Father on 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; again to you <lb/> on 16t<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>. I do hope you have <lb/> since received them as I am <lb/> now very badly off for boots <lb/> &amp; looking anxiously every day <lb/> for those trench books to turn <lb/> up. The boots I had have <lb/> simply gone to pieces with the <lb/> trench work &amp; my feet are <lb/> always wet. With regard to <lb/> the pair of boots which you say <lb/> have arrived from Manfields <lb/> I cant remember whether I <lb/> ordered them or not but at <lb/> any rate they have come just  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0716_img_2217_2"/>
              at the right time &amp; you might <lb/> please have them also sent on <lb/> as soon as possible. I <lb/> think I asked you to post me <lb/> a box of <seg type="unclear">Cockles</seg> pills — these have <lb/> not come yet so if by chance <lb/> they have been overlooked would <lb/>you please get them for me. <lb/> There was a terrific bombardment <lb/> this evening to the left of our <lb/> Sector — it was like continuous <lb/> thunder &amp; the flashes of the guns <lb/> lit up the whole sky. Our <lb/> particular part of the the line has <lb/> been rather more peaceful during <lb/> the past day or so but one of <lb/>my gun teams had a great <lb/>escape. We had been annoying <lb/> the Germans considerably the <lb/>night before with 2 guns so <lb/> they started to look for us <lb/> with artillery &amp; actually dropped  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0716_img_2217_3"/>
              2 shells right on top of the <lb/> emplacement where the men <lb/>were taking shelter. Fortunately <lb/> it had a concrete roof &amp; the <lb/>shell did not penetrate for <lb/> otherwise everyone would have <lb/> been killed &amp; they were all <lb/> men of my own original section. <lb/> Am kept awfully busy — never <lb/> seem to have a minute — but <lb/> have been keeping all right in <lb/> spite of the weather. Trenches <lb/> have been flooded &amp; yest I <lb/> was wading all morning up to nearly <lb/> the knees &amp; with my ordinary old <lb/> boots so you can imagine what <lb/>a state I was in. Must be off <lb/> to bed. With fondest love to all. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son,  Jim </seg>  A Zepp as just been passing over <lb/>but too high to see   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0716_img_2217_4"/>
              <lb/>On Active Service<lb/>  24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>/16   Mrs. S.C.Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland    JDavidson   19/2/16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>