<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4345">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mabel FitzGerald [June 1916]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mabel FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958) wife of Desmond and mother of Garret, writing to an unidentified correspondent regarding the Rising stating that Desmond is now in Dartmoor. From other letters by Mabel we known that Desmond Fitzgerald was in Dartmoor from June 1916. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Jackie Clarke Collection</repository>
                  <collection>12-10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4345</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1642">2 Loretto Villas, Bray, Co. Wicklow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1958</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4345_img_3702_1"  type="Letter"  url="446fa7c178a28398ef2dd7108e76502f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4345_img_3702_2"  type="Letter"  url="7f7be3355278debf5b3705bfc2d9fad6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4345_img_3702_3"  type="Letter"  url="7c16dd7f4f8fae948658d2ace04b4414.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4345_img_3702_4"  type="Letter"  url="4cbd0155a9ddca8c5b56d4fbda8c7b6d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4345_img_3702_1"/>
             2 LorettoVillas<lb/>Bray   Wednesday    Aoife,   I must thank you for<lb/>the letters you sent me on Satur-<lb/>day; the reason I have not<lb/>done so sooner is that I thought<lb/>to be in town and meant to go<lb/>and see you.  Desmond spoke often of<lb/>you during the nine days he<lb/>spent here at home with me<lb/>after the Rebellion before his<lb/>arrest; he thought a great<lb/>deal of you &amp; urged me to<lb/>get to know you &amp; since he  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4345_img_3702_2"/>
             was arrested he asked me on<lb/>several occasions if I had come<lb/>across you yet.  I grieve for you, Aoife,<lb/>in your loss; it must leave<lb/>a terrible aching blank. I know<lb/>how it feels for I thought all<lb/>those long days from Tuesday<lb/>to Saturday that Desmond was<lb/>dead. And life didn't seem to<lb/>hold much for me. You fool<lb/>dear with all before you,<lb/>it is dreadfully sad to have<lb/>lost your friend so. But I<lb/>know you don't grudge him<lb/>to Ireland and must have great<lb/>pride in his willing sacrifice.<lb/>For their names shall be<lb/>remembered forever.  I did indeed say a<lb/>prayer for your friends' soul  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4345_img_3702_3"/>
             none the less fervent for any<lb/>being a Protestant and I will<lb/>tell Desmond about him and ask<lb/>him to pray for him when I<lb/>get an opportunity. But they<lb/>all went straight to Heaven<lb/>I am sure - I have heard<lb/>priests say so too.  I am not supposed to<lb/>see Desmond now for four<lb/>whole months or hear if he is<lb/>alive or dead. Unless<lb/> <seg type="unclear"></seg>gets them<lb/>better treatment before then.<lb/> He is in <seg type="unclear"></seg>- went<lb/>quite gaily and cheerfully of<lb/>course.    I was very glad to  have <lb/>his farewell letter and I was<lb/>much touched by <seg type="unclear">O'Reilly's</seg>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4345_img_3702_4"/>
             thoughtfulness to sending me<lb/>a line to say how woeful<lb/>Desmond was; I suppose he<lb/>thought Desmond would never<lb/>get out alive and wanted to<lb/>leave me something to help<lb/>to make it seem worthwhile.  Forgive this scribble;<lb/>I am in great haste. I<lb/>would like to meet you and<lb/>should be very glad if you<lb/>could come and see me. If<lb/>not we will meet in town<lb/>at some informal event<lb/>I am sure. I am at home on<lb/>Sundays  [Questonable reading.] 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>