<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1527">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Julia Evans to Nancy O'Rahilly, 1 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Julia Evans</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter of condolence from Julia Evans to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). The writer expresses sorrow for Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s loss. The writer&#39;s own husband was recently released and was in a terrible state, having been wounded in action at the South Dublin Union - she describes the bad treatment of her husband by &#39;G-Men&#39;, detective in G Unit of the Dublin Metropolitan Police. Mrs. Evans&#39; husband is hoping to get his old job back but in the meantime they are in need of charitable assistance - she asks Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly to put them in touch with a charitable committee.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/38</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1527</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0455">Julia Evans</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0435">22 Harolds Cross Road, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1527_img_988_1"  type="Letter"  url="23e8983502c23aadd2b7b1b6f5e6aee8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1527_img_988_2"  type="Letter"  url="8e6755edd4728948140434278784086b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1527_img_988_3"  type="Letter"  url="83b68ad0a7fcb3f8d456db298508f0ad.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1527_img_988_4"  type="Letter"  url="61774626b80868b33d78805c38285963.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1527_img_988_1"/>
                22 Harolds Cross Road    June 1st 1916   Dear Madam   I trust you will excuse the<lb/> liberty I take of writing to you in<lb/> your bereavement I am sincerely <lb/> sorry for your loss His geniality <lb/> won for him the affection and <lb/> respect of all who came in <lb/> touch with him may he R. I. P. <lb/> my Husband thank God was <lb/> released on 26th of May. he got <lb/> home here on Saturday morning <lb/> in a deplorable condition. <lb/> He was wounded when in action in  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1527_img_988_2"/>
              the S. D. Union. and remained a patient <lb/> there for a week. when two <hi rend="underline">G.men</hi><lb/> called for him on the 6th of May and<lb/> actually pulled him out of the bed, and<lb/> his boots could not be found, so<lb/> they gave him a horrible old pair of <lb/> boots, with nails in them and about <lb/> 4 sizes too big for him and they<lb/> could not get his overcoat or hat.<lb/> so they took him away to Kilmainham<lb/> in torrents of rain. he was not able<lb/> to walk so they had to help him. and<lb/> then they put him in a cell to himself<lb/> and left him there for 5 hours in<lb/> his wet clothes without even looking<lb/> at him or giving him a drink. he<lb/> was then removed to Richmond Bkgo <lb/> he was not so bad there as he was <lb/> with 24 of his own sort. he was<lb/> deported on the 8th of May to Wandsworth<lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1527_img_988_3"/>
              the treatment there was cruel. until<lb/> some of the M. P.'s. went to interview <lb/> the prison and then they got a little<lb/> better. it is <sic>miraculos</sic> my husband <lb/> being released it was all through<lb/> prayer. A. Byrne the M.P. did a lot<lb/> for him. He was very much the worse<lb/> of what he went through and come <lb/> home to me a complete wreck.<lb/> his suit he could not wear it<lb/> any more. and he has no boots.<lb/> The boots he got in the Union remain<lb/> here we intend to keep them as<lb/> a memento. and his overcoat also<lb/> gone. His place of <sic>Bussiness</sic> was<lb/> was badly looted. and they are <lb/> not started yet. He was charge<lb/> of the Hat dept. in Mr McEvoy's of <lb/> Redmonds Hill. I think Mr McEvoy<lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1527_img_988_4"/>
              will take him back as he was<lb/> with him for a number of years.<lb/> but his appearance has to be<lb/> seen too, so I thought it best<lb/> to write and ask you if you could<lb/> influence any committee or charitable<lb/> ladies who would help to get him <lb/> fixed up until he gets back to <lb/> work, and he will do what he<lb/> can to help his fellow country-<lb/> men who are deported when he<lb/> gets settled in work.  Thanking you for your past kindness<lb/> may the The Lord reward and comfort <lb/> you. Mr Evans also send his very<lb/> deep sympathy  <seg type="closer"> Respectfully Yours  <hi rend="underline">Julia Evans</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>