<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4269">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 4 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/206</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4269</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4269_img_3634_1"  type="Letter"  url="50a3226919dcb6c333ca219ebe4871e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4269_img_3634_2"  type="Letter"  url="a72dbdb763a11701607a2b364a3d7d19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4269_img_3634_3"  type="Letter"  url="32f17775352166a0a344db20a36bbef5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4269_img_3634_4"  type="Letter"  url="f2c62526fddc135a2f3a4c06b824f09b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4269_img_3634_1"/>
             Your <seg type="unclear">figures</seg> are all wrong about words on a page   April 4 16   My p r    I should have liked to have seen you <lb/> at Mrs Stewarts ! I can imagine your indigna <lb/>tion but not for the life of me who Elsie is. <lb/> I believe the lady on whom there were <lb/> designs — not on the part of the b w — was <lb/> Lady Stewart <seg type="unclear">Bam</seg>, so perhaps you were skating <lb/> on rather thin ice without knowing it, but as <lb/> usual you got over it splendidly.   The b w wanted you very badly <lb/> last night. Very wakeful for a change &amp; <lb/> seemed to be in unspeakable black — never <lb/> quite felt the likes before rather depressing 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4269_img_3634_2"/>
             It was probably the result of black coffee anyhow <lb/> b w wanted a p r badly except that she inconven- <lb/>iently popped up whenever the b w got drowsy.   I had a piece of dissipation last night <lb/> going to our travelling concert group's perform- <lb/>ance at another village. Really they were <lb/> wonderful very nearly equal to the Ulster singers <lb/> &amp; the tone was so good — nothing vulgar <lb/> but real good music — tho too little of the <lb/> Irish tunes.   A very pretty song on the Origin of <lb/> Ireland was entirely spoilt by an added verse <lb/> of Singhton's on the origin of Germany. To add <lb/> to a hymn tune a rather ribald verse showed such <lb/> a complete lack of appreciation of the Irish nature <lb/> that one could barely keep patience — Result this song quite one of the best of the evening fell
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4269_img_3634_3"/>
            <lb/>absolutely flat. I felt sorry for S but glad in <lb/> a way that he should be made to see a little <lb/> of the Ulster feeling. All references to Ulster were <lb/> studiously omitted — a pity when one considers that <lb/> they visit other Divisions.   I heard a thing today about the men's <lb/> feelings to Sir Edward which was a most <lb/> painful shock. Some think that having got <lb/> them to enlist he <seg type="del">is fr</seg> takes no more <lb/>interest in them. Others that he is fright-<lb/>ened to come out ! It seems incredible <lb/> &amp; I am writing to Craig tomorrow about it ! <lb/> Mob thoughts really are unfathomable. This <lb/> shows to me the immense importance of <lb/> your work. Please rub in the Carson touch <lb/> with the wounded.  I will get Craig to <seg type="del">send</seg> think 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4269_img_3634_4"/>
            <lb/>out the best course.   Russell has just left with some very <lb/> nice remarks. He wants me to look him up <lb/> in town if I get there but this is problemati-<lb/>cal for leave again looks visionary.    Perhaps "Elsie" is Mrs Costello, wife of <lb/> Major Costello V C. a nice man And a RC a <lb/> relation of Mab's — Niece — I have seen her once <lb/> &amp; why she should call me Wilfrid passes the <lb/> cheek of women. I'm glad you restrained yourself <lb/>in what you said. It is best tactically to do as <lb/> you did &amp; get dangerously polite with such people. <lb/> They hate your remaining a Lady when they have <lb/> failed to do so.   No more as I have to take papers to <lb/> the G including some tricky ones left as a <lb/> legacy by R   Best love feeling better after a <lb/> long ride Your bw    Wilfrid BS. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>