<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4525">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Fitzgibbon to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, circa 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Fitzgibbon </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Fitzgibbon to Fr. Nolan regarding John Fitzgibbon&#39;s meeting with the Catholics of the Division. 

Fr John Fitzgibbon SJ (1882-1918). His adopted name was Jack. His father, John Fitzgibbon, was a successful draper and subsequent Member of Parliament (PM) the time period 1910-1918. His brother, Michael Fitzgibbon, was captain in the Royal Dublin Fusiliers and was killed in the Battle of Gallipoli.  Jack was ordained a priest on 31st July, 1915. Subsequently, he served in the 6th Division of the British Army, and enlisting shortly after the death of his brother. He was promoted to senior chaplain in 1917, and in the same year he was gassed at Loos on 5th September and was awarded the military cross. Next year, on 18th September, Jack was killed in action by an artillery shell at Attilly and buried at Trefcon, St. Quentin, Picardie.

Father Nolan (1867-1941) was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives </repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/8-9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4525</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0333">John Fitzgibbon </persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1022">France </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V. Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1918</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4525_img_3868_1"  type="Letter"  url="9560f3b5f31f56218c68dbc337e8ef2a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4525_img_3868_2"  type="Letter"  url="897b5e6f016e8dd2cb1e7d00c8348c48.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4525_img_3868_1"/>
             My dear Fr Nolan, —   Only a word <lb/>to let you know I am quite well <lb/>&amp; as happy as possible. Since my <lb/>last letter I have had many and <lb/>varied experiences <seg type="del">which</seg> about which <lb/>I shall try &amp; write about later, as <lb/>I am exceptionally busy trying <lb/>to see all the Catholics of the <lb/>division; and to organise some <lb/>means by which the chaplains of <lb/>the Division will be able to see <lb/>their different units at least once <lb/>a fortnight; as I am responsible <lb/>for the Catholics of the Division, <lb/>having being publicly made <lb/>senior Chaplain (R.C) by General <lb/>Sims at a conference which <lb/>he called the week before last. <lb/>I do pray &amp; hope that I will be <lb/>able to efficiently work the Division <lb/>as an s.j. is well watched out here. <lb/>I here are about sixty units in <lb/>the Division scattered about in <lb/>enemy direction some them ten <lb/>miles apart as there will be <lb/>plenty of <sic>minning</sic> about. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4525_img_3868_2"/>
             I should have sent you the <lb/>cheque for £12 but I was waiting <lb/>for my bank book from McGrigor <lb/>I am sending it now.   Father Farley would have had <lb/>my Mass list in before now, had <lb/>not our movement &amp; post here <lb/>being rather uncertain. I was <lb/>fortunate in being able to say <lb/>the full 20 for his intentions doing <lb/> <seg type="del">March.</seg> April.   Sorry for such a scrappy <lb/>letter.   I reamin dear Fr Nolan <lb/>yours very sincerely in Xt   J. Fitzgibbon s.j. <lb/> C.F. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>