<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5762">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 19 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
In this letter James was worried that May had been unwell because he had not heard from her. He is eager to see her at Easter and speaks about his cousin&#39;s happiness on becoming engaged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5762</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5762_img_862_1"  type="Letter"  url="53c0c3a41af76d5d4570b50284282442.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5762_img_862_2"  type="Letter"  url="6946b02e1aca1563f4ab7754669d620b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5762_img_862_1"/>
             19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April 1916   My dearest and best, <lb/>I was overjoyed to get<lb/>your letter this morning as I came down to<lb/>breakfast with the most gloomy forebodings. I had<lb/>been worrying overnight about that trouble you<lb/>got off the table and conjuring up pictures of<lb/>the injuries you got turning out more serious than<lb/>you had supposed with the result that you<lb/>were very ill. The result was that I was looking<lb/>out for the post from my window while I<lb/>was dressing. I missed seeing him coming to my<lb/>door but I saw him going to the next house<lb/>and concluded that there was no letter for me 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5762_img_862_2"/>
             I came down therefore in a very gloomy mood<lb/>quite determined to wire as soon as I got down<lb/>and to leave for Castletown by the afternoon<lb/>train unless I got a satisfactory wire in<lb/>reply. My relief was very great as you can<lb/>easily understand when I read your letter and<lb/>saw there was nothing wrong. As I told<lb/>you in my letter yesterday I shall be down<lb/>by the evening train and hope to see my<lb/>darling about half past seven. We were all<lb/>delighted to see that Louis had got on so<lb/>well and was so pleased with himself<lb/>and with his girl. It’s a great blessing that<lb/>he will be settled any how especially before   the father sails out as there might be rows<lb/>between Stanny and himself if they were both<lb/>in Markethill together. He must be very pleased<lb/>indeed with himself when he compares his<lb/>happiness to mine but I hardly think that<lb/>it will come up to the high water mark that<lb/>I have reached. However it shows you that<lb/>people generally are inclined to think I am<lb/>a lucky chap to pull off the first prize<lb/>when they take me as a standard of happiness.<lb/>I hope I’ll live to deserve my happiness<lb/>anyhow with God’s help and yours, my dear.  I have absolutely nothing to say except<lb/>that I love my dearest May with all the<lb/>strength I have. I send you my warmest love<lb/>as ever.  Your ever loving<lb/>James    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>