<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0635">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from C. Moran to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 15 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>C. Moran</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Miss C. Moran to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 until his death. In this letter Moran expresses disdain at the stance taken by John Redmond (1856 – 1918), in view of the recent executions of the Easter Week rebels and Sir Roger Casement (1864 – 1916). Moran, as the daughter of two Irish parents, voices concerns over the Anglicization of Ireland and expresses hope that conscription will not be extended to the country. In this letter Moran clearly does not support Irish involvement in the First World War or the British treatment of the Irish. Roger Casement had been imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. A campaign was launched featuring many prominent figures such as W.B. Yeats and George Bernard Shaw to secure a reprieve for Casement but he was hanged on 3 August 1916. John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/M/4, LDA/BI/ET/M/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/635</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0561">C. Moran</persName>
              <date>1916-08-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0806">154 Blythe Road, West Kensington, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0556">Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0635_img_2104_1"  type="Letter"  url="2629336c7d89e5761770f9fc1d77c808.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0635_img_2104_2"  type="Letter"  url="62b8f6bcaa4c5033c14e199ee1d79baa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0635_img_2104_3"  type="Letter"  url="61dc9140fd7616a9c408d76310b2b8e8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0635_img_2104_1"/>
                154, Blythe Road,  West Kensington,  London,    15th August 1916     To   The Rt Rev. The Lord Bishop of Limerick.   My Lord,   I have read with interest your Lordship's spirited letter in the<lb/> 'Freeman' re patriotism as inculcated by Mrs Starkie. The enclosed cutting<lb/> will show you that this pamphlet has an English origin and is <seg type="del">a</seg> merely one  of <lb/> the British Lion's 'feelers'. As both of my parents have been natives of<lb/> Limerick I take the liberty of writing to you. I have been deeply grieved <lb/> on reading of the horrible executions in Ireland, and it is inconceivable how,<lb/> in the face of those brutal murders, and the recent murder of Roger Casement<lb/> Mr John Redmond should still be bragging of the Irish people have 'done<lb/> their duty' in the war. While this latest Irish Martyr was awaiting the hang<lb/> man's rope Mr Redmond was boasting in parliament that 150,000 Irishmen were<lb/> bleeding and dying' on the plains of France for England and that he still  held <lb/> to his opinion that Ireland had done her duty in the war. It is difficult to<lb/> see what allegiance Ireland owes to England simply because she was conquered<lb/> by the sword, and for centuries of oppression and tyranny. Mr Redmond's sen-<lb/> timents have changed very much, and a man like that is surely not fit to lead<lb/> the Irish people. I see all the papers in the Free Library every day and <seg type="del">he</seg> John Redmond <lb/> seems now, like the 'Tommies', to be the darling of the English people. They<lb/> all comment on his <hi rend="underline">loyalty.</hi> When the Irish martyrs had been brutally shot down  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0635_img_2104_2"/>
              like rats, it was stated in the newspapers that Mr William Redmond had written<lb/> to his brother, informing him that the Germans had pasted up notices outside  the <lb/> Irish trenches informing them that the English were shooting down their country<lb/> men, and that they responded on their mouth organs with 'Rule Britannnia'. When<lb/> the war was started, and the soldiers marched through the streets they sang the <lb/> different National Anthems. We heard God save the King' and 'Rule Britannia'.<lb/> We heard the stirring strains of the 'Marsellaise'. For the Irish National<lb/> air we heard the unmeaning ditty 'Its a long way to Tipperary'. The National<lb/> air 'God save Ireland' was evidently  not  considered loyal enough by the Redmonds<lb/>, hence it was discarded, and this has become the National 'Anthem' for Ireland. <lb/> Recently I have heard the air of 'God save Ireland' sung in the streets by<lb/> English Children. I was surprised, but on listening to catch the words I heard<lb/> the word 'Munitions' and some other such words. At the present time everything<lb/> is being done to anglicize Ireland. This Home Rule question caused a great deal<lb/> of dissatisfaction over here. England is ruled by the press. I saw letters in<lb/> the 'Times' advocating conscription for Ireland as the only means of settling<lb/> the Irish Question. It stands to reason that if Conscription for Ireland came<lb/> into force, this, in addition to all that have been already killed in the war<lb/><seg type="del">and</seg> the tide of emigration <seg type="del">and</seg> the loyal spirit displayed by the Redmondites<lb/> and the number of Sinn Feiners locked up, must help to kill Irish patriotism,<lb/> and <seg type="del">she</seg> Ireland  would in time cease to be a nation, especially if English settlers<lb/> should settle in Ireland and intermarry with the people. The loyal spirit of<lb/> the Redmonds at the present time is very unpleasant reading for sensitive  Irish <lb/> people. The English are indignant when the Germans shoot down any of <hi rend="underline">their</hi><lb/> countrymen, but they think it is all right,  when  they murder Irish patriots who could  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0635_img_2104_3"/>
              not possibly be 'traitors' to a foreign foe. At the time of the rebellion, the <lb/> papers ridiculed the Irish language, the people assuming Irish names, and called<lb/> attention to the fact that <seg type="del">that</seg> one of the leaders had an Irish name. The fact<lb/> of Irish Streets being renamed with Irish names etc. was supposed to foster<lb/> this rebellious spirit. They speak of the Irish as if they were only serfs and<lb/> slaves of England. The English Empire is trying to raise a Nation in England<lb/> out of vice and immorality to make up for the numbers killed in the war. The <lb/> most loathsome suggestions are held out to Englishwomen in this connection.<lb/> While this is being done Ireland is being drained of some of her best blood,<lb/> and Irishmen from the 'Island of Saints' go out to take their places with the<lb/> murderers condemned to death who have been let out of Scotland  Yard  to fight for<lb/> the King, and have been awarded the Victoria Cross. The sins against the Almighty <lb/> God can be glossed over, 'sins' against the King of England, never. I sincerely<lb/> hope Conscription will never extend to Ireland. Surely the Clergy ought to<lb/> have a greater influence over the people than John Redmond who is only looking<lb/> for a Baronetcy from the king, which will descend to his Soldier Son of whom he<lb/> seems to be so proud. I hope you Lordship will not consider it disrespectful<lb/> of me to send you the enclosed cutting. It is not certainly intended as such.<lb/> The Lord Mayor of London has been advocating the necessity for 'one great<lb/> British Church'. They want new and reformed Divorce Laws instead of the ' antiqu<lb/> ated' laws in force, and the trouble they say is the Clergy. One paper express ed <lb/> the opinion that the Country was saturated with ecclesiasticism, but that 'they<lb/> had yet got to learn that the New Testament was not the last <seg type="del">thing</seg> word  in Christ<lb/> ianity'. Truly we live in the days of Antichrist. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be<lb/>, Your Lordship's most obedient servant  (Miss) C. Moran </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>