<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4566">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Dr Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick, 7 February 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI/2/3/3/16/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4566</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1917-02-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2019">Bank Buildings, Kinsway, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1207">11 Fitzwilliam Place, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4566_img_3908_1"  type="Letter"  url="7f76d9ff31b1c6becedba7b641c15c16.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4566_img_3908_1"/>
             National Council for Combating Venereal Diseases.   President: The Right Hon. LORD SYDENHAM of Combe, G.C.S.I., etc, <lb/>Vice-Presidents: <lb/>Sir THOMAS BARLOW, BART., K,C,V,O M,D The LORD BISHOP OF SOUTHWARK. <lb/>MEMBERS OF THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE: <lb/> Sir Clifford Allbutt, K.C.B., M,D., F,R,S. Rev. J. Scott Lidgett, M.A., D.D <lb/>Sir Francis Champneys, BART., M.D Dr. C.J. Macalister. <lb/>Sir Watson Cheyne, BART., F.R.,S P Sir Malcolm Morris, K.C.V.Vo., F.R. <lb/>President Royal College of Surgeons. Dr. Mott, F.R.S. <lb/>Sir JOhn Collie, M.D Miss M.L. Rawlins, M.B <lb/>Mr. W.A.Coote. Mrs. Scharlieb, M.D <lb/>Mrs. Creighton. Mr. Charters Symonds, F.R.C.S. <lb/>Major Leonard Darwin (Hon. Treasurer). Dr. Frederick Taylor, <lb/>Colonel T.W. Gibbard, R.A.M.C President Royal College of Physicians <lb/>Sir Rickman Godlee, BART., K.C.V.O., F.R.C.S. Mrs Torrey. <lb/>Mrs. James Gow. Mr. E.B. Turner, F.R.C.S. <lb/>Dr. T. Wardrop Griffith. Mrs. R.P. Wethered. <lb/>Lord George Hamilton. Dr. Douglas White. <lb/>Mr. J. Ernest Lane, F.R.C.S <lb/>Hon. Secretaries— DR. OTTO MAY and MRS. A.C. GOTTO <lb/>Secretary— MISS H.F. NORRY.    BANK BUILDINGS, <lb/> KINGSWAY, LONDON, W.C.   7th February, 1917    Dr. Kirkpatrick, <lb/> 11, Fitzwilliam Place, <lb/> Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I have just heard from Sir John Moore that in all pro- <lb/>bability you would be interested in the work of this Council.   It is hoped that a Dublin Committee of Council may <lb/>be formed in the near future, if you would be willing to <lb/>co-operate with those members of Council already in <lb/>Dublin who are proposing to take the initiative in the <lb/>formation of Committee, would you communicate with <lb/> Sir John Moore.   I enclose further particulars of this organisation, and <lb/> need not say we should be most grateful for your support.   Yours very truly   <seg type="unclear">J. Fetto</seg>  <lb/>Joint Hon. Secretary.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>