<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1110">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emily Adelaide Wynne to her mother Alice Katherine Wynne, 19 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emily Adelaide Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Emily Adelaide Wynne to her mother, Alice Katherine Wynne (d. 1928). The letter is written from Dublin where Emily was staying with relatives. It refers to a relative who had been ill but is recovering, and to Emily&#39;s time in Dublin.The Wynne family ran successful German mining operations from the end of the nineteenth century and had an estate in County Wicklow.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>Wynne Collection, Ms. 10247/1/1098</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1110</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0670">Emily Adelaide Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-01-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1470">52 Lower Mount Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1267">Alice Katherine Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1110_img_337_1"  type="Letter"  url="f1f823b4bf9597f8b1030942a84281e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1110_img_337_2"  type="Letter"  url="6aab8cbb0b59d631ee17614a7bfeb230.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1110_img_337_3"  type="Letter"  url="8c44d9ec9e5a46d2c4a3e1d9ff2344c9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1110_img_337_1"/>
                52 Lower Mount Street    Jan 19th 1916   My dearest Muddie   Dr. Taylor looked in this evening <lb/> while I was there (he is a funny <lb/> man, but most friendly &amp; benign) <lb/> &amp; remarked that C. might leave <lb/> tomorrow or next day if he <lb/> liked, which you can imagine <lb/> is great joy. C. has sundry things <lb/> he wants to do &amp; must go to <lb/> see Dr. Ball, so we decided <lb/> it was better to wait till <lb/> Friday. If all avocations are <lb/> done we should hope to go down <lb/> by the 10.10 train, but I think <lb/> it is quite possible we may not <lb/> get off till the 4.30. I shall know <lb/> better tomorrow. C. has <seg type="foreign">carte blanche</seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1110_img_337_2"/>
              as to food &amp; may do any reasonable <lb/> going about but is not to mountaineer <lb/> or ride for a fortnight after which <lb/> he may do whatever he likes. <lb/> I think he will have no temptations <lb/> as to ride at any rate! He looks <lb/> very washed out now that he is <lb/> up &amp; dressed &amp; cannot yet straighten <lb/> himself quite in walking but his <lb/> Dr. is really pleased with him. <lb/> He is coming out shopping tomorrow. <lb/> The dear Aunts have most unjustifiably <lb/> bestowed 5/2 for locomotion <lb/> so we are going to have a vehicle <lb/> per hour. He will now be able to <lb/> clear off his liabilities with the help <lb/> of your advance. The electric clock <lb/> for J. has been the greatest resource <lb/> &amp; he wants to get some of the materials <lb/> to start it when at home. Today <lb/> was perfectly horrible after luncheon, <lb/> a tearing gale, which still continues &amp; <lb/> horrid   of rain. I had hoped to <lb/> get through some shopping but did practically <cb/> none, it was too wet &amp; horrid. C. &amp; I <lb/> had a very good tea together &amp; he <lb/> then discovered a delightful occupation <lb/> i.e. decorating the glass burners of the <lb/> electric stove with ribald drawings <lb/> which kept him very happy all <lb/> the evening. I don't know what <lb/> the sister will say to him! But I <lb/> think they are all much inclined <lb/> to spoil the young man! He has <lb/> been walking about a lot &amp; out into <lb/> the passages &amp; was to have a bath <lb/> this evening. All his dressings have <lb/> been taken off the wound which <lb/> makes him much more comfortable <lb/> but he still complains of being 'tied <lb/> up in a bind' from it, but the <lb/> Dr. &amp; nurses are not at all sym- <lb/> pathetic as to that. No doubt it <lb/> will soon wear off as the skin gets <lb/> limber again. I hope to do the <lb/> commissions tomorrow. I enclose <lb/> another letter C. got from J. Please keep  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1110_img_337_3"/>
              it for him. Also will you give <lb/> my letter to Hilda and Wm who <lb/> will deal with it.   Now goodbye Mother dearest, it is <lb/><hi rend="underline">very</hi> joyful to look forward to <lb/>being together again so soon &amp; the <lb/>boy, please God will be really better <lb/> &amp; stronger than ever before. <lb/> Much love to all  <seg type="closer"> Your very loving child  <hi rend="underline">E.A. Wynne</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>