<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0863">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cecil Spring Rice to Sir Edward Grey, 23 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cecil Spring Rice</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Cecil Spring Rice (1859–1918) to Sir Edward Grey (1862–1933) concerning the patronage of Cardinal John Murphy Farley (1842-1918) over the Irish Relief Fund. According to Spring Rice Farley&#39;s patronage is based on the condition that his actions are not associated with support or sympathy for those who partook in the Easter Rising. Rice notes the pre-existing and increase in hostility shown towards England in the Irish-American community which has been inflated by the executions of the leaders of the Easter Rising. In 1916 Cecil Spring Rice was serving as the British ambassador to the United States. Spring rice took up the position in 1912 and remained until 1918. Sir Edward Grey, 1st Viscount Grey of Fallodon, was a British Liberal statesman. He served as Foreign Secretary from 1905 to 1916, the longest continuous tenure of any person in that office.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5618/12620/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/863</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1238">Cecil Spring Rice</persName>
              <date>1916-06-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1399">British Embassy, Washington, United States of America</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Grey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0863_img_2422_1"  type="Letter"  url="edc970be3aa6b77387d318cac0dbbb3b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0863_img_2422_2"  type="Letter"  url="0d28d6a6cc94d5d60d3640bb9195cbe5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0863_img_2422_3"  type="Letter"  url="d35d6d15caffb1c02eac7e90dc233883.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0863_img_2422_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">COPY</hi><lb/>(123255/45A) <lb/>No. 559    BRITISH EMBASSY  WASHINGTON    June 23rd 1916.   Sir,   I understand that His Eminence Cardinal Farley of <lb/>New York has consented to become Honorary President of <lb/>the Irish Relief Fund as he has done in the case of the <lb/>Polish and other charitable associations, only upon the <lb/>express condition that no political significance should <lb/>be attached to his honorary protection of the work.  His patronage has attracted a great deal of attention <lb/>and was thought at one time to signify his <lb/>sympathy with the extreme section of the Irish party who advocatâ <lb/>ed a policy of physical force and were promoting a <lb/>revolution in Ireland. You will observe however that <lb/>the action taken by His Eminence was in a line with <lb/>that already taken in regard to charitable funds for <lb/> Catholic sufferers by the war. His present intention <lb/>is, I believe, to convey the money collected by the Reâ <lb/>lief Society for the sufferers by the troubles in Ireland <lb/>by a special messenger to Dublin where the funds will <lb/>be received by His Grace Archbishop Walsh. The Archâ <lb/>bishop has, I understand, undertaken to consult with <lb/>the Society of St. Vincent de Paul. The delegate <lb/>chosen is a friend whom the Cardinal knows well and <lb/>highly appreciates as well as recommends. The sums are <lb/>to be distributed for benevolent and not political purposes.  In the opinion of some competent observers it is <lb/>thought that in the highly strained condition of Irish <lb/>opinion here it might be dangerous to send any one reâ <lb/>presenting  The Right Honourable <lb/>Sir Edward Grey Hart., K.G., M.P. <lb/>etc. etc. etc.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0863_img_2422_2"/>
              presenting the Irish Political party to Dublin. There is <lb/>however a proposal which would probably be considered obâ <lb/>jectionable by His Majesty's Government, namely to dis <lb/>tribute the product of the collection, which represents <lb/>a considerable sum, through the hands of persons here <lb/>formerly strong adherents of Mr. Redmond but who are now <lb/>strong opponents of any sort of connection between England <lb/>and Ireland. It would seem to be the wisest course to <lb/>take advantage of the good offices of Archbishop Walsh <lb/>and the Society of St. Vincent de Paul in order to seâ <lb/>cure the distribution of the fund to bona fide sufferers <lb/>and to prevent the misuse of the money for political <lb/>purposes. I have no doubt that His Majesty's Government <lb/>will adopt a benevolent attitude to any movement actuated <lb/>by motives of racial sympathy and of christian charity <lb/>such as is outlined in the scheme which appears to be viewâ <lb/>ed with favour by Cardinal Farley.  It will of course have been apparent to you from the <lb/>reports which I have sent home as to most of the meetings <lb/>held in order to collect subscriptions for the sufferers <lb/>from the Dublin insurrection, that the spirit animating <lb/>most of the speakers was one of extreme hostility to <lb/>England. Many of the meetings have a strong proâGerman <lb/>tinge and most of the promoters were men who have no intentâ <lb/>ion whatever of residing in Ireland and whose main motive <lb/>in promoting Irish hostility to England is not by any <lb/>means their concern for the welfare of Ireland but the <lb/>necessity in which they are placed to maintain their own <lb/>position here on the basis of hostility between the two <lb/>neighbouring islands. As I have already reported this  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0863_img_2422_3"/>
              <lb/>hostility has very much increased as of late by the <lb/>Irish executions and is at present so far as Irish <lb/>Americans are concerned as intense as it has ever been. <lb/>The main difference between the present situation and <lb/>that in former years is that on the whole the opinion <lb/>of the general American public is more indifferent to <lb/>the Irish cause than it was, a fact which is mainly due <lb/>to the German Irish alliance which has excited great <lb/>antipathy here, and to the general sympathies with the <lb/>cause of Belgium and France with which that of England <lb/>is united. <seg type="closer"> I have etc.  (Sgd) CECIL SPRING RICE </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>