<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0663">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Jerome O'Mahony SJ to his Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ, 25 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jerome O&#39;Mahony</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr Jerome O&#39;Mahony SJ (1869-1930), 5th Canadian General Hospital, Salonika 1917 to his Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941), 25 May 1916. He refers to the Easter Rising 1916, a conference of chaplains in Salonika, discussion on the dispensing of carrying an ordinary altar stone for those travelling on horseback, the numbers in hospital, their ailments and the 10th Division. He praises the work of Fr. O&#39; Connor of Clonfert diocese.Fr Jerome O’Mahony SJ was born 28 November 1869 at Kilmallock, county Limerick His family moved to Charleville, county Cork when he was a baby. Educated at the Christian Brothers, Charleville, Tullabeg and Clongowes Wood College, Fr. O’ Mahony taught at Clongowes Wood College, Belvedere College, Mungret College, Limerick, St. Ignatius, Galway, and Crescent College, Limerick, before the war. He served as a chaplain from 1915-1919.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/47/6, IE IJA/CHP1/47/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/663</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0977">Jerome O&#39;Mahony</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0954">Salonika, Greece</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0663_img_2146_1"  type="Letter"  url="639c2c1605cd85c037d6c7fcf76b11ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0663_img_2146_2"  type="Letter"  url="79c892ebc44ae01881129c6eee534183.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0663_img_2146_1"/>
                5th Canadian Gen. Hospital  Salonika  M.E.F.     May 25th â16    Dear Fr. Provincial,   P.C. (Pax Christi) Your Reverence will be glad <lb/> for a breath of the peaceful air of Salonika amidst <lb/> the stress of battle in Dublin. We get a bundle <lb/> of English papers about once a week or once in <lb/> ten days here &amp; from the last batch that came <lb/> I was very glad to see that things are <lb/> becoming quiet &amp; settled in Dublin. I heard <lb/> on Wednesday that Dr. Walters &amp; Fr Stafford were <lb/> both killed. We had a conference yesterday of <lb/> all the R.C. chaplains in Salonika district. About <lb/> 19 turned up out of 21. Two S.J. of the English <lb/> Province Fr. H. Day and Fr. Luck, an Irish Franciscan <lb/> Fr. Dore &amp; Irish Seculars Fr. Morrissey (Waterford) Fr OâConnor  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0663_img_2146_2"/>
              Clonfert &amp; Fr. Farrell (Ardagh). This was the first we had <lb/> but they are to take place once a month in future. Monsignor Cavendish <lb/> announced that the dispensing with ordinary altar stone for chaplains <lb/> who have to travel distances on horseback is under consideration <lb/> &amp; something like Agnus Dei with relics to be placed on altar to <lb/> be used instead. We had over 1100 in hospital here about <lb/> ten days ago &amp; <seg type="del">will</seg> shall have about the same number in <lb/> the coming week as it is our receiving week ie the four <lb/> Gen. hospitals take week in turn to receive all cases of the <lb/> region that are likely to require treatment for anything over a <lb/> week the milder cases giving to Casualty stations &amp; Sta-<lb/> tionary hospitals. The big numbers in hospital are the <lb/> after effects of the cold and privations of the winter brought <lb/> to the surface by a wetting, extra long march etc. A great <lb/> many are 10th division who are about ten miles off.<lb/> One section has a splendid priest seeing after them. Fr. O' <lb/> Connor of Clonfert not unlike our Fr. Claffey. I have <lb/> hardly found one in hospital here belonging to his Sec-<lb/> tion who had not made his Easter duty. I hope all <lb/>are keeping well at home. I must now conclude. <seg type="closer"> With best wishes<lb/> I remain<lb/><seg type="unclear">r<hi rend="superscript">de</hi> R<hi rend="superscript">al</hi></seg> Servus in Xto <lb/> <lb/> Servant in Christ  J.C. OâMahony, C. F. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>