<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1545">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Griffin to the Hon. Sec., Mayo Prisoners of War Fund, November, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Griffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The writer&#39;s brother is a 12th Lancers Prisoner of War and a native of Galway. He was refused assistance by the Galway Fund because he wasn&#39;t a Connaught Ranger - Mr. Griffin encloses a letter from the Galway Fund to this effect (not available. He thinks that it is unfair that his brother should be forgotten because he belongs to another regiment.
Finally he thanks the ladies of Mayo for their kindness to his brother and he expresses the hope &#34;that we will soon be victorious and beat the Huns&#34;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/10/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1545</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0723">John Griffin</persName>
              <date>1916-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1097">Provincial Bank, Galway, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Honorary Secretary, Mayo Prisoners of War Fund</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1664">35 Molesworth Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1545_img_1012_1"  type="Letter"  url="5138b9c032c5e7e9f52ade531eac56f5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1545_img_1012_1"/>
             Provincial Bank <lb/>Galway  <lb/>To the Hon. Secty <lb/>Co. Mayo Prisoners of war fund  Dear Madam   With reference to your enquiry re my <lb/>Brother Peter Griffin of the 12<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Lancers <lb/>a prisoner of war. I beg to say that he is <lb/>a native of Galway town but I enclose <lb/>you a letter from the Hon Secty of the <lb/>Galway fund to show you that he has <lb/>never received any<seg type="del">thing</seg>assistance from <lb/>it because he is not a Connaught Ranger. <lb/>I think it is very unfair to him that he <lb/>should be forgotten because he belongs <lb/>to another regiment. I beg to thank <sic>they</sic> <lb/>Ladies of Mayo for their kindness to him <lb/>and hope that we will soon be victorious <lb/>and beat the Huns.   Yours very grateful   John Griffin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>