<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1201">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr William Keary to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 25 September 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W. Keary</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Keary (1881-1958) to Fr Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding the death of Fr. John Fitzgibbon.Fr. Thomas V Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War. Fr William Keary SJ was a member of the English Jesuit Province and served as a chaplain in the First World War. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/24-25, IJA/CHPI/21/24-25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1201</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0303">W. Keary</persName>
              <date>1918-09-25</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1201_img_3883_1"  type="Letter"  url="ccc335b67ff0a463fc4e1c3d2ae3d0f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1201_img_3883_2"  type="Letter"  url="ea398bf7a9c888b090db0e36f5ada8cd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1201_img_3883_3"  type="Letter"  url="762f2a5b6d5dc8f1a76a835ed6c45cba.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1201_img_3883_1"/>
                Wednesday 25-9-18   Dear Fr. Provincial P.C.   You will already have heard the <lb/>very sad news of Fr. Fitzgibbon's death.  Will you please accept my most sincere <lb/>condolences and those of all the Officers and <lb/>men of his unit (16. Field Ambulance).  I last saw him at Boulogne, on my way <lb/> to England for leave on the <seg type="del">1</seg>6 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of this month. <lb/>He had just come back from Lourdes, and <lb/>had said Mass, just returning to the sacristy <lb/>as I was vesting for mine. An hour or so later <lb/>he saw me off on the leave boat. He was <lb/><hi rend="underline">full</hi> of Lourdes; &amp; no doubt Our Lady has <lb/>conferred on him what she considers the best <lb/>favour.  I did not learn of his death till my <lb/>return from leave on Sunday last (22 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>). <lb/>On Wednesday (18<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi>) he was called out from <lb/>lunch about 1:30 p.m, to bury a Catholic boy; <lb/>after the funeral he was chatting with a German <lb/>Catholic prisoner in the cemetery when a shell  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1201_img_3883_2"/>
              landed in their midst; and the poor Father <lb/>fell first on his knees and then forward <lb/>on his face, praying aloud. One of our <lb/>'boys' (who gave  me  those details later) rushed to <lb/>his assistance, but hed only raised him on to <lb/>his knees when another shell burst in on <lb/>them and he had to drop his burden and <lb/>throw himself on the ground to avoid death. <lb/>A few minutes later Fr. Fitzgibbon's body <lb/>was removed, and he was buried next day <lb/>by Fr. McGuinness who wrote to his father, <lb/>but told me he had not written to you.  Wont you please excuse my not having <lb/>written sooner. We are having a pretty rough <lb/>lively time <seg type="del">jus</seg> since my return and I am <lb/>taking advantage of a lull in the in-coming <lb/>of the wounded to write these few hurried lines.  I cannot tell you what a dreadful loss Fr. <lb/>Fitzgibbon is to the Division. He was a splendid <lb/>organiser, most tactful, always working, and <lb/>most kindly and helpful to us junior Chaplains.  Then of course he and I were very close <lb/>friends, for we were both Jesuits and I knew  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1201_img_3883_3"/>
              him during his philosophy at St. Marys Hall.  I have come to 16 Field Ambulance in his <lb/>stead, as I consider it a better centre to <lb/>work from now that he is gone; and we <lb/>have lost our Artillery Chaplain, <lb/>Fr. Brown (a secular priest) who has gone down <lb/>seriously wounded. So you see <seg type="del">Fr. M</seg><lb/>Fr Mc. Guinness &amp; myself who are the only <lb/>two chaplains left in the Division have <lb/>a great deal of work on our hands.  Good bye now dear Fr. Provincial, <lb/>and please remember us and our work in <lb/>your Mass sometimes. <seg type="closer"> Yours respectfully in Christ  W. Keary S.J. <lb/>16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Field Ambulance <lb/>B.E.F.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>