<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3450">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Albert Augustus Wynne to Alice Clara Veronica Wynne, 30 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Albert Augustus Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Albert Augustus Wynne to his daughter Veronica (Alice Clara Veronica Wynne). Albert thanks her for her letter; mentions Charlie (Charles Wyndham Wynne; her brother); writes about missing her very much and about the war being depressing; however, it should be noted that Albert&#39;s handwriting is very difficult to decipher and it is therefore hard to establish greater detail without a very detailed assessment.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/375</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3450</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0838">Albert Augustus Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-01-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2122">Co. Wicklow (Tigroney, Avoca), Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Clara Veronica Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0049">(Perhaps London; as an envelope (TCD MS 104247-1-376) addressed to her (Alice Clara Veronica Wynne) dated 16 March 1916 specifies London)</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3450_img_286_1"  type="Letter"  url="c1a23f436ea3319a294d432f79d2e065.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3450_img_286_2"  type="Letter"  url="ee07c8ed5e60eaf6c815eaf4b42438f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3450_img_286_3"  type="Letter"  url="4c5c56d9c1574932a9f489749456bfe9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3450_img_286_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">Tyrone</seg>   30/1/16   Dear V   I was very pleased to get<lb/> your letter of 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; as this day<lb/> is considered too wet  for me  to be<lb/> in church with mother, Eve<lb/> &amp; C and Win is occupied<lb/> in the Hitchens. I thought I<lb/> <sic>wd</sic> fill this time by writing<lb/> you a line in reply to yours.   I am afraid you must<lb/> feel it rather desolate<lb/> being among entire<lb/> strangers &amp; coming back<lb/> in the evening after <sic>yr</sic> work<lb/> must miss a loving greeting<lb/> as you were sure of at Richmond.   We were glad to get your
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3450_img_286_2"/>
            <lb/>act. of your Charlie &amp; of <lb/>your company — perhaps <lb/>some more sympathetic <lb/>humans may in time develop <lb/>or turn up.    The night darkness must <lb/>be further depressing, I hope <lb/>you are not often <seg type="unclear">headaching</seg> <lb/>&amp; that you will have enjoyed <lb/>your morning with      We all miss you here very much, <lb/>my own little daughter &amp; I <lb/>am constantly being reminded <lb/>of your absence — but we mustn't <lb/>want too much, we have so much <lb/>which to be thankful for when <seg type="unclear">down</seg> <lb/>I think of the many sorrowing <lb/> households all round.   Charlie is progressing <lb/>splendidly &amp;and it seems to be <lb/> he is now beginning to realise <lb/>what an improvement in his <lb/>life he may look forward to <lb/>now instead of this much <lb/>suffering which he now admits <lb/>to. He is looking forward to <lb/>his full emancipation &amp; <lb/>2 <seg type="unclear">cherishing</seg> the next Wednesday.    Mr McCausland, Mr <seg type="unclear"> &amp; Lettie</seg> <lb/>were here to lunch yesterday &amp; <lb/>in spite of dreary, foggy day <lb/>seemed to enjoy their visit.    We are looking forward to <lb/>May's (Mrs.J.B.W) visit tomorrow <lb/>evening, she will probably stay <lb/>till end of week &amp; she will be       War news is depressing <lb/>these times — I wonder do you hear <lb/>more than we —   The worker at Glendalough are <lb/><seg type="unclear">at last again Martin</seg> &amp;
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3450_img_286_3"/>
            <lb/>&amp; I believe   <lb/>well — but Smith is bad <lb/>at writing. I hope <seg type="unclear">Em</seg> <lb/>will now be able to run up <lb/>and stir him up   No more for the present.   Your very loving Father   Albert Wynne 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>