<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0366">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from E. F. Batty to Robert Chalmers, 17 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>E. F. Batty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by E. F. Batty to the under-secretary of Ireland. In this letter Batty argues in favour of arming the police force of Dublin, and handing over control of that force to the government for the duration of the war, in light of the recent events of Easter Week. Batty believes that this move would maintain law and order in Dublin while also restoring confidence. The letter is addressed to the under-secretary, which at this time is Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary following the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5611/8530/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/366</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0533">E. F. Batty</persName>
              <date>1916-05-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1938">2 Isabella Place, Bath, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0366_img_1612_1"  type="Letter"  url="092709745ad6d149d86861e3a5240b50.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0366_img_1612_2"  type="Letter"  url="0b70152a3472eeef55b184d0ba2ef820.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0366_img_1612_3"  type="Letter"  url="af8a38bb48f0a686cf5fc1e569999739.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0366_img_1612_4"  type="Letter"  url="092709745ad6d149d86861e3a5240b50.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0366_img_1612_1"/>
                2 <sic>Issabella</sic> Place  Combe Down  Bath    May 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916  <lb/> 7425 <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>  To the Under Secretary Dublin  Castle   Sir   I suppose that there is<lb/> some secretary to attend to<lb/> letters <seg type="unclear">it</seg> at present though<lb/> there is no regular Irish Government<lb/> now —  I beg to acknowledge the<lb/> receipt of your letter of<lb/> the 10<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> of May &amp; to point out<lb/> that my name is EF BATTY.<lb/> I fear I do not always write<lb/> it sufficiently distinctly<lb/> It might lead to some<lb/> mistake if you read it wrong  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0366_img_1612_2"/>
              <lb/>I presume your letter is a <lb/> mere form - sent to hundreds <lb/> but in case it is not I <lb/>beg to say I did not offer <lb/> my services - though if on <lb/>the spot I would have been <lb/>glad to be of use — you <lb/> might just run your <seg type="unclear">hen</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">though the route of the offer</seg><lb/> It is a friendly hint that <lb/> I should have done so I <lb/> must mention I am 53 and <lb/>short sighted &amp; have never <lb/> handled a rifle.  I want to make a non <lb/> political suggestion that <lb/>only occurred to me today <lb/> If Dublin had been policed <lb/>by the RIC the late events <lb/>could not have taken so <lb/> serious a turn &amp; the prob <lb/> lem would have been far <lb/>less —  Would it not be a good <lb/>thing if <hi rend="underline">during the war the <lb/> control of the Policing of <lb/> Dublin was in the hands of <lb/>the Government &amp; not the <lb/> Corporation</hi> — and if the <lb/> Police force was (like the RIC) <lb/> mostly  trained to the use of the Rifle  All are interested in the <lb/>maintenance of law &amp; order <lb/>&amp; I think it would tend to <lb/> restore confidence —  It might be well to <seg type="unclear">leave some</seg><lb/>of the police force unarmed <lb/>but most of them would I expect  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0366_img_1612_3"/>
              <lb/>be fit to train as RIC are <lb/> trained (for town watch anyway)  It might or might not be <lb/> well to combine the two <lb/><seg type="unclear">forces</seg> -(So far as armed) <lb/> The safety of Dublin is the <lb/> main point &amp; this would <lb/> seem to tend to it.  There is no reason why in this <lb/> way a considerable body <lb/> properly armed trained &amp; <lb/> under the control of the <lb/> Government should not be <lb/> added to the forces available <lb/> in the safety of Dublin.  Armed Police would seemingly <lb/> have been able to prevent <lb/> many of the places being seized <lb/> &amp; much of the damage &amp; <lb/> left things far easier for the soldiers <lb/> to deal with. <seg type="closer"> Your Obed. Serv.  EF Batty </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0366_img_1612_4"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> PS There may be members<lb/> of Police Force - all right unarmed<lb/> who it would not be well to<lb/> arm </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>