<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0326">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Denis McCullough to James Ryan, c. June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Denis McCullough</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Denis McCullough (1883-1968) to James Ryan (1891-1970) was written while McCullough was a prisoner in Knutsford prison. In the letter, McCullough notes his surprise that Ryan had been arrested as he was only serving as a doctor during the Rising. He says that he is done &#39;for life&#39; with Eamonn Dore, who had served as a bodyguard to Seán MacDiarmada during the Rising. He refers to letters and visits from friends and describes prison regulations. Seeing Dublin on his way to England, he writes that it looks &#39;as if it had got struck by an earthquake&#39;. McCullough, who ran a piano tuning business in Belfast, writes that, if he is held much longer, his business would collapse. He expresses concern about the Home Rule Act (which had been postponed by the First Would War) potentially excluding Ulster, stating that &#39;the Pope will not have the life of a dog there after that.&#39;Denis McCullough was a founder of the Dungannon Clubs (which later merged with other groups to become Sinn Féin) and a member of the Irish Volunteers Executive. Kept aloof of the plans for the Rising, McCullough&#39;s attempt to take part in Connacht failed and he was arrested. James Ryan studied medicine at University College Dublin. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch, and was released in August 1916. Ryan became founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister. McCullough married Ryan&#39;s sister Agnes in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P88/4 (1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/326</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0986">Denis McCullough</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0577">Knutsford Prison, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0326_img_155_1"  type="Letter"  url="29932343323bf58a86c2be2c23175b6b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0326_img_155_2"  type="Letter"  url="ff6b1aec0a22e4eca6923b7b0b4c22b5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0326_img_155_1"/>
                Denis McCullough, Irish Prisoner C1-3  Knutsford   c/o Chief Postal Censor London  My Dear Jem   As Katie Phelan would say ye're a dote to write me <lb/> such a nice letter. I was wondering how you were &amp; quite expected <lb/> to be receiving 'comforts' from you, from home or Dublin long before <lb/> this. What the deuce are they keeping you for? It's a breach of <lb/> the Geneva Convention &amp; you doing medical work only. What is <lb/> the good of being a Doctor if you are not allowed to practice? And <lb/> Dore too. Where the devil did he come from &amp; how did he get <lb/> rounded into this? Remember me to him &amp; say that I am done <lb/> with him for life â I'll have nothing more to do with criminals, <lb/> especially from the South. I have just written to Mick Carolan. <lb/> Do you know him? He is there with a lot of the Belfast boys <lb/> &amp; I am sure has looked you up. He is a man after your own <lb/> heart â steeped in sin. I hear from Tomcoole occasionally <lb/> &amp; was delighted to hear about Kit getting home â it will be <lb/> Nell's turn next and I hope soon, too. I had a note from <lb/> Maureen Cregan yesterday &amp; a letter from Margaret Browne today. <lb/> Needless to say, they both speak of you in affectionate terms. <lb/> Margaret's is a screamer. All about a letter they had from Liam <lb/> O'Brian and a discussion between him &amp; Cole over the value <lb/> of a beard in <seg type="foreign">'affaires de Coeur'</seg>. In Maggie's best style â always <lb/>  Liam's beard is a triumph, I believe. What <lb/> is your own like? Mine is only incipient yet. The girls inform <lb/> me that Chris &amp; O'Malley are in Dublin this week. Not bad â his  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0326_img_155_2"/>
              intentions must be serious after all. And in war time too!   Pearse McCann &amp; myself and one or two others are kept away <lb/> from &amp; not allowed to mix with the common herd, but conditions <lb/> were relaxed today &amp; we are allowed to converse during <lb/> exercise. Seven of us in all. We get smoking &amp; reading also, <lb/> so it is more bearable now, at all events.   How are you off the smokes &amp; eatables etc.? I suppose <lb/> you get parcels from home â and other places. Some of <lb/> the <seg type="foreign">Cailini</seg> from Manchester &amp; Liverpool come down here <lb/> every day &amp; see that the boys want for nothing. I manage <lb/> tolerably well myself. If they do not let me out soon, I <lb/> will have to apply for a job on a farm or something, <lb/> as there will be no business left for me â especially <lb/> if they are going to make Ulster into a foreign territory &amp; <lb/> exclude Belfast from the Home Rule Bill. The Pope <lb/> will not have the life of a dog there after that.   I say, I saw Dublin when they were bringing us down <lb/> to the boat &amp; I must say they made 'some job' of it, during <lb/> Easter Week; looks as if it had got struck by an earthquake! <lb/> Got a great send off â all the girls were down to wave us a good <lb/>bye and blow kisses after us. I quite enjoyed it, but when we <lb/> got to sea â and a rough night â amongst the cattle &amp; the boxes of <lb/> dead fish, Oh, Lord. Don't remember anything more until we <lb/> struck here. Well, Goodbye now Jem and hoping to meet all soon again  <seg type="closer"> Yours always  Denis </seg><seg type="postscript"> PS Sean T. is at Wandsworth it would be nice to join the family <lb/> party, wouldn't it. Regards to all friends at Stafford. D.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>