<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2252">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a typed copy of letter written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924). The first page is missing. Montgomery was a lawyer and politician. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
The letter concerns details arising from a private Ulster Unionist Council meeting in Belfast and the British Cabinet decision to offer John Redmond (1856-1918) Home Rule due to international pressure. In addition to this, they have authorized Lloyd George to make a settlement so as not to coerce Ulster into Home Rule. The basis for this settlement is a six county Ulster. Montgomery writes that it would be better to maintain a six county exclusion rather than a nine county exclusion in order to keep the ratio of Unionists to Nationalists in the Unionist&#39;s favour. The opinions expressed by Montgomery in this letter reflect the importance Unionists placed on international perception in order for their cause to be successful. Montgomery also writes that while in Dublin he got the impression that another rebellion was imminent whether the terms put forward by Lloyd George were accepted or not. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/44</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2252</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2252_img_1696_1"  type="Letter"  url="d0d1538ee65945837c0913d3f34fad95.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2252_img_1696_2"  type="Letter"  url="0bbcea878a81dcf1a6bbac617f841dde.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2252_img_1696_3"  type="Letter"  url="3b3b5ff1610fba473b4790c2e7b27de7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2252_img_1696_4"  type="Letter"  url="8dc8c941e7f9b34a5b7063df9698dc2c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2252_img_1696_5"  type="Letter"  url="37a43ad0c011c4dd27289a25a864bfd6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2252_img_1696_6"  type="Letter"  url="110fb138468f72835212efa71bb5775c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2252_img_1696_1"/>
             0627/429  -2-  I think I gave you in a letter I wrote to you on the 9th<lb/>in the the main details of the situation as it was put before us in<lb/>Belfast. It took Carson an hour &amp; a half to explain the<lb/>situation at the private meeting of the Unionist Council, &amp; I<lb/>cannot pretend to tell you all he told us; but the main point<lb/>was this - The Cabinet having unamimously decided that under the<lb/>pressure of difficulties with America, the Colonies Parliament<lb/>(but chiefly with America) they must offer Redmond Home Rule<lb/>at once; <seg type="del">but that</seg> am (not being prepared to coerce Ulster) <seg type="del">they had</seg> having<lb/>authorised Lloyd George to arrange a settlement, Carson, after what<lb/>happened at the Buckingham palace Conference in 1914, could<lb/>not well refuse to submit to his followers the exclusion of six<lb/>counties as a basis of negotiation. Carson had satisfied him<lb/>- self apparently that he had lost all the ground he &amp; his<lb/>colleagues had gained in their anti-Home Rule campaign before the<lb/>war, &amp; that the majority of the Unioniist members &amp; voters<lb/>took the same view as the majority of the Unionist papers as to<lb/>the necessity of a settlement. If Ulster Unionists refused to<lb/>consider such a settlement the Nationalists &amp; Radicals would<lb/>hold them up to odium as the people who were preventing a settle-<lb/>ment of the Irish question, &amp; they could not hope for any sympathy<lb/>or support in Great Britain now or hereafter. The Home Rule Act<lb/>was on the Statute Book <hi rend="superscript">and</hi>now that the Unionist leaders in the<lb/>Coalitiion Government had become parties <seg type="del">of</seg>to a proposal to bring<lb/>it into immediate operation in 26 counties where was no hope 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2252_img_1696_2"/>
             0627/429  -3-   of removing it from the Statute Book at the end of the war . If we did not agree to<lb/>a settlement we should have the Home Rule Act coming into<lb/>operation without the exclusion of any part of Ulster, or subject<lb/>only to some worthless Amending Act which Asquith might bring in<lb/>in fulfilment of this pledge, &amp; we should either have to<lb/>submit to this fight. To begin fighting here at the end<lb/>of the great war would be hopeless &amp; we could not hope for any<lb/>support. If, in spite of our apparent weakness we succeeded<lb/>in our fight we could not possibly hope to get more than we<lb/>were now offered without fighting, viz the exclusion of six<lb/>counties, we should probably get less: <seg type="del">therefore </seg>We should be<lb/>in a better position to hold our own and help our friends with<lb/>only six counties excluded returning 16 Unionists and 9 Nationalists<lb/>then we should be with 9 counties excluded returning 17 Nationalists<lb/>&amp; 16 Unionists. <seg type="del">perhaps</seg>We should be in a better position to<lb/>help Unionists in any part of Ireland if we are excluded than if<lb/>we formed portion of a permanent minority in a Dublin Parliament:<lb/>therefore on the whole Carson was justified in coming to us &amp;<lb/>recommending us to authorise him to enter upon negotiations on<lb/>the bases of the exclusion of the six counties, &amp; the chief reasons<lb/><seg type="del">ofr</seg>for recommending us to agree to this were:- (1 ) that if we did<lb/>not agree to do this we should lose any remaining sympathy<lb/>we had in Great Britain as the people who had prevented Ireland<lb/>being pacified. (2) That if we did not take this offer we should<lb/>never get as good a one again. ( 3 ) that the Cabine<seg type="del">t</seg> having  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2252_img_1696_3"/>
             0627/029  -4-    unanimously made up their minds to give some form of Home Rule<lb/>at once we could not prevent it: of course if the Home Rulers<lb/>themselves refused the offer that is a different pair of shoes.    It appears now however, that Lloyd George told a great<lb/>many lies, &amp; that some of the Unionist members of the Cabinet<lb/>were not parties to the decision which was the basis of all this<lb/>negotiating. I conjecture that Walter Long and Lansdown were<lb/>both rather ill at the time and did not fully take the thing<lb/>in, and that Bonar Law was, as my friend says he found him,<lb/>last week, helpless in face of Colonial opinion in favour of<lb/>Home Rule; but if Redmond's Convention refuses to accept the<lb/>terms in spite of his having <seg type="del">corroborated</seg> interpreted them in a different<lb/>sense to that conveyed to Carson by Lloyd George of course,<lb/>the thing must fall to the ground, and then the Nationalists,<lb/>and not the Unionists will carry the blame for preventing the<lb/>settlement. The only danger is that Lloyd George should come<lb/>back to us &amp; say that the Nationalists wont accept the six county<lb/>basis you must sacrifice something more for the sake of the Empire<lb/>and agree to a four county basis or to no exclusion. Carson<lb/>will, I am confident, refuse to put any such proposal before the<lb/>Unionist Council. It was quite clearly understood that the<lb/>six counties was minimum. The Nationalists will then try<lb/>after all to say that we were the people that prevented Ireland<lb/>being pacified: but I do not think they would succeed, as all<lb/>the papers have put on record their view of the reasonableness<lb/>of our decision.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2252_img_1696_4"/>
              0627/429  -5-    Carson holds a letter from Lloyd George stating that the<lb/>proposed Amendment of the Government of Ireland Act is to be<lb/>a definitive one &amp; not an Emergency Measure for the duration<lb/>of the war; but of course if the Nationalists refuse to approve<lb/>of the whole thing tomorrow even as presented to them by Redmond<lb/>that question will not arise. The Ulster Unionists will be<lb/>more or less on velvet when the matter comes to be finally settled.      The machine is evidently being worked for all it is<lb/>worth to secure a decision at to-day's Nationalist Convention<lb/>in favour of agreeing to the Lloyd George Settlement; but it<lb/>seems to me that if Redmond accomplishes this his difficulties<lb/>will be only beginning. I was in Dublin for two or three days<lb/>last week, &amp; the Southerners I met are all convinced that there<lb/>will be another rebellion whether the Lloyd George terms are<lb/>accepted or not. The fact that these terms were suggested has<lb/>enormously strengthened the Sinn Feiners in the country. The<lb/>mischief has been done by the suggestion. The acceptance of the<lb/>suggestion by the Ulster Unionists has not had much effect on<lb/>this part of the question. The Unionists acceptance under protest<lb/>had only increased Redmond's difficulties, &amp; as we are given to<lb/>believe placed us in the position in the eyes of British public<lb/>opinion of being reasonable people. If Redmond actually<lb/>forms a Government and tries to rule this country the Rebellion    
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2252_img_1696_5"/>
             0627/429  -6-    will be directed against him; if he does not the Rebellion will<lb/>be directed against the existing Government: in any case<lb/>the country will have more or less to be reconquered outside the<lb/>six counties, and that may possibly be the best way out of all our<lb/>troubles which all have their root in the British Prime Minister<lb/>having brought in a Home Rule Bill. The only actual serious<lb/>harm done by the action taken by the Ulster Unionists on Carson's<lb/>advice is the creation of bad feeling towards us among those who<lb/>think we have abandoned them in order to secure the privileged<lb/>position for ourselves. I don't think this charge is justified;<lb/>but it is difficult to get it out of the heads of our Southern<lb/>friends.    I have just seen the Morning Post &amp; think the remark<lb/>with which they begin their leader is not very far astray.<lb/>To set our Government against the German Government is<lb/>rather like putting a doe rabbit to fight a tom cat    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2252_img_1696_6"/>
             0627/429/44  P.S. What puzzles me most, about this Lloyd George Irish<lb/>Settlement business is, that <hi rend="underline">you</hi> should apparently be quite<lb/>ignorant of the other  cause of the whole thing, which must be a<lb/>F O matter, &amp; though you are on a particular job, it seems<lb/>to me that the nature of that job would require you to be<lb/>informed  of a critical matter of that kind , although the original despatch, or whatever it was<lb/>did not pass through your hands. I do not think that Carson<lb/>or Craig or the other Irish Unionist members would have e taken<lb/>Lloyd George's word without corroboration for the exceedingly<lb/>alarming nature of the complication which induced the Cabinet  (as<lb/>C&amp; C were given to believe)  unanimously to resolve to give Redmond Home Rule at once<lb/>&amp; ask Lloyd George to arrange for it being done peaceably<lb/>as regards Ulster. From the way in which both Craig &amp; Carson<lb/>put the matter to us at Belfast I am convinced that they were<lb/>convinced that the Cabinet were unanimously resolved to do this.<lb/>and that the American and Colonial complications were of a<lb/>sufficiently serious nature to account for, (though not to excuse<lb/>or justify) such a very unfortunate decision. From what I have<lb/>heard since, I think it is probable that they obtained their<lb/>information in corroboration of what Lloyd George told them<lb/>from Bonar Law, as I saw a man yesterday who saw Bonar Law<lb/>last week, and said he appeared to be absolutely helpless.   Under these circumstances I do not find any difficulty<lb/>in understanding why Carson came to the conclusion that it<lb/>would be bad tactics to simply oppose the introduction of a<lb/>measure of Home Rule at the present time.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>