<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4123">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lady Granard to John Redmond, 20 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Beatrice Forbes</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Beatrice Forbes to John Redmond regarding her husband&#39;s intentions towards Ireland. According to Mrs Granard her husband had hoped to arrange some position in Ireland, but, when told that they had nothing for him and that he could only occupy an honorary position he could not accept. As a result her husband as returned to the Salonika front.

Beatrice Forbes (1883-1972), née Mills, was an American heiress. In 1909 she married Bernard Forbes (1874-1948), the 8th Earl of Garnard. Forbes was a professional soldier and politician. He was recalled to command the 5th Battalion, Royal Irish Regiment in 1916. He was later Military Secretary to the Commander-in-Chief of the Salonika Forces from 1917.

John Redmond (1856-1918) was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers; MS 15,192/3/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4123</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0251">Beatrice Forbes</persName>
              <date>1916-01-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0103">Forbes House, Halkin Street, S.W., London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4123_img_3499_1"  type="Letter"  url="8938d76d72367a6e0cba570c6a8bbb84.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4123_img_3499_2"  type="Letter"  url="9587b00ac1112220e58c1b39b3cac483.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4123_img_3499_3"  type="Letter"  url="f23f8ba22958185d8befbb81d32e04aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4123_img_3499_4"  type="Letter"  url="c89bfbf4b4280c2e99165ed811cce660.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4123_img_3499_1"/>
             Jan <hi rend="underline">20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi>   FORBES HOUSE, <lb/>HALKIN STREET, S.W.   Dear Mr Redmond ,  Granard has gone back <lb/>to Salonica, and as you <lb/>have taken such a kindly <lb/>interest in his having the <lb/>opportunity of doing some <lb/>important work in Ireland <lb/>he asked me to write <lb/>&amp; explain to you why <lb/>nothing has happened. <lb/>It was as you will quite
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4123_img_3499_2"/>
            understand absolutely <lb/>essential that <hi rend="underline">if</hi> he came <lb/>away from active Service <lb/>he should have really important <lb/>work to do. We had hoped <lb/>that he might be either be <lb/>allowed to take over <lb/>"Manpower" in Ireland <lb/>with the rank of Brig. General <lb/>and do some <seg type="unclear">oficially</seg> good <lb/>work on the Civil side, <lb/>under the Ch. Secretary. Mr <seg type="unclear">Dukes</seg> <lb/>was very friendly, but at <lb/>present no <seg type="del">scheme</seg> scheme <lb/>has been decided. On
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4123_img_3499_3"/>
            the Military side when it <lb/>came to the real point <lb/>Granard was informed <lb/>that they could do nothing <lb/>better for him than put <lb/>him on the staff, really in <lb/>an honorary capacity for <lb/>for he was told that he would <lb/>have nothing much to do. <lb/>This of course was useless <lb/>for Granard to do, so <lb/>he has left again for the <lb/>Salonica Front. I trust that <lb/>you will   appreciate <lb/>that Granard was really
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4123_img_3499_4"/>
            most anxious to <hi rend="underline">serve</hi> <lb/>Ireland, but — he felt <lb/>that the only offer he <lb/>had, gave him no oppertunity <lb/>for doing so.   I hope that something good <lb/>may yet come of the <lb/>Civil side of things <lb/>&amp; that he may be recalled. <lb/>I hope you will forgive <lb/>me bothering you with <lb/>this long letter, but you <lb/>have been so very <hi rend="underline">kind</hi> <lb/>that Granard felt he would <lb/>like you to know what really <lb/>took place.   <hi rend="underline">Sincerely </hi>Yours   Beatrice <hi rend="underline">Granard</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>