<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3888">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 10 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Irish Jesuit Chaplain, Fr Willie Doyle SJ (1873-1917) to his father, Hugh Doyle, regarding his activities before being sent to the front. Doyle informs his father that they have finally received their marching orders and that the regiment will join up with the rest of the 16th Division on the following Saturday in France. As a result of their change to active service Doyle and his fellow officers were warned of the consequences of desertion. While swearing off the act himself Doyle acknowledges that there was many a poor fellow who was seeking an end to it all. Doyle writes that the number of Catholics has increased to 3,500 and that many are anxious to swear their accounts with God. In a postscript on the first pages he notes that three soldiers have asked to become Catholics.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3888</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1916-02-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1503">Bordon Camp, Hampshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1210">Melrose, Dalkey, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3888_img_3267_1"  type="Letter"  url="9cb29d05724f50618ad0e6183635746a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3888_img_3267_2"  type="Letter"  url="a171727c49d00dd546fc4bae6d8cea16.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3888_img_3267_3"  type="Letter"  url="1a1879e625fd943f5de60f07f1233ece.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3888_img_3267_4"  type="Letter"  url="dd5b9506c7593f9ea174dfcdeec8e21c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3888_img_3267_1"/>
             I am instructing<lb/>three soldiers who<lb/>have asked to<lb/>become Catholics.   Bordon Camp<lb/>Hants.    10/2/'16.    My dear Father,   At long last I<lb/>can say I am nearly a<lb/>gonner, as we have just<lb/>got marching orders for<lb/>Wed; next the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. It will<lb/>take two or three days to get<lb/>the whole Brigade away,<lb/>our artillery alone, when on<lb/>the march, reaching in an<lb/>unbroken line for at least<lb/>three miles! I shall remain<lb/>here till the last so as to<lb/>get as many to confession<lb/>as possible, but at latest<lb/>the last regiment will go  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3888_img_3267_2"/>
             2.  on Friday night, board ship<lb/>at Southampton and be<lb/>in France on Saturday. It<lb/>is an open secret that we<lb/>are going there to join<lb/>up with the rest of the<lb/>16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division.  The imparting this little<lb/>bit of news entailed a<lb/>pleasant ceremony. Our<lb/>Colonel informed us officially<lb/>that as we were now under<lb/>orders for active service any<lb/>officer who attempted to<lb/>desert would be arrested &amp;<lb/>at once shot. Made a<lb/>good resolution not to<lb/>desert, at least till I was<lb/>tired of life. Of course<lb/>there is not the smallest<lb/>possibility of any of us  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3888_img_3267_3"/>
             3.  trying for do so, but I am<lb/>not far wrong in saying<lb/>that in his heart of hearts<lb/>many a poor fellow is<lb/>wishing himself well out<lb/>of it all. As for this child,<lb/>like the Scriptural war-horse<lb/>he scents the battle from<lb/>afar and snorts, at the<lb/>same time (figuratively<lb/>at least) waggeth of his<lb/>tail from joy.  I could easily get leave of<lb/>absence to run across and<lb/>see you before we leave, but<lb/>I know you would far<lb/>sooner I should stay with<lb/>my men who during<lb/>the last couple of days<lb/>have been coming with<lb/>a rush to square their<lb/>accounts with God. The<lb/>new drafts have brought our  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3888_img_3267_4"/>
             4.  number of R. Cs to 3,500,<lb/>not including the artillery<lb/>and South Africans who are<lb/>also here, so I am not<lb/>exactly eating the bread<lb/>of idleness just now.  I shall write as often as I can<lb/>from the Front, but you must<lb/>not mind if you do not<lb/>hear from me for some<lb/>weeks. When a big battle<lb/>is on, lasting perhaps a<lb/>fortnight or more, the doctors<lb/>and chaplains are working<lb/>day &amp; night, snatching an<lb/>hour's sleep when best they<lb/>can. After Friday your<lb/>letters should be addressed<lb/>as enclosed.  Once more <seg type="foreign">au revoir</seg>.' I am<lb/>leaving behind me close on<lb/>a ton of miraculous medals<lb/>etc sent by pious nuns as I<lb/>think our Blessed Lord, Whom I<lb/>shall carry with me day &amp; night<lb/>to give Viaticum to the dying,<lb/>will be protection enough.   Will.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>