<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4312">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J.M. Wilson to Edward Carson, 11 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.M. Wilson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from J.M. Wilson to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4312</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1553">J.M. Wilson</persName>
              <date>1916-05-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1670">Currygrane, Edgeworthstown, Co. Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4312_img_3673_1"  type="Letter"  url="8ecce86fcb131b320b22f71538f7168f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4312_img_3673_2"  type="Letter"  url="61181249b27578a1d2349a7443d2f226.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4312_img_3673_3"  type="Letter"  url="f75de3da74878663bc121bdfbd03b69b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4312_img_3673_1"/>
             RAILWAY STATION, M.G.W.R.<lb/>EDGEWORTHSTOWN<lb/>TELEGRAMS —<lb/>BALLINALEE, 1 1/4 MILES.   J. M. WILSON,<lb/>CURRYGRANE,<lb/>EDGEWORTHSTOWN, <lb/><lb/> 11 May 1916 <lb/><lb/> Dear Sir Edward   D1507/A/16/15  There is no use in<lb/>blinking the fact that the<lb/>greatest apprehension is<lb/>felt here that too much<lb/>indulgence will be granted<lb/>by the Cabinet to the pleas<lb/>ad misericordiam of Redmond<lb/>&amp; C<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>.  No one asks for vengeance,<lb/>but weakness now would<lb/>be fatal. The following are<lb/>outstanding points, viz:  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4312_img_3673_2"/>
             1/<lb/>Martial Law to be kept in<lb/>force for <hi rend="underline">at least</hi> six months.<lb/><lb/>2/<lb/>The fact brought home to the<lb/>English people that this is<lb/>far from being merely a<lb/>Sinn Fein movement. I<lb/><hi rend="underline">assert positively</hi> that amongst<lb/>large sections of U.I.L. and<lb/>A.O.H. the utmost sympathy<lb/>exists with the rebels.<lb/><lb/>3/<lb/>The disarming of <hi rend="underline">all</hi><lb/>Not merely of Sinn Feiners.<lb/>including shot-guns &amp; revolvers.<lb/><lb/>4/<lb/>The absolute necessity of<lb/>discounting the <hi rend="underline">pretended</hi><lb/>concern of Redmond &amp; C<hi rend="superscript">A</hi> for<lb/>the interests of the Empire. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4312_img_3673_3"/>
             5/<lb/>The urgent necessity that<lb/>you or somebody for you<lb/>should employ at this<lb/>great crisis someone<lb/>thoroughly competent to piece<lb/>together all the parts of<lb/>evidence which may prove<lb/>hereafter invaluable as<lb/>showing how widespread the<lb/>conspiracy may be.  <lb/>6/<lb/>No successor  to Birrell  yet having<lb/>been appointed, there is a<lb/>tremendous necessity for a<lb/>strong man — Harcrust or<lb/>  would be disastrous.<lb/>The man you &amp; I talked<lb/>about would be far the best,<lb/><lb/><seg type="unclear">I</seg> have urged him strongly but,<lb/>I feel it may be impossible for<lb/>him, but, nothing at this<lb/>moment would so re-assure<lb/><seg type="unclear">public</seg> confidence as that he<lb/>was coming to Dublin.   <lb/>7/<lb/>The weak-kneed action of the P.M.<lb/>last night in refusing conscription<lb/><hi rend="underline">because</hi>, forsooth, Redmond op-<lb/>posed it is <hi rend="underline">disastrous.</hi> I<lb/>learn on all sides that the<lb/>feeling here amongst all<lb/>except the farmers, is one of<lb/>astonishment &amp; disgust that<lb/>the Cabinet has not had the<lb/>strength of mind to apply it<lb/>to Ireland. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>