<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0856">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 20 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). This letter is actually comprised of three separate sheets of paper, sent on the same date, but described by Spender as &#39;scrawls&#39; written in his spare time. Spender discusses financial matters, plans for his upcoming leave, and Lillian&#39;s current moves to secure a new house. He expresses frustration that he has received little news of his brother Rex. In the second section of the letter, Spender suggests that as &#39;Mab&#39;s children may be having a dull time, the Spenders&#39; &#39;Xmas gift&#39; to them could be &#39;an outing in town&#39;. He also notes that he has enclosed a cheque for three pounds. In the third section, Spender recounts a recent trip to the trenches, and mentions his gladness that Lillian has &#39;hit it off so well with Lady C&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/112, D1633/1/1/114</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/856</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0856_img_2416_1"  type="Letter"  url="0d763455a956dae0d774a1cc13395961.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0856_img_2416_2"  type="Letter"  url="26bf81dd674a0c0e1af1b9b996071f59.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0856_img_2416_3"  type="Letter"  url="e5ac7bf412f9f2e2e0c55ee68106f77e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0856_img_2416_4"  type="Letter"  url="0da7b61e61c4251b8d6ac395877ce69f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0856_img_2416_5"  type="Letter"  url="af16ec59d8e7376305c23e353d8eba63.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0856_img_2416_1"/>
                Posted 20th    I have a little spare time tonight whilst the others are out <lb/>so will begin a scrawl tho' it probably won't be worth posting <lb/>till Tuesday.   1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> business. You might send for my passbook to be ready <lb/>for me <hi rend="underline"> if </hi> I turn up, but don't ask for it till the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I shall <lb/>also want 'my' cash. box please. I shall probably turn <lb/>up travelling quite light with only my rucksack with underclothes  &amp; trousers  so <lb/>shall be glad if you can turn out a pair of boots, shoes, <seg type="del">trouser</seg> &amp; a <lb/>bag if I'm to travel anywhere.   I think those 5% bonds may be the things for you as<lb/> you will get good interest &amp; should have no depreciation 5 years<lb/> hence. I wish I could say the same of the past !   I have cashed a further for <seg type="del">Â£</seg><seg type="foreign">f<hi rend="superscript">co</hi></seg> 125.   I am longing to hear about the house &amp; whether you have <lb/>taken it. I expect now you will be simply dismayed at not having <lb/>got a burrow in time for b w. Shall he postpone his leave <lb/>if he gets it till Feb 7 ( &amp; probably a good bit further too ).   I cannot understand about Rex. Has he already gone to <lb/>Havre with a draft or as conducting officer ? The family are <lb/> very bad at forwarding letters &amp; I almost think they had better <lb/>come via me in spite of the time.   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0856_img_2416_2"/>
              All my Xmas letters will be reserved strictly till the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Very <lb/>good of me as they give me <lb/>quite a lot of curiosity already, as I only half remember them.  The date provisionally fixed for me is 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Jan 17 Victoria 7.45 pm <lb/>if I turn up it will be a deferred Xmas gift. Poor pr nothing but <lb/>an empty pawed BW. I hear 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> are not in the lines but shall <lb/>hope to see something of them. <seg type="closer"> Your bw </seg><seg type="postscript"> Genl back from boar hunt. I think he caught <lb/>the spirit of the chase, for his temper is <seg type="unclear">boorish</seg> ! He ought to <lb/>sleep well. </seg>  20 Dec   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0856_img_2416_3"/>
              As Mab's children <lb/>seem likely to have a <lb/>dull time perhaps we <lb/>could give them an outing <lb/>in town as our Xmas <lb/>gift. Any how I leave <lb/>this to you &amp; Mab  I have written a cheque <lb/>for Â£300. to <seg type="unclear">Jim</seg>part <lb/>for the other maids at 24   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0856_img_2416_4"/>
                Dec 20    Just back from a very pleasant day in the <lb/>trenches with 107 <seg type="unclear">Bsc</seg>. The have done <lb/>quite well. The men are anxious to come <lb/>back to the Div. The Officers are not! <lb/>Douglas was with me.  No more now. <seg type="closer"> Your B W   WBS  </seg><seg type="postscript"> ( 2 letters from you today but rather short. <lb/> So glad you hit it off so well with Lady C &amp; Lady F. <lb/>Very likely they will appear to cool off a bit later when <lb/>less keen on the work  1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>still possible unless Huns attack. </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0856_img_2416_5"/>
                Dec 20   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>