<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4288">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J.M. Wilson to Edward Carson, 3 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.M. Wilson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from J.M. Wilson to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4288</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1553">J.M. Wilson</persName>
              <date>1915-11-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1924">Currygrane, Edgeworthstown, Longford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4288_img_3651_1"  type="Letter"  url="0eaf53f826e8776d54d76c93898adc0e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4288_img_3651_2"  type="Letter"  url="f7684a90ff4faffb53f384e47042f1a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4288_img_3651_3"  type="Letter"  url="98ad0485e4533a0cfcd91168bb4fe9d7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4288_img_3651_1"/>
             RAILWAY STATION, M.G.W.R. <lb/>EDGEWORTHSTOWN. <lb/>TELEGRAMS — <lb/>BALLINALEE, 1 1/4 MILES.   <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   How 'cute of Redmond too, last night, in his fulsome <lb/>praise of W.A! <lb/>whom he once <lb/>refused to trust !!   J.M. WILSON, <lb/>CURRYGRANE, <lb/>EDGEWOTHSTOWN.   <hi rend="underline">3 NOV: 1915</hi>   Dear Sir Edward   Every honest man will <lb/>be delighted with your <lb/>speech of last night, you <lb/>have done much to <lb/>expose the shocking os— <lb/>cillation <sic>wh:</sic> has gone <lb/>on. No need for me <lb/>to dilate on this — I know <lb/><seg type="unclear">only</seg> too much, expecially <lb/>from the military point <lb/>of view — But this <lb/>letter is just to say one
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4288_img_3651_2"/>
            word regarding the <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> stand— <lb/>point of the war.   Surely you, or, someone who <lb/>will be listened to will <lb/>expose the pestilent nonsense <lb/>talked by J.Redmond last <lb/>night both as regards his <lb/>Volunteers  who melted when war was declared!  (<seg type="del">when</seg>, especially he <lb/>was talking 'through his hat' !) <lb/><hi rend="underline">and</hi> the bunkum about his <lb/>grievance over the Irish Regts: <lb/>not being appreciated — Poor <lb/>chaps they have fought <lb/>splendidly, and have earned <lb/>great praise from many <lb/>quarters as they <hi rend="underline"> fully</hi> deserve, <lb/>&amp; all this talk of his is only a blind to de—
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4288_img_3651_3"/>
            ceive England, &amp; give him <lb/><seg type="unclear">some sort</seg> of an apparent <lb/>grievance which he will <lb/>try to exploit against <lb/>NatService being applied <lb/>to Ireland.   One word of warning as <lb/>to above.   If my information is good <lb/>it goes to show the ex— <lb/>—istence of a gigantic <lb/>conspiracy over here, headed <lb/>by Redmond, Devlin, — Dillon <lb/>and abetted by certain <lb/>high officials in the Castle, <lb/>which would result in <lb/>a differentiation being made <lb/>as regards Ireland if &amp; <lb/>when Nat Service comes <lb/>on. You saw Devlins <lb/>speech at Kilkenny, on <lb/>Sunday last, I enclose you <lb/>J.Dillon's latest. What <lb/>right have these men to <lb/>indulge in such impertinent <lb/>assertions as to policy?   It would be <hi rend="underline">absolutely fatal</hi> <lb/>if Ireland were left out <lb/>of the scheme — Redmond only <lb/>represents farmers &amp; <seg type="unclear">shop boys,</seg> <lb/><hi rend="underline">none</hi>of them are enlisting.   Pray do not trouble to answer <lb/>this, you can have no <lb/>time.       <hi rend="underline">J Mackay Wilson</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>