<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6366">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell. to William J.H. Tyrrell 5, August, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Something has gone wrong with the post and William Upton Tyrrell has not received any lately. He suspects they will arrive together and soon. Rain has been heavy and unrelenting. He has been free to visit the nearby villages and is staying in a comfortable farm house. He mentions his new servant is very good, unlike his predecessor. Includes a detailed discussion of pencils. The best at the time being The Royal Soveirgn HB which costs 4 pence. William Upton Tyrrell asks if any of his letters have been opened by the sensor. William Upton Tyrrell Suggests that William J.H. Tyrrell take Bobby out for the 12th and wishes them a good day. Flypaper is included with rations. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6366</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-08-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6366_img_None_1"  url="0908dfb616ace5eee34889cd5a787c87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6366_img_None_2"  url="dccfdd3ff75651ef6fe5f513ed0095eb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6366_img_None_3"  url="91d093061055dc88e9f37e2d1ffae613.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6366_img_None_4"  url="728e5b08b4ae4431d527fdc74dc23658.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6366_img_None_5"  url="e2b256b4fd307bcc580570cdb37286d2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6366_img_None_6"  url="9cdf5631bd5c84a9300d5634ffbcadec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6366_img_0_1"/>
              5 August 1917    My dear Daddy   No news and I have no letters<lb/>to answer as something has gone wrong<lb/>with the post and letters have not<lb/>been forwarded yet. I know there<lb/>are lots for me somewhere and so<lb/>I will have a great read one of these<lb/>days. They will all come together I<lb/>expect. I am sure they will very soon<lb/>come as things are getting straightened<lb/>out here now. This is a nice<lb/>bright sunny morning and every place<lb/>drying up well but I never recollect<lb/>such continuous rain at any time<lb/>before. However there is one<lb/>consolation and that is that the<lb/>huns cannot build trenches in the wet.  Certainly the rain has done for<lb/>him this week what all the guns<lb/>in Germany could not have done 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6366_img_0_2"/>
             2<lb/>However it is only delayed.<lb/>The rain has also done an awful<lb/>lot of damage to crops. They were<lb/>very heavy and just ripe and<lb/>now they look as if they had<lb/>been rolled.  There are some very nice villages<lb/>near here where we can get<lb/>tea or dinner and we are allowed<lb/>out as much as we like as we are<lb/>only here to wait until we are<lb/>needed again.  You need not be imagining that<lb/>I am wading about in water or<lb/>anything like that. I am in a nice<lb/>comfortable farm house and have<lb/>a nice comfortable bed every night.<lb/>And yet I do not feel satisfied<lb/>I would much rather be where the<lb/>regiment are. I am afraid my<lb/><hi rend="underline">old</hi> regiment have had rather a rough<lb/>time but I have not been able to<lb/>get any particulars yet. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6366_img_0_3"/>
             3.<lb/>I think I have got a very good<lb/>servant again. The one I got after<lb/>poor Gault was killed was no good,<lb/>so we parted. However I have got<lb/>a good one this time. The leave<lb/>for the men is very good now.<lb/>We are sending as many as 12<lb/>per week sometimes. A few officers<lb/>are getting away also so if it remains<lb/>open my turn may come sometime<lb/>about the end of September.  I wonder could you get me a<lb/>couple of good lead pencils and put<lb/>them in a parcel. I still have the<lb/>indelible but I cant write anything<lb/>that might get wet with it. The<lb/>best pencil made now that the Austrian<lb/>Koh-E-noor is gone is the Royal<lb/>Sovereign H.B. They ae 4<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> each but<lb/>I have used one constantly for the<lb/>last six months and it is nearly 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6366_img_0_4"/>
             4.<lb/>worn out. If you cannot get<lb/>them any thing will do. It is<lb/>impossible to get a good pencil<lb/>out here. Are any of my letters<lb/>ever opened by the Base Censor?  He wouldn't find much information<lb/>if he did.  I went out yesterday afternoon<lb/>to a town near here and I<lb/>travelled in quite a variety of ways.<lb/>1<hi rend="superscript">st </hi>I went for a bit in a cart. Then<lb/>another bit on a motor lorry. Then<lb/>walked a bit. Coming back I<lb/>started in the side car of a motor<lb/>bike and finished up again by<lb/>walking not because the motor<lb/>broke down but because <seg type="del">but<lb/>because</seg> it was not going any<lb/>further.  I have just been thinking that<lb/>this day week will be the 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>you must take Bobby out this 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_6366_img_0_5"/>
             <hi rend="underline">5</hi><lb/>year and I hope you will have<lb/>a very good day.   It will be a <lb/>great day for Bobby.  With luck<lb/>I will get a shot at a partridge<lb/>or pheasant.  I wonder will it be<lb/>a good grouse year.  I rather<lb/>think not as it was too dry if<lb/>you had it as dry as we had.<lb/>It should be very good for<lb/>partridge and pheasants.  It is<lb/>very good indeed that you are<lb/>meeting so many.  This is a very sultry day as the<lb/><seg type="del">heat</seg> wet is drying out of the <lb/>ground with the hot sun.  I wrote to Mrs Waters Jasfar<lb/>since &amp; Governor during the <lb/>week.  I took advantage of the <lb/>wet days.  We got an order<lb/>yesterday to move and so we all<lb/>packed up and got ready to go    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_6366_img_0_6"/>
             and then got a message cancelling<lb/>the whoe thing.  I see great talk<lb/>in the papers of the caterpiller plague<lb/>in England.  That is what you told<lb/>me about weeks ago.  Flies are<lb/>a great nuisance out her now.<lb/>They give us sticky paper now in<lb/>the rations for catching them.  No more news now as with<lb/>very best love to all from<lb/> Your most affec. Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>