<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1484">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kathleen Hogan to Nancy O'Rahilly, 31 July 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Hogan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Kathleen Hogan to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). Kathleen writes to congratulate Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly on the birth of her son and asks for a postcard letting her know how she is. Finally he congratulates &#39;little Michael Joseph&#39; and hopes he will take his great father&#39;s place for his mother and for Ireland.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/092/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1484</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0087">Kathleen Hogan</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1743">3 Bagview, Bettystown, County Meath, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1484_img_937_1"  type="Letter"  url="6e80c77064da98227bf03c829efc99e7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1484_img_937_1"/>
                3 Bayview,  Bettystown.    July 31st   My dear Madam O'Rahilly,   Just a line to congratulate you <lb/> on the birth of your little son, for whom <lb/> I can wish nothing better than to be a <lb/>worthy son of his dear father. I was hoping <lb/>for a little girl for you, but I am quite <lb/>sure you are satisfied with God's gift, and <lb/>no doubt it must be for the best.   How are you yourself? I hope you got <lb/>over your illness well, and that you are <lb/>as strong as usual. I should like very <lb/> much to have word of you, if Mae <lb/> could be persuaded to send me a postcard. <lb/> I know boys hate writing, but he might <lb/>get through half a dozen words on a p.c. I <lb/>ask no more.  <seg type="closer"> With all good wishes for you and Baby, <lb/>and affectionate regards, dear Madam O'Rahilly, <lb/>Your sincere friend   Kathleen Hogan. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>