<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1248">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn [24] January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from May Fay (1897-1976) to James Finn (1877-1922) informing James that she may be coming down with the mumps. May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. Following her husband&#39;s death May held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1248</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-01-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1248_img_437_1"  type="Letter"  url="2c5d9bfcb69d65798dce540ba15651bc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1248_img_437_2"  type="Letter"  url="6fae0c11fee2aea72e7f09ab665d1164.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1248_img_437_3"  type="Envelope"  url="b77fc5bc83ba9fa8d5aed61c97e05807.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1248_img_437_4"  type="Envelope"  url="640f90cae2bb0f41b63f1bb64f482210.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1248_img_437_1"/>
                Togherstown   My darling little Man,   I just see this <lb/>chance of posting a line <lb/> to you hope you got card <lb/> from M. Gar Mother whose <lb/> saying she is coming  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1248_img_437_2"/>
              home tomorrow (Tues) so <lb/> we are off on Sat next. If <lb/> I am not the <sic>obstical</sic> again <lb/> I would not be at all <lb/> surprised if I was getting <lb/> the mumps. I feel my neck <lb/> very sore of course they <lb/> are not very dangerous <lb/> but Mother would never <seg type="del">g</seg> let me on that journey <lb/> with them. God send tho' <lb/> it is nothing at all  No more time so goodbye <lb/> with all my best love. <seg type="closer"> Yours  May. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1248_img_437_3"/>
               
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1248_img_437_4"/>
                J. E. Finn Esq  39 Belgrave Sq.  Rathmines  Dublin    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>