<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3875">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. to Hugh Doyle, 1 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Willie Doyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Father Willie Doyle S.J. (1873-1917) to his father, Hugh Doyle, regarding his activities before being sent to the front. Doyle informs his father that he has been assigned to the 8th Royal Irish Fusiliers, the Faugh-a-Ballagh regiment and hopes to &#39;clear the way&#39; for God&#39;s grace when he is among them. Doyle also writes about the weather and his companion chaplain in the brigade, Fr Kelly. After detailing his travel arrangements Doyle writes about Lord Kitchener&#39;s remarks regarding the calm nature of the Jesuit order.

Fr Willie Doyle served as a military chaplain with the 8th Battalion of the Royal Irish Fusiliers, 16th Irish Division. In April 1916 he was recommended for the Military Cross (MC) for helping to dig wounded men out of a collapsed shelter under fire. He moved to the 8th Battalion, Royal Dublin Fusiliers around Christmas, 1916. He was killed during the third battle of Ypres while going to the aid of a wounded man near Frezenberg and his body was never recovered. His name is commemorated on the Tyne Cot memorial, Zonnebeke, Belgium.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE-IJA-J2-83-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3875</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1272">Willie Doyle</persName>
              <date>1915-12-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0955">Woking, Surrey, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hugh Doyle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2113">Melrose, Dalkey, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1917</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_1"  type="Letter"  url="20b5f07df140091224934c94c6dcd207.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_2"  type="Letter"  url="a26b3e2a515de877bcc379b47f1d4c05.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_3"  type="Letter"  url="0a8eef55e026cb0e5dbf13351a290add.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_4"  type="Letter"  url="de3eae71fc41c6e19aafd2b810abc5aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_5"  type="Letter"  url="880ed09febeae6d99cc497257f92989c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_6"  type="Letter"  url="ccd2346190f10c7dd572c10f3018644f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_7"  type="Letter"  url="82980c7585028e23628bf89235468e9b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3875_img_3255_8"  type="Letter"  url="7773f34e1652e3c6fc1fe3201bb7ee1f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_1"/>
             8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Royal Irish Fusiliers  49 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Brigade<lb/>16 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Division<lb/>Woking<lb/>Surrey   1 December 1915    My dear Father,   This must<lb/>only be a short note<lb/>as I am in a state<lb/>of transition at present.<lb/>I am writing from<lb/>the Head Chaplain's<lb/>home (Fr Mason) where<lb/>I slept last night,<lb/>and this morning<lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_2"/>
             2  <lb/>reported myself to the <lb/>Commanding Officer of <lb/>the 49 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Brigade, General <lb/>Longe, who was extremely <lb/>kind and gave me a <lb/>really warm welcome. <lb/>He nominated me to <lb/>the 8 <hi rend="superscript">th </hi>R.I. Fusiliers - <lb/>the famous "Faugh - a - <lb/>Ballagh" regiment, so I <lb/>hope soon "to clear the <lb/> way" for God's grace <lb/>when I get among them. <lb/>I have charge of two <lb/>Battalions, nearly 1,000 <lb/>strong each, of whom 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_3"/>
             3  I hear, there are some<lb/>500 Dubliners, including<lb/>many old friends, I<lb/>am sure. I am<lb/>going over now to<lb/>report to Colonel Brown<lb/>who lives in Morehampton<lb/>Road, a regular fire<lb/>eater of the old school,<lb/>and get my quarters<lb/>in the Barrack. This<lb/>will only be for a<lb/>few days as we under<lb/>orders to march to a<lb/>new camp, Wakely,<lb/>Surrey. The prospect<lb/>at present is most  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_4"/>
             4  cheery; rain is falling<lb/>in sheets and blankets<lb/>too! I believe there<lb/>were roads here once but<lb/>they have long since<lb/>vanished beneath mud<lb/>and water — however we<lb/>are well fortified and<lb/>rather revel in slush &amp;<lb/>wet.  I am very lucky in<lb/>having as companion<lb/>chaplain in the Brigade<lb/>a splendid Tipperary<lb/>priest, Fr Kelly, with a<lb/>heart as big as himself<lb/>and he is huge. I<lb/>believe he is bringing<lb/>an elephant to the Front  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_5"/>
             5  as all the horses struck<lb/>when they saw him. We<lb/>are fast friends already<lb/>and as he has been<lb/>here some months he<lb/>has given me many<lb/>useful hints.  We are bound for<lb/>France, which I think<lb/>will please you, but<lb/>we do not sail till<lb/>January. At present<lb/>we are under marching<lb/>orders for another camp<lb/>and leave this in a<lb/> (Excuse repetition.)   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_6"/>
             6  few days, our des-<lb/>tination being Witely,<lb/>Surrey.  I heard in London<lb/>yesterday that some time<lb/>ago Lord Kitchener asked<lb/>the Provincial for 25<lb/>more chaplains: I can't<lb/>quite understand you<lb/>Jesuits, he said;  a man<lb/>comes in, listens to his<lb/>orders in silence and<lb/>carries them out exactly<lb/>without a word of<lb/>complaint, no matter<lb/>how unpleasant the<lb/>duty may be. You  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_7"/>
             7  must be either a fine<lb/>body of men <hi rend="underline">or very<lb/>deep</hi>! which shows that<lb/>even the great Kitchener<lb/>is afraid of the cunning<lb/>S.J.  The Queen is coming down<lb/>to Aldershot tomorrow to<lb/>review the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division<lb/>so I shall have an<lb/>opportunity for the<lb/>first time of seeing<lb/>an army on parade,<lb/>not to speak of a<lb/>view of her gracious<lb/>Majesty. I suppose  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3875_img_3255_8"/>
             8  I am safe in<lb/>giving her your love.<lb/>I shall write as often<lb/>as I can but do<lb/>not write to me till<lb/>I send you my new<lb/>address. As regards<lb/>myself I am as fit<lb/>as a fiddle, as happy<lb/>as a sky-lark and<lb/>still going strong.  Love to all and<lb/>sunday souls.   Ever your loving son<lb/>Will.    My proper address is<lb/>Rev William Doyle, C.7.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>