<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4131">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lord Granard to John Redmond, 3 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Bernard Forbes</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Lord Granard to John Redmond discussing his return to Salonika and the on-goings of a [problematic army chaplain, Father Stafford.

Bernard Forbes (1874-1948), the 8th Earl of Garnard,  was a professional soldier and politician. He was recalled to command the 5th Battalion, Royal Irish Regiment in 1916. He was later Military Secretary to the Commander-in-Chief of the Salonika Forces from 1917.

John Redmond (1856-1918) was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers; MS 15,192/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4131</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1447">Bernard Forbes</persName>
              <date>1916-02-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0527">Army Headquarters, Salonika, Greece</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1948</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4131_img_3505_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa0084ba9945d7281671e702e5e0cbcb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4131_img_3505_2"  type="Letter"  url="d29e11a2e5830f043afa96c5ea3cf918.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4131_img_3505_3"  type="Letter"  url="6ef5e63efa6ed7b3accf01ac04c78f72.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4131_img_3505_4"  type="Letter"  url="7cc020dac96aea45ae799ba612a6fc63.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4131_img_3505_1"/>
             Army Headquarters <lb/>Selonica   Private   Feb 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>   My dear Mr Redmond.   I arrived here the <lb/>other day after a very <lb/>long ardous journey, <lb/>but one must be thankful <lb/>that we met no <seg type="unclear">subversions</seg> <lb/>or other danger on the <lb/>way.   I find everything going well <lb/>here. General Nugent
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4131_img_3505_2"/>
            In very good health and <lb/>spirits. He is doing very <lb/>well indeed and the <lb/>cordial relations that <lb/>exist between the French <lb/><seg type="unclear">poilus</seg>and ourselves is <lb/>entirely due to the tact <lb/>he has evinced in dealing <lb/>with these people.   I think it right to enclose <lb/>you a note, I received <lb/>from Father Stafford <lb/>Saturday, in case that
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4131_img_3505_3"/>
            he should approach you <lb/>in this matter. I have made <lb/>very full inquiry into the <lb/>facts and find that the <lb/><seg type="unclear">Monuments</seg><seg type="unclear">secrets</seg>in the <lb/>enclosed letter are not <lb/>in accordance with fact. <lb/>I am sorry to say that Father <lb/>Stafford has not done well <lb/>since he was appointed <lb/>Chaplain to the 10th Division. <lb/>There were continual complaints <lb/>sent to Headquarters of the <lb/>neglect of the men under <lb/>his charge. He was a <lb/>continual source of trouble <lb/>to us, and in fact to speak <lb/>quite plainly, I was really
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4131_img_3505_4"/>
            quite ashamed of him. <lb/>Our Chaplains, other than <lb/>this problem one in question <lb/>were a pattern of what <lb/>Catholic Priests should be <lb/>and in consequence it <lb/>was all the more unfortunate <lb/>to have any exception to <lb/>the above rule.   With Kind regards to you <lb/>&amp;M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>Redmond, &amp; many <lb/>thanks for all your <lb/>Kindness to me.   Yrs vy Sincerely   Granard 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>