<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3059">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr. Thomas Addis Emmet, M.D. to P.A. Philbin, 30 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dr. Thomas Addis Emmet</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Dr. Thomas Addis Emmet (1828-1919) thanking Mr. Philbin for the use of his scrapbooks. Emmet mentions sketches and portraits of the United Irishmen and his ancestors, Robert and Thomas Addis Emmet.

Thomas Addis Emmet was the grand nephew of Robert Emmet, a medical doctor of much renown and a leader of Irish opinion in America.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>American Irish Historical Society</repository>
                  <collection>The P.A. Philbin Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3059</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0772">Dr. Thomas Addis Emmet</persName>
              <date>1916-09-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1228">89 Madison Avenue, New York, New York, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">P.A. Philbin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0343">Archebald, Pennsylvania, United States</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3059_img_2458_1"  type="Letter"  url="530eafba62512eb908993012a0a8720b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3059_img_2458_2"  type="Letter"  url="754eb76db184a4d69da5e36a8ce6b25e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3059_img_2458_1"/>
             89 Madison Avenue   Sept. 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>1916   Hon: P. A. Philbin   Dear Sir   I feel under the greatest <lb/>obligation to you for letting me <lb/> see the Scrap Book —   The portrait is simply a copy <lb/>of Petsie's sketch of Robert Emmet <lb/> on the back of a letter which I <lb/>have &amp; if he found in the <seg type="unclear">Memorium</seg> <lb/>of Robert Emmet. The full length <lb/>figure is copied from a large wood <lb/> cut  gotten up in New York on the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>and has no special value.    I found by good luck the <lb/><sic>sketchs</sic> of the United Irishmen <lb/>published in the Weekly Freeman <lb/>which I have been trying to get <lb/>hold of for years, <seg type="unclear">as</seg>especially <lb/>as the author had access
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3059_img_2458_2"/>
            <lb/>to a copy of the proceeding <lb/>of the United Irishmen from 1791 <lb/>to 1794, which belonged to T. A. Emmet <lb/>my grandfather and fully <lb/>annotated by him during a <lb/>period of which I could not <lb/>obtain a trace of his work. <lb/>To me this will prove of so <lb/>great a value as to call <lb/>for a second edition of my <lb/>work at some future day, <lb/>which I will get ready <lb/>when called for after my <lb/>death — I have also <seg type="unclear">scanned</seg> <lb/>the second Scrap book but I  have  had <lb/>only time to glance through it.   I shall take the greatest care <lb/>of the books, but, as I have trouble <lb/>with my eyes and can only work for <lb/>a limited time I must ask the favor I <lb/>may keep them for some weeks <seg type="del">I</seg>until <lb/>I return to town.   Very Truly Yours   <hi rend="underline"><sic>Tho</sic> Addis Emmet</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>