<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6675">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from WB Yeats to Squire, 20 January 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.B. Yeats</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 8. Folder: 11 ALS..to Squire, Sir John C (8.1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6675</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date>1920-01-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1573">Hotel Owalia, Upper Woburn Place, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John C. Squire</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6675_img_None_1"  url="php57e8v1.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6675_img_None_2"  url="php4ztbXV.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6675_img_None_3"  url="phpNRf1oQ.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6675_img_0_1"/>
              Telephones:<lb/>CITY 5010 &amp; 5011    Telegrams    GWALIATEL, LONDON    HOTEL GWALIA<lb/>UPPER WOBURN PLACE,<lb/>LONDON, W.C.1    January 11 1920   Dictated    Dear Squire    One never knows whether one's work<lb/>is<seg type="unclear">obscure </seg>or not, till one has shown<lb/>it to some one else. One has<lb/>the clue oneself. The meaning<lb/>is as plain to oneself as<lb/>certain hidden representations which<lb/>Beardsly used to secrete in a<lb/>drawing for a publisher whom<lb/>he disliked - as plain to<lb/>oneself as that representation<lb/>was to the publisher when    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6675_img_0_2"/>
             he discovered it one day<lb/>after publication ---.  I will try &amp; send you something<lb/>else, but if I do not the<lb/>reason will be that the<lb/>only alternative is a group<lb/>of poems which I want published<lb/>together &amp; which get their<lb/>weight &amp; fire from a little group<lb/>of <seg type="unclear">verses</seg> suggested by the Irish<lb/>Rebellion. I doubt if you<lb/>would care to risk these in<lb/>the present disturbed state of<lb/>Ireland, I havent made up<lb/>my own mind as to whether I 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6675_img_0_3"/>
             Telephones:<lb/>CITY 5010 &amp; 5011  Telegrams  GWALIATEL, LONDON   HOTEL GWALIA<lb/>UPPER WOBURN PLACE,<lb/>LONDON, W.C.1   ought to risk them.  While Irish<lb/>youth is in its inflammable state<lb/>I may end by publishing them<lb/>only in one of my sisters expensive<lb/>little books where they can do<lb/>no harm.  I dont feel at this<lb/>present moment that I should<lb/>separate the other poems from<lb/>them.   Yours sincerely<lb/>W B Yeats  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>