<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6461">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ellen Mary ("Nellie") Daly to Susan Daly, 26 January 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ellen Mary Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/9/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6461</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1122">Ellen Mary Daly</persName>
              <date>1923-01-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1756">Knockane Coolteen, Ballyfinane, Firies, Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0193">Susan Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1930</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6461_img_None_1"  url="f645c452a8d686ecea0892890578c92d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6461_img_None_2"  url="7e0cb84c08fd497dd764021046c0f7da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6461_img_None_3"  url="4e71a240a28c606362aa54f3bdd5439d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6461_img_None_4"  url="a303ef0da533fc7d81d30b94121cdeee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6461_img_None_5"  url="8234bb8b17e61ffcf701420758076481.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6461_img_0_1"/>
              Knockane,<lb/><seg type="unclear">Firies</seg>     Jan 26-1923   41/9/2   Dear Susan,   Got your welcome letter<lb/>a few days ago. Nell was buried at<lb/><seg type="del">Killlal</seg> Killallagh by her own wish.<lb/>She said good bye to everyone and<lb/>gave them all some little token.<lb/>She left her child of Mary ribbon to<lb/>Eileen the baby. She gave Mollie and<lb/>Katie Maria handkerchiefs and some<lb/>other little things. Kathleen went<lb/>home, she was sick but any thing<lb/>wouldn't keep here till she'd get<lb/>better. She had to stay at Dowds for<lb/>she was'nt able to go home. I suppose<lb/>they made a show when they heard<lb/>of May's death. I was staying at the<lb/>Bungalow for the past week. K.M<lb/>misses Josie now, she <seg type="del">h</seg> is tormented<lb/>for trying to keep her hands <sic>her<lb/>hands</sic> clean. There is a very nice<lb/>little stove in parlour, in the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6461_img_0_2"/>
             (2)  next to the road. She is delighted<lb/>how nicely it's working. It warms up<lb/>the whole place. Tubby <sic>had'nt</sic> the<lb/>pups yet. We must send Josie a wire<lb/>when she will, it will be as good as a<lb/>wedding to her when she'll hear it.  O! I must tell you  about  who I saw and<lb/>talking to in the jail. My mother got into to see the Brig first of all.<lb/>I am afraid she would have a poor<lb/>chance <seg type="del">u</seg> if K M had'nt written a<lb/>letter for the Brig. The Stater at the<lb/>gate said the Brig was too busy<lb/>and could'nt bee<seg type="del">n</seg> seen. My mother<lb/>said she had spesial word from<lb/>himself. He then asked had she a<lb/>letter, he took up, and returned<lb/>and told her come on. She return<lb/>all smiles, and we knew she was<lb/>to be let in. She told him there<lb/>was too little girls outside, and could<lb/>they go in. He said of course. Is'nt KM<lb/>a nice lttle girl. We met a nice fellow<lb/>named Nolan at the gate, my mother<lb/>said we were her daughters, so KM<lb/>got in as one of us. Goodness! the<lb/>jail is a frightening old place with 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6461_img_0_3"/>
             (3)  the lonesome grey colour. I wonder how<lb/>J.D got over the great high walls.<lb/>When we got inside the inner gate<lb/>and turned to left. We went into a<lb/>nice little room, it was belong to Nol-<lb/>an. We had to wait for a while<lb/>as the lads were saying the Rosary<lb/>over the graves. The men passed<lb/>the window with spades after closing<lb/>the graves. After a while Tom came<lb/>in. He was in wicked humour over the<lb/>execution, but he looked fine. Wille<lb/><sic>was'nt</sic> in at that time, but after a<lb/>while he marched in, as well as Tom<lb/>was he <sic>was was </sic>much better, and in<lb/>great humour. They said everything<lb/>they before the Stater. He did'nt like<lb/>the executions of the lads were out<lb/>the time of the Tans.  We were there for two hours,<lb/>but Nolan told us to say half an<lb/>hour. We were going to say good bye<lb/>to lads when the rest of the prisoners<lb/>came out. You should see the look-<lb/>ing they had at all of us. it was so strange<lb/>to see anyone. Willie showed us Peter G<lb/>standing in a doorway, with a <seg type="del">p</seg> broad    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6461_img_0_4"/>
             (4)  smile as usual. I ran across to him<lb/>so he called Mattie and <seg type="del">i</seg> the rest.<lb/>Nolan said we could only stay a<lb/>few minutes a the whole would be<lb/>coming out. Mattie was a bit thin,<lb/>but Unky was as gay as ever. Connie<lb/>Casey did'nt come out, and we were<lb/>very sorry. We saw a couple more<lb/>of the lads we knew also. You<lb/>would think the bell-man was out<lb/>that everyone knew we were in<lb/>Willie showed his room and number<lb/>Tom expected to be removed, because<lb/>the Brig said there was a bit of<lb/>a row the last time he was in<lb/>Dublin. I suppose they thought they<lb/>had too good a time. I'm sure Tom<lb/>will miss Mrs. B parcels, she was<lb/>very good to them.  Tadie O' was at the Bungalow<lb/>today, and he <seg type="del">w</seg> is'nt over the<lb/>effects of the batle yet. The <seg type="unclear">6</seg> main<lb/>people are all shell shocked. Billy<lb/>Smith and six or seven more deser-<lb/>ted yesterday. Tis unknow what<lb/>Billy Smith join next.  I <seg type="del">bougth</seg> bought a canary 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_6461_img_0_5"/>
             (5)  coloured cardigan for six and six. I<lb/>have a new navy dress and Nancy's<lb/>is making. God help you if you<lb/>thought Flora would write. Jhon Joe<lb/>was pleased with the look, altho'<lb/>my mother thought it was thrash<lb/>I must end now Do'nt mind the<lb/>writing as I am tired of it. I won't<lb/>post this a few more <seg type="del">news</seg> days for<lb/>I might get more news. Good bye.   With love<lb/>From Nellie   P.S.  Bill Kirby and Kate Lynch are<lb/>marrying tomorrow. Ellie O sent an<lb/>account of a match to Willie Hickey.<lb/>Hannan Maria is getting loads of<lb/>accounts.  <hi rend="underline">N</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>