<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3187">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John J. Farrell, 10 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John J Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-7954</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3187</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0308">John J Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1032">Cloonfaughna, Knock, Claremorris, Co. Mayo, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3187_img_2610_1"  type="Letter"  url="5e0839e7e6bfed11600beb3075974031.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3187_img_2610_1"/>
             CHIEF SECRETARY'S OFFICE<lb/>7954 11 MAY 1916   Cloonfaughna<lb/>Knock<lb/>Claremorris<lb/>Co. Mayo    10th May 1916    Sir   Having learned that a Censorship of<lb/>inland letters is to be immediately established<lb/>in Ireland, I beg to offer my service to<lb/>the Board of Censors.  I am ineligible for Military service and<lb/>am at present unemployed. I am a<lb/>trained National Teacher and have spent<lb/>five years as Assistant in a N.S. Two<lb/>years ago a nervous breakdown forced me<lb/>to resign. I am strong  enough  now to resume<lb/>work and have been so for some time<lb/>but my illness is militating against my<lb/>obtaining a suitable school  I have a fairly good knowledge of Irish<lb/>should the consideration of such<lb/>application as this not come within<lb/>your jurisdiction I would respectfully<lb/>request you to forward it to the proper<lb/>quarter or inform me to whom I should<lb/>apply  Awaiting a reply, and thanking<lb/>you in anticipation.   I am<lb/>Sir<lb/>Respectfully yours<lb/>John J Farrell   P.S. I am 29 years of age, and a Roman Catholic. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>