<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5586">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lord French to Sir John Maxwell, 29 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Denton Pinkstone French</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Lord French, John Denton Pinkstone French, 1st Earl of Ypres (28 Sept. 1852-22 May 1925), commander of all British forces on home service, 1916-1918,  to Sir John Maxwell (12 Jul. 1859-21 Feb. 1929), primarily responsible for government policy in the immediate aftermath of the Rising.
The letter was written on the same day that the leaders of the Easter Rising surrendered in Dublin and contains references to the movement of troops between Northern Ireland and the South, searches for arms and the prospect of a German landing on the west coast.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera papers, P150/512</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5586</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0358">John Denton Pinkstone French</persName>
              <date>1916-04-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1673">G.H.Q. Home Forces, Horse Guards, S.W., London.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1925</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_1"  type="Letter"  url="2dc0fff6c4c42b5f2917ef7f78bd2b4a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_2"  type="Letter"  url="183202834bb850b6b23dedb3266ee44c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_3"  type="Letter"  url="633d414fbbd585fd255a9fbda3da7b44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_4"  type="Letter"  url="493f00d0f7229cdbe7afc1f3ffdae56f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_5"  type="Letter"  url="a90a1616e0b7a075c243f440d0785a8b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_6"  type="Letter"  url="5d2e6a229b973bc26a68a911c9772418.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5586_img_680_7"  type="Letter"  url="1f99542d1dcbf8a4db3dfb0007f4a54d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_1"/>
              G.H.Q. Home Forces, <lb/>Horse Guards, <lb/>S.W.     <hi rend="underline"> April 29. 1916 </hi>    My Dear Maxwell,  <lb/>Thank you for your letter <lb/>which I have shown to the <lb/>Prime Minister &amp; am taking to <lb/> the King.   We are sending you The Cavalry <lb/>from Aldershot &amp; for <seg type="unclear">Shillham</seg> <lb/>the <seg type="unclear">'Hilton'</seg> from  . <!-- These may be horses names --> <lb/>I am glad to learn you have <lb/>approved of <seg type="unclear">whether steps</seg> which 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_2"/>
             had been taken by Friend and <lb/>Lowe before you arrived. <lb/>You are in exciting and interesting <lb/> surroundings.   I have had long talks with <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Carson</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Redmond</hi>.   Carson tells us there are 50000 <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Ulster</hi> Volunteers (all around) <lb/>now at their homes and ready <lb/> to answer any call which 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">2</hi>   which  may make upon him. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Redmond</hi> (who Carson says is <lb/>with Ireland) says <hi rend="underline">his</hi> volunteers <lb/> will also render help.   <hi rend="underline">Carson</hi> thinks the Troops you have <lb/> drawn into Dublin from Belfast <lb/> should be sent North again as <lb/> soon as you can spare them <lb/> from Dublin —You must of course <lb/>use your own judgement as to this 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_4"/>
             128  but I only tell you what he says.   <seg type="del">Cor</seg> <hi rend="underline">Cork</hi> has been upended <lb/> this by both <hi rend="underline">Carson</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Lord Middleton</hi> <lb/> as a dangerous point - they <lb/>have sent you over there <lb/>(to Lansdowne) an infantry   <lb/>of this GOD in from Salisbury. <lb/> A <hi rend="underline">show</hi> of force will do <lb/>good in the South.    Let me know your wants and 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_5"/>
             <hi rend="underline">3</hi>   they shall receive prompt <lb/>attention.   I don't think there is much <lb/>chance (now) of a German <lb/>landing on the West Coast <lb/>of Ireland but that is what <lb/>we must be prepared for.   Yours sincerely <lb/><hi rend="underline"> French </hi>  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_6"/>
             <hi rend="underline">P.S.</hi>   The King <seg type="del">went</seg> <seg type="unclear">over</seg> to <lb/>London last night to report as to <lb/> Ireland.—   His Majesty asked me to tell you <lb/>(1) that in his view it was absolutely <lb/>necessary to institute a search of all <lb/>houses for Arms as<seg type="unclear">some</seg> as this is <lb/>possible — (ii) The King is very anxious <lb/>that Civilians, and those not engaged <lb/>in rebillion should be cleared away <lb/>&amp; protected to this at least.    I told His Majesty that I would <lb/>give you this message but assured 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5586_img_680_7"/>
             him that you were fully alive to <lb/>the importance of these points and <lb/>would give them all the attention <lb/>you could — 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>