<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1419">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J.H.G. Stantin to Mabel FitzGerald, 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.H.G. Stantin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter is from Colonel J.H.G. Stantin of the Irish Command, British army, to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). The letter informs Mrs. FitzGerald of the sentence passed on her husband at court-martial, and advises her of his transfer to Mountjoy Prison.Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1575/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1419</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0395">J.H.G. Stantin</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0399">Headquarters Irish Command, Parkgate, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1746">2 Loretto Villas, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1419_img_830_1"  type="Letter"  url="8116a64767d88edfa7037272527adeaf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1419_img_830_1"/>
              109/A.    Headquarters Irish Command,  Parkgate, Dublin.    20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, 1916.   Madam,   In reply to your letter of the 17th instant, I <lb/> have to inform you that the Court Martial on Mr Desmond <lb/> Fitzgerald was <seg type="del">considered</seg> confirmed  to-day by the General Officer <lb/> Commanding in Chief. He was sentenced by the Court to <lb/> twenty years Penal Servitude ten years of which were <lb/> remitted by the General Officer Commanding in Chief. He <lb/> will be removed to Mountjoy Prison where he will be permitted <lb/> the visit usually allowed to convicts during the <lb/> first week of their sentences. Application should therefore <lb/> be made to the Governor, Mountjoy Prison. Any <lb/> property belonging to Mr.Fitzgerald which may be found in <lb/> Richmond Barracks will be forwarded to you. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  J.H.G.Stantin <lb/> for  Brig.Genl. <lb/>D.A.G.   Mrs Fitzgerald,  2 Loretta Villas,  BRAY.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>