<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4274">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Note from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, circa April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Note from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). The note appears to have been written on the back of company orders. 

Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/211</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4274</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4274_img_3639_1"  type="Letter"  url="170e9ed663d0b3455bf33658db5e9ce4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4274_img_3639_2"  type="Letter"  url="e079390baec875fe44720b4a5d819686.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4274_img_3639_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="40e2d0914f4cc1c5c61216eb70ff927f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4274_img_3639_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="0c080552822ba760c0d8f45335767b48.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4274_img_3639_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/211  The budget will hit<lb/>us badly, as not only<lb/>do we pay 1/4 of our<lb/>income in income<lb/>tax but we shall pay<lb/><seg type="del">at</seg>  well  over another 1/4<lb/>with the excess profits<lb/>tax, as tho' our income<lb/>in some   has gone<lb/>down to nearly nil, that<lb/>from others e.g. Rubber has<lb/>suddenly increased &amp; this<lb/>Govr is taking 60 per cent<lb/>of the profits. We shall<lb/>contribute £1000 to the state<lb/>this year, but thanks to<lb/>a <seg type="unclear">prb</seg> management<lb/>we can do so all right  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4274_img_3639_2"/>
             D1633/1/1/212  Douglas not yet returned<lb/>Hope he is all right.  My house might be<lb/>worse. It is a labourer's<lb/>cottage but won with<lb/>brick floors &amp; rather<lb/>damp but I am getting<lb/>it better now. We are<lb/>in a Protestant village,<lb/>but the church has had<lb/>to be used as an office 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4274_img_3639_3"/>
             LANCASHIRE DUMP and AUTHUILLE VILLAGE <seg type="unclear">completed</seg> <lb/>17th instant. He estimates that it may take another 6 <lb/>weeks before he can extend the tramway to the bottom of <lb/>THIEPVAL WOOD, and until this extension is made the tramway <lb/>is of little value to the Division, except as an alternative <lb/>route for taking stores. Stores are now being taken into <lb/>AUTHUILLE VILLAGE by transport at night and as long as this <lb/>is possible it will not be worth while unloading them at <lb/>on to the trench tramway for conveyance up 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4274_img_3639_4"/>
             <hi rend="underline">36th Div. No. G.S/5/</hi>   10th <hi rend="underline">Corps.</hi>   Your G. 347 of 8.3.16.  The Officer Commanding the 3rd Monmouths Company<lb/>detailed by you for tramway construction near AUTHUILLE<lb/>expects to get the portion of the tramway between<lb/>about 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>