<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0910">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Tweedy to his Mother, letter 7 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Tweedy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>An account of the Easter Rising from Robert Tweedy (1875-1956), a member of the Trinity College Officer Training Corps (OTC), to his mother. Tweedy served in the defence of Trinity College over a nine day period. His account describes the initial confusion of the Rising, his perilous journey Dalkey to Trinity, and the arrival of confused ANZAC, South African and British troops to the gates of the college. He writes of the looting in the streets, the burning skyline and of the grim reality of urban warfare.Robert Naudin Tweedy was an English born electrical engineer and member of the Officer Training Corps based in Trinity College Dublin. During the Easter Rising, Tweedy was involved in the defence of the College. Tweedy would later work with the Free-State government, solving industrial disputes.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, TCD MS 7533/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/910</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0098">Robert Tweedy</persName>
              <date>1916-05-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs Tweedy, Robert Tweedy&#39;s mother</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0910_img_255_1"  type="Letter"  url="ee06108e5a6bae18366411fdc2e7df46.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0910_img_255_2"  type="Letter"  url="7f2049a5f96416c1370b03921e271547.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0910_img_255_3"  type="Letter"  url="878b5841e652a4cefe79ab05333fce01.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0910_img_255_4"  type="Letter"  url="84fe8ee1da803b63b50f788d7d31e9fc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0910_img_255_5"  type="Letter"  url="70cb48f7434a168122140f341f9dae19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0910_img_255_6"  type="Letter"  url="3e75e7789493a50c9dca1d2c57ebf793.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0910_img_255_1"/>
                Wilmount,  Killiney,  Co. Dublin.    May 7, '16.   My dear Mother,   After 24 hours' sleep, I feel able to write to you,<lb/> and you will be glad to hear at first-hand that I am none the<lb/> worse for my experience of active service. <seg type="del">Josie</seg>One wrote<lb/> and telegraphed to you several times, but nothing could get<lb/> out, or, in, as you know. No one seems to know how one of<lb/> your wires got through. The whole thing came on us like a<lb/> thunderbolt on Monday, and out here we could not <sic>guage </sic>the<lb/> seriousness of the rising. As I could not get in on Monday<lb/> night, I went down to the Dalkey Police Station to see if they<lb/> wanted special constables, but all the police were in barracks<lb/> and seemed to be taking matters with a light heart. They<lb/> assured me that everything would be quiet in the morning, so<lb/> I went home to bed, and cycled in early on Tuesday morning<lb/> in mufti, riding quite unconscious of danger down one side of<lb/> Stephens' Green, which was in the hands of the rebels.<lb/> I was the only living thing in the street at the time, and<lb/> I went along slowly to get a good view of the barricades.<lb/> Rifle firing from the  Sh <seg type="del">H</seg>elbourne Hotel into the Green, the<lb/> sight of a dead horse at the corner, and a crowd more or less<lb/> sh e eltered in Merrion Row, (which runs into Stephens' Green)  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0910_img_255_2"/>
              gave me the first impression of danger.  There were no police or military to warn people from<lb/> straying into <seg type="del">side</seg> such  places, and I was to see later how<lb/> idiotically contemptuous of rifle firing the crowd is until<lb/> someone gets hit, and even then how quickly the effect is<lb/> overpowered by morbid curiosity. I went straight to Trinity<lb/> College, and found a dozen others arguing with the porter,<lb/> who would not budge from his orders to admit no one. Nor<lb/> would he send a message to head-quarters at the front gate<lb/> facing College Green, so we gave it up for the time and<lb/> wandered about for a bit to see how things were looking.<lb/> There were crowds of foot passengers quite orderly, and not<lb/> in the least understanding the situation. Shots were being<lb/> fired here and there, especially between Dublin Castle and<lb/> the rebels in the Daily Express building just across the road,<lb/> but the entire absence of any armed person in the streets<lb/> produced a feeling of unreality, almost of deliberate drama,<lb/> in the beholder. For instance, the huge breadth of Sackville<lb/> Street at the G.P.O. was spanned by a strand or two of barbed<lb/> wire, and one callow youth in the uniform of the Sinn Fein<lb/> (pronounce 'Shin fane') army was leaning on his rifle<lb/> chatting to a knot of people while keeping the wire inviolate.<lb/><seg type="del">One window</seg>The windows of the G.P.O. were smashed, mail-bags, office-<lb/> furniture and miscellanea, formed cover for the defenders, and<lb/> some of these could be seen more or less at their ease  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0910_img_255_3"/>
              looking down upon us, just as if they were awaiting the arrival <lb/> of some royal procession. In Sackville Street there was no <lb/> shooting, and the crowd laughed and talked gaily. A few shops <lb/> had been looted to the last article, but it seems only those <lb/> into which the rebels had forced an entrance for purposes of <lb/> defence. At that time the mob had not taken the initiative.  My friend and I returned to the <sic>Collage</sic> gates and obtained <lb/> admission at about 11 a.m., and until the following Sunday I <lb/> left it only once, and that for the purpose of guarding <lb/> prisoners at the Custom House, just opposite the famous <lb/> Liberty Hall, now blown to bits.  The duty of the O.T.C. <sic>re-inforced</sic> by stray soldiers <lb/> of all kinds --- Anzacs, Canadians, A.O.C., South Africans, <lb/> R.I.R., R.D.F., Manchesters, and others who had fled from <lb/> the streets on Monday night --- was to hold T.C.D. which <lb/> happens to occupy the <seg type="del">next</seg> most  important strategic position in <lb/> the City. When the rising occurred about midday on Monday<lb/> afternoon and night there were never more than 40 to 60 <lb/> armed men in the garrison. The military acumen of the rebel <lb/> leaders may be judged from the fact that they did not make <lb/> any serious attempt to capture the position. If they had <lb/> done so the rebellion might have been a much more serious matter.  During the afternoon of Tuesday, the first regiment of <lb/> soldiers arrived from the Curragh and you may imagine that we  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0910_img_255_4"/>
              cheered them as they entered the gates. From that time the <lb/> College was the scene of the greatest military activity, and <lb/> at one period later in the week a whole brigade with cavalry <lb/> and artillery billetted and bivouacked within the walls. The <lb/> actual defence of the College was left in our hands and we <lb/> had a strenuous ten days of manning windows and roofs and <lb/> mounting guards. A machine gun and a party of sharp-shooters <lb/> on the roof did good execution down Sackville Street, and <lb/> T.C.D. may <sic>de</sic> said to have saved the banks and business <lb/> premises of the most important thoroughfares of Dublin. Only <lb/> one shop within range of our rifles was looted and I shall never <lb/> understand how the riff-raff of the streets could brave the <lb/> hail of bullets - even though most of them were fired high - <lb/> in order to steal boxes and sacks full of fruit and vegetables.  The College buildings are high and formed a perfect <lb/> protection from the enemy's bullets, but it was not a pleasant <lb/> experience to do guard duty in the various quads, while rifle <lb/> and machine gun fire was going on briskly overhead, but I <lb/> got used to it in a short time. I know now what a diet <lb/> of bully beef and biscuits means, for we had them three times <lb/> a day almost the whole time, very rarely seeing bread or <lb/> butter, and meat of the uncanned variety only once. Even <lb/> jam was scarce, and after the first two days there were no<lb/> potatoes. That was nothing, but we all felt the want of <lb/> sleep, as the garrison was not strong enough to permit a <lb/> proper system of reliefs. For five nights I slept something  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0910_img_255_5"/>
              less than ten hours, and that of course with all clothes and<lb/> equipment on. But what is that compared with one spell of <lb/> duty in the driest trench at the front. If the rebels had <lb/> possessed anything heavier than a machine gun we should have<lb/> slept still less.  The madness of it all! But was the plan mere madness?<lb/> I do not believe it. The rebels were convinced, in my<lb/> opinion, that they were taking part in a great German push<lb/> by sea and by land, and you will find that they had good<lb/> reason for their belief. The rebels adopted defensive<lb/> tactics from the beginning, and they gambled upon (a) a<lb/> general rising of the populace, (b) German assistance<lb/> arriving before the British could send enough men from<lb/> England. They hoped that the German Navy, or the Submarine<lb/> part of it, would deal with the transports, and that the paral-<lb/> ysis of Dublin would be followed immediately by a rebel<lb/> occupation of every important town in the country.  We call them madmen now because they did not succeed,<lb/> but we shall not know for a long time how mad they really<lb/> were.   If it were not for the wanton burning of Sackville Street,<lb/> the city and the country would have suffered no more than trifling<lb/> inconvenience, and a few hundred casualties, but that immense<lb/> act of arson has ruined Dublin for the time. I saw the fire,<lb/> and it will never fade from my memory. No photographs can<lb/> reproduce the awful devastation which it wrought, nor any  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0910_img_255_6"/>
              writing the misery which it leaves behind.  Nevertheless, this rebellion has done <seg type="del">no</seg> one  good thing in<lb/> that the reality of war has been brought to our doors, and<lb/> I shall have more hope for Ireland from now on. Perhaps if<lb/> the rebellion had flared up in the provinces before it was<lb/> suppressed, the ultimate result would be happier, but in the<lb/> Dublin area at least the people will turn from the pleasure<lb/> of making profits out of the war to the sterner task of fighting<lb/> adversity.  There is still an O.T.C. garrison in T.C.D., but the<lb/> business men are being relieved, and I gave up my rifle on<lb/> Friday, after 9 days continuous duty. It is said that<lb/> T.C.D. saved the city, and I am proud to have been one of<lb/> the garrison. Luckily the long range shooting of the rebels<lb/> was poor while ours was fair to good, so that we suffered<lb/> no casual<seg type="del">i</seg>ties.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>