<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4368">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sharman D Neill to Edward Carson, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sharman D Neill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sharman D Neill (1858-1934) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.. Neill was one of the finest Irish silversmiths of the late 19th century and designer of the cap badges of the Ulster Volunteer Force from 1912 until 1914. Neill would lose both of his sons in the First World War. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/19/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4368</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0523">Sharman D Neill</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1602">22 Donegall Place, Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4368_img_3723_1"  type="Letter"  url="78034817b55638683470b77a04aaab9f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4368_img_3723_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   22 Donegall Place Belfast,  Oct 7 1916  <lb/>IRISH SILVER FACTORY- 14. FADE ST ., DUBLIN   Dear Sir Edward Carson   Although I have never taken any active part in Politics I am constrained to <lb/>offer you the opinion of a plain man in the street which I know is the opinion <lb/>of many others like myself —   It seems to me in this hour of the Empires urgency for Man Power, you have <lb/>a supreme opportunity to show the bona fides of Ulsters <sic>Attatchment</sic> to the Empire. <lb/>Why not offer on behalf of the Six Counties to agree to Conscription?    The friends of those Conscripted (even if the police would not) would see <lb/>to it that any Nationalist who crossed their borders to take the place of <lb/>men called up, would automaticaly be arrested &amp; made to serve. <lb/>This would to my mind effectually put out of Court the Nationalists, before <lb/>the bar of public opinion in England, unless they fell into line, which <lb/>there seems to be no prospect of their doing.   It would definately kill Home Rule for it would seperate the Six <lb/>Counties from the rest of Ireland by a barrier that could never <lb/>be broken down.   We know Conclusively the Nationalists will never accept Home Rule <lb/>with the Six Counties left out.   Many many of us Unionists feel deeply humiliated that so many <lb/>hundreds of eligible men calling themselves Unionists, are sheltering <lb/>themselves and their sons under the Nationalist umbrella. <lb/>A Unionist cannot logically object to doing his part for the <lb/>Empire in her hour of need.   Now is the time Sir to speak out and save our province from <lb/>the lasting stigma of cowardice and our Beloved Division from extinction.   I remain <hi rend="underline">with</hi> humble apologies <lb/>Yours faithfully   <hi rend="underline">Sharman D Neill</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>