<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5499">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty to Sir Roger Casement, 30 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from the Dominican priest Fr. Thomas Crotty (d. 1930, born James but took the name Thomas after he joined the order) to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written during Casement&#39;s eighteen month stay in Germany, where he was attempting to gain German support for an Irish rebellion against British rule. The letter refers to Casement&#39;s attempts to create an Irish Brigade of Irish-born British army soldiers who were then held as prisoners of war in German camps. It was the camp at Linberg, in the Lahn valley, that was designated for the project. Fr. Crotty was one of the priests who administered to the men in the camp at Limberg. The project was, however, largely unsuccessful and only fifty-six men signed up. The letter refers to mainly to a meeting with a cardinal in Munich and also requests that Casement enquire about a letter that Crotty had sent seeking permission to visit all the camps with Irish prisoners in them but which had not been replied to. He also refers to some of Casement&#39;s published writing on Irish history and proposes a meeting with Casment before Christmas.
Casement was later arrested in County Kerry having returned to Ireland in a submarine to try and prevent the Easter Rising from taking place as he felt German support was insufficient. He was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,085 /20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5499</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0444">Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</persName>
              <date>1915-11-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0529">Limberg, Lahn, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1930</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5499_img_531_1"  type="Letter"  url="e62fb0bad68a564ed3b746af4d929b90.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5499_img_531_2"  type="Letter"  url="7438a02dd26078b3517a03f20e5ccbe5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5499_img_531_3"  type="Letter"  url="9a3bb788d958b73e362ac4ac4422f90d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5499_img_531_1"/>
             Missionshaus<lb/>Limburg a/ Lahn   30. Nov. 1915    Dear Sir Roger   I beg to thank you for the<lb/>scraps from Journals, and also for<lb/>P. Ford's Book. All very interesting, and<lb/>for me sad reading.  You will be glad to hear that my<lb/>journey to Munich and stay of<lb/>8 days there were very satisfactory.<lb/>The Cardinal Nuntius hopes to do<lb/>something for me and my flock. He<lb/>quite understands matters, and is<lb/>of my opinion regarding the changing<lb/>of the men to the various camps. He<lb/>sees no reason, considering my mission,<lb/>why I should not be allowed to visit<lb/>the camps where Irishmen are. I laid<lb/>before him a full account of my 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5499_img_531_2"/>
             years work. I am having my statement<lb/>in writing copied and hope to have a<lb/>copy sent in to the Auswaertiges Amt.<lb/>The Cardinal asked me if I had made<lb/>application to the Ministry of War for<lb/>permission to visit the camps, or if I had<lb/>suggested the advisability of having<lb/>all the Irishmen brought into one<lb/>camp so that my ministry should<lb/>be thereby very much lighter than<lb/>it is. I told him I had written to<lb/>a gentleman in the Auswaertiges<lb/>Amt. and told him my grievances,<lb/>and asked him to obtain this<lb/>permission for me. I was assured both<lb/>by Count von Wedel and Mr. Meyer<lb/>that they would help me in everything.<lb/>It was therefore to them I applied,<lb/>but for some reason, no answer is forth—<lb/>coming.  A copy of my letter is I believe by <lb/>this time in the Vatican, and I have<lb/>reason to believe that it shall be<lb/>a testimony to the truth of affairs<lb/>as they are, and not as they are repre—<lb/>sented to be by the Press reports that<lb/>reach Rome.  I shall say no more of my interview<lb/>with his Eminence. Probably you shall<lb/>get a look at my report when it reaches<lb/>Berlin.  Could it be possible that Mr. Meyer is<lb/>from home? or has my letter been lost.<lb/>In it I repeated my request for the<lb/>leave to visit the camps just as the<lb/><hi rend="underline">English Protestant</hi> Mr. Williams has.<lb/>I also reminded him that I am to<lb/>settle my accounts for expenses of<lb/>the past five months, for it is now that<lb/>length of time since I had any funds<lb/>given me.  If you should meet either Mr. Meyer<lb/>or the Count von Wedel, I would ask you 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5499_img_531_3"/>
             as a favour to let them know what I write<lb/>to you, or at least of as much of it as you deem<lb/>necessary.  The weather is very cold here, and we<lb/>are having much snow and frost. I hope<lb/>myself and the boys escape any<lb/>bad colds during this inclement season.<lb/>I heard during my stay in Bavaria, of the<lb/>many interesting articles that appeared<lb/>from your pen in the Press there. It is well<lb/>to have people know the history of Ireland.<lb/>In Bavaria Irish History is always interesting<lb/>as the people of that Nation, owe their<lb/>Christianity to the labours of an Irish<lb/>Missionary, whose name is honoured<lb/>and revered there - Kilian - the Martyr<lb/>Saint.  Is there any chance of meeting you before<lb/>Xmas? In any event may the Great Feast<lb/>bring us joy and happiness and peace.  Yours v. sincerely   J.T. <hi rend="underline">Crotty</hi> O.P.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>