<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6630">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Seán O'Casey [Seán Ó Cathsaigh], Killarney Gaelic League, to Gregory Ashe, [1917]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Seán O&#39;Casey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Seán O&#39;Casey expresses sympathy on Thomas Ashe&#39;s death and condemns the treatment he received, mentioning that Ashe and &#34;other brave men [were] suffering their Purgatory at the hands of saviours ? [sic] of small nations&#34;. Thomas Ashe (* 1885) was a member of the Gaelic League, the Irish Republican Brotherhood (IRB) and co-founder of the Irish Volunteers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Thomas Ashe Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6630</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0270">Seán O&#39;Casey</persName>
              <date>1917</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0421">Killarney Gaelic League, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Gregory Ashe</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6630_img_None_1"  url="phpCWGJG7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6630_img_0_1"/>
              Connradh na Gaeilge    Craobh na nAirne    i gCill Airne    A Cara   At a special meeting of the<lb/>Committe of the above the following was proposed<lb/>seconded &amp; passed in silence. Resolved<lb/>That we tender to the Father &amp; Relatives of the<lb/>late Tomás Ághas our sincerest sympathy<lb/>in their great Bereavement in the loss of<lb/>a worthy son and a noble and brave<lb/>Irishman, and that we condemn in the<lb/>strongest manner possible the treatment meted<lb/>out ot himself and the other brave men who<lb/>are suffering their Purgutory at the hands of<lb/>Saviours ? of Small Nations  In forwarding this message may I ask you to<lb/>accept my own personal sympathy I had the<lb/>honour and privillege of the acquaintance of your<lb/>Gallant Son and I believe that he has died the<lb/>death he himself wished, for what nobler End<lb/>could any man be than to die for God and Ireland.   mise le meas mor    Seán O Cathsaigh  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>