<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5368">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nora Ring to Susan Daly, March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nora Ring </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/23/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5368</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0549">Nora Ring </persName>
              <date>1923-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0417">77 Harcourt Street, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0193">Susan Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5368_img_4652_1"  type="Letter"  url="c34335fe534c2354508faf15f25a207f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5368_img_4652_2"  type="Letter"  url="172ad7b8e85587847090348f7bab4757.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5368_img_4652_3"  type="Letter"  url="f96f7c62522e151a06b3264cea6aebe4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5368_img_4652_1"/>
             77 Harcourt st.<lb/>Dublin.  P41/23/12   My dear Susan —   I address you by your Christian name<lb/>because I feel as if I already know you, from all<lb/>I have heard of you. I intended writing to you<lb/>every day asking you to call but as your cousin<lb/>Mary Maloney told Jen you were thinking of doing<lb/>so yourself I did not write.  However in view of what happened this week<lb/>I cannot possibly delay in writing you a few<lb/>lines to express to you my sympathy in your<lb/>Great sorrow. The news of Charlie’s death (RIP) has<lb/>stunned us all. Only on Saturday last I had<lb/>a letter from him and indeed I did not think<lb/>it was to be his last one. As a matter of fact I<lb/>wrote to Kerry specially for some shamrocks to<lb/>send him on St. Patricks day but instead of that I<lb/>find that we are praying for his soul on that day.<lb/>Well! May the Holy Will of God be done in all<lb/>things. He is our only hope and consolation<lb/>now and the only One from whom we may expect<lb/>Justice.  Charlie has died a soldier’s death and has<lb/>remained true to the Cause when so many have failed 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5368_img_4652_2"/>
             You have good reason to be proud of your brave<lb/>brother and you need not grieve over his death<lb/>because he died true to the Flag and faithful to<lb/>the last. May God reward him for it.  Only for him and his Comrades poor Ireland<lb/>would indeed have to bow down her head in<lb/>shame and sorrow on account of the slavish attitude<lb/>of her children towards the old enemy. They have<lb/>given their life’s blood to blot and the stain that<lb/>now lies on our country’s name. I feel confident<lb/>that their sacrifice will soon bear fruit. Already<lb/>the people are beginning to realize that they are<lb/>going into the Empire and not getting a Republic<lb/>through this so—called <hi rend="”underline”">Free</hi>—State.  Of course it is only natural that you will miss<lb/>him — I know what I should feel like myself if<lb/>anything happened my brother. But God will give you<lb/>strength and courage to bear this trial.  I will never forget poor Charlie in my prayers<lb/>and I am writing to my brother who is a priest<lb/>in U.S.A. and I will get him to say Masses for<lb/>him and his four comrades who were executed by the traitors.  All her join me in sending you our deepest and sincerest sympathy in your bereavement. Jen and I are dying to meet you. I would go out to Carysfort but I do not know what day I could see you. Could you arrange to come into town any day and we would meet you anywhere. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5368_img_4652_3"/>
            <hi rend="”underline”">3</hi> you like or perhaps you would call here directly.<lb/>It is two houses above the Standard Hotel.  We have only a flat yet but we are looking<lb/>everywhere for a house. We shall be more than<lb/>delighted to meet you. My father Tomas<lb/>well. In fact he stayed in Kenmare with him.  Are you going home for Easter? If not I hope<lb/>we will often meet during the holidays.  This will be a terrible blow for your Mother<lb/>but God will sustain her and reward her for<lb/>giving such a hero to Ireland.   With love and deep sympathy<lb/>From your friend<lb/>Nora Ring  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>