<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1151">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 14 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s new address and his duties. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/6, IJA/CHPI/54/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1151</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-06-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1151_img_3828_1"  type="Letter"  url="1f291cbcc9283bb5d799cb4099c14273.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1151_img_3828_1"/>
                14 June 1916   Dear Father Provincial, P. C.    My proper address until <lb/>Further notice is: 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Batt. Hampshire Rgt. <lb/>B. E. F. France. I shall, you see, be <lb/>a bit nearer to the seat of operations <lb/>than I have been so far; and, of <lb/>course, I shall have to more to do. The <lb/>Lord, and Our Lady, will have to take <lb/>care of me for the future. I <lb/>had a letter about a week ago from <lb/>F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Fitzgibbon; he gave me news of <lb/>Frank Browne, who is quite close to him.  I shall write more soon. <seg type="closer"> Asking your Reverences prayers, and a <lb/>remembrance in Mass, <lb/>I am <lb/>Yours very sincerely in Christ,  F. M. Shaw S.J. C.F. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>