<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1647">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 27 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. Marie was a born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the out break of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British Army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary. Marie states that she received a letter from her sister Violet (1896-?) which informed her about her brother Charlie&#39;s (1895-1915) death. She then goes on to discuss her brother Tommy (1891-?) who is also in the war. Marie goes on to discuss what is happening where she is and her day to day activities. She goes on to say that she hopes the last letter she sent to her mother did not worry her too much as it was rumours. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF133</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1647</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-02-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1647_img_1108_1"  type="Letter"  url="3729aae07bb653870312f122babfa3f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1647_img_1108_2"  type="Letter"  url="62b09d09f05359b153bc829aefb1d10d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1647_img_1108_3"  type="Letter"  url="9602d58bdbac43fe464aea7f2494197a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1647_img_1108_1"/>
             27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb: 1916<lb/><hi rend="underline">11.15p.m.</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   I had been trying to write to<lb/>you every day since your Cable &amp; your letter<lb/>dated Feb: 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which I received on Thursday<lb/>with a very old one of Jan: with all<lb/>Hennesy row in it, I have at last received<lb/>Violet's letter with Major Whyte's letter, I had<lb/>no idea Charlie did so well &amp; how proud<lb/>you must feel of him, I know <sic>I very</sic> proud<lb/>to be his sister, I wish we could get news<lb/>through to him &amp; not make the time feel<lb/>so long, I hope the War will end very<lb/>soon &amp; that he will be back with us all<lb/>well &amp; strong. Mother I cannot tell you<lb/>how disappointed I am about Tommy I do<lb/>not <sic>ofcourse</sic> know whether he is in Solonika<lb/>or France but I know this much he has<lb/>never called at Malta, I have been living<lb/>on the thoughts of seeing the boys ever<lb/>since I came out but my luck is out.<lb/>I have been very busy this last week, as<lb/>we got a convoy from Solonika (mostly the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>Div:) &amp; they were sent to my Block .H. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1647_img_1108_2"/>
             &amp; as well as this we (the nursing Staff) are<lb/>giving a concert for the Patients on Tuesday<lb/>&amp; all our spare time is given up to<lb/>rehearsals etc, we have just finished one.<lb/>I shall write &amp; tell you all about it<lb/><sic>latter</sic>. They are also starting giving us<lb/>V. A. Ds <sic>lecture</sic> the M. O. are giving us<lb/>3 a week &amp; a Sister is giving us a practical<lb/>one every sunday, so you see things are<lb/>changing. I think it is a very good<lb/>plan &amp; am sure they will be very<lb/>interesting. I have not seen A. Lily<lb/>for ages, she rang me up to go to<lb/>Tea to-day, but could not get off.<lb/>The Irish boys (men) are ripping but<lb/>some of them are so old, how they<lb/>ever stood it is beyond me, we<lb/>have a great number C. Rangers<lb/>7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> D: F. Leinsters, Innis: Fus: R. I. Reg<lb/>etc. so A. Agnes money is turning in<lb/>useful. I enclose two <sic>phoos</sic> which I<lb/>think awfully good &amp; I may tell you<lb/>they are in great demand, I have<lb/>to be very careful what I say in<lb/>my letters as I hear one of St Georges<lb/>girls wrote indiscreet things &amp; the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1647_img_1108_3"/>
             governor has the letter.  I hope I did not worry you with the<lb/>letter with all the Rumours but at that<lb/>time we were really <sic>suppose</sic> to be on<lb/>the move but I have heard nothing<lb/>more since, <sic>ofcourse</sic> I shall not go<lb/>on further, I will go home at the<lb/>end of my time for a rest &amp; then<lb/>do something again. I suppose by<lb/>the time this reaches you, you will<lb/>have had a visit from Gerald, I had<lb/>a long letter from him the other day<lb/>dated 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb: &amp; he said he was <seg type="del">on</seg><lb/>getting leave very soon, how I should<lb/>love to be at home to hear all his<lb/>news. Well I must end this<lb/><sic>Iam</sic> dead tired.  Hoping you are all very well.<lb/>With every loving thought &amp;<lb/>wish.  Your most gratefull &amp; loving   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>