<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1244">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 19 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from May Fay (1897-1976) to James Finn (1877-1922) informing James about her latest correspondence from friends and family about their recent engagement. May expresses her happiness that James would choose to be with her but worries over her own inadequacies. Before signing off May tells James about her recent illness.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. After her husband&#39;s death May held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1244</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-01-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0557">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1244_img_433_1"  type="Letter"  url="64b6d25135a71d522b3cc83ca6fa8a0c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1244_img_433_2"  type="Letter"  url="39dd2c0ca891a3ba4516f0fdbc10047c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1244_img_433_3"  type="Letter"  url="61040ca271e98af79610dcfbad6cb11f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1244_img_433_4"  type="Letter"  url="ad8034ec1d080c997b9113fd91b8f574.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1244_img_433_5"  type="Letter"  url="46bda9f90e994982e519224cd3b11731.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1244_img_433_6"  type="Letter"  url="d3dd04418cd63c4cf9cb4e6043599915.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1244_img_433_1"/>
                Togherstown  Ballinea    19â1â16   My dearest James   Your nice letter <lb/>was indeed very welcome <lb/>This morn I was watching <lb/>out for it but had long  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1244_img_433_2"/>
              given up when Paddie arrived <lb/>about 12:30 we were expecting <lb/>a line from Mother, but did <lb/>get one still I suppose she <lb/>is safe or we would hear <lb/>before this.  I had a very nice <lb/>letter from Moll although <lb/>I have never had the pleasure <lb/>of meeting her It was very <lb/>good of her to write. Oh Joe <lb/>Wynne wrote me saying <cb/> how delighted she was about <lb/>my engagement &amp; what a lucky <lb/>girl I was, for myself I cannot <lb/>imagine even yet one like <lb/>you could be content with <lb/>a plain country girl of course <lb/>The thought that you are <hi rend="underline">realy</hi><lb/>fond of me makes me <hi rend="underline">very</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">very</hi> happy but I cannot <lb/>help letting my worthlessness <lb/>in every way rest very heavily <lb/>on my mind.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1244_img_433_3"/>
              About going to town I see now <lb/>it  was  all for the best <seg type="unclear">too</seg> allowed Mother <lb/>off first had we decided on <lb/>taking the longed for visit <lb/>on Sat I certainly would  be <hi rend="underline">left</hi><lb/>The cold I had the day you <lb/>left which seemed nothing <lb/>proved much worse than <lb/>I even knew it did <seg type="unclear">until</seg> last <lb/>night I was very restless <lb/>coughing smothering etc. <lb/>I remained in bed till very  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1244_img_433_4"/>
              late today but Thank God I <lb/>feel <sic>quiet</sic> on the mend now <lb/>I am managing to keep <lb/>the 'blossoms' off my lips &amp; <lb/>nose by means of Corbetts <lb/>ointment so I expect I will <lb/>feel <sic>realy</sic> fit by the time <lb/>Mother comes home Tommy <lb/>Derry spent last night <lb/>with us his Mother being <lb/>in B. More he said it <lb/>was a 'Gods Charity' I had  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1244_img_433_5"/>
              no one to do anything for <lb/>my cold whas made I <lb/>leave my own road &amp; <lb/>he always so nice to me <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> S. says every one in <lb/>there is delighted with the <lb/>news Josephine wrote <lb/>me good wishes thro' <lb/>Mrs. Seery would have sent <lb/>wires to us both but was <lb/>afraid of being laughed at <cb/> Mrs. S says she is very <lb/>jealous at not hearing from <lb/>you but sends warmest love <lb/>I was in town (on 9th) Sat <lb/>last I payed a long promised <lb/>visit to Brother Casey  I was very glad to get <lb/>out of him nothwithsanding <lb/>how nice he was to me <lb/>took me on knee put his <lb/>arm round my neck  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1244_img_433_6"/>
              in fact did every thing but <lb/>kiss me I was going to tell <lb/>him Id tell you but thought <lb/>it better not.  What you said of me <lb/>in the end of your letter did <lb/>indeed make me laugh &amp; <lb/>laugh hearty I was going <lb/>to tell Nano what I was <lb/>laughing at but I knew <seg type="unclear">drunkness</seg><lb/>would be her first thought  Bye Bye now dearest James <seg type="closer"> lots of love from your own  May </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>