<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2045">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Matthew Nathan to Andrew Philip Magill, 22 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Matthew Nathan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the under-secretary Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) to Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941), the private secretary for the Chief Crown Secretary of Ireland, Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). In the letter Nathan is sending Magill the original report of a incident between the Irish Volunteers and the police on the 22 March 1916. The attack happened at an anti-Sinn Féin demonstration which took place in Tullamore, Co Offaly. Fourteen Irish Volunteers were besieged by a hostile mob in the local Sinn Féin hall. Believing they were inadequately protected by the police they fired revolvers to keep the mob away, and when the police moved in to disarm them they resisted arrest, and shots were fired seriously wounding Sergeant Ahearn. The report is from the head policeman at the scene.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI; Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8125/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2045</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date>1916-03-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2045_img_1492_1"  type="Letter"  url="328ffd967455f21c121c6d8dfe4f23ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2045_img_1492_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="3333f3475028193bfd3914e2280d089d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2045_img_1492_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="20980d284dd11fc6dce0ee0897ec3a7a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2045_img_1492_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="68606c2a11d8e7e8223485f71c935309.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2045_img_1492_1"/>
             CHIEF SECRETARY'S OFFICE. <lb/>DUBLIN CASTLE.   22/3/16   Dear Magill,   I want the original report <lb/> on the Tullamore incident for <lb/> the moment so send the <lb/>attached copy for Mr. Birrell <lb/>to see.   Yours sincerely   Matthew Nathan 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2045_img_1492_2"/>
            (Copy).  Attempted murder by shooting &amp;c. <lb/>R. v. Joseph Rafter; Joseph Morris; <lb/><hi rend="underline">Henry McNally &amp; Thomas Byrne</hi>   TULLAMORE, <lb/>King's Co.   21st March 1916.   I beg to report that on last night an anti-Sinn Fein <lb/> demonstration was made through the principal streets in <lb/>Tullamore by about 200 women, men and boys. They halted <lb/>opposite the Sinn Fein rooms in William Street where the <lb/> Irish Volunteers also hold meetings and drill. The Police <lb/> moved the crowd away several times, but it reformed after <lb/> short intervals and made demonstrations of ill-feeling towards <lb/> the Irish Volunteers, calling them "Germans" and such names <lb/> as they thought would annoy them. They principally con- <lb/>sisted of the mothers, wives, brothers and sisters of men <lb/> who are fighting in the British Army at the front.    The night was dark and the public lamps were not lit <lb/> in the town. It was therefore difficult for the Police <lb/> to see what the individual members of the crowd were doing. <lb/> Stones were thrown at the Sinn Fein rooms and revolver shots <lb/> were fired from the rooms in retaliation.   At about 10.30 p.m. matters became threatening. I went <lb/> to William Street and with the available force I moved the <lb/> greater part of the crowd to a distance from the rooms and <lb/> gave instructions to the police to keep the people there and <lb/> induce them to go home. I then entered the Sinn Fein rooms <lb/>with Sergt. Philip Ahern to investigate the allegation of <lb/>shooting.    (1) James O'Brennan, one of the leaders of the Irish <lb/> Volunteers, with 15 others whose names are as <lb/> follows, was present :- <lb/>(2) Joseph Grehan <lb/>(3) Joseph Rafter <lb/>(4) Peter Bracken <lb/>(5) Frank Brennan
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2045_img_1492_3"/>
            (6) Joseph Morris <lb/>(7) John Delaney <lb/>(8) John Spain <lb/>(9) James Clarke <lb/>(10) Henry McNally <lb/>(11) Thomas Byrne <lb/>(12) Thomas Hogan <lb/>(13) Thomas Deigan <lb/>(14) Edward Downe <lb/>(15) John Martin; and <lb/>(16) John O'Flynn - all aged between 19 and 35 Years.   O'Brennan complained of the conduct of the crowd <lb/>and showed me a few stones that he stated came through <lb/> the windows of their room. I informed him I required <lb/> the names of all present in the room, and by my direction <lb/> Sergeant Ahern noted them in his book. At this time <lb/> Co. Inspector Crane &amp; Head-Const. Stuart arrived in the <lb/> room and the Co. Inspector gave orders to search the <lb/> party for arms in connection with the shooting. The <lb/> Sinn Feiners objected. Sergeant Ahern got hold of Frank <lb/> Brennan and the Co. Inspector went to his assistance. <lb/> There was a scuffle in the room, and immediately eight <lb/> or ten of the Sinn Feiners drew revolvers and fired <lb/> deliberately at us. We got mixed up with them, and the <lb/> firing continued by some while others attacked us with <lb/> hurleys and sticks. We were not armed. While I was <lb/>endeavouring to wrench a revolver from James O'Brennan <lb/> which he had aimed, and from which he had fired two shots <lb/> at the Co. Inspector and Sergeant Ahern, I was struck on <lb/> the head and arm and dazed with a hurley. My left arm <lb/> was powerless for the remainder of the fight, but <lb/> I wrenched the hurley from my assailant and kept him <lb/> prisoner with my right arm. The Co. Inspector was several- <lb/>ly
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2045_img_1492_4"/>
            severally injured in the face and head, presumably from blows <lb/> of a heavy instrument and his clothes show marks of at least <lb/> one discharged bullet. Sergeant Ahern had to be conveyed <lb/>to hospital with his right arm broken and two bullets in his <lb/> arm and side. Head Const. Stuart got off with slight <lb/> injuries to his face &amp; hands. It was a desperate attempt <lb/> on our lives, and it is marvellous how we escaped as we did, <lb/> for at least 20 shots were fired, and intended for us, but it <lb/> is rumoured some of them lodged in our assailants. We arrested <lb/> four of the Sinn Feiners in the room and afterwards conveyed <lb/> them under armed escort to the barracks where I charged them <lb/> with firing at and attacking us with intent to murder. When <lb/> cautioned they made no statements.   Their names are given in front and they have been <lb/> remanded in custody until 11.15 a.m. on Monday, 27th instant <lb/>. Two revolvers &amp; an automatic pistol were found in the room - <lb/>one revolver on prisoner Rafter.     None of the other offenders have gone to their homes and <lb/> I am trying to locate them and arrest them.     I consider as we may have to search other persons' houses <lb/> it is safer to procure warrants for their arrest.     On examination to-day of the Sinn Feiners' room there were <lb/> found 15 bullet marks on the wall, varying from 3 to 5 feet <lb/> high from the floor. There is also a bullet mark through<lb/> the plate glass window across the street on Mr. Scally's <lb/> drapery establishment.    Sergt. Ahern was conveyed by motor by direction of Doctor <lb/> Moorhead to Steven's Hospital at 3 p.m. to-day for X-Ray <lb/> treatment. I have communicated with the Commandant to have <lb/> him watched, and his dying declaration taken, if necessary. <lb/>I shall send copies of the evidence in due course, and I request <lb/>that the Crown Solicitor of this County be directed to take <lb/> charge of the prosecution.   J. FITZGERALD  <lb/>2 D. I.  LK. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>