<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0175">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alexander Crawford to Sir Matthew Nathan, 28 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alexander G. Crawford</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Alexander G. Crawford to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). Crawford is continuing his correspondence with Nathan about the pension of a Derry school principal, Mr Houston. Crawford informs Nathan of the sacrifices Houston had made during his career and suggests that he deserves the pension grant offered by the school&#39;s main benefactor, the Irish Society. Mathew Nathan had become under-secretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned as under-secretary due to his misjudgement and failure to stop the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5498/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/175</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0485">Alexander G. Crawford</persName>
              <date>1916-03-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1349">Coleraine, Derry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0175_img_1311_1"  type="Letter"  url="75be760e01e3f2867e56d8c2de41017b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0175_img_1311_2"  type="Letter"  url="77a6f40fb348b761f31efecae7d49612.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0175_img_1311_1"/>
                Academical Institution  Coleraine    March 28. 1916   Sir,   I am in receipt of <lb/> yours of 25th inst. (4904)   Might I take the liberty of <lb/> pointing out that during a <lb/> large part of Mr. Houston's <lb/> Principalship, he was entitled <lb/> to a percentage of the school <lb/> fees but refrained from claim= <lb/> ing it &amp;&amp; received instead the <lb/> balance on hand at the end <lb/> of the year, thus suffering con- <lb/> siderable loss.   The Grants from the Irish  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0175_img_1311_2"/>
              Society were made largely to <lb/> relieve Mr. Houston of <lb/> financial strain.   Would it not meet the <lb/> case if the Irish Society ear- <lb/> marked £100 of these grants for <lb/> Mr. Houston, besides the £200 which <lb/> they have voted for his pension? <lb/> I know that the Agent of the Society <lb/> would be agreeable to the arrang- <lb/> ment, as it would carry out the <lb/> intentions of the Society.   In case that it is necessary <lb/> to have an amended Scheme, <lb/> what  would <seg type="del">would</seg> the approximate <lb/> cost of the same be to the Governors?   Believe me, <seg type="closer"> Your obedt. servant,  <hi rend="underline">Alex G. Crawford <lb/> Hon Secty. </hi>   The Under Secretary  Dublin Castle.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>