<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4365">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Strachey to Edward Carson, 27 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Strachey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John St Loe Strachey (1860-1927) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Strachey was a British journalist and newspaper proprietor.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/29</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4365</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0792">John Strachey</persName>
              <date>1916-07-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1796">1 Wellington Street, Strand, London, W.C., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0151">Newlands Corner, Merrow Downs, Guildford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4365_img_3720_1"  type="Letter"  url="c071236573c03f1a6231240665603c21.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4365_img_3720_2"  type="Letter"  url="2fec229cefed55bcda49193c7aa627ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4365_img_3720_1"/>
            <seg type="del">The Spectator <lb/>1 Wellington Street, <lb/>Strand, London. W.C.</seg>  <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   Newlands Corner <lb/>Merrow Downs <lb/>Guildford.   Friday July 27th. 1916.   My dear Carson,   I feel I must write to you to express my unbounded <lb/>admiration for the manly, honest and generous part you have <lb/>played in the late negotiations. i have tried to say this <lb/>publicly in the "Spectator", both in my leaders on the <lb/>Fiasco and on the Future and also in a Note to your letter <lb/>in regard to Hugh Cecil. But I desire to go beyond a mere <lb/>public laudation. After all that has passed you could not <lb/>have stultified yourself by changing your ground and in <lb/>effect refusing to accept exclusion and the 'clean cut' when <lb/>it was offered to you as it was. But quite beyond this, <lb/>for of course I realize that there was nothing Machiavellian <lb/>but only what was perfectly straightforward in your attitude, <lb/>you have by your wise action made the British public understand <lb/>in a way they never understood before that the Union <lb/>is a necessity, not a arbitrary evil, and that if you try <lb/>to abrogate it on just terms, i.e. with exclusion, you bring — <lb/>Ireland being Ireland and the Irish people the Irish people— <lb/>the whole Home Rule structure down.   This is why ever since I have been in the Irish <lb/>controversy and especially in the two years before July 1914 <lb/>I always rubbed in Ulster for all I was worth and tried to <lb/>force people to concentrate on Exclusion. I knew that if <lb/>they would do this, exclusion, though honestly asked for, <lb/>was almost certain to act as a chemical which would dissolve <lb/>Home Rule. Exclusion was the thing that brought all the <lb/>unrealities, all the rhetoric, invective and flummery of <lb/>the Irish question to the test and showed that the Union, <lb/>whatever else it might be, was a grim necessity. Further the <lb/>"exhibition', as the doctors might say, of exclusion, might <lb/>prove how false were all the Colonial analogies and force <lb/>people to understand the existence of the two Irelands. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4365_img_3720_2"/>
             Do you remember the marvellous passage in the "Duncaid" <lb/>where Pope talks of the "uncreating word". The exclusion <lb/>of Ulster is absolutely just per se and absolutely <lb/>necessary if Civil War is not to be permanent, but it <lb/>is also the "uncreating word" as far as Home Rule is <lb/>concerned.   In some ways I am very sorry that Exclusion should <lb/>both be necessary and "the uncreating word" for I like <lb/>other people am weary of the Irish problem and would be only <lb/>too thankful to see it got rid of. But after all facts are <lb/>facts and weariness cannot alter them, or rather if one <lb/>tries to let it alter them one is sure to commit some <lb/>hideous cruelty. To my mind we have just got to bear <lb/>the Irish question and admit that it is one of the many <lb/>problems in life which are insoluble, or at any rate <lb/>insoluble under existing conditions - unless of course <lb/>some miracle is somehow worked in the next few days. <lb/>Perhaps some day the nature of the Southern Irish will <lb/>change and we shall get a new heaven and a new earth across <lb/>the water, Bothas instead of Redmonds, Smuts' instead of <lb/>Dillons. Then of course there will be a dozen easy <lb/>solutions.   I am ashamed to have inflicted so long a letter upon <lb/>you, but I have been deeply moved by the injustice with <lb/>which you have been treated by Unionists who ought to <lb/>have known better.   Yours very sincerely,   J. St Leo Strachey 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>