<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0760">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Wilfrid Spender to his wife, Lillian, Spender gives an account of his departure from the Ulster Division - his current location being the HQ of the 2nd Army. He expects to be given a training position, and expresses dismay at the thought that three quarters of the new recruits will be from Derby: a step down after the men of Ulster, whose equal was not &#39;ever seen in the history of mankind&#39;. Spender expresses concern that the representation of the Ulster Division by newspapers has changed from lack of interest to &#39;gush&#39;. He finishes with a brief description of the local countryside. This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender (née Dean, 1880-1968). The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/341</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/760</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0760_img_2292_1"  type="Letter"  url="c308b859d33c9331cca4012ff0cc1aa8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0760_img_2292_2"  type="Letter"  url="7774ddeff5e1a6ee4203e4e2b80fd891.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0760_img_2292_3"  type="NULL"  url="7a0bf89617ce7f03125ea3b20c7b5f81.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0760_img_2292_4"  type="NULL"  url="df71a700b3fc1e6fa0f90ab40369d126.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0760_img_2292_1"/>
                July 11 1916   My pr   I've been up since before 5<lb/> motoring over the country with S,<lb/> a journey which the pr would have <lb/> enjoyed far more than a BW. We<lb/> went behind the greater part of this<lb/> British front seeing the smoke of this<lb/> big battle early on then coming <lb/> down hill to the flat plains later.   I went to H.Q of the 2nd army<lb/> seeing Turner who is GS01 &amp; <lb/> who was a fellow subaltern at<lb/> Woolwich with me  nearly  10 20 30 <lb/> years ago. He was friendly without<lb/> being cordial.  Tonight I am stopping temporarily <lb/> in a chateau more English than<lb/> any I have seen with a French lady<lb/> not unlike <seg type="unclear">Mol</seg> as hostess.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0760_img_2292_2"/>
              We <seg type="del">hope</seg> expect  to go very shortly a <lb/> little way away to a training area<lb/> at which we shall I suppose get our<lb/> drafts, but one 's heart fail one a little  <lb/> at, making up our battalions with<lb/> 3/4 of Derby recruits. The Ulster Div-<lb/> ision which I can think fairly<lb/> claim to have helped train can never <lb/> be the same again. I doubt if its<lb/> equal will ever be seen in the <lb/> history of mankind.  The newspaper reticence has <lb/> been <seg type="del">filled with</seg> changed into  something <seg type="unclear">approaching</seg> gush &amp; I am a little afraid of <lb/> its being over done. I also <seg type="unclear">criticise</seg><lb/> the inspiration of their fulsome account <lb/> in the DM &amp; the Times. Are they  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0760_img_2292_3"/>
              intended to distract attention from <lb/> other matters, or is their <seg type="unclear">courses</seg><lb/> quickened.  I'm so sleepy that I can<lb/> hardly stay wake, &amp; I'm<lb/> without my maid to <seg type="unclear">inspire</seg><lb/> me. S who often talks rather<lb/> poor wanted to go to a <lb/> big hotel but I absolutely<lb/> declined &amp; much prefer my<lb/> chateau billet with Douglas <lb/> to look after me, &amp; I<lb/> persuaded him to do the like.  I wish I was staying  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0760_img_2292_4"/>
              here as the country is nice not <lb/> unlike Norfolk whilst what we<lb/> go to on the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> is likely to<lb/> be like Cambridgeshire only much<lb/> less industry. <seg type="closer"> To bed<lb/>Your bw  WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>