<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4235">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his family. Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/72</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4235</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4235_img_3603_1"  type="Letter"  url="150008d18213645cfdc1ce0fd780786e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4235_img_3603_2"  type="Letter"  url="552dc7c1bb05366996adda43858abdb7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4235_img_3603_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Mater</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Mab</seg> <lb/> <seg type="del">Edmund</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Rex</seg> <lb/> Please return <hi rend="underline">to Lil</hi>   22.Nov   My dear folks,   Just a line to say that I have <lb/> got no letter from home today, but a line <lb/> from Rex which I must answer. Consequently <lb/> You won't get much from me &amp; it is <lb/> nearly post time.   I was out teaching the bombers today &amp; <lb/> found it necessary to take personal control myself. <lb/> The GOC appeared when I was in the middle of it. <lb/> Perhaps it was as well that I was there or there <lb/> would certainly have been some strafing As it is <lb/> he is holding an inspection with "live bombs" tomorrow, <lb/> when the difficulty is not to carry out the drill <lb/> but to let the GOC see it in <seg type="unclear">safety.</seg>   What do you think of Redmond's tour. Perhaps <lb/> it is well for the papers to make the most of it, as <lb/> the recruiting in S Ireland is proving such a fiasco, &amp; as
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4235_img_3603_2"/>
            there is real danger of trouble there — if it is not dealt <lb/> with firmly at once. I wish someone would write to the <lb/> papers &amp; suggest that there should be a new punishment <lb/> for unpatriotic agitators, to take the form of so many <lb/> months deportation to the trenches. It would stop it <lb/> at once as they are all blustering funks, &amp; wouldn't <lb/> we have some fun in showing them round !   I have a dug-out tomorrow so may not be <lb/> able to write much more than I have today.   The Greek outlook is interesting but one fears <lb/> that our government will again show that silly sentiment- <lb/> al weakness in dealing with the situation which they <lb/>always display to smaller nations. I thought <lb/> the new loan was due out now. I am not yet quite <lb/> sure whether to subscribe this time or to save up <lb/> for next time. If the Government get its money <lb/> too easily it will continue it's reckless expenditure.    Best love to all my dear folks including <lb/> Jessie. I did not see her nephew as I did not <lb/> go to those parts again after all   Wilfrid   WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>