<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3837">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A.J. Cockington to the Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 24 October 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A.J. Cockington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from A.J. Cockington, on behalf of the General Council of Medical Education &amp; Registration for the United Kingdom, to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) regarding the application of Ulick Joseph Burke to be reinstated on the medical register. Cockington enquiries whether there would be any objection to Burke&#39;s reinstatement.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-1-58-T94</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3837</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0563">A.J. Cockington</persName>
              <date>1916-10-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0329">299 Oxford Street, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1406">Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3837_img_3216_1"  type="Letter"  url="b3a7b5a715b236df33063e15682d8653.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3837_img_3216_1"/>
             Journal pp 300 &amp; 306   General Council of<lb/>Medical Education &amp; Registration<lb/>of the United Kingdom,<lb/>299, Oxford Street, London, W.   October 24, 1916.   Dear Sir,   Pursuant to the Standing Orders of the General<lb/>Medical Council, I have to inform you that the name of<lb/>Mick Joseph Burke<lb/>was erased from the Medical Register on November 3, 1915<lb/>that at the time he held the qualification of L.L.M.R.C.P. Irel. 1896<lb/>that he has made an application for the restoration of his<lb/>name; and that this application will be considered by the<lb/>executive committee of the Council on November 27, 1916.     I am directed to inquire whether (a) he still<lb/>holds any qualification granted by your Body that entitles<lb/>him to be registered, and (b) whether you know of any<lb/>objection to the restoration of his name.   I am,<lb/>Yours faithfully,   AJ Cockington, <lb/>Acting Registrar.  The Registrar of the<lb/>Royal College of Physicians<lb/>of Ireland.   J.V.C. 3/11/16  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>