<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0711">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí, 9 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí (1881-1965) on Zeppelin bombing raids in Hull and other places in England. He remarks that many people have broken noses as a consequence of stumbling about during the blackouts.Patrick Langford Beazley was born near Killarney, Co. Kerry, son of a tenant who had been evicted from the Lansdowne estate. The Beazleys were an old family in Kerry, of English origin. Married with Nancy (Nanny) Hickey, he was the father of Piaras Béaslaí. He was the editor of the Catholic Times from 1884 until his death in the early 1920s. Piaras Béaslaí (born Percy Frederick Beazley) was an English born writer, revolutionary, politician, language revivalist, journalist and a member of the IRB. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers. He soon abandoned it and became involved in politics and would later fight in the Easter Rising. He wrote twenty plays between 1913 and 1939.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 33,972 / 11, MS 33,972 / 11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/711</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1204">Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-03-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0711_img_221_1"  type="Letter"  url="73ea48469a2eed012c15e976a6250c05.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0711_img_221_2"  type="Letter"  url="8dc8ca8ed9808a7202198b808990e3aa.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0711_img_221_1"/>
                'Glengariff'  Rudgrave Square  Egremont  Cheshire    9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March, 1916   My dearest Pierce,   Mother is sending <lb/>you in this packet <lb/>one pair of socks and <lb/>the <seg type="unclear">rest</seg> will be sent <lb/>to-morrow without fail. <lb/>They are washed already. <lb/>We have no news here <lb/>except what appears in <lb/>the papers, and with <lb/>that of course you are <lb/>familiar. Nora Murphy <lb/>must have had a bad <lb/>time at Hull. I am <lb/>told that that was the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0711_img_221_2"/>
              <lb/>town most heavily bom<lb rend="hyphen"/> barded by the zeppelin <lb/>raiders on their last <lb/>visit. Doubtless the train<lb rend="hyphen"/> ing college escaped in<lb rend="hyphen"/> jury, but the experience <lb/>of those in it must have <lb/>been very unpleasant. It <lb/>is certainly not comforting <lb/>to hear bombs crashing <lb/>and to think that you <lb/>may be a victim of one in <lb/>a few minutes or even <lb/>seconds. There is some <lb/>indignation that no ar<lb rend="hyphen"/> rangements had been made <lb/>whereby the raiders might <lb/>have been kept on the move. <lb/>The mayor has been com<lb rend="hyphen"/><cb/> plaining and has said they <lb/>remained over the town for <lb/>more than an hour. Here <lb/>they cause us trouble by mak<lb rend="hyphen"/> ing it necessary to keep <lb/>the streets dark. A good <lb/>many people have broken <lb/>noses in consequences. We <lb/>are getting something of a <lb/>remedy now by having the <lb/>posts and pillars painted <lb/>white. It is well for Dublin <lb/>that it need take no pre<lb rend="hyphen"/> caution of the kind, I hope <lb/>you are in good health and <lb/>spirits. Write and let us <lb/>know how you are and how <lb/>things are going with you. <lb/>We are well, thanks God, but <lb/>have no news. <seg type="closer"> With fondest love from Mo<lb rend="hyphen"/>ther and myself, Ever affectionately <lb/> Father. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>