<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2069">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Diarmid Coffey, 12 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Jane Coffey, née L&#39;Estrange (1857-1921), to her son, Hugh Diarmid Coffey (1888 - 1964). 

Diarmid joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914 and became secretary of the Irish National Volunteers after the organisation split in 1915. Although not involved in the 1916 Rising, he feared he would be arrested for his involvement with the Irish Volunteers and his known Sinn Féin sympathies.

In this letter Jane asks Diarmid about work and tells him of her activities from the previous day in North Stoke.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Coffey &amp; Chenevix Trench Papers Collection List No 153, Ms. 46301/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2069</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1823">Bath, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2069_img_152_1"  type="Letter"  url="1f87f3dbf046e352857ba8d4b4c58871.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2069_img_152_2"  type="Letter"  url="8a457bbf871ac588fd6f31f9f7ff9c1a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2069_img_152_3"  type="Letter"  url="d0a11a132e29e508781643e4db8679c7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2069_img_152_1"/>
             &amp; talks much of <seg type="unclear">revenge</seg>. I suggested E's idea that   <lb/>faults are always <lb/>copied in times <lb/>of war —  yr mother   Tangridge House <lb/>Near Bath   (3 miiles)   Oct 12.16   Dearest D.   I sent you yesterday <lb/>as usual in a great hurry <lb/>&amp; I fear insufficiently <lb/>addressed — so send this <lb/>today. Edward Carpenter's <lb/>letter which I enclose is <lb/>good &amp; might interest <lb/>the Storkleys. The Chronicle <lb/>seems the most enlightened
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2069_img_152_2"/>
            of the London papers. I see <lb/>the I.T. is at it again — so am <lb/>glad I wrote &amp; hope others <lb/>will — Tell me how they <lb/>feel. How have you got on <lb/>in work — &amp; have you done <lb/>any for Lord Monteagle? — <lb/>&amp; I was much interested <lb/>in the Storkleys &amp; Glengarriff <lb/> was <seg type="unclear">Tiny</seg> there? First <lb/>she would come to us on <lb/>her way over — I've not seen her <lb/>for so long — we spent <lb/>yesterday at North Stoke — <lb/>lunched in the <seg type="unclear">Gibbs</seg> &amp; <sic>tead</sic> with <seg type="unclear">groups</seg>, an awfully <lb/>nice village &amp; church tho' <lb/> <hi rend="underline">not</hi> up to the lovely little <lb/>church here. where the monument is dated 1300, or rather towards <lb/>the end of that century &amp; <lb/>is a beautifully proportioned <lb/>building with rich carvings <lb/>all over it — 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2069_img_152_3"/>
             I am writing to T.P. Gill today <lb/>&amp; say that I have asked you <lb/>to send on E Carpenters letter. <lb/><hi rend="underline">So do.</hi> It is very good to <lb/>circulate it. &amp; it will please <lb/>T.P. to hear from you &amp; make <lb/>him remember his promises <lb/>re. her work — If you think the <lb/>other worth send it too — I think <lb/>the Storkleys <sic>wd</sic> like E.C.'s I am <lb/>sure he <sic>wd</sic> say more but hardly <lb/>does in present war feelings <lb/>over here. I made E &amp; H read it as <lb/>they are pretty uncompromising  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>