<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4295">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Edward Carson,  25 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Wilfrid Spender (1876-1960) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4295</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-25</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4295_img_3658_1"  type="Letter"  url="e6bc7c27347815c5696db606748f8009.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4295_img_3658_2"  type="Letter"  url="54c1190660cfc0e4bcc57c3f48f11108.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4295_img_3658_1"/>
             You have no doubt <lb/>heard that many <lb/>of our reserves have <lb/>gone to other Units <lb/>&amp; that the 5th <lb/>RIR - a well <lb/>Known Orange <lb/>lodge! - is to <lb/>act as drafter <lb/>for the Nationalist Brigade!  <lb/>Please do not answer.   <hi rend="underline">Spender</hi> <lb/>Redmond's speech <lb/>in the trenches   25 Nov 1915   Dear Sir Edward   I am moved to write by Redmond's latest <lb/>&amp; not least wicked speech. I will deal only with that part of it <lb/>in which he refers to the Dubliners &amp; the Ulster Division fighting side <lb/>by side. If anything could be more likely to stir up trouble between <lb/>them than a speech like that I should  not  like to discover it. I hear <lb/>the 107th Bde at the front has done very well &amp; like good soldiers they <lb/>can carry along very well with those S Irishmen - none too many- <lb/>who have <seg type="del">tht</seg>had the pluck to fight. If however, this fine toleration <lb/>is to be used to their detriment it is asking a little too much.   We have in the place of the 107th Bde <seg type="del">3</seg> 4  battalions of which 3 are <lb/>largely Lancashire Irishmen. I have had to use all the influence I have <lb/>with our lads to prevent a row, &amp; there will I think be one "now" or <lb/>at Xmas, &amp; I'm not altogether inclined to prevent it. The worst <lb/>of it is, that some of the big Generals are already talking of the <lb/>success of the experiment &amp; the solution of the Irish question-this <lb/>was mentioned in quite good faith at a Divisional Commanders' <lb/>Conference!    When a General says that the Ulster rebels took the appointment <lb/>of 3 successive R C Staff officers to their Dir' Staff like a child to <lb/>sweets, I feel inclined to let myself go. I am sure none of these 3 <lb/>officers are in any conspiracy - they are all good chaps- I am <lb/>now not equally certain of those  officers  who made the appointments.    i do not know whether you could take some steps to take <lb/>the wind out of the nationalist sails &amp; at the same time inspire <lb/>our men, by writing to the papers saying that you know the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4295_img_3658_2"/>
            <lb/>Ulstermen will continue to <lb/>show the utmost toleration to their Nationalist comrades who have <lb/>proud themselves worthy sons of the Empire by joining the colours, <lb/>&amp;that they need not fear that the Country will take a false view <lb/>of their attitude in this respect. If this is made clear one would <lb/>of course do all one could to prevent trouble, but otherwise I think <lb/>an eyeopener for us silly Englishmen may do good.   The 107th Bde has done so well-so I hear- &amp; our regular <lb/>brigade have not proved so wonderful an example, that I think Gen' <lb/>Nugent is now anxious to get them back at the end of their 2 months <lb/>away. I hope they  -the Brigade-  won't try to prevent it as they were very sore when <lb/>they left.   General Hacket Pain is still with us but expects to leave any <lb/>day, &amp; I sincerely hope one of our own COs may succeed him, as it is <lb/>very disheartening for a first class man like Hessey to see a youngster <lb/>brought in from outside over his head. Unluckily Gen' Nugent does not <lb/>think Irishmen are good in command of their own countrymen, but <lb/>prefers a mixture I think.   I have seen several reports on our battalions attached to the  Divisions at the  <lb/>front, &amp; in all cases except the 107 Bde- which has since retrieved itself- <lb/>they have been of the <hi rend="underline">most</hi> favourable character.   Our former Artillery are now coming out to join us &amp; we <lb/>are now in the new corps at any rate for the time. We still <lb/>get a turn at the trenches &amp; I hope to get up again next week.   I wish to Heavens you would boot out the whole Govern- <lb/>ment- the Censor may not like this officially!- &amp; take charge. <lb/>The gunrunning would not be 1 year later if it had been under you.  <lb/>Believe me  Yours sincerely   Wilfrid. B. Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>