<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1014">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward J. Birmingham to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 26 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward J Birmingham</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward J. Birmingham to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877 - 1946). Birmingham writes to thank Skeffington to confirm plans for a get together, though says if she is truly suffering she can meet with him earlier.Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47, MS 33,604/16-26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1014</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0342">Edward J Birmingham</persName>
              <date>1916-02-26T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0338">32 Harocurt Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1014_img_2868_1"  type="Letter"  url="7ad59e858f80871609ed1a642818a695.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1014_img_2868_1"/>
                32, Harcourt Street  Dublin    Feb 26 1916   Dear Mrs Sheehy Skeffington   Thanks very much for the £2 <lb/>received. Thursday <seg type="del">Feb</seg> (March 2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>) <lb/>at 4.00 PM will be suitable to me <lb/>if convenient for you.   Of course, if you are suffering <lb/>pain, come at once.  <seg type="closer"> Yours Faithfully  Edward J. Birmingham </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>