<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2934">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 19 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1916 served at Advanced General Headquarters, his duties mainly involving the writing of reports for the cabinet, for the Press, and for posterity. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.

In this letter, Spender discusses Lillian&#39;s imminent move to a new house, and the problem of what is to be done with her maids, Maggie and Sarah. He alludes to his and Lillian&#39;s pet-names for each other, &#39;Pink Rabbit&#39; and &#39;Brown Wolf&#39;. He recounts a recent trip to a Division which has achieved great success in the fighting, and confesses that this experience at the front has proven that much of the report he is writing is &#39;out&#39;. Spender briefly discusses his toothache, his diet, the wet weather, and a budget he has attached. Spender emphasises his pride in the work Lillian is doing with the Comforts Fund, stating that &#39;it probably means more to the men and to the Division than we ever imagine&#39;. He finishes with an anecdote about a much-edited communique.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/391</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2934</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2934_img_2341_1"  type="NULL"  url="04b64f4de501115982bee6b6e5f5cdaa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2934_img_2341_2"  type="NULL"  url="0f561eb2f4c2935f11748c247f8d9264.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2934_img_2341_3"  type="NULL"  url="b09686fe613128267ab4e21f6aa49316.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2934_img_2341_4"  type="NULL"  url="2b046b0486d0a380467d24e994cfdd4d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2934_img_2341_5"  type="NULL"  url="8ad13a4fc0d0ea0d1a062d1961330199.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2934_img_2341_6"  type="NULL"  url="a6e04de946b405593d7dd8b3f3daacdc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2934_img_2341_1"/>
             1   Aug. 19.   D1633/1/1/391  You are evidently needing a holiday pretty badly<lb/>old thing &amp; I am much concerned. It seems doubtful<lb/>if you ought to put it off till you move and I'm<lb/>afraid the bother of moving &amp; house hunting will<lb/>also upset the <sic>pr</sic> <sic>tho</sic> she could of course use<lb/>24 as a temporary home. If it were not for Mater's<lb/>deafness it really might have done for you with the<lb/>study as your room, but I expect your are better<lb/>alone after your experiment. As to the maids<lb/>cannot you make a special case &amp; keep them on<lb/>after the month especially as <seg type="del">  </seg> the cause of<lb/>the bother will then have ended — <seg type="unclear">the</seg> 2 masters —<lb/>Perhaps I could be brought in as a special reason for<lb/>any apparent weakness. I really feel inclined to plead<lb/>for them as I believe they are fond of you and would 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2934_img_2341_2"/>
            be prepared to go to the country later. However you<lb/>will be able to settle this better yourself tho ' I hate<lb/>one lapse causing a complete estrangement especially<lb/>in this hot weather. If you decide this couldn't<lb/>Sarah be sent on a holiday for 10 days. I believe<lb/>Maggie could do all the work &amp; perhaps be the better<lb/>for it - <sic>tho'</sic> it sounds like rewarding the naughty— I really am concerned old thing and it is no good<lb/>going on with your work just too long, &amp; isn't<lb/>fair on your work either in the end.  You end your letter the <sic>pr's</sic> <sic>bw</sic>! At<lb/>other times I should treat this as part playfulness<lb/>to be treated with surprised &amp; dignified growls, but<lb/>I rather wonder if it is not a tired little <sic>pr</sic>. If she<lb/>is winning the <sic>b w's</sic> sympathy under false pretences<lb/>in this there will be some distinct pink  bw  paw<lb/>marks later! I do not know if Bagley <seg type="unclear">wood</seg><lb/>with one of the sisters in <seg type="unclear">town</seg> or the seaside<lb/>would be best but expect you will not at first  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2934_img_2341_3"/>
             2 D1633/1/1/391   Aug. 19   feel fit enough for children and romps<lb/>which you would get at <seg type="unclear">Crowborough</seg> or<lb/>Rugby <sic>tho'</sic> this might be all right later.  I had a pleasant outing yesterday to<lb/>the —<hi rend="superscript"> the  </hi>Division which has done very<lb/>well in the war. The GSO is an<lb/>old SC friend and I went to get local<lb/>colour, but got something more for I<lb/>found that much that I have written<lb/>is hopelessly out &amp; that this ice is<lb/>very thin indeed - much too thin for<lb/>a <sic>b w</sic> to walk over without a <sic>pr</sic> in 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2934_img_2341_4"/>
            front as a guide. I think I am bound<lb/>to go in &amp; to find the water under the<lb/>ice distinctly hot (!) but it won't be the<lb/>first time the <sic>bw</sic> has been in hot<lb/>water. He never was good at skating. Toothache quite gone tho' rather<lb/>unexpectedly &amp; I slept well last night<lb/><sic>tho'</sic> very late indeed ! Perhaps it suits<lb/>me after my big dinner: I have<lb/>cut <seg type="del">down</seg>  out  my butter at dinner &amp;<lb/>think I shall have to cut one course<lb/>too if I don't find I keep fit. Poor<lb/>greedy <sic>bw</sic>.  A letter from C   really rather  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2934_img_2341_5"/>
             a nuisance as I know I answered his,<lb/>but I suppose  as  it is kindness of heart<lb/>I ought to be glad.  Wet weather today when we<lb/>especially did not want it here, &amp; I<lb/>did not want it for you as I hoped<lb/>you would get a beautiful garden<lb/><seg type="unclear">large</seg>. Perhaps you may tomorrow.  This is a fairly thick budget<lb/>for you <sic>tho'</sic> I cannot pretend there<lb/>is much in it except a good deal of<lb/>love for the <sic>bw's</sic> <sic>pr</sic>!<lb/><lb/> from the <sic>bw</sic> <lb/> WB Spender<lb/>P.T.O  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2934_img_2341_6"/>
             If I don't enthuse about your <lb/>work you know that I am very proud of <lb/>what my <sic>pr</sic> is doing. I think it probably <lb/>means more to the men and to the Division <lb/>that even we imagine, and I am quite <lb/>sure <seg type="unclear">Sredward</seg> and the Ulster people &amp; the <lb/>cause will owe a lot to you for prevent— <lb/>ing the divisions and soreness that would <lb/>be bound to come if the thing was <lb/>mismanaged, or not done at all.  <!-- Following written in 2 columns. Left hand column. -->  I hear the Daily Mail <lb/>of <seg type="del">Wed</seg> Thursday or Friday <lb/>or Saturday last week <lb/>backed up the Division <lb/>Did you see it  <!-- 2nd column, right hand side. -->  I had an amusing experience <lb/>today —After writing my <seg type="unclear">communication</seg> <lb/>I showed it to Gen C who said it is too <lb/>cold in tone &amp; added a flamboyant first <lb/>para &amp; made some amendments as <lb/>I also did. I missed Gen' B, so <lb/>sent it up to the Chateau where <lb/>the CGS got it &amp; proceeded to demolish <lb/>it. He sent for me &amp; he complained <lb/>that it was much too Daily Maily 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>