<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5113">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Amy to May Daly, 15 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Amy </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives </repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/5/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5113</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0822">Amy </persName>
              <date>1923-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0872">Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">May Daly   </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5113_img_None_1"  url="faeeb232e859b25c1eac090726b1672a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5113_img_None_2"  url="1146f19190ca1ab85f30daa98fb6d8e0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5113_img_0_1"/>
              P41/5/5    Cork    15 March, 23    <seg type="foreign">May a <seg type="unclear">cara</seg> </seg>   I can hardly find words to express<lb/>my sympathy to you all in your great<lb/>sorrow. Sean came up this morning and asked<lb/>me if I had seen the paper which i hadn't,<lb/>and when he told me I got quite foolish. I<lb/>couldn't understand what he was saying<lb/>for a while. Oh May. it's terrible but Cha<lb/>died as he lived to God and Ireland true<lb/>and he must have gone straight to Heaven.<lb/>May God strengthen ye to bear your trouble,<lb/>and give your poor Mother comfort.  When I received your letter I<lb/>was very hopefull from what you told me,<lb/>and the <sic>negociations</sic> that the executions<lb/>were at an end and sure twas way too<lb/>soon I realized how mistaken I was. All<lb/>the people in Cork that know Cha, <seg type="del">and</seg> are<lb/>horrified. Don't greive too much May, although<lb/>I know how you worshipped him, sure we'll<lb/>all meet again, and he wouldn't change<lb/>places with us now hes far too <seg type="del">f</seg> happy.  Sean and I are getting a 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5113_img_0_2"/>
             mass offered up for him though God<lb/>knows he doesn't need any he was too<lb/>good, May.  Mrs Vaughan took it very much to<lb/>heart and so did the boys and Sean<lb/>came in crying this morning.  Mother &amp; Nellie send their<lb/>deepest sympathy also to you and all<lb/>home.  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">Is mise te grad mor</seg></seg>  Amy.  P.S.  Monica was gone when we got the<lb/>news but they saw the papers. a.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>