<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5226">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charlie Daly to Kate Allman, 21 November 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charlie Daly </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/10/1/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5226</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0548">Charlie Daly </persName>
              <date>1922-11-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1693">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Tirconail, Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1484">Kate Allman </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2063">Providence Convent, Wood Green, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1923</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5226_img_None_1"  url="347b4bf5f58da803270f2634de698cca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5226_img_None_2"  url="4663c136452f0b52213c23351daf60dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5226_img_None_3"  url="b9964d4d913fc72ebac7fe9e61e73e87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5226_img_None_4"  url="a0827e6d11be0b2f41d8cb413f884fa9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5226_img_0_1"/>
              21st Nov 22    Miss K Allman<lb/>Providence Convent<lb/>Wood Green<lb/>London  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5226_img_0_2"/>
             P41/10/1/7   Dromboe Castle<lb/>Stranorlar<lb/>Tirconaill    21st Nov 22    A Chara   Though I'm not quite certain of your<lb/>new address (you ommitted letting me have it)<lb/>still I'm chancing this note in the hope that it<lb/>will reach you alright. I know that you<lb/>must be anxious to know if I got your<lb/>letters. I'm glad to be able to tell you that<lb/>they have <hi rend="underline">all</hi> reached me safely. Twas only<lb/>this morning that I received that you wrote on<lb/>the 6th inst &amp; the other written on the eve<lb/>of your departure from London. Rather a<lb/>coincidence! wasn't it that I should<lb/>get them on the same day as you entered<lb/>the convent? I also got the books<lb/>&amp; accompanying note as well as your<lb/>reply to my first letter written from here,<lb/>only on Thursday last or else I would<lb/>have acknowledged them before you<lb/>left London. As you know all letters &amp; 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5226_img_0_3"/>
             2  parcels to us were held on account of our<lb/>refusal to work, but seeing that their<lb/>treatment of us hadn't the desired effect<lb/>they gave it up and so on Thursday we<lb/>got back to our Status quo &amp; got what-<lb/>ever parcels &amp; letters were due to us (An<lb/>other victory for the Reps!) when you<lb/>informed me that you had written on the<lb/>6th to the add. which I gave you I was<lb/>very much afraid lest it should get lost<lb/>on account of my being arrested in the<lb/>meanwhile so you can guess how glad<lb/>I was when it turned up this morning I<lb/>was quite pleased with its contents &amp; with<lb/>all the home news which it contained.<lb/>The Censor here hadn't the satisfaction of seeing<lb/>it or perhaps I wouldn't have got it at<lb/>all &amp; that would indeed be a great<lb/>pity. I should regret to have missed it for<lb/>there was lots of news which I was anxiously<lb/>awaiting. It will be a loss to me in future<lb/>that I wont be any longer able to get 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5226_img_0_4"/>
             4<lb/>way uneasy for the future. Should I by any<lb/>chance ever find myself in the same position as<lb/>any of the four chaps my only anxiety would<lb/>be I get the Sacraments before going. A matter like<lb/>that should make anybody anxious and you<lb/>know the present attitude of the priests. Pray for<lb/>me Katty, that no matter when I die or how<lb/>that it shall have the grace of a happy death,<lb/>thats all that really matters in the end. As<lb/>I informed you already I havent forgotten to<lb/>say that little prayer for you. Indeed I have<lb/>lots of time for that at present. I am quite<lb/>certain that you will be quite content in<lb/>your new life, my most sincere wish &amp; prayer<lb/>is that you will. I must now wind up I<lb/>would not have written so much but I may<lb/>not easily get another chance of writing in this<lb/>way. You see like the last one I <sic></sic>sending it<lb/>without the knowledge of my keepers or their<lb/>Censor. I dont know how long we shall be<lb/>here, but we are having a good enough<lb/>time now. I hope that I shall hear from you 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>