<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5667">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Kilmainham, to the Chief Crown Solicitor, 10 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A colonel</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the Area Administrative Superintendent of the Royal Hospital Dublin to the Chief Crown Solicitor of Ireland, Malchy Kelly (1850-1916). The letter concerns the injury of Patrick Sheehan (1879-?), a cork labourer who dislocated his ankle while carrying sacks while working. The letter states that the accident happened during Sheehan&#39;s ordinary course of duties.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3785</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5667</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1352">A colonel</persName>
              <date>1916-03-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0704">Royal Hospital Kilmainham, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1023">Malachy J. Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5667_img_760_1"  type="Letter"  url="b302cf10d7fa8734d456f04627d315d2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5667_img_760_1"/>
            <lb/>Ref. No. 92/ <lb/><hi rend="underline">Subject. Injury to Patrick Sheehan</hi>  A.A.O., Ireland <lb/>Royal Hospital, <lb/>Dublin.   10th. March, 1916.   The Chief Crown Solicitor, <lb/>Dublin.   Sir,   In reply to yours of 8.3.16, with <lb/>reference to Patrick Sheehan. This man’s <lb/>accident occurred in the ordinary course of his <lb/>duties. He was employed by the Forage Dept. <lb/>for casual labour, and in the ordinary way would <lb/>have to handle hay, straw, or oats, as required. <lb/>The bags he was carrying were oat bags.   Yours faithfully,   GM   Colonel, <lb/>ADMINISTRATIVE AREA OFFICER <lb/>G.B./  Solicitor General <lb/>In conjunction with your remit <lb/>18.3.16 <lb/>M. Kelly <lb/>11.3.16   The permit is not free from <lb/>doubt: but I think the <lb/>war depot is liable to pay <lb/>compensation <lb/>EOF <lb/>12.3.16   Administration Area Office <lb/>Please see Solicitor General's opinion above <lb/>M - Kelly <lb/>13.3.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>