<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5801">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn 1 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5801</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-06-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5801_img_902_1"  type="Letter"  url="46602d546b6ade153be870eba5eb4ab0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5801_img_902_2"  type="Letter"  url="309ea7c2c6136c7917becfc7a6b110a6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5801_img_902_1"/>
             Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar  <lb/> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June 1916 <lb/> My dearest James   I got your letter this morn also card to fit ring<lb/>and a paper I think addressed by your Mother we were very<lb/>glad to get it and see Dr Dwyer s letters to Maxwell<lb/>I wonder they got on papers at all that were very good<lb/>We are having awful weather <sic>hear</sic> at present <sic>quiet</sic> cold<lb/>as well as wet I hope <seg type="unclear">they</seg> are trying to <hi rend="underline">spit up</hi> all the<lb/>bad weather before we go off  Christy is gone to M. Gar to day &amp; will take home<lb/>all my dress etc neatly, so they wont be late at that<lb/>rate. Mrs.   was called over to Balrath last night<lb/>the boy there was at deaths door with drink but is slowly<lb/>recovering Mrs Kiernan had got word from Gertie Duffy<lb/>saying if she went to Dublin with her to see the Doctor<lb/>she would pay her expenses for one day I believe she is<lb/>very delicate (Gertie) but does not think it, like every one<lb/>of her said <sic>complant</sic> people all pity John the take in<lb/>he got but I think one is as much to be pitied as the other<lb/>I am returning the ring card Size <hi rend="underline">T</hi> is my size.<lb/>About your present I will look at somethings in  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5801_img_902_2"/>
             Mullingar if I dont get something I think you would<lb/>like I will wait till we go to Cork wont that be<lb/>all right—  Well Christy has not gone to Mulingar at all<lb/>there were arrangements made to drive the filly<lb/>&amp; Mrs S— pressed her <hi rend="underline">car</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">son</hi> also when Christy<lb/>went down he asked the loan of the <hi rend="underline">bit</hi> from <hi rend="underline">Tom</hi><lb/>he got it and threw it on the ground to him<lb/>&amp; <seg type="unclear">they</seg> were all giving him short answers he that<lb/>so seldom goes near them so he did not go, with the<lb/>going on they had he'd be late for Mass there.<lb/>The whole cause of the general bad humour was a letter<lb/>Johnnie had got saying that firm was not going<lb/>to be opened <seg type="del">at all</seg>  for the present  &amp; they therefore did not require<lb/>him — it was hard of course after such a long<lb/>wait for both parties. but I cant understand them<lb/>showing temper to Christy that would give them the<lb/>house from over his head.  I am sure tho' like ourselves she will be disappointed<lb/>for Johnnies job.  I have more news now dearest James. I hope you<lb/>will get to make out this, I would not be half as mad as if it were<lb/>to myself it was done because I have the <hi rend="underline">gift</hi> of the <hi rend="underline">gab</hi><lb/> Warmest love from your loving<lb/>May <lb/> <lb/><hi rend="underline">  </hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>