<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6727">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Michael O'Flanagan to Bishop Michael Fogarty, Bishop of Killaloe, 22 October 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr Michael O&#39;Flanagan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Bishop Michael Fogarty survived an assassination attempt by the Black and Tans during the War of Independence in response to his outspoken opposition to partition and conscription. O&#39;Flanagan indicates having sent a copy of his own letter to TP Gilmartin, Archbishop of Tuam, to Dr Fogarty. He indicates being hopeful that Gilmartin may be able to help him achieve some level of reconciliation with his own Bishop and goes on  to suggest this will be necessary for him to have before the Ard Fheis.  He refers to his own history with Fogarty of them uniting to oppose Conscription and suggests that they once again need to shown a united front.  O&#39;Flanagan goes on to express frustration with John Dillon, leader of the IPP (Irish Parliamentary Party).  O&#39;Flanagan also speaks of getting co-operation from Bishops in the north of Ireland in an effort to get complete international recognition for Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O&#39;Flanagan Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6727</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0313">Fr Michael O&#39;Flanagan</persName>
              <date>1918-10-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1163">6 Harcourt Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Bishop Michael Fogarty of Killaloe</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1942</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6727_img_None_1"  url="phpsEEwwc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6727_img_None_2"  url="phpkRP7TK.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6727_img_0_1"/>
              6 Harcourt Street<lb/>Dublin    This letter was<lb/>composed but not<lb/>sent MOF<lb/>for <seg type="unclear">?</seg>    My dear Lord Bishop,   I take the liberty of sending you a copy<lb/>of a letter which I have recently sent to the Archbishop of Tuam.<lb/>Resolutions about me have been sent up from a number of clubs, and<lb/>it will be difficult to prevent them from being made a subjet of<lb/>discussion by the Ard Fheis unless some sort of reconciliation<lb/>between Dr. Coyne and myself can be effected in the meantime. I<lb/>have received a reply from Dr Gilmartin in which he says that he<lb/>will do his best to bring this about and I have every hope that he<lb/>will be sucessful.  My principal object in writing to you is about another<lb/>matter: The clear distinction made by President Wilson between<lb/>autonomy and self determination, especially in the case of the<lb/>Jugo-Slava-who are not recognised as belligerents, seems to me<lb/>to give Ireland a unique opportunity. If we could now show the<lb/>same united front that we did in opposing Conscription in asserting<lb/>publicly before the world that the people of Ireland deserve as<lb/>much consideration as the Jugo-Slavs it is difficult to see how<lb/>we could be frustrated. John Dillon is the great oracle. Once<lb/>before he made a great personal sacrifice in the cause of Ireland<lb/>united when he stood aside in favour of Redmond. The recent<lb/>tone of the Freeman, as well as some statements recently made 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6727_img_0_2"/>
             -2-  by John Dollon himself in private conversation with people who<lb/>are in touch with us, give me to understand that he now feels<lb/>the dire straits into which his Party has fallen, and that he<lb/>might be willing to consider a reunion of all Ireland on the<lb/>basis of full and unconditional self determination. If this<lb/>could be done the difficulty of the Northern Bishops which you<lb/>spoke about in the Gresham Hotel would be obviated. Would there<lb/>be any possibioity of getting Dr. O'Donnell to bring pressure to<lb/>bear upon DIllon in this direction? Some of the other Northern<lb/>Bishops who are most favourably disposed towards Sinn Fein, such<lb/>as Dr. McKenna or the Bishop of Derry, might be able to influence<lb/>Dr O'Donnell. There are strong reasons which I cannot fully<lb/>explain in this letter that urge me to write to you and see if<lb/>you could do something to carry out what I have suggested. It may<lb/>be the first step in carrying out a plan for avoiding the<lb/>disedifying spectacle of a hotly contested General Election at a<lb/>time when all force ought to be concentrated upon one united<lb/>effort to get complete international recogntion for our Nation.  Assuring you of my sincere sentiments of gratitude and<lb/>esteem I remain, My Lord Bishop,   Your obedient servant,  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>