<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2186">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to the Chief Secretary of Ireland, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was addressed to the chief secretary of Ireland. At this time there is no official chief secretary for Ireland following the resignation of Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) on 3 May 1916. Birrell&#39;s resignation was a consequence of the 1916 Rising for which he accepted responsibility. His successor, Henry Edward Duke (1855-1939), was not officially appointed until 31 July 1916.
The letter is simply signed by &#39;One Who Knows&#39;. The letter concerns the appointment of magistrates in Ireland over the past decade.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9734</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2186</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Chief Secretary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2186_img_1632_1"  type="Letter"  url="19e75f03ac1e3f7345edf8cc8d77b1aa.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2186_img_1632_1"/>
             The Chief Secretary <lb/>Dublin Castle   Sir   I enclose a cutting from Irish Daily Independent of <lb/>26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May Instant for the purpose of bringing under <lb/>your notice that portion of it which refers to the appointment <lb/>of magistrates in Ireland for the past ten years and <lb/>which are known to the nationalist public as popular appts. <lb/>There is nothing but jobbery and corruption in Connection <lb/>with such appts and there is no reliance to be placed in <lb/>members so appointed as in now quite evident. Major Price <lb/>from practical experience knows the value of such men as <lb/>is shown by his evidence. It is not a fact that there <lb/>are a great many Ex District Inspectors of the RIC and <seg type="unclear">Ex </seg> <lb/>Constables of that <seg type="unclear">Faree</seg> who are fully qualified for the Commission <lb/> of the <seg type="unclear">Beau</seg> on account of their legal knowledge and loyalty <lb/>very few Districts but there are such men residing <lb/>but very few of them <seg type="unclear">JPS</seg>. They are too proEnglish which <lb/>in itself is a disqualification in the eyes of those who have <lb/>the recommendation of such appointments. <seg type="unclear">nt mps</seg>   Yours Respectfully   One who knows 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>