<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3112">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Katie Mooney to her brother Peter Mooney, 31 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Katie Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Katie Mooney (b. 1884)  to her brother Peter (b.1886) with news of the neighbors (commenting on certain neighbours and their wealth), recent events, farm matters, the weather and news of  recent flooding. She asks him if he needs anything and says that she hopes he will have word of when he will get leave. 
While Katie does not write about the war or Irish politics, she does mention that she has not heard heard much about the Irish Volunteers. 

Peter Mooney was born 5 February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne, Co Meath. Orphaned at age 7, he and his sister Katie were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. 

He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This  letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3112</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-01-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1461">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0602">101267 29th Battery, Royal Field Artillery, Ballincollig, Co. Cork, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3112_img_2519_1"  type="Letter"  url="ec547196ae74b597e46a265ec3da7ef7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3112_img_2519_2"  type="Letter"  url="8d0851d7c1e85a12ca34604e3061fd99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3112_img_2519_3"  type="Letter"  url="df3cd17ed822ffa6939106c41285e02b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3112_img_2519_4"  type="Letter"  url="a608610ca74879056b81e0c442a6c7e0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3112_img_2519_1"/>
             Caulstown, <lb/>Dunboyne, <lb/>Co. Meath.   31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>Jan 1916   My Dear Peter,   I received your ever <lb/>welcome letter on Sunday. <lb/>Delighted to see by it that <lb/>you are so well. I trust <lb/>that the next letter you <lb/>write, that you will be able <lb/>to give definite word about <lb/>your leave.   They seem <lb/>to have got very careless <lb/>in the Paddock about <lb/>writing to you. I am going <lb/>down that direction tomorrow
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3112_img_2519_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline">2</hi> Tuesday as I want to get <lb/>some money from your account <lb/>and also the money for Magee. <lb/>I am sending you on a pound <lb/>of Tobacco this evening along <lb/>with the paper.   Everything <lb/>and everyone are going on <lb/>alright both here and in <lb/>Foliestown at least I never <lb/>hear any complaints either <lb/>sides. Mrs Farrell went to <lb/>the Hospital to—day. Jem is <lb/>here helping Paddy and Tommy <lb/>to dip Kiernan's sheep. Joe Farrell <lb/>was home for eight days from <lb/> the front. He is going back <lb/>to night by the 906 boat <lb/>leaving North Wall. He was <lb/> on the borders of Switzerland <lb/>Dee expects leave soon. I think <lb/>he is somewhere in France. <lb/>I don't hear any word about <lb/>the Volunteers these times  <hi rend="underline">3</hi> <lb/>only that the other side have <lb/>some very ugly song made <lb/>up about them. They are trying <lb/> to get the words of it, to write <lb/>it down and then they are <lb/>going to give it to Father Kelly. <lb/>I hear they were beaten by Trim <lb/> in the Hurling match on Sunday <lb/>in Navan. They had a taxi to <lb/>bring them down and back at <lb/>the rate of <seg type="unclear">4/a</seg>man. So times <lb/>mustn't be hard with them. <lb/>I believe <seg type="unclear">bromen</seg> has all the bricks <lb/>drawn for Herbertstown on last <lb/> Friday. It is a blessing that <lb/>some of the heavy loads are <lb/>off the road.   Foliestown side <lb/>is in fact worse than this. <lb/>They had to put planks across <lb/>it to keep it from sinking <lb/>beyond at the long turn <lb/>at Patrick's Hill. They are <lb/>drawing to Pat Ward's House <lb/>now. I hear that it is to be <lb/>on the flat something like <lb/>Balfestown. The men are
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3112_img_2519_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">4</hi> <lb/>digging away for the foundation. <lb/>We were all asked yesterday <lb/>at mass to pray for <seg type="unclear">rich Roths</seg> <lb/>recovery or happy death. I believe <lb/>he is on the last. Poor fellow. <lb/>I heard also that the brother <lb/>Paddy is not much better <lb/> The Doctor ordered him to stay <lb/>in bed. Paddy   is gone <lb/>to hospital since last Tuesday. <lb/>There were a lot of   <lb/>on Sunday. They do have great <lb/>sport with old Paddy and Biddy <lb/>McDonagh. I never saw John <lb/>Younell this mouth or more. He <lb/>must be under cover in the cold <lb/>weather.   I will now say a <lb/>fond good bye to you with <lb/>best love from all here.   May God bless &amp; protect you <lb/>Is the sincere prayer of your <lb/>fond Aunt &amp; Sister.    P.S. I may be in town either on <lb/> Thursday or Friday. If you are <lb/> in need write for Thursday <lb/>Katie. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3112_img_2519_4"/>
             Driver Peter Mooney <lb/>101267. 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Battery <lb/>R.T.A. Ballincollig <lb/><hi rend="underline">Co Cork</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>