<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1056">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Ashcroft to Samuel Cleland &amp; Clara Davidson, 3 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Worsley Ashcroft</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Worsley Ashcroft (1879-1918) to Samuel Cleland (1846-1921) and Clara Davidson regarding the death of their son, Captain James Davidson (1877-1916). Ashcroft informs the Davidsons how their son died at the front and expresses his sincerest sympathy for their lost. He mentions how greatly James was admired by his company and writes that, although the 36th (Ulster) Division has done grandly, it has come at a heavy cost. Initially commissioned with the 13th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles in 1915, Lieutenant William Ashcroft landed in France in October 1915. He was promoted to the rank of Major with the Machine Gun Corps before he was killed in action on 11 April 1918. Sir Samuel Cleland Davidson was an Irish inventor and founder of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast. During the First World War the Sirocco Engineering Works manufactured and exported equipment for cooling, drying, dust collecting, heating, ventilating, pneumatic conveyance for the Royal and Merchant Navy.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Papers, D3642-A-2-5-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1056</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1059">William Worsley Ashcroft</persName>
              <date>1916-07-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1149">Samuel Cleland Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1056_img_3147_1"  type="Letter"  url="9c72331c5ee3c924507cd490fe59b5a7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1056_img_3147_1"/>
              COPY    108th Brigade, Machine Gun Company  B.E.F.    3rd July, 1916.   My dear Mr &amp; Mrs Davidson:-   By the time you get this(which is scribbled <lb/>on all I can find in a moving Camp) you will, I hope and yet more <lb/>than sincerely regret, have received an official notice of your <lb/>son's death.  All I can tell you in consolation is that no <lb/>man in this terrible War could have done his duty better, or died <lb/>a finer death.  Mr Davidson may remember me; at all events I <lb/>remember seeing him at Bordon,and I shall never forget looking back <lb/>as we left the Review the day the King was down,and seeing the <lb/>solitary figure looking back at the 13th R. I. R., and the 108th <lb/>Brigade in particular. I know he said to himself ' if he goes <lb/>' he goes for the Nation's good,and he has gone, but if ever a <lb/>man as a civilian soldier founded a Company, ran it as a unit, did <lb/>his duty as a Senior Officer,and gained the respect of all ranks, <lb/>and died like a man and a soldier, Jim did.  When things went badly,and he no doubt felt his <lb/>obvious duty was to take up reinforcements, off he went,and for a <lb/>long time he held up more or less single handed a dangerous position; <lb/>although shot through the knee,he refused to be carried back; alter- <lb/>nately he fired his Gun, and threw bombs until he had to retire to <lb/>bind up his wound; he returned, and did what he could ,and finally he <lb/>started back to try and find reinforcements. He was shortly after <lb/>shot through the head.  I wish I could tell you what I thought of him in <lb/>adequate words,and also what the Company thought of him,and I know <lb/>also what the higher authorities he came in contact with thought. <lb/>You knew him better than all of us,and you can imagine a little of <lb/>what a tower of strength he was.  It was through him that I came to the 13th at <lb/>Clandeboye,and with he, and Dermot Neill gone from this Company, <lb/>and nearly all my good and best friends in the 13th gone also,I <lb/>feel very lonely and sad,but it is all in a good cause,and there's <lb/>no good any of us making the worst of it. I hope I will come across <lb/>you some day,and that you will be given help to bear your terrible <lb/>burden.  Rely upon it,his body will be respectfully buried,and <lb/>please write me if there is any help or information I can give you. <seg type="closer"> Believe me yours in sincerest sympathy and deepest <lb/>regret,  W. Worsley Ashcroft. </seg> P.S. The Ulster Division has done grandly, but has had to pay a very heavy penalty. <lb/>W.W.A.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>