<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0998">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Florence Doey to Margaret McCoubrey, 23 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Florence Doey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Florence Doey writes to inform Margaret McCoubry (1880-1956) that she cannot attend an Irish Women&#39;s Franchise League committee meeting regarding Hanna Sheehy Skeffington&#39;s lecture on America due to a prior engagement. Doey is not in favour of the lecture, and finds the subject inappropriate considering the violent goings-on in Ireland. Margaret McCoubrey was a suffragette, pacifist and Labour activist. She was committed to helping women, children and the working class with local, national and international causes.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47, MS 33,604/15-13</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/998</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0962">Florence Doey</persName>
              <date>1916-01-23T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0371">72 Kansas Avenue, Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0264">Margaret McCoubrey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0998_img_2845_1"  type="Letter"  url="9df4ae749ac64d58d86bc71788e7f3b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0998_img_2845_2"  type="Letter"  url="8f1b1f6fa204c32ac93c2a181e760489.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0998_img_2845_3"  type="Letter"  url="a69c4913603dcdd05f2b920d66eca41d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0998_img_2845_4"  type="Letter"  url="8d258d15ac6e447d3dfda4951485229c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0998_img_2845_1"/>
                72 Kansas Ave  Belfast    23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Jan '16   Dear Mrs M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Coubrey   I had <lb/>your note &amp; am sorry I <lb/>cannot attend Committee <lb/>meeting as I am engaged <lb/>at that time.  You mentioned that <lb/>it is to discuss a proposition <lb/>that a meeting be held  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0998_img_2845_2"/>
              for Mr Sheehy—Skeffington's <lb/>lecture on America. Do <lb/>you think it would be <lb/>wise to attempt such a <lb/>thing at this time? It <lb/>seems to me that while <lb/>our country is engaged <lb/>in such a struggle, with <lb/>such great issues at stake, <lb/>a meeting of that nature <lb/>would be entirely frivolous <lb/>and out of place. One has <lb/>only to lift the news—paper <lb/>to read of friends &amp; acquaint— <lb/>ances either wounded or  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0998_img_2845_3"/>
              killed, and if we cannot go <lb/>into the trenches &amp; fight, we <lb/>can at least do everything <lb/>in our power to help, and <lb/>not waste time bothering <lb/>over things that do not matter.  Besides, the subject is <lb/>rather <sic>hacknayed</sic> to be <lb/>attractive, &amp; the Americans <lb/>haven't made themselves <lb/>too popular here of late.  In any case, there would <lb/>be plenty of time for lectur— <lb/>ing when the war is over— if <lb/>we're still here then.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0998_img_2845_4"/>
              Of course these are only <lb/>my own ideas, I am sorry <lb/>I can't be there to hear what <lb/>decision is arrived at, but <lb/>perhaps I will hear later.  <seg type="del">Mamma sends her love <lb/>&amp; regards &amp; hopes you managed <lb/>to get your valise that day <lb/>I hope so too.</seg> <seg type="closer"> Very sincerely yrs  Florence Dory. </seg> <seg type="del">P.S. If you would let me know <lb/>how much I am in your debt for <lb/>the papers, I would like to get it <lb/>squared at once, please tell me soon.</seg><lb/>F.D.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>