<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5725">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 18 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Marie opens this letter to her mother by saying how little time she has had to write due to the fact that the hospital is so understaffed.  She is clearly finding the work very hard and she refers to a patient of hers who had earlier died from dysentery and another who is very ill and she had written to his mother in Canada.  She also tells her mother trivial things such as how most of the patients on the blue ward wear blue pyjamas.  She takes a break from writing the letter and finishes on the 22nd November when she writes that her friend, Mr Boase, is returning to England and he will post the letter from there.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Malta Letters</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5725</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1540">Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_1"  type="Letter"  url="ecb0bc995fbf72517ed5ed51b3616799.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_2"  type="Letter"  url="29abb99a2dc6c85d3edb769b7eb7fdf2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_3"  type="Letter"  url="cd28c995e1e81fc483a7140dfc249cae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_4"  type="Letter"  url="f32cd615b20677bb9fa051cb3ebde486.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_5"  type="Letter"  url="c891d77283df0f3f52badc3538cd2964.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_6"  type="Letter"  url="22d6818045a051928e581d39aedd380f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_7"  type="Letter"  url="86f107878e9f4aa0a398f6b84d0076d4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_8"  type="Letter"  url="ab332ec8427d9d2b673c280909a10de2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_9"  type="Letter"  url="1d52d4bff3d939c9e1817e170667abeb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5725_img_826_10"  type="Letter"  url="25d6dc52ad8f5b7935cc092bb66d8a64.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_1"/>
             18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <hi rend="underline">November 1915</hi>   My Dearest Mother,   It seems ages since I have <lb/>had time to write you a long letter <lb/>not since the day I wrote when <lb/>I had my days rest in bed, I <lb/>am glad to be able to say I <lb/>have felt A.1 ever since that day <lb/>&amp; it is just as well as we have <lb/>been terrible busy infact one <lb/>day this week we were not <lb/>able to get off at all, a convoy <lb/>came in with very bad cases &amp; we <lb/>were frightfully under staffed so there <lb/>was nothing for it, it was really <lb/>more satisfactory as it gave both <lb/>the patient &amp; ourselves a better <lb/>chance &amp; start as we were able to
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_2"/>
            get them all washed &amp; comfortable <lb/>at the start, poor creatures what <lb/>they do suffer, one who came in on <lb/>Tuesday with Dysentery died this <lb/>morning &amp; I have spent my time <lb/>off this afternoon writing to Canada <lb/>to a mans mother, he is very bad <lb/>but we are hoping with great care <lb/>all may go well, this is where <lb/>the sad part of our work lies <lb/>we are so short handed we are not <lb/>able to give the individual attention <lb/>necessary without neglecting the other <lb/>patients &amp; instead of things getting <lb/>better they are getting worse as <lb/> so many orderlies &amp; V A Ds are <lb/>getting knocked up, our staff is <lb/>2 shorter now as one has gone <lb/>ill &amp; the others had to be taken <lb/>for another block as one of the six <lb/>that came out with me developed
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_3"/>
            S. Fever the other day but am glad <lb/>to say is getting on well &amp; has been <lb/>sent to St Patricks Camp—   Saturday 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I had not time to <lb/>finish this the other day so am <lb/>continuing it to —day, I wish you <lb/>could see me &amp; you would laugh <lb/>I am lying on my little bed <lb/>with hair hanging collar &amp; Apron <lb/><sic>of</sic> &amp; enjoying the rest — very <lb/> much — We are in great delight <lb/>to—day as instead of having 140 <lb/>beds to our Block it has been <lb/> divided &amp; our Staff Sister is <lb/>only responsible for 7 Wards of <lb/>10 she has under her another <lb/>Trained Sister &amp; myself &amp; we have <lb/> five orderlies, so things are looking <lb/>a little brighter all though we
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_4"/>
            could do with more V.A.Ds, until <lb/>today I have had a terrible <lb/>week as all morning I spent in <lb/>Lower E &amp; the afternoon Upper <lb/>We have some frightfully bad <lb/>patients with Dysentery we do <lb/>not seem to be getting so much <lb/>  just now. Well I never <lb/>had time really to tell <lb/>you about my patients the <lb/>whole 71 are very nice but there <lb/>is one ward which we call the <lb/><seg type="unclear">blue</seg> ward they have mostly <lb/>Blue Pajamas which were sent <lb/>over from Ireland to Miss Bates <lb/>the other V.A.D who unfortunate <lb/>has got knocked up she is a <lb/>great admirer of E <seg type="unclear">Carson</seg> <lb/>but an awfully nice girl
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_5"/>
            Well most of the Patients in this <lb/>ward are Gentlemen Tommies &amp; they <lb/>are so nice &amp; never grumble <lb/>about anything although at <lb/>times when we have been so <lb/>busy they have only seen us <lb/>about twice a day No 1 bed <lb/>is a great favorite of mine <lb/> a Mr Boasse so am asking <lb/>him to post this for me in <lb/>England when he goes. I am <lb/>sorry he is leaving us as <lb/>he was really very nice but <lb/>glad he is getting home for <lb/>Xmas. It was so funny to-day <lb/>something happened &amp; his dinner <lb/>never came from the cook house
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_6"/>
            so we were all in distress to know <lb/>what to do so we gave him 2 <lb/>lovely fresh eggs &amp; asked one of <lb/>his pals to go up to Cook House <lb/>&amp; have it cooked, it was just <lb/>my dinner time so had to go <lb/>off duty but ran down after <lb/>to see if he was alright before <lb/>I came off duty for afternoon <lb/>to find eggs still beside his <lb/>bed &amp; could not get them <lb/>cooked anywhere down there <lb/>so had to bring them up <lb/> to my room &amp; do them there — <lb/>which is 3 or 4 mins walk away — <lb/> however it was better than leaving him without <lb/> - I have another who is very bad &amp; <lb/> asked me to write to his mother
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_7"/>
            which I did yesterday poor creature <lb/>he has been very ill for 4 weeks <lb/>&amp; yesterday seemed very bad <lb/>indeed, he has lost so much blood <lb/>&amp; they all said if they could <lb/>only get Burgundy or something <lb/>for him he might do, I was <lb/>off for a couple of hours last <lb/>night so went into Valetta <lb/>&amp; bought some. I am glad <lb/>to say he is a little better <lb/>they say. I have not seen <lb/>him on account of being in <lb/> Upper E altogether today. It is <lb/>a terrible place for money every <lb/>thing is so scarce for patients <lb/>&amp; when one realizes a little <lb/>extra thing may save a mans
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_8"/>
            life one never <seg type="unclear">things</seg>but I shall <lb/>have to close my heart unless <lb/>you can get up the little <lb/>collection I spoke of it is <lb/>the greatest charity possible <lb/>as otherwise it is impossible <lb/>for us ever to get them any <lb/>thing extra &amp; things are <lb/>so short I think I shall <lb/>write to ask U Charlie of when <lb/>he is giving his <seg type="unclear">Xmas</seg> charity <lb/>to loan me a £1 even if it <lb/>is only enough to buy them <lb/>chocolate or something for <lb/>Xmas to make a difference <lb/>for the poor creatures.   Monday 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> I had to stop this <lb/>letter the other day so am going to <lb/>finish it to-day with Luck &amp; my
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_9"/>
            friend Mr Boase who is leaving <lb/>for England to-day has said he <lb/>will post it in England for me - <lb/>I am very sorry he is going as <lb/>he is awfully nice, if by any <lb/>chance he should be sent to <lb/>Ireland get the girls to look <lb/>him up &amp; see that he has every <lb/>thing comfortable so that he will <lb/> go away with good impressions <lb/>of Ireland - Must end this <lb/> now as a message has just <lb/>come to say they are off in <lb/>a minute. I have my day <lb/>off to-day so will write a <lb/><seg type="unclear">serious</seg> letter to-day some time <lb/>Hoping this will find you <lb/>all very well
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_5725_img_826_10"/>
            With heaps &amp; heaps of Love   Your most loving<lb/> daughter   Marie 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>