<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0646">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy (Dussie) Duffin to Auntie B, 27 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Dorothy Duffin (b. 1881) to her Aunt. Dorothy&#39;s main news is that her sister Emma (1883–1979) has returned from Alexandria, Egypt, where she served as a VAD, and is currently in London. Dorothy is hoping that she, Olive and Celia will get to see her. She remarks on seeing women employed by the railway and comments that a job as a bus conductor would be &#39;infinitely more attractive than ordinary clerical work&#39;. She describes a trip to St. John&#39;s Gate with her sister, Celia, and they discovered that there is little chance of Celia getting a posting abroad (France), of of Dorothy herself being called up.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/31/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/646</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0232">Ardeevin, Epsom, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Auntie B</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0646_img_2119_1"  type="Letter"  url="3254ea0f682e4fbd33405734a7f83fad.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0646_img_2119_2"  type="Letter"  url="be90e4a52d0114be5c7f0c32848d86da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0646_img_2119_3"  type="Letter"  url="aa19569c6daa3e553e4cd121d2dd312b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0646_img_2119_4"  type="Letter"  url="7a8ada7afbfb94575cab375a3f5a9f8d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0646_img_2119_5"  type="Letter"  url="e0f3946e2f1dd37c9298eff399f724c6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0646_img_2119_1"/>
                March 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi rend="underline">Sunday</hi>    Ardeevin  Epsom   Dearest Auntie B.   Emma has just<lb/> telephoned to say she is at the<lb/> Strand Palace Hotel! I am going<lb/> to meet her <sic>to-morrow</sic> morning &amp; she<lb/> has wired to Olive so I expect she<lb/> will be there too. I hope Celia can<lb/> get off. Such a gathering! I could<lb/> not hear a word she said over the<lb/> telephone <hi rend="underline">except</hi> the address! What<lb/> a lot she will have to tell!  I have been doing all I can to find<lb/> a job &amp; have been to several Bureaux<lb/> Associations etc. Miss <seg type="unclear">Sharok</seg> started<lb/> me with two letters. I was passed<lb/> on to several people who took notes<lb/> about me, but I can't tell if any<lb/> thing may turn up. I am not going<lb/> to take ordinary office work on small<lb/> pay. They tell me private residential work<lb/> is now almost nil. Since the<lb/> War. I sent in a form to the War  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0646_img_2119_2"/>
              Office. It is disappointing about the<lb/> Admiralty. Uncle Edmund says it is <lb/> no use going there without a definite <lb/> letter of introduction to a definite <lb/> man. I wrote to Mrs Arnold-Forster <lb/> about a week ago asking for her <lb/> advice &amp; if she  would  give an introduction <lb/> but have heard nothing from her <lb/> so I am stuck.  Aunt Fanny &amp; Uncle Edmund are as <lb/> kind as possible &amp; I expect to stay <lb/> here <sic>till</sic> April 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> &amp; then go to <lb/> the <seg type="unclear">Donnets</seg> at Eastbourne. After <lb/> that Olive tells me she will be <lb/> 'on the loose' for a fortnight as<lb/> Miss Roberts is closing her house <lb/> to give the household a rest, and <lb/> will not require her. I hope we can <lb/> arrange to join together somehow for <lb/> that fortnight.  Baby <seg type="unclear">Lee</seg> is a great joy. I don't <lb/> know what they would do without <lb/> her. She is a plain but attractive  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0646_img_2119_3"/>
              little soul. <seg type="unclear">Emmie Epson</seg> has decided <lb/> to remain on in India for the present.  My heart aches for Charlie &amp; Marjorie <lb/> but I am glad they are together, if <lb/> only for a short time. It is vexing <lb/> that Charlie's training is not what was <lb/> expected. If Marjorie wants me I shall <lb/> go to her but perhaps she will think <lb/> of being with her <seg type="unclear">poor Aunts</seg> for <lb/> a little bit.  Uncle Edmund has gone off to golf &amp; <lb/> Aunt Fanny &amp; I are going to walk <lb/> over the Downs to <seg type="unclear">Tadworth</seg> and <lb/> see Harry and Janet. I am anxious <lb/> to see their children. It will be <lb/> a cold, stormy, long walk but Aunt <lb/> Fanny says she is able for it.  I hope Aunt Charlotte's throat and <lb/> ear are better &amp; that Craig can really <lb/> make her well. Have you good <lb/> news of <seg type="unclear">Effie</seg>? I trust the change <lb/> is a success.  I have met Celia twice, &amp; she stayed  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0646_img_2119_4"/>
              a night here. She looks well and is <lb/> cheerful.  It is interesting seeing women in <lb/> London employed at all the railway <lb/> stations, on lifts, omnibuses etc. <lb/> I think being an omnibus conductor <lb/> would be infinitely more attractive <lb/> than ordinary clerical work.  Celia &amp; I made our way over to St <lb/> John's Gate &amp; interviewed Lady <seg type="unclear">Olivia</seg>,<lb/> who was covered with orders and <lb/> ribbons. She told Celia there was not <lb/> much chance of her getting abroad.<lb/> I doubt if I shall be called up <lb/> at all now as the demand for <lb/> V.A.D. nurses is evidently not so great.<lb/> St John's Gate is a quaint old <lb/> place. The walls lined with portraits <lb/> of the knights, suits of armour etc.<lb/> We got lost several times in the <lb/> back streets of <seg type="unclear">Clerkenwell</seg> but found <lb/> the place eventually.  I was all over London the other day  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0646_img_2119_5"/>
              from the heart of the City to South <lb/> Kensington. Finding the way was quite <lb/> amusing, but interviewing the heads <lb/> of offices &amp; Bureaus became wearisome <lb/> &amp; I got a glimpse of the deadly boredom <lb/> of London offices!  Best love to all the Aunties â I <lb/> was so glad to get your letter. <lb/> Days are very long here, but I try <lb/> to be cheery for Aunt Fanny, and <lb/> if we all 4 meet in London <sic>to-morrow</sic><lb/> it will be splendid. <seg type="closer"> Your loving  <hi rend="underline">Dussie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>