<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4265">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 1 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/201</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4265</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-01</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4265_img_3630_1"  type="Letter"  url="1ad47492017e232ef6713d2abdc5da63.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4265_img_3630_2"  type="Letter"  url="27695aae3b70c0097654153a517394bf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4265_img_3630_3"  type="Letter"  url="49cba06ea8f76ceb7b1026fbe375e8c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4265_img_3630_4"  type="Letter"  url="f6e980f6fbac1aee8ce1fc2e5ad44f1b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4265_img_3630_1"/>
             April 1   My pr   2 very fat sleek nice letters. What a <lb/> lucky b w.    I suppose it's <sic>all right</sic> about baccy if <lb/> Douglas says so but honestly I don't think <lb/> your funds ought to go to that   Rather alarmed at your account of the <lb/> blizzard. You musn't let my economies <lb/> be too strict please.I have looked at the <lb/> pass book &amp; growled at  Mother Hubbard<seg type="del">s</seg> like a real <lb/> black wolf, but on the whole it was a congenial <lb/> animal who thinks the p r very good.   He was a little disappointed not to be able to do
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4265_img_3630_2"/>
            something for the pr's 1000 but hope to do so <lb/> in another 2 <sic>month</sic>when further divs come in <lb/> rather well. Could you find me a retired pay <lb/> form anywhere so that I may sign it for the <lb/> past 3 <sic>month</sic> if not ask Cox to send you a <lb/> few when you return the passbook.   I'm afraid I am very doubtful about <lb/> the wisdom of a suburb for you. I really think <lb/> the train journey the rush to the station, the <lb/> waiting for train will prove very much more <lb/> tiring than living in town. Shopping would <lb/> be a business. I don't want to be a coldwater <lb/> cart but honestly I am very doubtful, &amp; you <lb/> might find it very difficult to see the family. No
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4265_img_3630_3"/>
            really I think your flat is best tho' you may <lb/> possibly find another close by which would do.   If the other COs don't write to you  about PW I <lb/> should send out a pc to each with the reply <lb/> Dear Madam I do <lb/> I do not wish you — <seg type="del">&amp;</seg>——— <lb/> &amp; ask them to send it back. Ross Smyth not <seg type="unclear">Rinus</seg> <lb/> Smyth who is Bde Major. The former is the <lb/> orangest of the oranges.   B'Gen' Parker who commanded the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Lancers at the Curragh <seg type="del">is</seg> was here &amp; I never <lb/> knew it was he. I called to see him this <lb/> afternoon when he was out. Such a pity.   I think the RE Companies etc would <lb/> probably be able to notify you of their wounded <lb/> but I believe a request from the Duchess that <lb/> they should send PCs to you would be put in orders
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4265_img_3630_4"/>
            by most COs but unfortunately they will never <lb/> remember the address<seg type="del">es</seg>.if wounded so it isn't much <lb/> good.   Sorry about Mrs Hugh. Glad I don't think <lb/> as she does. In the next life you &amp; I will be much <lb/> more of a unit than we now are &amp; I am content <lb/> with that.   I am so glad you &amp; Lady C still get on <lb/> so well but mind <hi rend="underline">NEVER</hi> hint at our wanting <lb/> Sir Es help, &amp; now of course you will see less &amp; <lb/> less of her if he really takes up work as you think.   Hope to send back pass book tomorrow   Ever <hi rend="underline">your</hi>b w    WBSpender  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>