<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1532">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kathleen Clarke to Fr Albert Bibby, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Clarke</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Kathleen Clarke (née Daly) (1878-1972), republican activist, to Fr Albert Bibby (1877-1958). Kathleen Clarke&#39;s husband, Thomas Clarke (1858-1916), and brother, Edward &#39;Ned&#39; Daly, were both executed for their part in the Easter Rising and Kathleen had been an active republican before the Rising. Fr Albert, born Thomas Bibby, was a Capuchin priest in Church Street in Dublin. In the aftermath of the Easter Rising, he ministered to a number of rebel prisoners in Kilmainham Gaol, including some of the executed leaders.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Capuchin Provincial Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Capuchin Papers relating to the Irish Revolution, CA/IR/1/1/2/2/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1532</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0082">Kathleen Clarke</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1654">15 Barrington Street, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Albert Bibby</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1532_img_1000_1"  type="Letter"  url="92f86dd7ca65a0f47e6673ff0b970e58.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1532_img_1000_2"  type="Letter"  url="016a594810ac19bd01f737523a0f8dcc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1532_img_1000_3"  type="Letter"  url="a38dfe04e4c51df78196c910991863d7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1532_img_1000_1"/>
             15 Barrington St<lb/>Limerick   Oct. 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916    Dear Fr. Albert   Many thanks<lb/>for your dear kind<lb/>letter. It gives me great<lb/>pleasure to know I am<lb/>always remembered in<lb/>your prayers.  I am not a good hands<lb/>at praying, but my thoughts<lb/>are a prayer for you and<lb/>more <sic>preists</sic> like you 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1532_img_1000_2"/>
             Laura and I were sorry to<lb/>miss you that day more<lb/>especially as Laura may<lb/>not be in Dublin<lb/>for a long time.  I am going up on Monday<lb/>and taking Tom to the<lb/>Doctor. Madge and Norah<lb/>are going also but they<lb/>are not going to stay in<lb/>Dublin,<sic>the</sic> are going to<lb/>Glendalough for a rest.<lb/>Madge will call to see<lb/>you. <sic>she</sic> was glad she had<lb/>not sent on the canary.<lb/>She is not well, but she hopes 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1532_img_1000_3"/>
             Glendalough will pull her 3)<lb/>up she is going to see<lb/>the prisoners in Portland<lb/>and Reading before returning<lb/>to Limerick.  My mother is getting better,<lb/>but she has become an old<lb/>woman suddenly. <sic>up</sic> know<lb/>she looked as young as<lb/>any of us and was full<lb/>of energy. Now she is tired<lb/>all the time and life seems<lb/>a trouble to her.  I will call to see you as soon<lb/>as I have Tom settled.  4) Limerick does not agree with<lb/>me, I am tired all the time<lb/>here. I have an unsettled feel<lb/>here too, as if it were only<lb/>on a visit I was, I find it<lb/>hard to realize that my<lb/>home and everything is<lb/>gone the only thing left is<lb/>hope and if our hopes for<lb/>Ireland's future are fulfilled<lb/>the sacrifices will have been<lb/>well worth the making.<lb/>Things look black at present<lb/>but the darkest hour is before<lb/>the dawn,  I hope to have a good long<lb/>chat with you next week. until<lb/>then good bye.   Yours very Sincerely,  <lb/> Kathleen Clarke 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>