<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0736">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Pollock to George Hackney, 30 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Pollock</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney (c. 1889-1977), a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;. In 1916 he was injured and spent some time a Hospital in Calais, France, and in Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield.Reverend John Pollock (1852-1935) was Minister of St. Enoch&#39;s Church in North Belfast, leading the largest Presbyterian congregation in the British Isles. He was also a prominent member of the Christian Endeavour movement , and composed many of its hymns. His only son Paul was killed in the Battle of the Somme.In this letter, Pollock writes of his &#39;bitter bereavement&#39; at the presumed death of his missing son. He argues, however, that Paul&#39;s death was both noble and worthy, that he gave his life &#39;for the noblest of causes... the protection, advancement, and consolidation of the Kingdom of God&#39;. Thus, Pollock argues, it is better for his son to be lying &#39;in an unmarked grave&#39; having accepted his duty than to be still alive, having shirked it. He gives information of his search for Paul, and speculates on his fate.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6-10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/736</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0769">John Pollock</persName>
              <date>1916-08-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0561">7, Glandore Park, Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0391">19 Ward, 35 General Hospital, Calais, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0736_img_2246_1"  type="Letter"  url="698b755d024a9e3e55316cb38ca03f0b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0736_img_2246_2"  type="Envelope"  url="3fddab5a65744fa7daab6a1d1fa94be3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0736_img_2246_3"  type="Envelope"  url="bc1499b770743eca637f96a61592cf74.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0736_img_2246_4"  type="Letter"  url="60b8c457856fc393d04e9e6dfc960703.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0736_img_2246_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">ST. ENOCH'S CHURCH</hi><lb/>Rev. JOHN POLLOCK <lb/>MINISTER <lb/>(Presbterian Chaplain <lb/>to the Forces) <lb/>  7 ,GLANDORE PARK  BELFAST    30.8.16   My dear George,   Since leaving home three <lb/> weeks ago I have had no heart to write <lb/> to anyone, so that you are not an exception. <lb/> We feel that there is now <lb/> nothing but the very faintest likelihood <lb/> of our dear boy turning up, and the <lb/> suspense has give place to a sense of <lb/> bitter bereavement. At the same <lb/> time we do not forget that we gave <lb/> Paul for the noblest of causes, and <lb/> he most enthusiastically gave himself. <lb/> The purest war is, on our part, 'for <lb/> the defence of the gospel'. the protection, <lb/> advancement, and consolidation <lb/> of the kingdom of God. That being <lb/> so, I had rather have my son's <lb/> body in an unmarked grace, having <lb/> done his duty, than sitting beside <lb/> me here, having shirked it. I never <lb/> honoured you and your comrades at <lb/> the front so much as I do now. And <lb/> God will richly reward you. There is <lb/> no heresy in that conviction!   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0736_img_2246_2"/>
               Accept of our united thanks for your <lb/> great kindness. Your letter was just <lb/> like you. Though it was not answered <lb/> promptly, it was acted upon without <lb/> delay. Mr. Smith and Elsie called <lb/> each of them on part of your list. <lb/> The addresses were all visited, <lb/> but no definite information was gained. <lb/> From information received through <lb/> my notice in the press, we have <lb/> reason to believe that Paul was <lb/> so seriously wounded by shrapnel <lb/> that he must have died before he <lb/> could be attended to, and not more <lb/> than fifty yards from our lines, but <lb/> away from the Y.C.V. position. His <lb/> body has not been found, the entire <lb/> ground having been ploughed up by <lb/> explosives. Of course we still <lb/> cling to the hope that his may be <lb/> one of the wonderful cases of reappearance <lb/> after long suspense.   Mother was bearing up wonderfully <lb/> when I saw her last, which was very <lb/> shortly before leaving home. May you <lb/> be spared to see her, and she to see <lb/> you!  <seg type="closer"> With united affectionate regards, Ever yours  John Pollock </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0736_img_2246_3"/>
              POSTMARK WEYMOUTH   11.45 AM 30 AUG 16     Corporal George Hackney,  B Company, 8 Platoon,  14th Irish Rifles,  19 Ward,  35 General Hospital    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0736_img_2246_4"/>
              Army Post <lb/> B <lb/> 10 <lb/> 16 <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>