<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4882">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward Carson to Richard Dawson Bates, 21 April 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Carson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Ulster Unionist Council, D1327-18-19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4882</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date>1919-04-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2112">Orion, Birchington, Kent, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1358">Richard Dawson Bates</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1935</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4882_img_None_1"  url="c24f20f736028460b1ff5bd9c76e4f0e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4882_img_None_2"  url="48c4d286e46892aaea79acff0f5da65f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4882_img_None_3"  url="e8b92252408149713c939a51e34ef2ce.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4882_img_0_1"/>
             COPY   ORION,    BIRCHINGTON    Labour cottages obair    APL. 21. 19.    My Dear Bates,   As I will not be present on Wednesday at the Standing<lb/>Committee owing to an important engagement in London I desire to<lb/>make one or two observations for the consideration of the Committee.  1. I should like to draw the earnest attention of the whole<lb/>Province to the necessity of placing our organisations on a thoroughly<lb/>democratic basis. It is essential that in the future we should avoid<lb/>all friction amongst those who deem the maintenance of the Union as of<lb/>paramount importance for the prosperity and happiness of the Province.<lb/>Complete unity can only be secured by taking care that all classes<lb/>and all views are thoroughly represented in our local organisations<lb/>and that opportunities are taken to keep in touch with the feelings<lb/>and requirements of the people. The outcome of the war must lead to<lb/>a great progression of democratic forces and ideals and this we must<lb/>encourage and make effective by a complete understanding of the wants<lb/>of the people. It is by unity alone that we can expect to maintain<lb/>our position in the councils of the State and enforce our policy of<lb/>obtaining for Ulster all that is thought essential for the democracies<lb/>of Great Britain. I venture therefore to express the hope that this<lb/>matter may have the serious attention of the Committee and that steps 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4882_img_0_2"/>
             -2-<lb/><lb/>may be taken which will prove effective in the direction I have<lb/>indicated.  2. No observer of the general unrest throughout the world<lb/>can fail to realise that advantage is being taken of it under<lb/>various pretexts to further the political aims and ambitions of cer-<lb/>tain sections of the community for their own ends, and I have no<lb/>doubt that our separatist opponents are working diligently both here<lb/>and in America with a view to harnassing to their cause various<lb/>elements of unrest in order to influence public opinion at home and<lb/>abroad in favour of the policy of what is called an Independent<lb/>Ireland. I have had numerous letters from America pointing out how<lb/>active our opponents are in that country in the Press and on the<lb/>Platform in trying by the grossest misrepresentation to bring about<lb/>an ante-English feeling in relation to Ireland.  I am convinced that the time has come when we should<lb/>establish an active propaganda department by which the true facts as<lb/>regards Ireland and especially as regards Ulster should be made<lb/>known.  We must recollect that after nearly five years a great deal<lb/>of our Educational work has been forgotten and with a new and enlarged<lb/>Electorate and a new Parliament the work must now be restarted and<lb/>continued if our case is to be properly understood.  Whether this work should be carried out under the Ulster<lb/>Council or jointly with the Unionist Alliance is a matter that<lb/>should be seriously considered. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4882_img_0_3"/>
             -3-  3. Finally I would like to point out that we should not<lb/>shut our eyes to the serious condition of affairs existing in the<lb/>South and West of Ireland. The open avowal of the leader of the<lb/>majority of the Irish people that their policy is the establishment<lb/>of a Republic in Ireland and his undisguised threat to Ulster in<lb/>the event of Ulster's refusal to abandon her loyalty to the King<lb/>and her citizenship in the British Empire must bring home to each<lb/>of us the necessity of being prepared for all eventualities. I have<lb/>myself but little trust in politicians or political parties in<lb/>relation to Ireland, and I say once more as I said at Craigavon<lb/>when I was/elected Leader of loyal Ulster that in the last ersort it<lb/>will be found that we must rely upon ourselves. This I believe we<lb/>are prepared to do.   Yours sincerely,    (Signed) EDWARD CARSON  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>