<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3776">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maud Gonne to Hanna Sheehy Skeffinton, circa May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maude Gonne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Maud Gonne MacBride (1866-1953) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) expressing sympathy in regards to the death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. Gonne writes that while the men&#39;s sacrifice will not be in vain it is very bitter for those who remain behind.

(Edith) Maud Gonne MacBride was an advanced nationalist and political activist. From 1916 onwards Gonne spent the majority of her time in France after a sensationalist divorce scandal, from her husband John MacBride (1865-1916), overshadowed her political ambitions. During the war Gonne served as a nurse in French military hospitals. However, the events of the Easter Rising altered her position as she wore mourning and called herself Maud Gonne MacBride, a title she had abandoned after the breakdown of her marriage some twelve years before. This change in circumstance allowed her to re-enter the Irish political scene. Aside from her politics Gonne was the subject of most of the love poetry of W. B. Yeats.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,608/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3776</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0381">Maude Gonne</persName>
              <date>1916-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1290">17 Rue de l&#39;Annonciation, Paris, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1953</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3776_img_3161_1"  type="Letter"  url="1cba04f961584d328de7dc8cceb5dee4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3776_img_3161_2"  type="Letter"  url="647069eb23a19b87f7f8ca372071305d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3776_img_3161_3"  type="Letter"  url="7774e2f93e78f438727df6c96620fa49.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3776_img_3161_1"/>
             <seg type="foreign"> de l'Annunciation</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Parry</seg> <lb/>Paris.   May June 1916  <!-- this added in pencil --> <lb/> My dear Mrs Skeffington  <lb/>How can I tell you how <lb/>much I think of you, <lb/>Feel with you in your <lb/>terrible loss — <lb/>I am over whelmed with <lb/>grief at the whole <lb/>ghastly tragedy. This <lb/>year I have lost almost <lb/>all my Dearest friends <lb/>&amp; Comrades — In France <lb/>through the War, &amp; <lb/>Now in Ireland.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3776_img_3161_2"/>
             I know that this<lb/>sacrifice will not be<lb/>in vain  for Ireland  but for we<lb/>who remain the loss<lb/>is very bitter.  Even amid the black<lb/>horror of military<lb/>impiety in Dublin<lb/>the murder of your<lb/>husband stands out<lb/>with such tragic<lb/>distinction that it<lb/>must bring justice &amp;<lb/>his brave Spirit will<lb/>rejoice that his death<lb/>serves the Cause of 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3776_img_3161_3"/>
             peace &amp; liberty for<lb/>which he worked so<lb/>unceasingly —  My work in the French<lb/>hospital has kept me<lb/>in France ever since<lb/>the War. I want to come<lb/>to Ireland  with my boy  if passport<lb/>difficulties can be overcome.  My love and Deepest<lb/>sympathy dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi><lb/>Skeffington to you and<lb/>your child.  <hi rend="underline">Maud Gonne.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>