<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0337">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegram to John F. Sweetman, 28 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>McAllister</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This telegram was addressed to John F. Sweetman (1844–1936) by a Mr McAllister. Sweetman was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. In 1915 he spoke out against conscription was arrested after the 1916 Rising and interned in England until the end of May 1916. In this telegram the author states that if the execution of Roger Casement is carried out dissatisfaction and bitterness will creep into the minds of the Irish people. He believes it would be prudent of the state to pardon Casement and will gladly sign the petition urging them to do so. Casement had been imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. A campaign was launched featuring many prominent figures such as W.B. Yeats and George Bernard Shaw to secure a reprieve for Casement but he was hanged on 3 August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, Ms.13,088/9/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/337</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0961">McAllister</persName>
              <date>1916-07-28</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1694">Mount Street, Gorey, County Wexford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0337_img_1566_1"  type="Letter"  url="c4046d20e61537b74634f2ba00024f7e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0337_img_1566_1"/>
              Gorey  TELEGRAM.    July 28th 1916  Dublin   TO J.F. Sweetman  Mount St. Gorey Wexford   Dear Sir   As to execution of 'Roger Casement', if carried<lb/> out will create disaffection and bitterness in<lb/> the minds of our Irish People, it would<lb/> be prudent of our statesmen to pardon him â  I hasten to sign enclosed petition <seg type="closer"> Yours obediently  <seg type="unclear">HG</seg><hi rend="underline">McAllister</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>