<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0358">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Irish Prisoners, Frongoch to William O'Brien, Esq., MP, 11 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by a group of Irish prisoners in Frongoch to William O&#39;Brien. The letter concerns the poor quality and quantity of food provided for Irish prisoners in Frongoch.Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; due to the influential effect it had on its inmates.The letter was addressed to William O&#39;Brien (1852-1928). O&#39;Brien was an Irish nationalist politician serving as a Member of Parliament in the Britain from 1883 until he withdrew himself and his party in 1918. Among the signatories to this letter are Michael Staines, Thomas Sinnott and Richard Mulcahy.Staines (1885 - 1955) was a member of the Irish Republican Brotherhood and served as Quartermaster in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was elected Head Leader by his peers.Sinnott (1893 - 1965) was the Officer Commanding Wexford Brigade, 1916. After the rising he was detained in Frongoch where he was a Room Leader.Richard Mulcahy (1886 - 1971) fought with Thomas Ashe in Ashbourne during the Easter Rising. After the Rising, he was detained in Frongoch where he was also a Room Leader.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, George Gavan Duffy Collection, BMH CD 45/4/10/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/358</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-10-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1045">Frongoch Prison Camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None"> William O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1638">House of Commons, Westminster, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0358_img_1596_1"  type="Letter"  url="c00ab599f424f9ec0ec8dee636b321f4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0358_img_1596_2"  type="Letter"  url="30fef2599974016a2c5c78db133e9bd7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0358_img_1596_3"  type="Letter"  url="798c04b380cbc027e4ed2b44d0ff9bf3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0358_img_1596_1"/>
                Irish Prisoners,  Internment Camp,  Frangoch,  Wales.    11th Oct. 1916.    To. William O' Brien Esq. M.P.  House of Commons.  Sir:-    We, the undersigned, being the duty elected camp leaders of<lb/> the Irish Prisoners, interned at Frangoch, are desirous of<lb/> drawing your attention to several very grave complaints concerning<lb/> the food supplied to us here, both with regard to its quantity<lb/> and quality. We have already lodged all these complaints both<lb/> to Military Authorities of this camp, and visiting Officials,<lb/> but no redress has been given.  First, with regard to the bread, generally speaking it has<lb/> been bad, both with regard to the quality of flour or other<lb/> substitutes used, and its baking, since our first arrival here.<lb/> For the month of July it was so bad that 160 of the prisoners<lb/> could not eat it all, while many others had to be content<lb/> with the crusts. An application was made to the Commandant, that<lb/> brown bread be supplied; and after some time he informed the<lb/> leaders that the Home Office would not accede to the request.  Secondly, with regard to the meat, we are only allowed 8ozs.<lb/> of meat per man per diem, and as this allowance, also includes<lb/> the bone, fat, and suet it will readily be seen that the quantity<lb/> is altogether inadequate. The meat which is invariably supplied<lb/> to us is New Zealand Frozen, and on two occasions it has been<lb/> condemned by the doctor as absolutely unfit for human consumption.  Thirdly, with regard to the potatoes. It is practically<lb/> impossible for an Irishman to imagine such potatoes - they are<lb/> small, wet, and soapy in appearance and texture. And they have<lb/> also been condemned by the doctor on one occasion as unfit for<lb/> human consumption, but nevertheless no change was made, or<lb/> anything else given in lieu, and the prisoner might either eat  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0358_img_1596_2"/>
              them or leave them.  Since the 19th August last, salt herrings have been<lb/> supplied to us for dinner of Fridays. But these herrings have<lb/> been very imperfectly cured with the result that they are also<lb/> unfit for human consumption. Our military guardians have<lb/> refused to supply a better quality of fish, or even a substitute<lb/> with the result that Friday's dinner costs the Prisoners £2<lb/> which have to be drawn from their private fund. In future the <lb/> prisoners do not intend taking these herrings from the military<lb/> as doing so only means that later on they are thrown into the<lb/> Camp <seg type="unclear">Swill tube</seg>.  Fourthly, with regard to the margarine supplied in lieu<lb/> of butter. Its flavour is wretched, and even if it was any <lb/> way palatable, the allowance per man per diem is totally<lb/> inadequate being only one oz. per man per diem.  Fifthly, with regard to the tinned milk. Tins of this<lb/> milk are being frequently condemned by the doctor, as unfit <lb/> for human food.  Sixthly, there is for too much preserved vegetables supplied<lb/> to the prisoners, and last August a request was made by the <lb/> prisoners that they be given more fresh vegetables in the <lb/> interests of their health, but no redress has ever been given<lb/> us in this respect. Skin disease is breaking out among the<lb/> prisoners as a result of the excess of preserved food supplied<lb/> to them — there being three prisoners at present isolated on <lb/> account of skin disease. The quantity of fresh vegetables <lb/> supplied, apart altogether from its quality is absolutely<lb/> inadequate, 2ozs. per man per diem only being allowed.  Seventhly, all the tinned food sent to the prisoners by <lb/> their friends and relations are opened by the censor with the <lb/> result that the prisoners must of necessity eat the contents <lb/> there and then, or else empty them into the swill tub.  Eighthly, owing to the pest of rats which infest the whole<lb/> place it is impossible to keep private supplies of food in the <lb/> room, without it being damaged, partly or in whole by the  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0358_img_1596_3"/>
              rodents. And in one case, a prisoner had his face bitten by<lb/> one of the rats, and was for some days under <seg type="del">the</seg> medical<lb/> attendance on that account.  Having read these details you will agree with us, that <lb/> detaining such a large body of untried and unconvicted <lb/> Irishmen under such conditions, is neither Christian nor <lb/> humane. <seg type="closer"> We desire to remain, Sir,<lb/> Your obedient servants,  Head Leader<lb/> (acting) No.1 Room Leader<lb/> No.2 ' '<lb/> No.3 ' '<lb/> No.4 ' ' </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S. Much larger quantities of food stuffs would be <lb/> received from committees, and even individuals, for distribution<lb/> among the general body of prisoners here, were it not for a rule<lb/> made by the Commandant whereby the acknowledging of such <lb/> foodstuffs is strictly reserved to himself, the Camp leaders<lb/> being entirely prohibited making acknowledgements of receipt<lb/> by them of such food stuffs. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>