<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3861">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley, 30 December 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley outlining his reasoning for proposing the College of Nursing and how he imagines the best possible way for the college to operate. 

Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>TPCK-2-6-1-1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3861</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1166">Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-12-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3861_img_3241_1"  type="Letter"  url="9e782f5e1e3e8cd7426b60ae227cfd60.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3861_img_3241_2"  type="Letter"  url="b8830bf38c495229175d98870403dc5a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3861_img_3241_3"  type="Letter"  url="d3dc0ccbaba7285e15fc601a12efe285.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3861_img_3241_4"  type="Letter"  url="70818e75f703886b9b5d7a9c32370ea3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3861_img_3241_1"/>
              83, PALL MALL, <lb/>LONDON, S.W.   30th December, 1915.   Dear Sir,    During my past year's work as Chairman of the Joint <lb/>War Committee of the British Red Cross Society and Order of <lb/>St. John I have been struck by the total lack of organization <lb/>amongst the various authorities responsible for the training <lb/>of Nurses and by the need for organization amongst the Nurses <lb/>themselves. Occupying a neutral position in relation to <lb/>these pressing problems I have given much time and attention <lb/>to considering how, in the interests of the Public and of the <lb/>Nurses themselves, the present unsatisfactory condition of <lb/>affairs may be remedied.   For something like 25 years there has been more or <lb/>less active agitation in favour of the Registration of <lb/>Trained Nurses, but for causes into which it is unnecessary <lb/>here to enter, this movement and others of a similar nature <lb/>have hitherto failed to attain the object sought.   There is no unanimous feeling either amongst those <lb/>responsible for the training of Nurses or amongst Nurses <lb/>themselves in favour of any system of State Registration. <lb/>Nevertheless I am convinced that something should be done at <lb/>once to co—ordinate the various interests involved, and, <lb/>without prejudice to ultimate developments whether by <lb/>legislation or otherwise, my own view is that for the time at <lb/>least we must rely upon a voluntary scheme of co—operation <lb/>amongst the Nurse Training Schools throughout the country.   I have confidence that a representative Association <lb/>would speedily attract so much support from the nursing <lb/>profession as to lend great weight and authority to any <lb/>decisions at which it might arrive.   Just as the Royal Colleges of Physicians and <lb/>Surgeons through the Conjoint Board organize the teaching and <lb/>examination of medical students, as the Chartered Institutes <lb/>of Accountants, of Surveyors, Engineers, and other bodies, as <lb/>Barristers and Solicitors organize the teaching and examining <lb/>of candidates for entrance to their respective professions so <lb/>do I feel most strongly that now is the right time for some <lb/>such movement in the Nursing profession. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3861_img_3241_2"/>
             With this end in view it is suggested that a College <lb/>of Nursing shall be founded. This College shall be a purely <lb/>voluntary body which will aim at securing the support and <lb/>sympathy of the Governors of Hospitals to which Nurse Training <lb/>Schools are attached, of the leading members of the medical <lb/>profession, of the Matrons and Lecturers at these Nurse <lb/>Training Schools, and last but not least of the Trained <lb/>Nurses themselves.   I suggest that Promoters of the College should be <lb/>sought amongst the Chairman and Governors of leading Hospitals, <lb/>Physicians and Surgeons lecturing to Nurses, the Principals <lb/>of Nurse Training Schools and of Nursing Associations, and <lb/>other persons interested in the education of Women, and I <lb/>hope your Hospital may be willing in due time to nominate <lb/>representatives to act in this capacity. The Promoters, <lb/>having obtained the sanction of the Board of Trade to the <lb/>registration of the College with its Memorandom and Articles <lb/>of Association, should appoint the first Council of Management, <lb/>two—thirds of whom should be Matrons of Hospitals or Superin— <lb/>tendents of Nursing. For effective administration it is <lb/>essential that the Council of Management should be relatively <lb/>small in numbers, but in order to secure a proper representa— <lb/>tion of all interests it is proposed that the Council should <lb/>form a large Consultative Board drawn from all classes of Nurse <lb/>Training Schools and Nursing Associations, and from Nurses in <lb/>practice throughout the Country. Further it is suggested that <lb/>the Council should always invite and receive a report from the <lb/>Consultative Board before coming to a determination either <lb/>upon courses of study and technical training for persons <lb/>intended for the nursing profession or upon the conditions <lb/>under which recognition may be extended to Nursing Schools. <lb/>The Council should also form an Examination Board, which will <lb/>advise upon the appointment of Examiners, the Scheme for <lb/>Examinations, and the acceptance under safeguards of internal <lb/>examinations in recognised Training Schools to qualify for the <lb/>Certificate of Proficiency in Nursing to be granted by the <lb/>College.   In addition to examining and giving qualifications <lb/>to Nurses, the College should take power to exercise similar <lb/>functions in all branches of Women's work connected with <lb/>Hospitals, whether naval, military or civil, and to give <lb/>certificates of proficiency to those who pass the necessary <lb/>examinations.   Such are the broad outlines of the Scheme, and I <lb/>should be glad to know whether they meet with the general <lb/>approval of your Hospital Committee. lt is put forward with <lb/>the idea of securing greater uniformity of training and <lb/>curriculum for Nurses, fuller co—operation between the <lb/>Nursing Schools, and the better organization of the Nursing <lb/>Profession generally. I shall be glad to submit to the <lb/>advisers who have already helped me any criticism you may
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3861_img_3241_3"/>
            be pleased to make. I have reason to hope that, should <lb/>these proposals meet with sympathetic support, I may be able <lb/>to secure financial assistance to launch the College in a <lb/>suitable building, but before asking the Board of Trade's <lb/>approval to omit the word "Limited" from the title of the <lb/>Association I must be assured of a substantial backing <lb/>throughout the country. When this step is gained, I shall <lb/>have the pleasure of asking your Committee to nominate your <lb/>representatives to take part in the establishment and <lb/>development of the College, which may I hope, promote the <lb/>welfare of Trained Nurses and of all other Women engaged in <lb/>attendance upon the Sick and Wounded, and may thus do <lb/>lasting service to our Nation and Country.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,   A Stanley <lb/>Chairman, Joint War Committee. <lb/>British Red Cross Society and Order <lb/>of St. John. </seg>
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3861_img_3241_4"/>
             Letter from Mr Stanley December 30, 1915 <lb/><hi rend="underline">re</hi> proposed College 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>