<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1843">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ella Young to Anna O'Rahilly, 13 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ella Young</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Ella Young (1867–1956) to Anna O&#39;Rahilly (d.1958). In the letter Young asks Anna if Pearse&#39;s school, St. Endas, will reopen and whether they might be looking for teachers. She also mentions that a petition for the reprieve of Roger Casement (1864–1916), the Irish nationalist who was tried for treason following the 1916 Rising.

Young was a poet, republican, and mystic actively involved in the Celtic Revival. After fleeing to Connemara during the aftermath of the 1916 Rising, she took a room in a Protestant-owned house in Dublin, where she later claimed that she had again hidden arms and ammunition, and helped two escaped republican prisoners to get out of the city.

Anna was the sister of Michael &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly. O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) was a nationalist and a journalist. In 1916 he aligned himself with Eoin MacNeill (1867-1945) and Bulmer Hobson (1883-1969) who opposed a preemptive rising. Although O&#39;Rahilly played a large role in delivering MacNeill&#39;s countermanding order he felt obligated to stand with the men he recruited and trained. O&#39;Rahilly was fatally wounded on Thursday 27 April when the GPO was being evacuated.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/263/001/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1843</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0825">Ella Young</persName>
              <date>1916-07-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0742">O&#39;Curry College, Carrigaholt, County Clare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1843_img_1298_1"  type="Letter"  url="35eaa2cb79adace0c44c9cd26ac42997.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1843_img_1298_1"/>
             The O'Curry College<lb/>Carrigaholt<lb/>Co. Clare   13 July 1916    Dear Miss O'Rahilly   I am very anxious<lb/>to know whether Pearses school<lb/>is to be closed or whether<lb/>arrangements are being made to<lb/>appoint teachers. If you know<lb/>anything about it or can give<lb/>me the names of any one interested<lb/>in the school and its arrangements<lb/>I shall be very grateful.     Petitions for the reprieve<lb/>of Sir Roger Casement are being<lb/>signed all round here - I hope<lb/>something is being done in Dublin.   Yours with fond wishes        Ella Young.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>