<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0464">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Stephen St. Lawrence Burke to the Chief Secretary’s Office, 19 June, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Stephen St. Lawrence Burke</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>An application from Stephen St. Lawrence Burke for the vacant position of Clerk of Crown and Peace for Co. Westmeath. He outlines his professional experience and encloses copies of testimonials obtained when applying for another appointment. The enclosures are brief testimonies, mainly from clients of his legal practice, as to Mr. Burke’s efficiency in the conduct of his business.The office of Chief Secretary for Ireland was vacated by Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) on 30 April, 1916. His replacement, Henry Duke (1855-1939), took up the position from 31 July 1916. Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) succeeded Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who resigned on 3 May, 1916 as Under Secretary. The Under Secretary was effectively the permanent head of the British administration in Ireland up to 1922.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/10359</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/464</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0372">Stephen St. Lawrence Burke</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0494">Roscommon, Co. Roscommon, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Chief Secretary&#39;s Office</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_1"  type="Letter"  url="c345698abe12d0dadea6be63a044f844.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="8fc41c70223601749ff0124fc77e475b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="a105739740e85e60661327cdd53c343b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="9de773e547227de2b810af29343c5343.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="56c2fa4227ef70408440c1af45a6cda9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="7001939736bc6a736f7f62c34e89c3e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="ae2db9f9cc550f64cc9ac2139e02cf80.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="247a0f879d3871af07c8aa55a42182d1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="c308c83c9dd62638133c451cd6589a8c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_10"  type="Enclosure"  url="b3f571623c4be29bbac8d9ff26d6362b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_11"  type="Enclosure"  url="bca0f35cb98424ef9b7b6ce0448c6593.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_12"  type="Enclosure"  url="f9dafda29406e7191f5347b08950c4d6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_13"  type="Enclosure"  url="4e0196242befa4da75ee827337ab96ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_14"  type="Enclosure"  url="719f356ccae2fee3e4790928cb99fe71.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_15"  type="Enclosure"  url="49dc4189617f56845232a7fc34e7128d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_16"  type="Enclosure"  url="512888b2397f605db990e281c2c1e54f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_17"  type="Enclosure"  url="a51b977f65965f36485a1c871caf89fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_18"  type="Enclosure"  url="d2b2ce70d5df0426b40b3009d37b8c69.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_19"  type="Enclosure"  url="2d4e2938d8cef7bf6fd39c58813fb7b0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_20"  type="Enclosure"  url="02b7169881f1252c4792b05372160bac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_21"  type="Enclosure"  url="a2b06646d7ef1a20e607a6a0d337a8cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_22"  type="Enclosure"  url="f66a3a509156ae5bdf864fd68a0fc1d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_23"  type="Enclosure"  url="6cdeb7f740a1fc8ac8027d4bc159b41f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_24"  type="Enclosure"  url="22c25e1e0f919e2ae3a760ef7a42d27f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_25"  type="Enclosure"  url="2757ff0aa4028bf2f364cc5d551a4e9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_26"  type="Enclosure"  url="c4220eae1e9fe1e68c22704d5bbaa73e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_27"  type="Enclosure"  url="900404fcb0984a7f6191cc6e0f38ac0a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_28"  type="Enclosure"  url="1e4794780dc14835032e5e84b2762e96.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_29"  type="Enclosure"  url="f2bdc5d8480bf1efeb19dd5df020c401.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_30"  type="Enclosure"  url="e7e746fd077271d844811b0b06a07636.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0464_img_1810_31"  type="Enclosure"  url="5b599260dd68dda3b290721d892d7562.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_1"/>
                TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS:  'J.BURKE,' ROSCOMMON.  JOSEPH BURKE &amp; SON,  County Solicitors   All letters on business should be <lb/> addressed to the FIRM   <seg type="del">Upper</seg>Ormond <seg type="del">Quay,</seg>  <seg type="del">Dublin,</seg>  <seg type="del">And</seg> ROSCOMMON     June 19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 16.    <seg type="unclear">Sir.</seg>   I beg to apply for the <lb/> position of Clerk of the <lb/> Crown &amp; Peace for the County of <lb/> Westmeath - rendered vacant <lb/> by the death of <seg type="unclear">Mr. J.</seg>R. Kelly â <lb/> My father was Crown. <sic>Solr</sic> for <lb/> this County for nearly 30 years &amp; <lb/> was Clerk of the Crown â here â <lb/> when he died. I was qualified <lb/> in 1891 &amp; am County. <sic>Solr</sic><lb/> for this County â I also hold <lb/> a number of other public <lb/> appointments, in addition <cb/> to which I am the Representative <lb/> of Connaught, on the Council <lb/> of the Incorporated Law Society.   I am known to the <lb/> Master of the Rolls (&amp; other <lb/> members of the Bench) to hold <lb/> a prominent position in my <lb/> progression.   I enclose copies of <lb/> a few Testimonials obtained <lb/> when looking for an appointment <lb/> on a former occasion.  <seg type="closer">  I am Sir, <lb/> Your <sic>obd.t</sic><sic>serv.t</sic>  S. S <hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Lawrance-Burke  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_2"/>
                 37, CHESHAM PLACE,   LONDON, S.W.,     June 26th, 1900.    Dear Sir,    I have much pleasure in testifying to the efficient <lb/> manner in which you have acted when employed profession ally in any business of mine, and I have from time to time <lb/> heard from my agent his satisfaction at the way my cases have <lb/> been conducted by you.  <seg type="closer"> Yours Faithfully,  HARLECH. <lb/> H. M. L for Co. Leitrim. <lb/> S. ST. LAWRENCE BURKE, Esq., etc., etc. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_3"/>
                CARLTON CLUB,    December 21st, 1899.   Dear Burke,   I think you have very efficiently performed the duties <lb/> connected with my Estate, which you have represented for <lb/> many years, and therefore I testify with pleasure to your zeal <lb/> and ability, in many a difficult case, and I shall always be <lb/> glad to hear of any good luck in the way of promotion that <lb/> may come your way.  <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely,  CROFTON. J. <seg type="unclear">G.</seg>D.L.  </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_4"/>
                CHARLESTOWN,  DRUMSNA,    July 4th, 1900   DEAR MR. BURKE,   I have much pleasure in testifying to the manner in <lb/> which you have conducted the legal business on my County <lb/> Roscommon estate, which has proved satisfactory.   And I have heard my father, the late Sir Gilbert King, <lb/> express satisfaction at the manner in which your father, the <lb/> late Mr. Joseph Burke, conducted legal business for him,  <seg type="closer"> I remain, <lb/> yours faithfully,   GILBERT KING, Bart. J. <seg type="unclear">P.</seg>D.L    S. ST. LAWRENCE BURKE, Esq.,  The Abbey,  Roscommon.  </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_5"/>
              Copy of Resolution passed by the Grand Jury at Roscommon <lb/> Spring Assizes, 1899.   Proposed by T. A. P. Mapother, Esq., D.L.; seconded <lb/> by W. T. Potts, Esq., J.P., andâ   RESOLVEDâThat We, the Grand Jury of the County of <lb/> Roscommon, assembled at Spring Assizes, 1899, desire to place <lb/> on record our appreciation of the able, efficient, zealous, and <lb/> satisfactory manner in which our Solicitor, MR. S. ST. <lb/> LAWRANCE BURKE, has conducted our legal business since <lb/> his appointment in the year 1892.  <seg type="closer">O'CONOR DON, <lb/> Foreman. </seg> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_6"/>
                GORNAMONA,  TULLAMORE,    December 8th, 1895   My Dear Sir,   I have had many opportunities since you joined the <lb/> Roscommon Quarter Session's Bar, of observing the efficiency <lb/> and good temper with which you conducted your large busi- ness. I am sure you would creditably fill any place held by <lb/> my friend, your lamented father.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  W. O'CONNOR MORRIS,  County Court Judge for Roscommon <lb/> and Sligo. <lb/>  S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq.,  Solicitor, Roscommon.  </seg> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_7"/>
                10, FITZWILLIAM PLACE,  DUBLIN,    April 15, 1896.   MY DEAR MR. BURKE,   You will allow me to add my contribution to the many <lb/> proofs you have the esteem and admiration which your zeal <lb/> and ability have won for you in Roscommon.   Your father's leading professional position in your County <lb/> gave you an introduction, your own talents, learning and <lb/> skilled advocacy have made you his not unworthy successor.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,  MacDERMOT. J.P.D.L. <lb/> Attorney General for Ireland. </seg> 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_8"/>
                31, FITZWILLIAM SQUARE,  DUBLIN,    October 10th, 1896.   DEAR MR. BURKE,   I have much pleasure in adding my testimony of your <lb/> zeal and efficiency to that of your other clients from my <lb/> experience of the zeal and ability you have always displayed <lb/> in acting as my Solicitor in matters connected with my small <lb/> property in the County Roscommon.  <seg type="closer"> Truly yours,  ROBT. WM. SHEKLETON, J.P., Q.C.  S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_9"/>
                50, UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN,    December 18th, 1899.   MY DEAR BURKE,   Since you lamented father's death I have had many <lb/> opportunities of observing the way in which you conducted <lb/> your business as a Solicitor. You have at all times acted <lb/> with diligence and ability, and I have known you to carry <lb/> through very complicated and difficult cases to a successful <lb/> conclusion. I also wish to bear testimony to your high <lb/> integrity.   You were placed in a very trying and difficult position <lb/> by the sudden death of your late father, at a time when you <lb/> had not completed your apprenticeship, and you wont the <lb/> admiration of your friends by the courage with which you <lb/> assumed your father's position and continued the work of <lb/> your office. Your subsequent success is the best proof of <lb/> your capacity for business.  <seg type="closer">  Very sincerely yours,  CHAS. A. O'CONNOR, Q.C. <hi rend="underline">Hon</hi> Master of the Rolls. <lb/> STEPHEN ST. L. BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_10"/>
              Coy of Resolution passed by the Grand Jury at Roscommon <lb/> Summer Assizes, 1894.   Proposed by Mr. T. A. P. Mapother, seconded by Mr. <lb/> Luke J. Irwin:â   RESOLVEDâThat We, the Grand Jury of the County of <lb/> Roscommon, desire to place on record our appreciation of <lb/> the very able and efficient manner in which the proceedings <lb/> before the Committee of the House of Commons, in the <lb/> matter of the transfer of the control of the roads within the <lb/> Borough of Athlone from the Grand Jury to the Town Comâ <lb/> missioners were conducted on our behalf by our Solicitor, <lb/> MR. STEPHEN. ST. LAWRENCE BURKE.  <seg type="closer">AdoptedâO'CONOR DON, <lb/> Foreman. </seg> 
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_11"/>
                STROKESTOWN,    December 7th, 1895.   DEAR SIR,   We have much pleasure in testifying to the careful and <lb/> able manner in which you have conducted our legal business <lb/> in this county.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,  GUINNESS MAHON &amp; CO. <lb/> S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_12"/>
                KILTEEVAN,  ROSCOMMON,    December 9th, 1895.   MY DEAR SIR,   Having been a client of yours for some years (during <lb/> which I entrusted to you matters involving considerable difficulty), <lb/> and having had frequent opportunity, as Chairman of <lb/> the Roscommon Board of Guardians, and as Magistrate and <lb/> Grand Juror of this County, of observing the skill, energy, <lb/> and tact, which you bring to bear upon the discharge of your <lb/> professional duties, I feel much pleasure in testifying to your <lb/> fitness for any office in which such qualities would find scope <lb/> for their exercise.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very faithfully,  THOS. A. P. MAPOTHER, D.L. <lb/>  S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq.,  Solicitor, Roscommon.  </seg> 
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_13"/>
                CARRANURE,  ATHLONE,    December 13th, 1895.   MY DEAR SIR,   From my own experience, and that of many of my <lb/> friends (your clients), I feel much pleasure in testifying to the <lb/> exceptional zeal, ability, and efficiency with which any legal <lb/> business, committed to your care, has been invariably conâ ducted, and I am happy to see in you a worthy successor to <lb/> your highly esteemed father, who for many years so ably disâ charged the duties of Sessional Crown Solicitor, and at the <lb/> time of his much-lamented death held the office of <lb/> Clerk of the Crown for our County.  <seg type="closer"> Very faithfully yours,  B. W. BAGOT, J. P. <lb/>  S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq.,  The Abbey,  Roscommon.  </seg> 
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_14"/>
                RENT OFFICE,  AHASCRAGH,    December 18th, 1895.   MY DEAR SIR,   I have much pleasure in bearing testimony to the care <lb/> and attention you have always given to any business we have <lb/><sic>intrusted</sic> to you. We think you a painstaking and careful <lb/> man of business.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,  E. G. ARMSTRONG, <lb/> For E. G. ARMSTRONG &amp; MAHON <lb/> S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_15"/>
                ATHLEAGUE VICARAGE,  ROSCOMMON,    December 10th, 1895.    I have known MR. STEPHEN ST. LAWRENCE BURKE for <lb/> many years, and I have had ample opportunity for observing <lb/> his assiduity and attention to his profession. He had the <lb/> great advantage of being for many years intimately associated <lb/> in business with his able and eminent father, the late Mr. <lb/> Joseph Burke, who so successfully conducted the many <lb/> important and critical cases <sic>intrusted</sic> to him.   I believe that it will be MR. STEPHEN BURKE'S uniform <lb/> desire to emulate the abilities of his father in the performâ <lb/> ance of any duties which he may be called upon to fulfil.  <seg type="closer">W. BOURKE-WRIGHT, <lb/> Vicar of Athleague and Mount Talbot, <lb/> Canon of Elphin. </seg> 
            <pb n="16" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_16"/>
                COLAMBER,  RATHOWN, WESTMEATH,    December 29th, 1895.   MY DEAR SIR,   I can with pleasure testify that you have conducted <lb/> the legal business of the five estates I am agent to, in the <lb/> County of Roscommon, efficiently and successfully.  <seg type="closer"> Very truly yours,  PHILIP O'REILLY, D.L. <lb/> S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="17" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_17"/>
                ESTATE OFFICE,  MILLMOUNT ROAD,  MULLINGAR,    February 18th, 1896.   MY DEAR SIR,   I have much pleasure in testifying to the care and <lb/> ability which you have uniformly shown in the large number <lb/> of cases which you have conducted as solicitor for me on the <lb/> several estates I am Agent for in County Roscommon.  <seg type="closer"> Very truly yours,  R. C. BARTON. <lb/> S. St. L. BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="18" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_18"/>
                ESTATE OFFICE,  CARRICK-ON-SHANNON,    February 18th, 1896.   DEAR MR. BURKE,   I have great pleasure in testifying to the attention and <lb/> skill with which you have managed the various cases I have <lb/> placed in your hands, both before the Land Commission and <lb/> Quarter Sessions Courts, that arose on some of the estates I <lb/> am Agent over in the County Roscommon.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,  HENRY S. DARLEY, J.P. <lb/> S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq., <lb/> The Abbey, Roscommon. </seg> 
            <pb n="19" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_19"/>
                BALLINDERRY,  BALLINASLOE,    February 19th, 1896.   MY DEAR SIR,   I have much pleasure in bearing testimony to the care <lb/> and attention you have invariably bestowed upon the legal <lb/> business with which I have entrusted you in connection with <lb/> the estates I manage in the County Roscommon.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  J. W. COMYN, Lieut.-Col. <lb/> S. ST. L. BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="20" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_20"/>
                73, MERRION SQUARE, DUBLIN,    February 17th, 1896.   DEAR MR. BURKE,   I have very much pleasure in giving expression to the <lb/> very great ability displayed in troublesome litigation with <lb/> tenants on various estates, mine inclusive. I found your <lb/> laudable emulation of your father's great energy and attention <lb/> to business as Clerk of the Crown for County Roscommon.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  HENRY TAAFFE-FERRALL, J.P., D.L., Lieut.-Col. <lb/><lb/> S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="21" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_21"/>
                47, DAWSON STREET, DUBLIN, and ESTATES OFFICE, ROSCOMMON,    January 6th, 1896.    I have much pleasure in <sic>indorsing</sic> the testimonial given <lb/> by me to MR. STEPHEN ST. LAWRENCE BURKE in 1892, viz.: <lb/>  'I have much pleasure in testifying to the very satisfactory <lb/> manner in which Mr. Stephen St. Lawrance <lb/> Burke has conducted the business <sic>intrusted</sic> to him <lb/> by me on the several estates over which I act as <lb/> Agent or Receiver. I am sure he can creditably fill <lb/> any post <sic>intrusted</sic> to him.'  <seg type="closer"> W. E. HOLMES, J. P. </seg> 
            <pb n="22" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_22"/>
                CASTLEMORE, BALLAGHADEREEN, CO. MAYO,    January 1st, 1896.   MY DEAR BURKE,   I have very great pleasure in stating that you, at all <lb/> times, discharged any business I <sic>intrusted</sic> to you with care <lb/> and ability. Many years ago your late lamented father acte <lb/> d as my solicitor when I was receiver and agent over several <lb/> large properties, and always with that ability and success <lb/> for which he was so remarkable, and I am glad to say his old <lb/> clients have found in you an able and zealous successor.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  V. J. BLAKE, J.P. <lb/><lb/> STEPHEN ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq., Solicitor. </seg> 
            <pb n="23" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_23"/>
                KILRONAN ESTATES OFFICE,    December 31st, 1895.   DEAR MR. BURKE,   There has been a great deal of complicated trouble- <lb/> some litigation with tenants on this and other estates in my <lb/> charge, both in the Superior and Land Commission Courts, <lb/> and all throughâmainly owing to your professional intelligence, <lb/> tact, and patient industryâthe interest of my <lb/> employers have been safeguarded.   I may add, that also much litigation has been saved owing <lb/> to your intervention as a faithful adviser to both sides.  <seg type="closer"> Believe me, <lb/> Very truly yours,   J. GARNETT TATLOW, J.P. <lb/><lb/>  S. ST. LAWARANCE BURKE, Esq., Solicitor, Roscommon.  </seg> 
            <pb n="24" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_24"/>
                ESTATE OFFICE, ROSCOMMON,    December 30th, 1895.   MY DEAR SIR,   All the work you have done for me since your father's <lb/> death has been most efficiently done. You have also in some <lb/> cases kept me form going on with legal proceedings, to your <lb/> own loss, but to my gain.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  W. D. TALBOT-CROSBIE. <lb/> S. ST. LAWARANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="25" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_25"/>
                BALLINAFAD, BALLYGLASS, CO. MAYO,    February 22nd, 1896.    I have much pleasure in testifying to the very satisfactory <lb/> manner in which MR. STEPHEN ST. LAWRANCE BURKE has <lb/> for several years conducted all the legal business I <sic>intrusted</sic><lb/> to him.  <seg type="closer"> LLEWELLYN BLAKE, D. L., <lb/> Lieut.-Colonel.  </seg> 
            <pb n="26" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_26"/>
                CARNACREGG, MOYLOUGH, CO. GALWAY,    February 24th, 1896.   DEAR SIR,   I have much pleasure in testifying to the very efficient <lb/> manner in which you have conducted my legal business in <lb/> Co. Roscommon.  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly,  EDWARD BROWNE. <lb/> S. ST. L. BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="27" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_27"/>
                SOUTH PARK, CASTLEREA,    February 29th, 1896.   MY DEAR BURKE,   I have great pleasure in testifying to the very efficient <lb/> and highly satisfactory manner in which you have conducted <lb/> the business on this estate, and other matters for me since <lb/> the death of your lamented father.  <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely,  M. J. BALFE, J.P., D.L. <lb/> S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq. </seg> 
            <pb n="28" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_28"/>
                BALLAGH, ROSCOMMON and ST. ARNAUD'S MERRION, CO. DUBLIN,    January 3rd, 1900.   MY DEAR SIR,   I have much pleasure in testifying to the able and <lb/> satisfactory manner in which you have for many years (since <lb/> the death of your father) transacted the legal business of my <lb/> Roscommon property.   Your able management has on several occasions saved me <lb/> from considerable trouble.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,  JAMES D. O'CONNOR, J.P. <lb/> S.ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq </seg> 
            <pb n="29" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_29"/>
                THE BUSH, ANTRIM,    July 20th, 1900.   DEAR MR. BURKE,   It gives me great pleasure to testify to the care with <lb/> which you have attended to the legal business I have inâ <lb/> trusted to you from time to time, and I shall be very pleased <lb/> indeed if I can assist you in any way towards obtaining the <lb/> appointment you now seek.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,  H. D. M. BARTON. <lb/>  S. ST. LAWARANCE BURKE, Esq., The Abbey, Roscommon  </seg> 
            <pb n="30" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_30"/>
                68, HARCOURT STREET, DUBLIN, and FORT LYSTER, ATHLEAGUE, CO. ROSCOMMON,    August 17th, 1896.   DEAR SIR,   I can with pleasure testify to the zeal and legal skill <lb/> which you have shown in conduction the business you have <lb/> undertaken from in the County of Roscommon, both on my <lb/> own estate, and on those over which I am agent.  <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly,  WILLIAM JAMESON, J.P. <lb/>  S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq., Solicitor, Roscommon.  </seg> 
            <pb n="31" facs="L1916_0464_img_1810_31"/>
                CARROWROE, ROSCOMMON,    July 26th, 1896.   MY DEAR SIR,   It gives me great pleasure to state that in all business <lb/> committed to you by me, you have always displayed great <lb/> ability, shrewdness, and attention. I have every confidence <lb/> in your capability to fill any office creditable and efficiently, <lb/> where legal knowledge, tact, and energy are requisites.  <seg type="closer"> Very truly yours,  M. A. BURKE, J.P., <lb/> Lt.-Colonel. <lb/>  S. ST. LAWRANCE BURKE, Esq.,  Roscommon.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>