<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0125">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward H. Andrews to Lord Clonbrock, 7 November 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this was a letter from Edward H. Andrews to Luke Gerald Dillon, Andrews acknowledges receipt of Clonbrock&#39;s earlier correspondence relating to the case of William Clery. Andrews assures Clonbrock that Joseph Byrne (1874-1942), Inspector-General of the RIC, will take the case into consideration. Edward H. Andrews was the honorary secretary of the Dublin Chamber of Commerce. Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron Clonbrock, Co. Galway, is the husband of Lady Clonbrock who was a member of the Irish Women’s Association and heavily involved in assisting Irish soldiers during World War I.The Dillon family of Clonbrock was descended from Sir Henry de Leon, an Anglo-Norman nobleman who arrived in Ireland with the Earl of Moreton (later King John of England) in 1185. As a reward for helping Prince John to establish his Lordship of Ireland, de Leon was granted a large tract of land on the Westmeath frontier with Connacht on which he built a castle at Drumrany. This family was among the first of the Anglo-Norman settlers</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NLI MS 35,766/12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/125</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-11-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1380">Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1862">Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0125_img_121_1"  type="Letter"  url="1fb6a35a6f7cb3c4b050d56181c2d3eb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0125_img_121_1"/>
              Irish Police &amp; Co<hi rend="underline">nstabulary Re</hi>cognition fund. President : The Right Hon. The EARL OF MEATH, K.P., H.M.L.<lb/> Vice&amp;#8212;President: SIR JOHN ARNOTT Bart.<lb/> Chairman of Committee : SIR MAURICE DOCKRELL, D.L. Hon. Treasurer : RICHARD W. BOOTH, J.P.<lb/> Deputy-Chairman : JOHN MOONEY, C.V.O., D L. Hon. Secs : V. C. LE FANU J.P., and ED. H. ANDREWS, J.P.<lb/> Committee:<lb/> LORD BARRYMORE, H.M.L. VISCOUNT POWERSCOURT, H.M.L. LORD TALBOT DE MALAHIDE.<lb/> RT. HON. MR JUSTICE ROSS. LORD HARLECH, H.M.L THE HIGH SHERIFF OF THE CITY OF DUBLIN.<lb/> RT. HON. THE EARL OF MEATH, K.P , H.M.L. RT. HON. T. LOUGH, M.P. JOHN MOONEY, C.V.O., D. L.<lb/> RT. HON. THE LORD MAYOR OF DUBLIN J. JACKSON CLARK, H.M.L. V. C. LE FANU, J.P.<lb/> MARQUIS F SLIGO, H.M.L. SIR THOMAS TALBOT POWER, BART. COL. EDGEWORTH JONSTONE.<lb/> WELLINGTON DARLEY, J.P J. F. HEALY LADY POWERSCOURT.<lb/> LORD RATHDONNELL, H.M.L. SIR ANDREW HORNE. LADY ARDILAUN.<lb/> EARL OF KENMARE, H.M.L. RICHARD W. BOOTH, J.P. MISS PRESTON.<lb/> SIR JAMES MURPHY, BART., D.L. ANDREW BEATTIE, D.L. SIR F. AND LADY SHAW.<lb/> EDWARD H. ANDREWS, J.P. SIR WILLIAM J. GOULDING, BART, D.L. MATTHEW J. MINCH, J.P.<lb/> COMMANDER GAISFORD ST. LAWRENCE, R.N., D.L. SIR W. WATSON. T. L. PLUNKETT D.L.<lb/> SIRE MAURICE DOCKRELL, D.L. BIRGADIER&amp;#8212;GENERAL BYRNE. S. W. MADDOCK, J.P.    Chamber of Commerce,  Dublin,    7th Novr 1916.   My Lord,   We are in receipt of your letter of the 31st ulto re the case<lb/> of William Clery, and have handed your letter on to General Byrne,<lb/> Commanding the R.I.C., who will no doubt take the case into his <lb/> consideration when dealing with the other cases. <seg type="closer"> I am,<lb/> My Lord,<lb/> Your Lordship's obedient Servant.  <hi rend="underline">Edward H. Andrews</hi> <lb/> On behalf of the Hon. Secretaries.<lb/>  The Rt. Hon. Lord Clonbrock, P.C., H.M.L.,  Ahascragh,  Galway.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>