<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0301">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Herbert Henry Asquith regarding the Casement Relief Petition, 27 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a covering letter from the Casement Relief Petition sent to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), British prime minister, from the Casement Relief Petition Committee. They are sending 46 signatures to be included with the petitions they have already sent by the same post. But, because these people are not &#39;people of note&#39; they are to be understood as a different category. Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) had been arrested at Banna Strand, County Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Though Casement had not been intimately involved in the planning of the Easter Rising and had travelled to Ireland from Germany to try and prevent it taking place, believing it should not happen without sufficient German support, he had been sentenced to sentenced to death for treason. The names of the relief committee, who were campaigning for a reprieve, are listed in full.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, Ms. 13,088/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/301</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0224">44 Parnell Square, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Herbert Henry Asquith </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0441">Westminster, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0301_img_1520_1"  type="Letter"  url="7c41411d47ec711a437f5a8e99b4129c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0301_img_1520_1"/>
                44, Parnell Square,  Dublin    27th. July,1916.    The Rt. Hon. H.H. Asquith M.P.  Prime Minister.   Sir,   We are sending by some post an eith list of 46 signatures, <lb/> to the Casement relief Petiton.  As they are not personally <sic>know </sic> to us and appear<lb/> to belong to a different category we have not included them in<lb/> the list of people of note. <seg type="closer"> We have the honour to be,<lb/> Your Obedient servant,  Hon. Secretaries <lb/> Committee:- <lb/> The Lord FFrench<lb/> The Lord Ashbourne<lb/> Rt. Rev. Mons. Ryan P.P.<lb/> Rev. Matthew Maguire P.P.<lb/> Dr. Hyde LL.D. Professor Nat. University<lb/> Col Maurice Moore C.B.<lb/> Lorcan Sherlock Esq. Late Lord Mayor Dublin<lb/> F.J. Allen Esq<lb/> Mrs Hutton<lb/> Mrs. O'Nolan<lb/> Miss O'Farrelly M.A Professor Nat. <sic>Univerisyt</sic><lb/> Miss Young Queen's Co.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>