<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6668">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. Figgis and Maude Gonne MacBride to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 24 March 1922</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. Figgis</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, M. Figgis and Maude Gonne MacBride tell Joseph Cyrillus Walsh about their concerns about former prisoners, who have suffered from immense hunger within British jails. They ask Walsh to do something for these people, the most pressing issues are, according to the two authors, to care for the wounded and disabled and to provide financial help.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph C. Walsh Papers. Letters Earls - Foy</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6668</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0235">M. Figgis</persName>
              <date>1922-03-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1903">24 Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6668_img_None_1"  url="php4VZzXz.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6668_img_None_2"  url="phpoE4wP2.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6668_img_0_1"/>
              24 Kildare st. Dublin   March 24th. 1922.    Dear Mr Walsh,   Enclosed you will find two newspaper cuttings of yesterday's date<lb/>which will give you the position of the men in whom you were interested.<lb/>We have, unfortunately, not been able to do very much, because the amount<lb/>we receive only just covers the cases we have on our books, and many of<lb/>the men sent on from the prisoners association are in desperate straits.<lb/>Many of them, as you will see from the cuttings, are there men who fought<lb/>through the war, others are ex-prisoners who have endured torture and<lb/>hardships in prison. Your remark that 'quite a lot of food can be<lb/>missed in twenty- four hours' remains and as the days go by the 'missing'<lb/>mounts up, as we know from those we come in contact with. It is<lb/>unnecessary for them to tell us that they are starving. Their appear=<lb/>=ance is enough.  When the British government had these men in their jails, they<lb/>acted on the assumption that there was nothing like starvation to break<lb/>the morale of these men. They were unsuccessful because something<lb/>entered, which had not been taken into their reckoning and that was a<lb/>spiritual quality that upheld them. That was one thing. It is<lb/>quite another for<seg type="del">t</seg> those men to return home and to find that the people<lb/>for whom so much had been endured, neglect them and leave them and their<lb/>dependants to starve. The Irish people are under the impression that<lb/>existing organisations are caring for these men, but it is stated that<lb/>no funds are available to deal with their cases.  The Lord Mayor of Dublin is Cahirman of This Prisoners Association<lb/><sic>ans</sic> is also trustee of The White Cross Funds and we are sure that if<lb/>anyone could get anything, he would, but as you will see so far, nothing<lb/>has been forthcoming.  Our committee ceases at the end of this month: after which even the<lb/>little we have been able to do  hitherto,   will also cease.<hi rend="underline"></hi>  <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">Could you do anthing for them</hi>?</hi> Either through the Prisoners Associa=<lb/>=ation or through Madame McBride and myself. As we told you when you<lb/>were here, we would prefer that you should deal direct either with The<lb/>Lord Mayor or The men's own organisation. We are pressing for the proper<lb/>care of the wounded and disabled, which will take up a good deal of our<lb/>time. The important thing is to give financial help as soon as<lb/>possible, or it will be a case of what is denied for food. will have to be<lb/>paid out for funeral expenses for a good many of these men.<lb/>Personally I strenuously object to funeral expenses except in cases where<lb/>every precaution has been taken against its necessity. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6668_img_0_2"/>
             2.  The work we have been engaged in for the past eleven months cures one<lb/>of extravagant sentiment: one gets doen to what is described in your<lb/>country as the 'brass tacks', and we can assure you that in the case of<lb/>these men that stage has been reached .   With all good wishes   M Figgis<lb/>Hon. Secy.  Maude Gonne MacBride<lb/>Hon. Treasurer.<lb/>Dublin Relief Committee    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>