<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3544">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Telegraph to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 16 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Chancery Lane, London, England</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This telegraph to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) expresses condolences regarding the death of Francis Sheehy Skeffington, Hanna&#39;s husband, from a meeting of United Suffragists in London. The United Suffragists were a group of suffragists comprised of both men and women of militant and non-militant beliefs.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3544</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0213">Chancery Lane, London, England</persName>
              <date>1916-05-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0278">Chancery Lane, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0184">11 Grosvenor Pl, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3544_img_2948_1"  type="Letter"  url="4724b480b81bde5fee941e94273519a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3544_img_2948_1"/>
             16 May 16  <!-- Not sure how to transcribe sending information -->  MRS SHEEHY SKEFFINGTON 11 GROSVENOR PLACE RATHMINES DUBLIN   MASS MEETING OF UNITED SUFFRAGISTS IN PORTMAN ROOMS LONDON ASSEMBLED TO <lb/>DO HONOUR TO THE MEMORY OF FRANCIS SHEEHY SKEFFINGTON DESIRES TO <lb/>EXPRESS THEIR PROFOUND SYMPATHY WITH YOU IN YOUR GREAT SORROW THEIR <lb/>DEEP SENSE OF THE LOSS THAT HAS BEEN SUSTAINED BY THE GREAT PROGRESSIVE <lb/>MOVEMENT OF WHICH THE SUFFRAGE MOVEMENT IS A PART AND THEIR REALISATION <lb/>ALSO OF THE TRUTH THAT FREEDOM ALL OVER THE WORLD WILL GAIN IMMEASURABLY <lb/>BY HIS COURAGEOUS LIFE AND DEATH 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>