<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4363">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 21 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4363</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1258">37 Royal Avenue, Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4363_img_3719_1"  type="Letter"  url="883b17a2ae9b0dc8d906b08a9ee39ad1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4363_img_3719_2"  type="Letter"  url="eff9666d9588b01379a0e1597ef55bf2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4363_img_3719_1"/>
             37, Royal Avenue, <lb/>Belfast.    21st July 1916.    Dear Sir Edward Carson,   Permit me to say that everyone in Ulster appreciates the <lb/>great skill you have exercised in the recent Home Rule negotiations, <lb/>and whilst we would all have desired the maintenance of the spirit <lb/>of the Covenant, yet, as regards practical politics, the exclusion <lb/>of six Counties is a better proposition than nine.   The success or non-success of your venture — as far as it <lb/>will affect the excluded area — will largely depend upon the pro—<lb/>visions made for economic and simple administration of our local <lb/> affairs.   You are of course aware that besides local adminis—<lb/>trations e.g., City, Urban and District Councils, there are at pre— <lb/>sent the following administrative Boards: — Agriculture and Techni—<lb/>cal Instruction, National Education, Secondary Education, Local <lb/>Government Board, Lunacy Board, National Health Insurance Commiss—<lb/>ion, Prison Board, (Irish Land Commission, Ulster <sic>instalments</sic> <lb/>should be paid through Banks in our province,) Board of Trade, Val—<lb/>uation Department, Board of Public Works, which control in their <lb/>several ways the spending of the grants which we receive from the <lb/>Imperial Exchequer, and in particular, exercise a check on the <lb/>popularly controlled Local Boards.   It would appear to be physically impossible for an Eng—<lb/>lish Home Secretary to carry on these duties without setting up a <lb/>large establishment with highly paid Officials at Whitehall and <lb/>Belfast, and be the cause of a serious overlapping in the adminis—<lb/>tration.   It is the opinion of many that this work should be <lb/>carried out under the control of one individual, as Secretary for <lb/>Ulster, alone responsible to Parliament for the control of these <lb/>Boards, and having his permanent offices in the Capital of Ulster.   If the procedure for Private Bill Legislation for the ex—<lb/>cluded area could be modelled on the Scotch system, with their <lb/>local Enquiry and Provisional Orders confirmed by the Imperial Par—<lb/>liament, it would certainly mitigate the grievances which the <lb/>smaller Urban Councils in Ulster consider they suffer from. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4363_img_3719_2"/>
             Once the new system of administration in Ulster has <lb/>been set up, we will have many fractious critics in our own party <lb/>community, and it is felt that now is the time to simplify the <lb/>Local Government Administration, and give inducements to our <lb/>best local men to offer their services to public boards, the per—<lb/>sonnel of which has unfortunately been latterly deteriorating.   We will, no doubt, also require our own High Courts of <lb/>Justice in Ulster, our own Land Registry and Deeds Registry, and <lb/>in this respect it is suggested that it would be advantageous to <lb/>the commercial Community if the County Court were given a wider <lb/>Jurisdiction, and the time of the County Court Judge not taken <lb/>up with small debt cases, which could easily be transferred to <lb/>the Petty Sessions which might be given more stringent <lb/>powers as to enforcing Decrees for debt.   It is to be presumed that the six excluded Counties will <lb/>have their proportionate share of the grants under the Financial <lb/>Provisions in the Home Rule Bill, and that the position of the <lb/>Lord Lieutenant, as affecting the six excluded Counties, will be <lb/>abolished, and possibly the individual appointed to have control <lb/>of the Ulster <sic>affirs</sic> will take this position as the Head of the <lb/>Magistracy.   My excuse for writing this lengthy letter must be my <lb/>fervent wish that the administration of the six excluded Counties <lb/>may be a pattern to the other parts of the United Kingdom    Yours sincerely,   R.I. Mc<seg type="unclear">Connell</seg>   Sir Edward Carson, K.C., M.P., <lb/>5, Eaton Place, <lb/>London, S.W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>