<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6633">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Michael O'Flanagan to Canon Doorly, 9 December 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael O&#39;Flanagan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter in relation to a query by Bishop Bernard Coyne over funds resting in the parish account. Fr. Michael O&#39;Flanagan had recently been removed from Cliffoney by Bishop Coyne, and as a response the villagers had locked the church in protest, an act of rebellion that lasted for ten weeks. 

Crosna,
Boyle,
Dec 9th, 1916.

My dear Canon Doorly,

I had a letter from Dr. Coyne a few days ago telling me that you had informed him that I had some Cliffoney Parish Funds that I had not handed over to you.

There is only one thing that I know that you can refer to.

A sum of £27 - 4 - 8 was held in the Hibernian Bank in the joint names of Father Shannon, Father Michael Keane and Mr. Bernard Clancy. The deposit receipt was lost or mislaid. In Dec. 1914 I got the three named to sign an indemnity form for the amount and Mr. McCaffery issued a new deposit receipt in the names of Father Shannon Mr. Clancy and myself. The interest accruing at the time was £2 - 14 - 7 making when added to the principal a sum of £29 - 19 - 3.

Father Keane told me that this money was collected by Father O&#39;Reilly for the purpose of building a ball court. Before the ball court could be erected Father O&#39;Reilly was changed and so the matter has not been attended to ever since.

At the time that I got this sum of money I had on hand a sum of £13 - 13 - 6 collected for the Volunteers. Not wishing to have too many seperate deposits in the Bank, I put in this last named sum along with the other, and so the new deposit receipt, dated Jan 9th 1915 was made out for the sum of £43 - 12 - 9.

Afterwards the Volunteers called upon me for the £13 - 13 - 6 to pay for equipment which they had purchased. I knew that if I sent the receipt to Father Shannon for signature, that it would be in danger of being lost like the other one, and I was unable to get the money at the time. Now I hope to get the Bank to transfer the money without Father Shannon&#39;s signature, when I shall be happy to turn over the £29 - 19 - 3 and interest, to you and Mr. Clancy, and anyone else that you may name.

The Cliffoney Church Account is in the joint names of the Bishop, Father Shannon and myself. The Bishop retained possession of Bank Book and Cheque Book. As this account is, as I understand, overdrawn, it can be transferred without consulting me. You will remember that I spoke to you about it last summer, but at the time you did not wish to assume liability for it. Until you were prepared to do so, I did not feel called upon to make any other returns to you. I now send you a statement of Cash Transactions up to the time I left Cliffoney. No cheques were drawn upon the Bank Account in my time, but two deposits were made amounting to £84 - 13 - 9. There are two bills to be paid, one for £5 - 8 - 11 to Mr. D. Hanly of Sligo, and the balance shown £5 - 11 - 5 to me.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6633</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1283">Michael O&#39;Flanagan</persName>
              <date>1916-12-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1482">Crossna, Boyle, County Roscommon, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Doorly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0201">St. Mary's, Sligo, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1942</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6633_img_None_1"  url="phprrOsnO.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6633_img_None_2"  url="phpLkYutd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6633_img_None_3"  url="phpAb9lwA.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6633_img_None_4"  url="php2uOPrB.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6633_img_0_1"/>
              Croona,<lb/>Boyle, <lb/><lb/> <hi rend="subscript"> Dec 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916 </hi>    My Dear Canon Doorly,   <lb/>                             I had a letter<lb/>from Dr. Coyne a few days ago<lb/>telling me that I had some Cliffoney<lb/>Parish Funds that I had not<lb/>handed over to you.         There is only one thing that<lb/>I know that you can refer to.          A sum of £27-4-8 was<lb/>held in the Hibernian Bank<lb/>in the joint names of Father<lb/>Shannon Father Michael Keane<lb/>and Mr. Bernard Clancy. The<lb/>deposit receipt was lost or<lb/>mislaid. In Dec. 1914 I got<lb/>the three named, to sign an<lb/>indemnity form for the amount<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6633_img_0_2"/>
             and Mr. McCaffrey issued a<lb/>new deposit receipt in the<lb/>names of Father Shannon<lb/>Mr. Clancy and myself. the<lb/>interest accruing at the<lb/>time was £2-14-7, making<lb/>when added to the principal<lb/>a sum of £29-19-3.  Father Keane told me that<lb/>this money was collected by<lb/>Father O'Reilly for the purpose<lb/>of building a ball court. Before<lb/>the ball court could be erected<lb/>Father O'Reilly was changed,<lb/>and so the matter has not<lb/>been attended to ever since.  At the time that I got this<lb/>money I had on hand a sum<lb/>of £13-13-6 collected for the<lb/>Volunteers. Not wishing to<lb/>have too many separate deposits<lb/>in the Bank, I put in this 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6633_img_0_3"/>
             last named sum along with<lb/>the other, and as the new<lb/>deposit receipt dated Jan 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>1915 was made out for the<lb/>sum of £43-12-9.  Afterwards the Volunteers<lb/>called upon me for the £13-13-6<lb/>to pay for equipment which<lb/>they had purchased. I knew<lb/><seg type="del">that </seg>if I sent the receipt to<lb/>Father Shannon for signature,<lb/>that it would be in danger<lb/>of being lost like the other<lb/>one, and so I was unable to<lb/>get the money at the time. Now<lb/>I hope to get the Bank to transfer<lb/>the money without Father Shannon's<lb/>signature, when I shall be<lb/>happy to turn over the £29-19-3<lb/>and interest, to you and Mr<lb/>Clancy, and any one else that<lb/>you may name. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6633_img_0_4"/>
             The Cliffoney Church Account<lb/>is in the joint names of the<lb/>Bishop Father Shannon and<lb/>myself. The Bishop retained<lb/>possession of the Bank Book and<lb/>Cheque Book as this account is,<lb/>as I understand overdrawn, it<lb/>can be transferred without<lb/>consulting me. You will remember<lb/>that I spoke to you about it last<lb/>Summer, but at the time you did<lb/>not wish to assume liability for<lb/>it. Until you were prepared to do<lb/>so, I did not feel called upon to<lb/>make any other returns to you. I<lb/>now send you a statement of<lb/>Cash Transactions up to the time<lb/>I left Cliffoney. No Cheques were<lb/>drawn upon the Bank Account<lb/>during my time, but two deposits<lb/>were made amounting to £84-13-9.<lb/>there were two bills to be paid, one for<lb/>£5-8-11 to Mr. D. Hanly of Sligo, and<lb/>the balance shown £5-11-5 to me. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>