<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0519">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Fitzgerald to Michael Gorman, 8 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Susan Fitzgerald (1891-1980) to Michael Gorman. The letter was written while Michael was in the Agricultural College and Susan commiserates Michael on the loss of his mother after a long illness. She mentions that she had joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.), a voluntary organisation providing nursing to wounded British army soldiers, but that she would not like to stay in Maryborough (now Portlaoise) to train.Michael Gorman was one of a large Catholic family living at a farm in Ballinalug, County Laois (then Queen’s County). Susan Fitzgerald was one a Church of Ireland family living in Raheenahone House near Stradbally, County Laois, also in the Slieve Bloom mountains. At the time the letter was written they were involved in a courtship but owing to the religious difference the love affair had to be kept secret. Eventually both were in Dublin: he in the Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin (where he eventually became Professor of Agricultural Botany and Biochemistry and she as a volunteer nurse in the Royal Hospital in Baggot Street. They eventually went to London to marry.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Michael Gorman</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/519</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1259">Susan Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916-01-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1800">Raheenahone House, Stradbally, County Laois</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Michael Gorman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1251">Albert Agricultural College, Glasnevin, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0519_img_1890_1"  type="Letter"  url="1a8d2ac856b41b56058ab2d456eb1203.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0519_img_1890_2"  type="Letter"  url="cf9c6be1dafffea62f6fde9d6e072601.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0519_img_1890_3"  type="Letter"  url="426960b44742aa1e9873119ca56d311c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0519_img_1890_4"  type="Envelope"  url="b8b0ef670759b02a61e8ac4b437d00f9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0519_img_1890_1"/>
                RAHEENAHONE HOUSE,  STRADBALLY,  QUEENS CO.  <hi rend="underline">Friday Night</hi>   My dear Mickie    I was awfully <lb/> sorry to hear of your <lb/> Mother's death. It must <lb/> be a great relief to <lb/> her to be at rest, considering <lb/> how much she has <lb/><hi rend="underline">suffered and what a long</hi><lb/><seg type="unclear">mass card from Nonnie</seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0519_img_1890_2"/>
              time she has been ill. It <lb/> is a very sad time <lb/> for you. I hope you <lb/> are not worrying too <lb/> much. I was away <lb/> staying down at Ballybrophy <lb/> and only arriving back <lb/> last night. How are you <lb/> getting on? I was delighted <lb/> to get your nice long <lb/> letter last week, &amp; I'm <lb/> sure you couldn't miss <cb/><lb/>me half as much as I <lb/> miss you. I often think of <lb/> the very pleasant time <lb/> we had together. I had <lb/> al letter from the Matron <lb/> saying she might be <lb/> able to have me in <lb/> February &amp; I 'm looking <lb/> forward to seeing you <lb/> again even though it <lb/> may be only occasionally <lb/> I might be staying in <lb/> the Nurse's Home, Mary's Rd. <lb/>I wonder where is that?   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0519_img_1890_3"/>
              I have joined the V. A.. D. <lb/> Maryborough. The Commander <lb/> wanted me to stay &amp; get <lb/> experience in Maryborough, but <lb/> that just wouldn't appeal <lb/> to me in the least. I <lb/> was expecting McAuley over <lb/> one evening last week, but <lb/> M <hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Barrett motored over <lb/> to say he  <seg type="unclear">alone</seg>  had to go to <lb/> England &amp; I don't know if <lb/> he is back yet. Did he <lb/> ring you up. I believe they're <lb/> going to Cahir soon &amp; that is <lb/> an awful hole â not even a <lb/> Picture House . I have a few q  <seg type="closer"> With love Ever Yours </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0519_img_1890_4"/>
                M D Gorman Esq;  Albert Agricultural College  Glasnevin  Dublin    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>