<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6667">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Harkin to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 3 February 1921</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Harkin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter, Michael Harkin proposes to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh that he should send a letter to John, B. McGauran, U.S. Surveyor General and a Denver representative on the American Committee for Relief in Ireland. Walsh should convince him of the importance of electing new officers that really have the confidence of the public.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Joseph Cyrillus Walsh Papers. Letters: Harkin, Michael 1920-1921 (2)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6667</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0181">Michael Harkin</persName>
              <date>1921-02-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1662">1929 Champa Street, Denver Colorado, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6667_img_None_1"  url="phpvycbx1.png"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6667_img_None_2"  url="phpgVKMZV.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6667_img_0_1"/>
              1930 CURTIS STREET    (MICHAEL HARKIN} <lb/> PHONE MAIN 5413   DENVER CATHOLIC REGISTER<lb/>OFFICIAL ORGAN OF THE CHURCH OF COLORADO<lb/><lb/> DENVER COLORADO<lb/>1929 Champs Street, <lb/><lb/> Feb. 3 1921 .<lb/><lb/> J.C. Walsh,<lb/>Washington. <lb/><lb/>A Chara:<lb/><lb/>I received tour second telegram Monday. Your letter I am ex-<lb/>pecting at any moment. thanks for your consideration in sending along<lb/>money to meet expenses. I hope soon to see your plans in reference to<lb/>organization. In regard to the city here I do not think it will be ne-<lb/>cessary to any incur any gret expense in getting a start made.  I daresay I should <seg type="del">position</seg> put the position as it exists here<lb/>before you. The F.O.I.F. wlil, I am certain, come into the organ-<lb/>isation in a body. While this looks promising there are drawbacks. for<lb/>example, ong.Joseph Morgan is secreatry of the F.O.I.F. If we have to <seg type="del">x</seg><lb/>take him on in a similar capacity in the A.A.R.I.I. we are going to<lb/>destroy the Irish movement in this city. In regard to the chairman, John<lb/>Conlon, while he would be a desirable member, he is absolutely unfitted<lb/>for leadership.  My suggestion is this. A letter should be sent here from your<lb/>office to , say John B. McGauran U.S. Surveyor General and a Denver rep-<lb/>resentative on the American Committee for Relief in Ireland, his address<lb/>is Post Office building-suggesting that when the F.O.I.F. branch comes<lb/>over, arrangements <seg type="del">should</seg> be immediately made for election of officers<lb/>at a subsquent meeting. The really important thing is to have such a<lb/>letter come to somebody like McGauran urging the absolute necessity of<lb/>electing officers that will command the confidence of the public.  I have been speaking to some influential men here. clerical and<lb/>lay, and they are of opinion that this unfortunate trouble will give<lb/>us an ideal opportunity of getting good business done in this city. The<lb/>Bishop, I know, will support us strongly, and I believe it will be pos-<lb/>sible to get in wealthy men who kept clear of the F.O.I.F. I know that<lb/>some of the men I have in mind accepted membership on the American<lb/>Committee for Relief in Ireland.  Of course not having your views yet on the question of organ-<lb/>ization I do not know what exactly is the best means to set about getting<lb/>in a big membership. Ed. Doyle, a former Labor organiizer, is now organ-<lb/>izing for the Hibernians, and while he is a first class man I know that<lb/>if he were to act for the<hi rend="underline"> <hi rend="underline">Association</hi></hi> as he is doing for the Hibs., he<lb/>would have to be paid. Of course, in regard to giving whole-hearted<lb/>assistance at the preliminary work of setting up the A.A.R.I.I he can<lb/>be counted on to spare no trouble and take no end of pains just out of<lb/><seg type="del">support</seg> for the movement. But systematic organizing I know he would have<lb/>to be paid for. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6667_img_0_2"/>
             Now this is not to be taken as suggesting the appointment of a<lb/>paid organizer. I am merely stating facts that I hope will be of<lb/>assistance. The reason I mention Mr. Doyle's name is because he told<lb/>me he has been corresponding with your office and showed me a letter<lb/>he had from you. Inccdentally he mentioned his position in regard to<lb/>the A.C.H.  Some time ago I understood Peter Golden was coming here to make<lb/>arrangements for the proposed visit of Presdt. De Valera. I wrote<lb/>something then in the Register stating it was expected Golden would<lb/>organize the district for the A.A.R.I.I. That is weeks ago. I know<lb/>that many people were enthusiastic over the prospect. Having one like<lb/>Mr. Golden in Denver till a definite start is made would, I am certain,<lb/>were it possible, be good business. But i daresay he has his hands full<lb/>elsewhere.  The Clan na Gael is not formidable in this state. Most of the<lb/>members <seg type="del">here</seg> are thoroughly disgusted with Devoy and his paper, and<lb/>they will be enthusiastic members of the new organization. I think<lb/>that Pueblo, Trinidad, Grand Junction and the|other cities of the<lb/>state will fall into line without any trouble.  At the moment I do not think there is anything more to be said.<lb/>I daresay <seg type="del">I will</seg> when your letter arrives I shall know how exactly<lb/>you propose we should get to work.   Sincerely yours,<lb/>Michael Harkin      P.S. Someof the things I mentioned might be treated, I think, as<lb/>confidential.  <hi rend="underline">Office now at 1929 Champa.</hi>  P.S.S. It would be a splendid idea to write Dan Sullivan,<lb/>Colorado Hotel 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Street and Tremont, Denver, on the question<lb/>of electing new officers, after the F.O.I.F Come over.<lb/>He is very influential and a good works. I know<lb/><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">these people like to have invitations or letters</hi></hi><hi rend="underline"></hi><lb/><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">direct</hi></hi>.</hi> Meantime, I shall see him. Already I<lb/>have been speaking to John M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gauran and others.<lb/>M.H.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>