<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0338">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Private C. Mumford to the Secretary, Dublin Castle, 22 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>C. Mumford</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Private C. Mumford of the 11th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers, to the secretary in Dublin Castle. Dependants of soldiers fighting during the Great War were entitled to a &#39;separation allowance&#39; and Private Mumford, who had been wounded on active service and was recovering in London General Hospital, writes that his mother&#39;s allowance has been stopped. He enquires about rectifying the situation and a note on the letter suggests that he should contact the military authorities.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary’s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/8789/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/338</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1156">C. Mumford</persName>
              <date>1916-05-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Secretary, Dublin Castle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0338_img_1573_1"  type="Letter"  url="bf1f4b1df1e192dea5eb593544464cb9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0338_img_1573_1"/>
                Monday 22. 5. 1916   14248 Pte. C. Mumford   11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Batt. Royal <seg type="unclear">Inniskilling</seg> Fusiliers  Ward C8 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> London General Hospital  Wandsworth Common  London. S.W  <hi rend="underline">To</hi> the Secretary <hi rend="underline">Dublin Castle</hi> Dear Sir   I understand from my Mother that her <lb/>allowance has been stopped without explanation &amp; I should feel <lb/>obliged if you could let me know the reason. <lb/>I might mention that my mother is a widow &amp; the <lb/>cessation of the allowance is a source of considerate <lb/>hardship to her.   Thanking you in anticipation <lb/>of your giving the case your attention. <seg type="closer"> Yours truly  Pte. C Mumford </seg>  Ack and state that if the allowance <lb/>referred to is an Army Separation allowance <lb/>he should place himself in communication <lb/>with the military authorities.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>