<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6538">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to William Tyrrell Sr., 5 November 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

In the present letter, Willie says that he received four parcels. Included were rubber boots, apples, pears, cakes, and some moldy pheasants. Twenty parcels were delivered to his regiment at the one time. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6538</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-11-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Tyrrell Sr.</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6538_img_None_1"  url="2c3c0361ea646a8d5f5f4e398bac12cf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6538_img_None_2"  url="d09f871b2cf5881894ad9acfd31f626c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6538_img_None_3"  url="350548a1d5f8e9677fa4e3f6df78156c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6538_img_0_1"/>
              5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>/11/17<hi rend="superscript"></hi>    My dear Daddy,   Just after I had sealed up<lb/>my letter yesterday the post<lb/>came bringing your letter of 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi><lb/>and four parcels. One containing rubber<lb/>boots. One containing muffles and a<lb/>delicious box of apples and pears,<lb/>which were in perfect condition.<lb/>Not a particle squashed or spoiled<lb/>and beautifully ripe. Each of the<lb/>other two contained a pheasant but<lb/>they were mouldy but did not smell<lb/>bad. The cakes and other things<lb/>in the parcel were absolutely alright.  I do not know how long they<lb/>had been on the journey as the<lb/>postmarks were unreadable.<lb/>One postmark I think was 20 Oct.<lb/>Everything was quite alright<lb/>except the pheasants and I 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6538_img_0_2"/>
             hardly expected them to be good.  This is particularly bad weather<lb/>for sending them as here<lb/><sic>is</sic> is muggy and close and<lb/>things go bad in no time.<lb/>I am sure you will be glad<lb/>to here they have arrived<lb/>alright. There were about<lb/>20 parcels in the post last night.  I am sure the pastman was saying<lb/>mad things.  By this day fortnight I<lb/>expect I may be near Garrett.<lb/>I hope so anyway. By the<lb/>time you get this letter we will<lb/>be out of the trenches again<lb/>+ in nice comfortable billets.  The book and magazines in the<lb/>parcels were particularly acceptable<lb/>as I had nothing to read and<lb/>nothing else to do.       
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6538_img_0_3"/>
             Now that I have my boots I am<lb/><seg type="del">of</seg> fortified on every end and side<lb/>against any weather that may<lb/>come. Today is bright and<lb/>sunny. The first time the sun<lb/>came out since we have been i<lb/>n the line - + it has made everyone<lb/>more cheerful.  No news. Best love to all<lb/>from   Your most affec Son   <hi rend="underline">Willie</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>