<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1665">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Doran to Matthew Nathan, 14 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Doran</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Henry Doran (1557-?) to Mathew Nathan (1862–1939). Mathew Nathan had become undersecretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell  (1850–1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned as undersecretary due to his misjudgement and failure to stop the Rising. The letter notes a letter sent from Nathan to Doran, a letter which Doran was unable to reply to due to being unwell. It goes on to discuss the situation of the Killorglin town in the Ventry Co. Kerry, explaining that it is the boards practice that when an estate is bought, the surrounding town is also purchased, having previously offered to buy the estate. The letter discusses the protocol for houses which are not occupied by the tenants, the position of the middle men in the purchase and the difficulty in buying and selling the holdings due to the vested interests of the middle men and Lord Ventry(1861-1923). Lord Ventry attempted to sell the estate to the Board however this was declined as the Board would subsequently become the landlord to the middlemen. Doran goes on to state that the tenants, along with the local MP Thomas O&#39;Donnell (1871-1943), have been informed of the situation. It ends stating that the majority of men who wish to but their holding do not have the means to do so. Enclosed is a copy of the Board minutes from 9 March 1916, and a report of the situation in Killorglin form 12 April 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/1916/6893/3/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1665</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0629">Henry Doran</persName>
              <date>1916-04-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0705">23 Rutland Square, Dublin, Co.Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_1"  type="Letter"  url="bfd9e882957b71fe0dc1b669bac6fa5d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_2"  type="Letter"  url="bb748bb032a825902efda6a4aabe396a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_3"  type="Letter"  url="9d138412dc9404b102d6e01769fda480.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="965d7512458c1860a41bb00585819b51.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="1757f581129cb7ccf1a664d7cbc0362c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="8aff165e88647ccec9fd05111e879a14.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1665_img_1124_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="2c87bb408cf9611c4d93973bcb494053.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_1"/>
             (<hi rend="underline">Dictated</hi>)   23 Rutland Square,<lb/>DUBLIN.    14th. April, 1916.    Dear Sir Matthew,   Your letter with reference to Killorglin town,<lb/>Ventry estate, was delivered to me last evening by hand,<lb/>but I was unable to reply to it, as I have been confined<lb/>to bed since Tuesday evening with a cold, and had no<lb/>papers at my home dealing with the estate.  The facts relating to the matter in question<lb/>are as follows: The Board offered to buy under the<lb/>Land Purchase Acts the Ventry estate including the town<lb/>of Killorglin. It has been the Board's practice to<lb/>include in the purchase all such towns when they form<lb/>part of an agricultural estate. On a valuation of<lb/>the property it was ascertained that a number of holdings<lb/>in the town of Killorglin were not in the occupation of  the <lb/>direct tenants who paid their rent to Lord Ventry, but<lb/>in a considerable number of cases the<seg type="del">re</seg> y  were <seg type="del">  </seg> let by the direct<lb/>tenants.   The policy of the Board in dealing with such<lb/>cases was explained to the people of Killorglin by me<lb/>to the following effect: That no tenant could buy<lb/>his holding under the Land Purchase Acts unless he was<lb/>in occupation of it, and that consequently a middleman<lb/>could only buy his holding for cash  down . The Board would<lb/>not put pressure of any kind on a middleman landlord to<lb/>sell his property to the occupying tenant, yet if the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_2"/>
            occupying tenant and middleman came to terms voluntarily<lb/>as to the price which the middleman would accept, the<lb/>Board would advance such portion of the price as they were<lb/>advised the holding was security for, and that the balance<lb/>should be found by the occupying tenant, to whom the Board<lb/>would then sell the holding at the price which they paid<lb/>Lord Ventry for the fee simple of it plus the Stock value<lb/>of the advance made to the occupying tenant to enable him<lb/>to purchase the middle interest. I further said that<lb/>any of the occupying tenants who were able to come to terms<lb/>provisionally with their middlemen would be informed of<lb/>the sum the Board were prepared to advance, if they so<lb/>requested. The judicial Commissioner subsequently made a<lb/>ruling that any holdings not in the occupation of the<lb/>direct tenants would be regarded as intervening interests<lb/>which should be either redeemed or excluded from sale.<lb/>Under this ruling 38 holdings in the town of Killorglin<lb/>held at rents amounting to £107 10 6 were excluded by<lb/>the Land Commission from the Vesting Order, and the sum<lb/>of £2,582, being the purchase price of these intervening<lb/>interests, was deducted from the original offer of the estate.  The Board are advised that it would not be possible<lb/>for them  now  to purchase these holdings <hi rend="underline">under the Land Purchase</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">Acts</hi>, as they are non-agricultural holdings. Lord Ventry<lb/>offered to sell to the tenant for cash, I understand, at<lb/>the prices which the Board had placed on these holdings, but<lb/>this price only included the purchase of the middlemen<lb/>rental. The only way I can see in which the purchase<lb/>can be effected is, if the occupiers can pay the middle—<lb/>men cash to buy out their interest, then they could 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_3"/>
             they could <seg type="del"><seg type="unclear">time</seg></seg> buy out Lord Ventry's interest for cash,<lb/>and if they cannot do this they must remain as they are.  Lord Ventry offered to sell these holdings to<lb/>the Board for <seg type="del">  </seg>  £2582  cash, but the Board by Minute (copy<lb/>of which is enclosed) of the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March, 1915 declined<lb/>to pay cash for the holdings. By doing so they would<lb/>merely be putting themselves in the position of the<lb/>middlem e n 's  landlord, and they would, in my opinion, be<lb/>quite unable to get rid of all the holdings as several<lb/>of the occupiers are unable to provide cash to purchase<lb/>the middle interest.  This question was several times before the Board<lb/>and the town tenants have been informed that the Board<lb/>cannot purchase the holdings. Mr O'Donnell M.P.<lb/>has also been informed. For your information I send<lb/>you portion of the file with the following communications<lb/>marked:  1. Copy of my letter of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> December 1915<lb/>to Mr M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>.Clure, Agent to Lord Ventry.<lb/>2. Letter dated 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <sic>Decemer</sic>, 1915 from Mr<lb/>O'Donnell M.P. to the Secretary.<lb/>3. Letter from Mr. Crowley, Hon. Secretary, Town<lb/>Tenants Leag ue , Killorglin dated 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January, 1916,<lb/>with copy of Secretary's reply thereto.<lb/>4. Letter from Mr Coghlan Briscoe, Secretary<lb/>Town tenants Leag ue  dated 16th. February, 1916,<lb/>and copy reply thereto.  Several of those who are most loudly clamouring to<lb/>purchase their holdings are men who have neither the<lb/>means nor credit to do so.  Yours faithfully,   Henry Doran   <!-- Note on the right of the letter written in red --> Returned to CDBd<lb/>18/4  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_4"/>
             (COPY).  Board Minute <hi rend="underline">dated 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March,</hi> 1915, No. 131.  Read letter from Messrs Rooke and Rooke<lb/>Solicitors for Lord Ventry. to the effect that his<lb/>Lordship was willing to sell for cash the excluded<lb/>holdings in the town of Killorglin, but he would not<lb/>sell portion of them. The Board directed that<lb/>Messrs Rooke and Rooke be informed that they cannot<lb/>provide cash for the purchase of these holdings in the<lb/>town of Killlorglin 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_5"/>
             Royal Irish Constabulary Office.<lb/>DUBLIN CASTLE.  Administrative Division.<lb/>SUBJECT<lb/>R.I. Constabulary,<lb/>Killarney,  12th Apr. 1916.   I beg to report that for some<lb/>time past portion of the little<lb/>town of Killorglin has been<lb/>in the hands of the Congested<lb/>Districts' Board, while the<lb/>remaining portion still belongs<lb/>to various small landlords.<lb/>A deputation of the Town Tenants<lb/>League is, I know, very anxious<lb/>to have an interview with the<lb/>Chief Secretary in the hope of<lb/>inducing him to compel the<lb/>Congested Districts Board to<lb/>acquire the remaining part of<lb/>the town. I am also aware<lb/>that Mr. O'Donnell, the local<lb/>M.P., is interested in this matter<lb/>and has promised the Town Tenants   The Insp General    L.T. Killarney<lb/>For early report direct<lb/> S O'Connell,<lb/>D.H.    10/4/16 <lb/>Under Line<lb/>submitted  S O'Connell<lb/>D.H.   13/4/16  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_6"/>
             to try and procure them an<lb/>interview with the Chief Secretary.<lb/>Since receiving this paper I have<lb/>made discreet enquiry and cannot<lb/>find that this deputation has<lb/>any other motive.  The above is, I am certain, their<lb/>reason for seeking the interview.  [illegible signature] D. 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1665_img_1124_7"/>
            <lb/>IMMEDIATE.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>