<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0854">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Pearse to his mother Margaret Pearse, 3 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Henry Pearse</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a handwritten copy of the last letter Patrick Pearse (1879-1916) wrote to his mother Margaret (1857-1932) before his execution. The letter is not in Pearse&#39;s handwriting. In the letter he says goodbye to his mother, siblings and friends, and refers to financial affairs and some poems he has written. He writes that he has received Holy Communion, that he is prepared to die and claims that &#39;people will say hard things of us now but later on they will praise us.&#39;There is a second letter of Pearse&#39;s copied on to the sheet. This is to his brother Willie (1881-1916), whom Pearse had not realised was due to be executed himself. The third section of the sheet contains the text of the poem &#39;A Mother Speaks&#39;, a poem written by Pearse in Arbour Hill Barracks. Although the letter is a copy, it has the stamp of Kilmainham Detention Barracks upon it, and is dated (by the stamp) 3 May 1916. This suggests that the copy was made within the Barracks itself.Patrick Henry Pearse, writer, educationalist, and revolutionary, was born 10 November 1879 at the family home, 27 Great Brunswick Street (latterly Pearse St.) Dublin, the elder son and second of the four children of James Pearse, stone carver and monumental sculptor, originally of London, and his second wife, Margaret (qv), a shop assistant, daughter of Patrick Brady, coal factor, of Dublin. Pearse was a key member of the military council of the Irish Republican Brotherhood, and was one of the signatories of the proclamation of the Irish republic (largely his own writing), which he read outside the GPO after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. As president of the provisional government, it was Pearse who called the surrender. He was executed on 3 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br. Allen Collection, Pearse Collection, IE/AL/PC/9/32</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/854</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0291">Patrick Henry Pearse</persName>
              <date>1916-05-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1249">Kilmainham Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1330">Margaret Pearse</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1141">St. Enda's College, Rathfarnham, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Last letters before death</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0854_img_2414_1"  type="Letter"  url="3e841b3b80e6424df277380fa385ed27.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0854_img_2414_2"  type="Letter"  url="14758b7bfe9dff22ee39e6740ca86a7a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0854_img_2414_3"  type="Letter"  url="14758b7bfe9dff22ee39e6740ca86a7a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0854_img_2414_4"  type="Letter"  url="14758b7bfe9dff22ee39e6740ca86a7a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0854_img_2414_1"/>
                Mrs Pearse,  St. Enda's College,  <hi rend="underline">Rathfarnham</hi>,   or Cullenswood House,  Oakley Road,  <hi rend="underline">Ranelagh</hi>      Kilmainham Prison,  Dublin    3 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> May 1916    My Dearest Mother,   I have been hoping up to now <lb/> that it would be possible for me to see you again, <lb/> but it does not seem possible. Goodbye, dear, <lb/> dear Mother. Through you I say goodbye to Wow- Wow, <lb/> M.B., Willie, Miss Byrne, Miceal, Cousin Maggie, <lb/> and everyone at St. Enda's. I hope and believe <lb/> that Willie and the St. Enda's boys will be <lb/> safe.   I have written two papers about financial <lb/> affairs and one about my books which I want you <lb/> to get. With them are a few poems which I want <lb/> added to the poems of mine in MS. in the large <lb/> bookcase. You asked me to write a little poem <lb/> which would seem to be said by you about me. <lb/> I have written it and one copy is at Arbour Hill <lb/> Barracks with the other papers, and Father <lb/> Aloysius is taking charge of another copy of it.    I have just received Holy Communion. <lb/> I am happy except for the great grief of <lb/> parting from you. This is the death I should have <lb/> asked for if God had given me the choice of all <lb/> deaths, — to die a soldier's death for Ireland and <lb/> for freedom.    We have done right. People will say hard <lb/> things of us now, but later on they will praise us.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0854_img_2414_2"/>
              Do not grieve for all this, but think of it as <lb/> a sacrifice which God asked of me and of you.   Good - bye again, dear dear mother. May <lb/> God Bless you for your great love for me and <lb/> for your great Faith, and may he remember all <lb/> that you have so bravely suffered. I hope <lb/> soon to see Papa, and in a little while we <lb/> shall all be together again. Wow, Wow, Willie, <lb/> Mary Brigid and mother, Good- bye. I have <lb/> not words to tell my love of you, and how <lb/> my heart yearns to you all. I will call to <lb/> you in my heart at the last moment.  <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">Your son</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Pat</hi> . </seg><lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0854_img_2414_3"/>
                William Pearse  Kilmainham Prison  Dublin    3 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> May 1916    Dear old Billy   Good bye and God Bless you for all your <lb/> faithful work for me at St. Enda's and elsewhere. <lb/> No one can ever have had so true a brother as you.  <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">P.</hi> </seg><lb/> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0854_img_2414_4"/>
              A Mother Speaks  Dear mary, that <sic>didst</sic> see thy first-born Son, <lb/> Go forth to die amid the scorn of men <lb/> for whom he died,   Receive my first-born son into thy arms, <lb/> Who also hath gone out to die for men, <lb/> And keep him by thee till I come to him. <lb/> Dear Mary, I have shared thy sorrow, <lb/> And soon shall share thy joy.  <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">P. H. Pearse</hi> . </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>