<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5264">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 9, July, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell has moved to less comfortable accommodation. He saw King George and Prince Edward drive through a nearby village. 

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5264</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-07-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5264_img_None_1"  url="b593f52ee1c0e046c4eafb23b72378bd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5264_img_None_2"  url="f6c42ce190e07e5d0db041a124d20c33.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5264_img_None_3"  url="024735c82f8b4da1c285c4237fa44089.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5264_img_0_1"/>
              9th July 1917.    My dearest Daddy,   I was delighted to get your grand<lb/>long letter yesterday. and to hear<lb/>all the news. It is a pity the meadows are<lb/>so bad but that is of course on<lb/>account of the dry weather.  M  Round<lb/>here there is not a single thing<lb/>except crops and all look very well.  But I do not know how they are to<lb/>be saved as there is not a man in the<lb/>country. All women but they spend<lb/>their days working in the fields. The<lb/>people are all here exactly as usual<lb/>and you would not know there was<lb/>a war on except that the men are all<lb/>away. We saw <hi rend="underline">George</hi> + Edward<lb/>the day before yesterday. They passed<lb/>through the village in a motor but did not stop. However they slowed down and we had a great look at them. I think it was a pity they did not stop for a minute just for a drink or something. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5264_img_0_2"/>
             We are out of our good billets but<lb/>only moved about three miles  The billets here are rotten so I am<lb/>living in a tent. It is clean<lb/>and very comfortable whereas the<lb/>houses are filthy. Why do they<lb/>put all villages down in a hollow<lb/>here? It is always the same tho!  I meant to write to you<lb/>yesterday but had not time as we<lb/>only got two hours notice to<lb/>move. However luckily they did<lb/>not decide to move us in<lb/>the middle of the night or anything<lb/>silly. Bobby seems to be getting<lb/>on A1. Anyway his letters are<lb/>much more easily read than they<lb/>used to be. His way of spelling<lb/>church always amuses me.  We may leave here in <seg type="del">aboo</seg><lb/>about a week but of course that<lb/>is only supposition. We know 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5264_img_0_3"/>
             Absolutely nothing! We had a<lb/>great thunderstorm on Saturday night<lb/>sometime in the middle of the night.  It was just like the night the big<lb/>tree at the hall door was split.  The lightning was so constant that<lb/>I am sure you could read the<lb/>newspaper. There was hardly one<lb/>second darkness all the time.  I would not wonder if we soon had<lb/>another as the wether feels like it.  Not a word of news so I must<lb/>shut up with very best love to all<lb/>from   Your most affec Son <hi rend="underline"> <lb/>Willie </hi>  Next parcel a few envelopes please<lb/>The chicken in the last parcel was<lb/>most excellent. I eat it last night    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>