<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3961">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Joseph Skeffington, 27 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Joseph Skeffington regarding various topics from the Irish Citizen to the Battle of Verdun. Francis mentions the censorship of his letters and his latest political interest, anti-Taxation meetings.

Francis Sheehy Skeffington, journalist, was a prominent feminist, activist and co-founder of the Irish Women&#39;s Franchise league in 1908. In 1912, he and his wife, Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), founded the suffragist newspaper The Irish Citizen. A staunch pacifist and nationalist, Sheehy Skeffington opposed Irish involvement in the Great War. During the Easter Rising, he attempted to organise a civilian defence force to prevent looting and saved the life of a British officer under fire. Arrested on the evening of Tuesday 25 April 1916, Sheehy Skeffington and two other civilians were shot by firing squad on the morning of Wednesday 26 April.

Joseph Bartholomew Skeffington (1850-1919) was a school inspector and father of Francis Sheehy Skeffington. Francis was privately educated by his father who believed that education, logic and discipline solved all problems.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,612/18-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3961</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-02-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Joseph Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3961_img_3336_1"  type="Letter"  url="8c2bf2136fe7f9b21deb0d44d55487f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3961_img_3336_2"  type="NULL"  url="5c93e0d1137ffa5710f5373d5fe81bc3.JPG"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3961_img_3336_1"/>
             11, Grosvenor Place,<lb/>Rathmines.   27-II.-16.    My Dear Father,   Your Letter and enclosure reached me duly. I think this<lb/>medium is much safer and more satisfactory than any of those you<lb/>suggested, who might not be sufficiently sympathetic. Many<lb/>thanks for the enclosure: I note what you say <sic>re rent</sic>.  The snowy weather continues; I am sure you are feeling it even<lb/>worse in the north, where it is usually colder. Owen has got a<lb/>little cold, but otherwise we are well. I hope you are all well in<lb/>Belfast.  I imagine the IRISH CITIZEN will pull through all right; now<lb/>that all papers are cut down, <sic>it s</sic> reduction will not seem to matter<lb/>so much. Considering all the circumstances, it is astonishing that<lb/>it has managed to keep on so long as it has. If it can keep on<lb/>till the end of the war, it will speedily recover.  Registering American letters would only call down on them the<lb/>attention of the special censors! But there are other methods,—<lb/>effective but slow— which I am using at present. Did you see<lb/>Chesterton's article, in the Illustrated London News of Feb. 26th,<lb/>about my Century article?  This attack on verdun is an amazing thing, —attacking the<lb/>strongest point of the whole line instead of the weakest! Of course<lb/>the calculation is that if this strong point is taken, the whole line<lb/>will crumple up. I fancy the fall of verdun, if it takes place,<lb/>will strengthen the Allies' knowledge that they cannot beat Germany<lb/>on land.  Politically the most interesting thing here is the Anti-Taxation 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3961_img_3336_2"/>
             Meeting arranged for next Tuesday. At present politics have gone<lb/>back to the pre-Davitt days,— a Constitutional movement which is<lb/>sunk in Whiggery and useless, while all the real Nationalism of the<lb/>country is diverted into the physical force movement. That is a<lb/>dangerous position; the Taxation question seems to offer the best<lb/>prospect of creating a new, militant, aggresive, movement not com—<lb/>mitted to physical force. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>