<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3474">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Roberta Mansfield to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington,16 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Roberta Mansfield</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Roberta Kerr Mansfield (1872-1937) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877 - 1946) , Mansfield expresses regret that she cannot act as a speaker at one of Skeffington&#39;s meetings and wile she enjoys speaking about education would have been put off by Skeffington&#39;s impressive line up of other speakers. Mansfield also praises Skeffington&#39;s broad minded and liberal programme. 

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/17-8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3474</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0399">Roberta Mansfield</persName>
              <date>1916-03-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1806">9 Montrose Terrace, Ranelagh, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1937</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3474_img_2883_1"  type="Letter"  url="a2fc0ec1be82efd9cc64e5ef8fce2296.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3474_img_2883_2"  type="Letter"  url="ae4206ac90735a7503d30614ca31ea46.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3474_img_2883_3"  type="Letter"  url="92de445fb87f884e21a25f990c18818f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3474_img_2883_4"  type="Letter"  url="d3d695136f4e7fdc6f4d4960c1f8994e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3474_img_2883_1"/>
             9 Montrose Terrace <lb/>Ranelagh   16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March. <lb/>1916   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Skeffington   Even if I <lb/>had been able to accept <lb/>your very kind invitation <lb/>to speak at one of your <lb/>meetings, I am afraid <lb/>that your formidable <lb/>list of speakers would <lb/>have quite frightened <lb/>me off!   I am not in any <lb/>sense a public speaker, <lb/>though I can manage
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3474_img_2883_2"/>
            to fill a gap at a <lb/>meeting sometimes when <lb/>the subject has to do <lb/>with education.   At present, having <lb/>yielded to persuasion <lb/>and become a member <lb/>of the Secondary Teachers' <lb/>as well as the Graduates' <lb/>committee, I am <lb/>quite unable to under- <lb/>take anything further, <lb/>particularly an <lb/>evening engagement, <lb/>as I have two invalids
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3474_img_2883_3"/>
            on my hands at home <lb/>as well as my school <lb/>work and private <lb/>teaching   I am going to take <lb/>part in the discussion <lb/>at the next Secondary <lb/>Teachers' meeting <lb/>but I am afraid that <lb/>must be my limit.   May I ask you <lb/>to make a note of <lb/>this address? I am <lb/>not at Alexandra <lb/>School every day, and <lb/>I do not think the <lb/>Doctor cares to have
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3474_img_2883_4"/>
            letters for the teachers <lb/>addressed to the school <lb/>in any case.   I very much <lb/>appreciate your wide <lb/>and liberal programme; <lb/>in the past women of strong <lb/>views have been too much <lb/>inclined to carve them- <lb/>selves in opposite camps <lb/>crying "Who so is not with <lb/>us is against us." You <lb/>will do infinite good <lb/>by your broad minded <lb/>policy.   I hear occasionally <lb/>from my cousins Dr. Ross C.S.P. <lb/>he is doing good work among <lb/>the Catholic students of the <lb/>University of Texas.   Yours sincerely   R. Mansfield 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>