<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3697">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Denis Johnston to John Redmond, 4 September 1916 </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Denis Johnston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Denis Johnston writes to John Redmond (1856-1918) on 4 September 1916 to ask him to send another cheque. 

John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers, Collection List No. 118; MS 15,198/2/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3697</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0318">Denis Johnston</persName>
              <date>1916-09-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3697_img_3089_1"  type="Letter"  url="7ea33d754367a22d36296186cff01200.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3697_img_3089_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="29ee86c166036a36f77c8a38d801c3ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3697_img_3089_1"/>
             Cheque sent <lb/><hi rend="underline">9 Sep 1916</hi>   3 Brighton Terrace <lb/>Monkstown <lb/>Co Dublin   4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Sep 1916   My Dear Mr Redmond;   Kindly send me to this <lb/>address by return quarters cheque <lb/>due £60-2-6. I am to offer young <lb/>Mr Redmond &amp; family my deep sorrow <lb/>that your good &amp; brave son has been <lb/>hurt in the trenches &amp; pray that he <lb/>may soon be well again   Kindest regards <lb/>Yours Sincerely   <hi rend="underline">Denis Johnston</hi>   John E Redmond M.P. <lb/>Aughevagh <lb/>Aughrim <lb/>Co Wicklow 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3697_img_3089_2"/>
             Cheque sent <lb/>12 Dec 1916 3 Brighton Terrace, <lb/>Monkstown, <lb/>Co. Dublin   4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dec 1916   My Dear Mr. Redmond;   Kindly send me my quarterly <lb/>cheque due £60-2-6 by return. I <lb/>am really in need of cash at present. <lb/>Please send to this address —   Kindest wishes <lb/>Yours as Ever   Denis Johnston   John E. Redmond Esq M.P. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>