<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4190">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Shaw to James Shaw, December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Shaw to his father, James Shaw, about his life aboard the H.M.S. Excellent. William starts the letter by discussing his his father&#39;s fishing business. William also writes about his prospects of getting put on a merchant ship. William mentions a firing excursion he was on and comments on the first crew members to fire all originating from Ulster.

William Shaw (1893-1934) was a gunner in the Royal Naval Reserve. He volunteered for active service in 1915 and served on ships such as the H.M.S. Excellent and H.M.S. Albemarle, a battle cruiser. Before the war he was a fisherman.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4190</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1233">William Shaw</persName>
              <date>1915-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0161">H.M.S. Excellent, Portsmouth, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4190_img_3562_1"  type="Letter"  url="c01764be264c41ba3af555129454390e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4190_img_3562_2"  type="Letter"  url="d60bd121578908afc4e5511ae8d7b782.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4190_img_3562_1"/>
             H M.S. Excellent <lb/> Portsmouth <lb/> 57 Mess Thursday   Dear Father   Just a few lines in answer to your <lb/> letter I am very glad you are able to fish again I <lb/> see by your letter that you are at the lines and the <lb/> haddocks is plenty and <seg type="unclear">the </seg> main thing is that your are <lb/> getting a good price for <seg type="unclear">them</seg>. You were wanting to know <lb/> how many boys went with Jack he went himself for <lb/>Liverpool but there was a <seg type="unclear">lot</seg> <seg type="del">f</seg>left for Cardiff and <lb/> Glasgow all of them for <seg type="unclear">merchant</seg>men. You were hoping <lb/> that I would get a merchant ship well there is every <lb/> chance of me going as I told you before that all R.N.R. <lb/> men are for the defence of armed merchant vessels.   All men that join them have to sign papers to work <lb/> about the ship as well as at the gun that is when they <lb/> get out the danger zone. I am glad that the boats are all <lb/> doing well. you were <seg type="unclear">wanting </seg> to know about Jack &amp; Andy <lb/> they only done 10 days course it is only a short one to see how <lb/> they get on but there was bigger block heads stayed behind <lb/> to go through for seamen gunner than Andy was at any <lb/> rate he was in a different <seg type="unclear">class</seg>than I was so I only can <lb/> take his word for it. <seg type="unclear">Well</seg>father I was out fishing on
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4190_img_3562_2"/>
            Tuesday and what do you think the first guns crew to <lb/> open fire was all Ulster men and the first shot went right <lb/> through the target so what do you think of that I was <lb/> britch worker and Charlie was butting in the shells and <lb/> a Belfast man was gun layer. well we fired 207 rounds <lb/> the gun was black with heat — she burned all the paint <lb/> I do no know how I got on but I had very good shooting <lb/> I fired 14 rounds and I can tell you I did not <seg type="unclear">fire</seg>much <lb/> for a while god only knows what it is like in France <lb/> I am glad Sam is still all right — I am sure he has <lb/> it pretty cold poor fellow I will close now give my love <lb/> to Jessie.    I remain <lb/> your Loving <lb/> Son Willie   P./S. <lb/> I will be going before the commander <lb/> shortly to see he will read out our points <lb/>I was told that I got a <sic>reck<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>mend</sic> for <seg type="unclear">CL3</seg> <lb/> W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>