<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5357">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cormac Ua Dálaigh to Nora Rice, 18 January 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cormac Ua Dálaigh </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/23/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5357</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0671">Cormac Ua Dálaigh </persName>
              <date>1923-01-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1004">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Co Tirconaill, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Nora Rice</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1460">Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5357_img_4639_1"  type="Letter"  url="08db378348828b5111c8e28517b27016.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5357_img_4639_2"  type="Letter"  url="c68cd39a568eca061f3824cc25876022.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5357_img_4639_1"/>
             P41/23/3   Dromboe Castle<lb/>Stranorlar, Tirconail <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Jan 18th 23</hi> <lb/><lb/> A Nora a cara, <lb/>If you were pleased to get my letter I<lb/>was at least as much so to get yours. Tis so pleasant<lb/>you know, to hear from a friend, especially a <hi rend="underline">Kerry</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">friend</hi>, in a place like this. And then it takes such<lb/>a long time at present to get a reply to a letter<lb/>home that I might almost as well be away in<lb/>S. Africa.  I would hardly be a true Kerryman,<lb/>I suppose if I didn't agree with you in what<lb/>you say about the 'Kingdom'. Of course people<lb/>say we are very Clannish and things like<lb/>that. Well, perhaps, tis true enough, but it does<lb/>neither us or anybody else any harm. Thanks<lb/>for emphasising the all. I hope so but tis<lb/>rather doubtful so far as some of the party<lb/>is concerned.  I remember <seg type="unclear">John</seg> o' Connell alright. I met him<lb/>once after '16. Do you know where his chum Donny<lb/>Daly is now or what he's doing? I heard that <seg type="unclear">Meese</seg><lb/>Kane got married last week also &amp; to a C.<seg type="unclear">sussein</seg> girl<lb/>I suppose you know them both. <hi rend="underline">Ifeaneis</hi> is an old pal<lb/>of mine. I got a bit of a shock some time ago<lb/>when I saw an announcement of what I thought<lb/>was Jerome Riordan's death in the 'Independent'. It<lb/>must have been a mistake though for I've just seen<lb/>in today's paper about another Jeremiah Riordan who<lb/>died a few weeks ago. The live 'Jeremiah' must have<lb/>been mixed up somehow. As well as being a cousin<lb/>Jerome is an old friend of mine and I'd be very<lb/>sorry if anything happened him. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5357_img_4639_2"/>
             I'm sorry to hear of Mrs Rice's illness. That's the<lb/>worst part of war — the mothers always suffer more<lb/>than their sons. I remember she was wild that I<lb/>didn't call when I was in K.mare one evening last<lb/>summer. I was there once before but hadn't time<lb/>that evening.  Of course I should know all the Sullivans<lb/>around Farranfore, but somehow I can't remember<lb/>who your friend Kathleen is. Say 'me' to her any —<lb/>way, and tell her remember me to my friends around<lb/>her place. I will be delighted to hear any news<lb/>that she brings you from there.  Judging the pen—pictures of the Special Corres—<lb/>pondent of the 'Independent' which are appearing<lb/>at present Kerry has indeed gone through the mill<lb/>since we saw it last. You asked me if we see<lb/>the papers at all. Oh yes we do and I will be<lb/>very pleased to get Dublin Opinion. I used like<lb/>it very much except for one Susie sent me<lb/>before Xmas I haven't seen a copy of it for ages.<lb/>Any joural in that line will be very welcome<lb/>here.<lb/><lb/> Ceannaic leat go foill<lb/>Do cara <lb/><hi rend="underline"> Cormac Ua Dálaigh </hi><lb/><lb/> P.S.<lb/>I'm enclosing an answer to Jenny's<lb/>letter along with this. C.U.D. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>