<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2199">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Henry Downing to the Clerk of the Council, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Henry Downing</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis Henry Downing (1865-1931), a solicitor from Kerry to the Clerk of the Council. enclosing a copy of a document pertaining to the Tralee and Dingle Light Railway or Tramway Company Ltd. The document, A Memorial of the Kerry County Council, contains an amendment of the  1896 order.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/4339/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2199</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0126">Francis Henry Downing</persName>
              <date>1916-03-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1365">Tralee, Kerry</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Clerk of the Council</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1931</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2199_img_1646_1"  type="Letter"  url="f8cc7254cbc86e7a774845d04626bfd5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2199_img_1646_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="c8c30e1bdc76edddb680304f9a4cc6ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2199_img_1646_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="aaaeb4ebe0933b0666fedca132497bb2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2199_img_1646_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="2152616e9e99e1e15eacee10b32a7718.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2199_img_1646_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="4e928356866db4c5a0d8479818bd70e1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2199_img_1646_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="5f3b795ff5424231cf5936f31a8451af.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2199_img_1646_1"/>
             22 Denny Street, <lb/>Tralee  <hi rend="underline"> 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> March</hi> 191<hi rend="underline">6</hi>  <lb/>11/16 <lb/><hi rend="underline">PC Dept</hi> <lb/>The Tralee &amp;Dingle <hi rend="underline">Light Railway</hi><lb/>  Sir,   I am obliged for your letter of the <lb/>16 Feb. and I now enclose one type <lb/>written copy of the memorial under <lb/>Seal of the Kerry County Council praying <lb/>for <seg type="del">ad</seg> amendment of the Tralee <lb/>&amp;Dingle Light Railway (Committee <lb/>of Management) order 1896 and <lb/>will thank you to acknowledge <lb/>receipt of same.   Yours faithfully   F.H. Downing   The Clerk of the Council <lb/>Dublin Castle <lb/>Dublin 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2199_img_1646_2"/>
            THE MEMORIAL <lb/>OF THE <lb/>COUNTY COUNCIL OF THE COUNTY OF KERRY <lb/>In the Matter Of The <lb/>TRALEE and DINGLE LIGHT RAILWAY or TRAMWAY COMPANY LIMITED.<lb/> <!-- line --> <lb/>TRAMWAYS (IRELAND ) ACTS. <!-- line --> <lb/>TO HIS EXCELLENCY THE LORD LIEUTENANT &amp; HIS MAJESTY'S <!-- line --> <lb/>PRIVY COUNCIL IN IRELAND.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2199_img_1646_3"/>
            <hi rend="underline">MEMORIAL</hi><lb/>  THE TRAMWAYS (IRELAND ACTS, 1860 TO 1896; THE TRALEE <lb/>AND DINGLE LIGHT RAILWAY ORDER, 1888; THE TRALEE AND <lb/>DINGLE LIGHT RAILWAY ORDER, AMENDMENT AND DEVIATION <lb/>AND ABANDONMENT ORDER 1889; THE TRALEE AND DINGLE <lb/>LIGHT RAILWAY (COMMITTEE OF MANAGEMENT) ORDER, 1896; <lb/>AND THE LOCAL GOVERNMENT (IRELAND ) ACT 1898.  <!-- line --> <lb/>TO HIS EXCELLENCY THE LORD LIEUTENANT <lb/>IN COUNCIL. <!-- line -->  THE MEMORIAL of the County Council of the County of <lb/>Kerry, the Owners of the Tralee and Dingle Light Railway <lb/>or Tramway Company, Limited,  <lb/>SHEWETH AS FOLLOWS:-  1. THE Tralee and Dingle Light Railway of Tranway Company <lb/>Limited was by the Tralee and Dingle Light Railway Orders <lb/>1888 and 1889 made under the provisions of the Tramways <lb/>(Ireland) Act 1883 and the Acts incorporated with and amend- <lb/>ing the same authorised to and did construct, equip and <lb/>maintain and work certain light Railways therein mentioned <lb/>between Tralee and Dingle in the County of Kerry with a <lb/>branch line to Castlegregory in the said County which said <lb/>Light Railways are hereinafter called "the Undertaking".   2. IT was provided by Article 48 of The said Order of 1888 <lb/>that, on the happening of the events in the said Article set <lb/>forth, the Undertaking and all the property of the Promoters <lb/>connected with it should become the property of the Grand <lb/>Jury of the County of Kerry, and that the Lord Lieutenant <lb/>might thereupon order that the Grand Jury appoint a Committee <lb/>of Management for the purposes of the Undertaking, and it
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2199_img_1646_4"/>
            was provided by Article 49 of the said Order that every <lb/>Committee of Management so appointed should be constituted <lb/>in such manner and should have such powers with reference <lb/>to the Undertaking as the Lord Lieutenant might order and <lb/>the Members of the Committee should be paid by the Grand <lb/>Jury, out of the monies to be levied as therein provided <lb/>such reasonable remuneration as The Lord Lieutenant might <lb/>by General or Special Order, prescribe.   3. BY Order entitled The Tralee and Dingle Light <lb/>Railway ( Committee of Management) Order 1896 made under <lb/>the provisions of the said Order of 1888 The Lord Justices- <lb/>General and General Governors of Ireland ordered that the <lb/>Grand Jury of the County of Kerry should appoint a <lb/>Committee of Management for the purpose of the Undertaking <lb/>and that, subject to any order which the Lord Lieutenant <lb/>might from time to time make, the said Committee of <lb/>Management should be constituted and have the powers <lb/>with reference to the Undertaking thereinafter set forth <lb/>and inter alia as follows:-  1. (a) the Grand Jury shall as each Summer Assizes <lb/>appoint six persons who shall form a Committee <lb/>of Management for the purpose of the Undertaking.   (b) The Grand Jury at each Summer Assizes shall <lb/>nominate one of the members of the Committee to be <lb/>Chairman of the Committee.   (c) the Grand Jury may at any Spring Assizes <lb/>nominate a person or persons to fill any vacancy or <lb/>vacancies which may have occurred in the Committee <lb/>of Management as therein.   (d) Every member of the Committee of Management <lb/>nominated as aforesaid shall be a <seg type="unclear">cesspayer</seg> of the <lb/>County of Kerry owning or occupying rateable lands <lb/>and hereditaments in the guaranteeing area of a <lb/>minimum value of £20. At least one of such members <lb/>shall in addition be a Town Commissioner of Tralee and for this purpose the Town Commissioners <lb/>of Tralee shall at each Summer Assizes submit the <lb/>name of one of the Town Commissioners to the Grand <lb/>Jury who shall thereupon appoint such Town <lb/>Commissioner to be a member of their Committee.   5. At any ordinary or special Meeting of the <lb/>Committee any three members of the Committee shall <lb/>form a quorum.   8. The Committee ma appoint a Secretary of the <lb/>Committee.   10. The remuneration of the Committee of Management <lb/>and the Secretary shall until further order of <lb/>The Lord Lieutenant (which he is hereby empowered <lb/>from time to time to make) be as follows (that is <lb/>to say):-    (a) the Chairman shall be paid such <lb/>salary as the Grand Jury at the Summer Assizes <lb/>may from time to time determine, not exceeding <lb/>£70 per annum.   (b) Every other member of the Committee <lb/>of Management shall receive the fee of £1 per <lb/>annum   (c) the Secretary of the Committee shall <lb/>be paid such sum as the Grand Jury may from <lb/>time to time with the approval of the Lord <lb/>Lieutenant direct.   34. If at any time hereafter it shall appear expedient <lb/>or desirable that any alteration should be made in <lb/>the constitution or functions of the Committee of <lb/>Management such alterations may be made by order of <lb/>the Lord Lieutenant on the application of the Grand <lb/>Jury.   4. BY virtue of the Local Government (Ireland) Act 1898 the <lb/>Undertaking and all the powers and duties of The Grand Jury <lb/>in relation thereto including those of appointing the Committee
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2199_img_1646_5"/>
            of Management thereof became vested in the County Council <lb/>of the County of Kerry, your Memorialists. Your <lb/>Memorialists, in appointing the said Committee of Manage- <lb/>ment have since the year 1898 always followed the custom <lb/>adopted by the Grand Jury and ( in unison with all other <lb/>County Councils in Ireland similarly circumstanced) have <lb/>always appointed a mixed Committee consisting of one <lb/>member of the Urban District Council of Tralee and the <lb/>remainder partly of qualified members of their own body <lb/>and partly of qualified outsiders. The County Council has <lb/>always appointed a member of the Committee other than a <lb/>member who is also a member of the County Council to be <lb/>the Chairman of the Committee, and the County Council has <lb/>paid to the Chairman a salary of £70 per annum and to each <lb/>other Member of the Committee a fee of £1 per annum in <lb/>accordance with the provisions of Article 10 of the said <lb/>Order of 1896, which provisions they are advised are <lb/>mandatory.   5. RECENTLY, that is to say in the month of November <lb/>1915 on a Case stated by the Justices of Kerry for the <lb/>consideration of The King's Bench Division of The High <lb/>Court of Justice in Ireland entitled the King ( <lb/>Moriarty) Complainant, Michael J O'Donnell Defendant, it <lb/>was decided by that Court that the payment of the <lb/>aforesaid fee of £1 per annum disqualified the recipient <lb/>from being a member of the County Council in as much the <lb/>said payment constituted the membership of the Committee <lb/>of Management an office or place of profit under or in the <lb/>gift of the County Council within the meaning of Article <lb/>12 (4) of the Application of Enactments Order of the <lb/>22nd December 1898 made under the Provisions of the Local <lb/>Government (Ireland) Act 1898 and that the Defendant who <lb/>was a member of the said Committee and of the County <lb/>Council was thereby disqualified from being a member of the County Council. The effect of this decision is that <lb/>The County Council can no longer appoint a member of their <lb/>own body to be a member of the Committee of Management of <lb/>The Undertaking, which is their property and for the <lb/>working and control and management of which they are <lb/>responsible and that the County Council can have practically <lb/>no voice in, but must entrust the working and control and <lb/>management of The Undertaking to outsiders and your <lb/>Memorialists are of opinion that they cannot, while this <lb/>condition of affairs exists exercise any real control over <lb/>or supervision of or discharge their duties in connection <lb/>with the Undertaking and The Members of the Count in <lb/>giving their decision in the said case expressed their <lb/>opinion that this state of affairs was a matter of grave <lb/>public importance and that a remedy ought to be provided.   6 . Your Memorialists are advised that the Lord Lieutenant <lb/>in Council has power under the <sic>Tranways</sic><!-- correct spelling --> Ireland Act 1883 <lb/>and the Acts incorporated with and amending the same and <lb/>under the provisions of the said Orders of 1888 and 1896 to <lb/>make orders amending the said Orders and giving them relief <lb/>in the premises.   YOUR MEMORIALISTS therefore pray that <lb/>the LORD LIEUTENANT in Council will <lb/>make an Order amending the said <lb/>Order of 1896 by annulling the <lb/>provisions of Article 10 (b) thereof <lb/>and in lieu thereof providing that <lb/>no fee or remuneration shall be <lb/>paid by the County Council of the <lb/>County of Kerry to, or shall be <lb/>received by, such members of the <lb/>Committee of Management as shall be <lb/>members of the County Council but <lb/>that the County Council shall be at <lb/>liberty to pay each other member of <lb/>the Committee, save the Chairman, a
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2199_img_1646_6"/>
            fee of £1 per annum, or that such <lb/>other provisions as may seem <lb/>moot in that behalf may be made.   F.H. DOWNING  <lb/>Solicitor for the County Council of the County of Kerry  17 D'Olier Street, Dublin.  <lb/>ALL NOTICES pursuant to the Tramways (Ireland) Acts in <lb/>relation to the said proposed Order may be served <lb/>on the said Solicitor at the said address <lb/>17 D'OLIER STREET, <lb/>DUBLIN.  Sealed with the Seal <lb/>of the County Council <lb/>this second day of <lb/>March 1916 in the <lb/>presence of <lb/>Edmond <seg type="unclear">Harty</seg> <lb/>Assistant Secretary <lb/>to the Council 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>