<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6494">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Victoria Mary Tyrrell, 19 November 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to his sister Victoria Mary (&#34;Minnie&#34;) Tyrell. Willie tells his sister that his regiment is about to move from France to Germany (&#34;hunland&#34;) and describes the effects which the First World War has had on the French countryside. It seems that Willie was part of the British troops who occupied the Rhineland after Germany&#39;s defeat. This occupation began in December 1918 and lasted till June 1930. The British headquarters were situated in the German city of Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6494</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1919-11-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6494_img_None_1"  url="f45104ea2ce46d4e8dd2227159e8b553.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6494_img_None_2"  url="5ff954e4d217e5a80487cda3c788a98a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6494_img_0_1"/>
              Tuesday 19/11/19    My dear Min   Today I spent with Garrett in + near Le<lb/>Quesnoy. I told you in yesterdays letters<lb/>that I had a note from him telling me where he was<lb/>so I started at 9 this morning + found him<lb/>quite easily. So we had great chat. I met him<lb/>on the road and there we stood talkin of days<lb/>that are gone. But not for long. We went for<lb/>a walk to inspect the city + then returned to<lb/>Garretts mess for lunch. I started for home<lb/>about 3 pm as I wanted to get back before<lb/>dark. You see I am afraid of the dark<lb/>always !! G. is looking very well and he too is<lb/>en route to hunland but does not expect to<lb/>move for sometime yet. He is coming along to see<lb/>me one day soon. You might tell Sissie all<lb/>this. There was no post in today and so<lb/>no letters from anyone - but that means<lb/>a double ration tomorrow. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6494_img_0_2"/>
             The weather has changed again and today<lb/>was cold + damp but no frost at all.<lb/><lb/>The roads are in a fearful state especially<lb/>in Mormal Forest. Nearly the whole forest<lb/>has been cut away + only the stumps of the<lb/>trees remain. The hun must have taken<lb/>thousands + thousands of tons of lumbers out<lb/>of it.  Our moves I believe are to be Namur <sic>Liege</sic> - Cologne - + very nice too !  Not a word of news   Very best love to all<lb/>Your most affec brother   Willie  P.S. My pilot Rowney is a great pal of Hamilton's<lb/>the dear little <seg type="unclear">elve</seg>. They spent six weeks<lb/>together in next beds to each other in hospital<lb/>at Malta. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>