<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0438">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 3 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (1866-1955). This letter describes the shock the medical staff had when two of the sisters almost drowned while swimming in the channel. The weather in France is very warm and Marie expresses her relief that she is no longer in Malta. She inquires after people at home.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>France Letters, B/F/1/64</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/438</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-08-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1543">Hardelot, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1257">Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_1"  type="Letter"  url="ee05664be0aa341d5ad6b501b67a6e22.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_2"  type="Letter"  url="fa8ff254288c9f4f1f58d8b7eb4343ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_3"  type="Letter"  url="58a2517ed9b0e8ee65b1e4d808cca080.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_4"  type="Letter"  url="147ed7cd88afa8849c2ae4ee7b159863.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_5"  type="Letter"  url="57bc02a79efacb46fdc09891d3b4d0a8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_6"  type="Letter"  url="87e8a6f45a7786418ad5ea7d5fd123e7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_7"  type="Letter"  url="848fb3d5535b92ffdeff493abcb0e3a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_8"  type="Letter"  url="c7295d7735e19f7c78fc86f7db57fe1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0438_img_1773_9"  type="Letter"  url="ee05664be0aa341d5ad6b501b67a6e22.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_1"/>
                3 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> August 1916    My very dearest Mother   A thousand thanks <lb/> for your very nice long letter <lb/> dated July 28 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. I am delighted <lb/> to hear you are feeling quite <lb/> yourself again. I suppose this <lb/> will find you hard at work <lb/> at home again looking after the <lb/> family, who I hope are well. <lb/> How is my darling Andrew &amp; <lb/> Desmond? also all the school <lb/> boys &amp; Bee, tell her to write <lb/> me one of her nice cheery <lb/> letters with all her news &amp; <lb/> ideas. Imagine I have never written  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_2"/>
              to M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Sheil yet <sic>infact</sic> I have <lb/> given the Hocks away to some <lb/> of the men as we were very <lb/> short of note paper one day. I <lb/> must really try &amp; write to her <lb/> to-day - You will be sorry to <lb/> hear my Tents 8 &amp; 9 have been <lb/> closed again &amp; my patients have <lb/> be moved down to <seg type="unclear">Sy</seg> &amp; I am <lb/> there again, it seems such a <lb/> pity as we have just got the <lb/> whole place straight &amp; the tents <lb/> to look very nice, Matron even <lb/> remarked them to the Colonel <lb/> yesterday &amp; we have only been <lb/> open a fortnight. On account <lb/> of this Diarrhea Epidemic we have <lb/> been unable to get convoy but <lb/> it seems to have fairly died  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_3"/>
              out again &amp; we hope to start <lb/> taking convoys again next week <lb/> The poor patients were very sorry <lb/> leaving, I must say we were a <lb/> very happy party, the patients were <lb/> very nice, all Australians &amp; the 2 <lb/> orderlies quite nice men -   We all had a terrible shock here <lb/> yesterday morning when two of <lb/> the Sisters were nearly drowned. <lb/> They went out Bathing after breakfast <lb/> &amp; the <sic>tied</sic> was rather far <lb/> out but coming in &amp; there is a <lb/> very dangerous <sic>channell</sic> which was <lb/> dry when <sic>the</sic> went out &amp; filled <lb/> in very quickly, one <seg type="unclear">onV</seg> the Sisters <lb/> got a very bad cramp so the <lb/> other went out to help her, I <lb/> may tell you neither of them could <lb/> swim, but unfortunately the one who  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_4"/>
              got the cramp was an <sic>ennormous</sic><lb/> woman &amp; the other small so that <lb/> the one pulled the other down <lb/> at last some people on the sand <lb/> heard the yells also one of the <lb/> patients undress &amp; went in <lb/> also an <seg type="unclear">orderly</seg> from the <lb/> Officer's Mess, he went out &amp; <lb/> just found Sister <seg type="unclear">Robinson</seg> in <lb/> time before she sank for the 3 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi><lb/> time &amp; was   her in thinking <lb/> she was the only one when he <lb/> felt something caught round his <lb/> legs &amp; put down his hand to <lb/> find it was the other sisters hair <lb/> round his legs of course she was <lb/><sic>pratically</sic> gone &amp; they had to <lb/><seg type="unclear">do</seg> artificial respiration &amp; gradually <lb/> got her round again, <sic>ofcourse</sic> both  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_5"/>
              their lungs are full of sand &amp; <lb/> sea water, Sister Robinson is doing <lb/> fairly well but Sister <seg type="unclear">Prisly</seg> is <lb/> having a hard fight, poor things <lb/> it is very sad, you can imagine <lb/> the shock we all got— It is a <lb/> great pity the beach is so dangerous <lb/> of course they were told not to <lb/> go out so far by another sister <lb/> that was bathing but they only <lb/><sic>laughted</sic> at the idea. Thank the <lb/> Lord they were not drown &amp; I <lb/> hope they will get on alright— <lb/> It may stop all the bathing which <lb/> will be a great pity as it is <lb/> very hot here lately &amp; they do <lb/> enjoy it so much in their off <lb/> time but at the same time <lb/> I can quite understand, it is  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_6"/>
              a terrible worry &amp; <sic>responsiblity</sic> for <lb/> Matron, when it is so dangerous— <lb/> I suppose you are having the same <lb/> glorious weather, it is terribly hot <lb/> here, I am only <sic>two</sic> delighted <lb/> to think I am not in Malta now <lb/> it must be terrible the heat, we <lb/> had a letter yesterday from one <lb/> of the Sisters, she says the heat <lb/> is over powering &amp; that they <lb/> are terribly busy convoys of <lb/> fever from Solonika every day. I <lb/> hope you have had good news of <lb/> Tommy lately &amp; that he does not <lb/> find the heat too much— Oh I <lb/> wish this war would end soon— <lb/> I am very sorry <sic>the</sic> hear about <lb/> Bernard &amp; Dick O'Kelly &amp; hope they <lb/> will soon get stronger <seg type="unclear">all</seg> the same  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_7"/>
              I think they are well out of France <lb/> are all the others well I have been <lb/> meaning to write to M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> O'Kelly but <lb/> there always seems so much to <lb/> be done in off duty time but <lb/> now that my tent is fixed up <lb/> it ought to be alright— Will <lb/> you please thank Violet &amp; <seg type="unclear">Ethel</seg> a <lb/> thousand times for the books they <lb/> arrived quite safely &amp; were a <lb/> real godsend.   The garden must be looking <lb/> heavenly now, will all the flowers <lb/> &amp; the Sweet Pea, is Henessy showing <lb/> anything at Kingstown this <lb/> year— How I often long to be <lb/> at home to enjoy it all but <lb/> at the same time it would be <lb/> very hard to remain at home &amp; <lb/> see &amp; know how short they are  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_8"/>
              for help out here &amp; at home <lb/> I believe they cannot get enough <lb/> V.A.Ds &amp; are taking people without <lb/> certificates at home now.   No I have not heard anything <lb/> more of G. Grattan I intend writing <lb/> to find out how he is to-day <lb/> I wonder did he get home for <lb/> a rest by any chance — I hope <lb/> he did— How are all the relations <lb/> Granny, Aunt Lissy &amp; Uncle Frank. <lb/> Now I must close as I want <lb/> to write to Tommy, did he ever <lb/> say he got the cake from <lb/><seg type="unclear">Busarch</seg> <seg type="closer"> With every loving wish &amp; thought <lb/> I remain <lb/> dearest Mother, your loving&amp; <lb/> grateful daughter   <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0438_img_1773_9"/>
               I am writing <lb/> to Switzers <lb/> to send me <lb/> out <sic>2pr</sic> of <lb/> shoes as I <lb/> have worn <sic>2pr</sic><lb/> out already <lb/> &amp; in the heat <lb/> &amp; sand we <lb/> have to change <lb/> very often. I <lb/> Am also asking <lb/> them to send <lb/> bill as I <lb/> would like <lb/> to pay for <lb/> them <lb/> Marie   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>