<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3460">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from D. C., Stafford, England, to James Ryan, 9 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>D. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.
The letter writer is from Stafford, where Ryan spent some time in prison and the letter was written after his return to Ireland. It makes reference to the campaign to secure amnesty for the release of the remaining 1916 leaders. It also refers to the execution of Roger Casement who was arrested before the outbreak of the Rising and hanged in England in August 1916. Reference is made to a campaign in the press to &#39;blacken&#39; Casement&#39;s name and the infamous &#39;Black Diaries&#39; that were used in evidence against Casement at his trial.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/48(1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3460</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0105">D. C.</persName>
              <date>1916-08-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0354">Acton Trussell, Stafford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3460_img_287_1"  type="Letter"  url="7003cb98215db64a23dff4e9967a0c2f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3460_img_287_2"  type="Letter"  url="47cb68534929b0337653fe8afa17bd66.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3460_img_287_3"  type="Letter"  url="2fb53f5daf874637e891c7486098225b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3460_img_287_4"  type="NULL"  url="669fc000d7fa1047e17442b985fbc37f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3460_img_287_1"/>
             Perhaps if you know <lb/> anything definite of <lb/> "Crowley" you will let me know. His people <lb/> would be pleased to know something definite <lb/> about him.   All here are very pleased at your release <lb/>and all hope you will be able to <lb/> keep the flag flying.   Yours very sincerely D.C.   The Grange <lb/>Acton Trussell <lb/>Nr. Stafford   9 Aug. 1916   Dear Jim,   Thanks very much for <lb/>your letter. I had already heard <lb/>from Fr. Moore that you had been <lb/> released and was glad to hear it. <lb/> Fr. Moore told me that of the <lb/> Stafford contingent only about <lb/> 100 remained in internment, all <lb/> the others having been released. <lb/> I hope this is not an exaggeration <lb/> but it seems too good to be true; <lb/> though it is evident a large <lb/> number have been set free.    Is there no possibility of any
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3460_img_287_2"/>
            public agitation in Ireland for <lb/> a general amnesty?    They hanged Casement alright, <lb/> though most of us expected they <lb/> would not have had the pluck <lb/> to do so. That they all had the wish <lb/> we knew. Still I have no doubt <lb/> he was quite prepared to die <lb/> and the failure of the reprieve <lb/> petitions did not worry him <lb/>much. The most disgraceful <lb/> thing about the whole affair <lb/> was the inspired attempt on <lb/> the part of a section of the press <lb/> to blacken his character.   We were treated to all sorts <lb/> of hints as to the horrible life <lb/> of vice he had led as shown <lb/> by his entries in his diaries, etc.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3460_img_287_3"/>
            Even The TImes was moved to <lb/> protest against it as being <lb/> generally disgraceful and un-English.    Is there any movement a foot <lb/> to subscribe Ginnell's <seg type="unclear">price</seg>. I <lb/> think it would be great to <lb/> organise a penny subscription <lb/> and I have no doubt the <lb/> necessary 24,000 pennies would <lb/> be forthcoming. It would probably <lb/> make the authorities regret they <lb/> had interfered. And after all <lb/> we would have reason to thank <lb/>   <lb/>the Stafford Commandant.   By the way, did you know <lb/> of any man named Crowley <lb/> connected with  the  Sinn Fein movement.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3460_img_287_4"/>
            in Dublin. If there was such a person <lb/>you would of course know of him <lb/>My reason for inquiries is that <lb/>These are some friends of mine of that <lb/>name in the South of Ireland — <lb/>formerly they lived in Banteer now <lb/>at Rathmore. Several of them have <lb/>been at <seg type="unclear">Siemans</seg> one in particular <lb/>called by the family   He was <lb/>rather a mild case and left Stafford <lb/>some years ago. Very little has been <lb/>heard of him since but of late there <lb/>had been rumours that he was <lb/>acting as a sort of go-between for <lb/>the Volunteers &amp; the Irish Americans or <lb/>at any rate in some such capacity. <lb/>In fact the day you were leaving Stafford <lb/>one of them to whom I was speaking at <lb/>the carriage window on learning I was <lb/>from Co. Cork Exclaimed 'Oh your friend <lb/>Crowley got away alright'. I had <lb/>not time to question him better. <lb/>Of course the expression "your friend" was <lb/>just a phrase and only a wee coincidence
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>