<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2642">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from  Terence Duffin to Maria Duffin, 29 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terence Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.


A fairly chatty letter from the front in which Terry writes about the weather, his family, a visit to his battalion from Colonel  Bob Wallace (which he knows personally). He also writes to his mother about conflicting orders for the men of is battalion. 

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2642</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0305">Terence Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1209">Head Quarters,107th Infantry Brigade, British Expeditionary Force </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0218">Dunowen, Belfast, ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2642_img_2068_1"  type="Letter"  url="04848706b85146801afdf31d15049a92.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2642_img_2068_2"  type="Letter"  url="f883f49bb87b9487f980a228069eff51.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2642_img_2068_3"  type="Letter"  url="dc9980582a02f9525a52a72d446d75d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2642_img_2068_4"  type="Letter"  url="185182832609fd8b4826bfe18c14b6fc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2642_img_2068_5"  type="Letter"  url="295bd3dc0a854e31280c1b204d300d7e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2642_img_2068_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/B<lb/><lb/> Hd Qrs<lb/>107 Infy. Bds<lb/>B. E. F.    Dearest Mamma   You appear from the papers to be<lb/>having much the same weather<lb/>at home as we are out here —  We had quite a heavy snow-<lb/>fall and had frosts at night<lb/>though it thaws a bit during<lb/>the day. With all the traffic about here you can<lb/>imagine the condition of the  <lb/>38    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2642_img_2068_2"/>
             D2109/10/1/B  roads. Our supplies and<lb/>  <seg type="unclear"></seg> have become somewhat<lb/>disorganised, likewise the<lb/>mails— I got about <seg type="unclear">from</seg><lb/>if Ruth's <seg type="unclear">Whip's</seg> tonight dating<lb/>back to the 21<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi>! I hope<lb/>it will improve soon as it<lb/>makes matters very uncomfortable.<lb/>We are somewhat disorganised<lb/>at present. Bds<lb/>Hd Qrs and two <seg type="unclear">Battns</seg><lb/>are at present in what are      <lb/>39   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2642_img_2068_3"/>
             D2109/10/1/B<lb/><lb/>called rest billets: the other<lb/>two still remain in the trenches,<lb/>one for work only. Rest<lb/>billets mean that you are<lb/>beyond shot and shell but<lb/>work continues just the same—<lb/>railways to be built, reserve<lb/>line trenches to be improved etc.<lb/>etc. We have been recieving<lb/>orders and  orders for<lb/>the last three days: at one moment<lb/>we are going right back to    <lb/>40  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2642_img_2068_4"/>
             D2109/10/1/B  doing this in several places<lb/>lately.  Col. Bob Wallace was<lb/>out here on a Cook's tour - He<lb/>stayed with the 109<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th Bds. </hi></hi> and looked fat and flourishing<lb/>- the men were all pleased to<lb/>see him - many, of course, knew<lb/>him personally and nearly<lb/>all by sight. I don't<lb/>think however that trench<lb/>warfare would suit him.   <lb/>45 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2642_img_2068_5"/>
             D2109/10/1/B  I have had letters from<lb/>Ruth, Edmund and Aunt<lb/>Ellen - all very welcome.  Nothing much else to tell<lb/>you at present - I keep<lb/>fit though just recovering<lb/>from a bad cold which I<lb/>have now passed on to the<lb/>General.  Best love<lb/>from your own<lb/><hi rend="underline">Terry</hi>  <lb/> P.S. Many thanks<lb/>for the basin which<lb/>arrived here safely<lb/>How much do I<lb/>owe you for it?   <lb/> <hi rend="underline">29</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">2</hi><lb/>16   46    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>