<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3159">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to Katie, November 20 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Orphaned at age 7, Peter Mooney and his sister Katie Mooney were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This letter part of a collection of over ninety surviving letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3159</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-11-20</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Katie</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3159_img_2580_1"  type="Letter"  url="2b4289fc15942cc79125028d1dff9fd8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3159_img_2580_2"  type="Letter"  url="4b0b999f4eecba64391c9c50f3e79a0a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3159_img_2580_3"  type="Letter"  url="f3318830944c1e11e0b77f1387344edd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3159_img_2580_1"/>
             Nov 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1915   Dear Katie,   I received the Breeches <lb/>&amp; Putters alright this morning. <lb/>Unfortunately they are the wrong <lb/>ones. You know the riding <lb/>Breeches with no strapping <lb/>they are firstly a <sic>Kakhi</sic> <lb/>colour. The Putters will <lb/>hardly do you can get a <lb/>good thick pair in Dublin <lb/>You can get them where you <lb/>got the <seg type="unclear">Numerals</seg> &amp; send them <lb/>on. It will send back the <lb/>others when I get them 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3159_img_2580_2"/>
            The sort of thing <sic>Picquet</sic> <lb/>duty is as follows. We go <lb/>on Duty at 4:30 until 6:06 <lb/>next morning. We have to be <lb/>on the watch live farm at <lb/>a time minding the Horses. <lb/>The night I was on duty I <lb/>was out from 6.06 until 8.06 <lb/>&amp; then again from 12.02 until 2.06. <lb/>We have to see that nothing <lb/>happens the Horses during the <lb/>night. It is a lonesome <lb/>job. I am glad poor old <lb/>Barry is alive still I hope <lb/>he lives until I see him <lb/>again.   2) I got a letter from Chris <lb/>Meehan and this morning which <lb/>I enclose . He is going on <lb/>well thank God . I have <lb/>found out the name of the <lb/>Col. It is John Harvey <lb/>He must be an Irishman <lb/>by his name. You can <lb/>show Chris Meehans letter <lb/>to his mother . John Meehan <lb/>is in England still. The <lb/>little dog was with me <lb/>the night I was on <sic>Piquet</sic> <lb/>Duty he is a nice little fellow <lb/>I suppose Paddy goes up <lb/>often to you I hope he does 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3159_img_2580_3"/>
             4) I am glad you had such <lb/>a good time in the Castle <lb/>on Saturday evening you all <lb/>deserve great credit for the <lb/>way you are working.    I hope Tommy enjoyed his <lb/>ride on the motor bike <lb/>I will have a great time <lb/>riding it when I get home. <lb/>Does John ever come over now. <lb/>I hope he is minding the <lb/>Greyhounds well. I have no <lb/>more to say at present. So <lb/>Good-Bye &amp; God Bless you <lb/>all.   Peter Mooney 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>