<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3939">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Donovan, 21 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Donovan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,604 /14-15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3939</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0287">Robert Donovan</persName>
              <date>1915-12-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1736">University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0603">8 Palmerstown Villas, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3939_img_3314_1"  type="Letter"  url="1de41dc940a847eee8d98e9f3589c25d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3939_img_3314_2"  type="Letter"  url="aa0d6ad5ebd5cc0547a18028a292102d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3939_img_3314_1"/>
             University College Dublin   Election of Members of the Governing Body by the <lb/>Graduate Members of the College.   Dear Madam,    Permit me to ask you for the favour of your vote and influence at <lb/>the coming election of Members of the Governing Body of University College, <lb/>Dublin, by the Graduate Members.    I am a past student of the College, and, at present, have the honour <lb/>to hold therein the office of Professor of English Literature. I have been <lb/>a member of the Governing Body since its institution.    Having had the progress and prestige of our Alma Mater always <lb/>closely at heart, I can promise the most loyal and independent service to its <lb/>interests.    I am a convinced supporter of the principles and the administrative <lb/>methods which have, within the short period of six years and while yet the <lb/>building and equipment of the College are in process of completion, already <lb/>placed it in the front rank of University Institutions in these countries. The <lb/>heads and organisers of the College have proved that it is possible to combine <lb/>the most patriotic care for Irish national ideals in education, with the keenest <lb/>devotion to the claims of progressive scholarship and scientific research <lb/>That the College, even as it stands to-day, commends itself to the people <lb/>is proved by its growth in numbers, which has even now placed it far ahead <lb/>of other University Colleges long established, and on the line of equality <lb/>with the most prosperous of the Irish Universities. Upwards of a thousand
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3939_img_3314_2"/>
            students are already on its rolls. It needs only a wise and steady perse- <lb/>verance on the path already chosen, to make our College more than fulfil <lb/>the most sanguine expectations of those to whose strenuous labours for the <lb/>educational advancement of the people the present position of the College <lb/>is due.   In the difficult future that awaits European countries the work of <lb/>such a College must be a vital necessity of the nation. I will, if elected, <lb/>support every well-considered scheme for extending as far as possible the <lb/>advantages of the College in the full measure of its resources and oppor- <lb/>tunities. But believing, as I do, in a policy of continuity and steadiness <lb/>of development, I will oppose any proposal that would tend to lessen the <lb/>efficiency of the College as a place of higher education, or lower its rank and <lb/>prestige, to the detriment of its students. I should regard it as a breach of <lb/>faith, especially with the past professional students, if I did not apply this <lb/>test to all the projects that may be submitted to the consideration and <lb/>decision of the Governing Body.   I have the honour to be, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   ROBERT DONOVAN   8 Palmerston Villas, Dublin,   December 21st, 1915.  <lb/>P.S.—A Graduate Member may vote for six candidates.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>