<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0250">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Robert Anderson, 22 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Robert Anderson (b.1860). The letter answers a series of questions posed by Anderson in a previous letter concerning how many men would be required for each post, the length of time their service would be required, whether the men would be sworn in as special constables, if they would be provided with sticks and whistles, if they must wear a uniform and who the men would be answering to.Anderson was the Honorary Secretary of the Irish Association of the Volunteer Training Corps. The IAVTC were a corps consisting of men who were over age or engaged in important occupations and therefore could not enlist for wartime service when war broke out in 1914. This was a volunteering training militia that came to be known by the nickname &#39;Gorgeous Wrecks&#39; due to the G.R. armbands they wore symbolizing Georgius Rex.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7964/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/250</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-04-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0902">Robert Anderson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0250_img_1430_1"  type="Letter"  url="d9851bf4c428b874571569041df73e13.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0250_img_1430_1"/>
                22nd April, 1916.   Dear Anderson,    The following are the replies to the six <lb/> questions asked in your yesterday's note:-  (1) One man will be required for each Post in 4 <lb/> reliefs :- <lb/>(a) Museum... ... ... ... 4 men <lb/>(b) Arbour Hill Barracks. ... 4 ' <lb/>(c) Royal Hospital. ... ... 4 ' <lb/>(d) General Post Office.. ... 8 ' <lb/>(e) Telephone Exchange... ... 4 ' <lb/>(f) North Wall Ships ... ... 16 ' <lb/> Total 40.  (2) The day tour for each man will be from 6 a.m. <lb/>to 9 a.m. and 3 p.m. to 7 p.m. on one day <lb/>and 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. on the next day and so <lb/>alternately. The night tours would be 7 p.m. <lb/>to 1 a.m. and 1 a.m. to 6 a.m. on alternate <lb/>nights.  (3) The men so employed would be sworn in as <lb/> Special Constables.  (4) They would be provided with whistles and could <lb/>provide themselves with sticks.  (5) Volunteer uniforms with G.R. armlet should be <lb/>worn.  (6) The men when sworn in as Special Constables <lb/> would come under Police control but there <lb/>would be no objection to their inspection by <lb/> one of their own Orderly Officers who should <lb/>however also be sworn in as a Special Consta <lb/>-ble. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely,  The numbers and hours apply to Dublin. I have <lb/>not yet got details w.r. to other towns.</seg> <seg type="unclear">Zua.</seg><lb/> 22/4  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>