<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0629">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Duffin to Maria Duffin, 5 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Emma Duffin (1883-1979) to her mother, Maria (1854-1954) describing how Emma spent the money her mother sent her at Christmas. After describing the celebrations Emma goes on to tell her mother of her acquaintances and activities in Alexandria. Emma also writes about the Northern Irish identity which she cannot seem to escape and notes the impending casualties that are sure to come with the deployment of the 36th (Ulster) Division. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/629</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1134">Emma Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1327">15th General Hospital Alexandra, Egypt</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0629_img_2073_1"  type="Letter"  url="657d3c3b5b8328d7e0a0cb97057e6e33.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0629_img_2073_2"  type="Letter"  url="24255be241355489b0689ab53ae06c99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0629_img_2073_3"  type="Letter"  url="261b7052337d8d303463abac3c69d489.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0629_img_2073_4"  type="Letter"  url="7a5f0f947a7c9eb065ac0018810c9cad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0629_img_2073_1"/>
              reference D2109/10/1/B<lb/>   15<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> Gen. Alex.    Feb. 5 1916   My dearest Mamma   Your Christmas present of the lovely voile <lb/>blouse arrived yesterday &amp; I enjoyed it all the more because <lb/>I had quite given it up I thought it was lost in the Persia <lb/>Thank you ever so much for it dear. You must have lost <lb/>several of my letters if you did not hear for a month for I write <lb/>regularly &amp; I mentioned twice about Aline Russell going <lb/>home. I know, I also wrote a long account of Christmas which <lb/>you do not seem to have got. You ask me to write you an <lb/>account of how I spent the money to publish, but the very fact that <lb/>you want it makes it rather hard to write naturally perhaps you <lb/>could glean different bits out of my letters &amp; piece it together <lb/>The cigarettes were greatly appreciated especially since 'Park <lb/>Drive' are sent by some people from Glengormley. I had some <lb/>Australians who said they were the best they ever smoked. I I <lb/>gave £10 of the money to Matron towards a general fund  she had  to be spent <lb/>on the hospital at Christmas and every man in hospital was given <lb/>a present <seg type="del">out of that fund</seg>. Then we bought all sorts of toys for the men such <lb/>as whistles, mouth organs, tin <seg type="unclear">hostess</seg>, false noses etc. etc. and you should <lb/>have seen how they laughed &amp; the noise they made, they could not have <lb/>enjoyed themselves more if they had been small children we bought <lb/>little tiny artificial Christmas trees for the tea tables and decorated <lb/>them and decorated the tents with coloured lanterns &amp; flags and <lb/>had small cakes &amp; sweets and a big chocolate cake with 'A happy Xmas'  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0629_img_2073_2"/>
              written on it in white icing. The hospital supplied fruit <lb/>and plumpudding &amp; turkey for all well enough to eat them and <lb/>the Red X people gave each man a present so they came off very <lb/>well and really enjoyed themselves. I did not spend all <lb/> the money at Christmas time but have spent it on papers, flowers <lb/>and sweets acid drops are always in great demand &amp; they all <seg type="del">Australians</seg> love sweets &amp; lollies as the Australians call <lb/>them. The books &amp; magazines you sent were a boon, and <lb/>the Irish Times always finds its way to an Irishman, if <lb/>I have not one in my ward I give it to one of the Sisters who has. <lb/>One man I found had a little volume of Byron in his locker and <lb/>he told me he loved poetry so I brought him a little collection of <lb/>verses which was among the books you sent, &amp; he was delighted.  Feb 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I got a parcel of magazines which I distributed yesterday <lb/>I also got your cheque and will take the £1 for myself out of it. <lb/>I wrote to the Aunts to thank them but so many of your letters <lb/>have got lost lately would you thank them in case they didn't get it, also <lb/>Aunt Margaret for the lovely white silk shirts she sent me. <lb/>I got a letter from Ruth &amp; one from Edmund today. I saw <lb/>in the paper that poor Aline Russells father is dead, poor thing. <lb/>She can only have got home just about in time. I do feel sorry <lb/>for her she was devoted to him.  The other day I went out to be with a dear old Mrs Crofton <lb/>who visits at the hospital here. She has such a nice house and  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0629_img_2073_3"/>
              garden, so 'homely' the whole atmosphere reminded me of <lb/>Strandtown. There were violets &amp; little jonquils out in the <lb/>garden &amp; roses but the latter had been rather spoilt by thunderstorms <lb/>There was an English Clergyman there for tea, who was comical <lb/>he was so typical the sort of man you would never meet in Ireland, <lb/>he talked in a mincing voice and pronounced each syllable separately <lb/>and quoted Milton 'as Milton says' he posed so, I cannot abide <lb/>that sort of man!   I and a girl from Bally— <lb/>money called McElderry went out to be with her cousin &amp; a rather <lb/>nice man called <seg type="unclear">Cusk</seg> at the Savoy Hotel here. I am hounded <lb/>by North of Ireland people &amp; they all seem to take to me whether <lb/>because I come from there or not, you will find I have a curious <lb/>collection of acquaintances when I return home. Miss McElderry is <lb/>typically Irish with a strong Northern accent but awfully decent and <lb/>good natured &amp; most devoted to me. I shall never forget how good <lb/>she was to me when I was sea sick. She herself being one of the few <lb/>persons who remained well &amp; hearty all the time. The night superintend— <lb/>ent at present is a Sister Quigley who trained in Belfast &amp; who <lb/>comes from Monaghan. She also takes an interest in me and I pass her <lb/>on my 'Weekly Whig' which she greatly appreciates. By the way I saw <lb/>Rea the dentist is dead in the Whig I got today.  I enclose a letter for Helen Carrington Smith, could you get <lb/>her address from the Blizards and forward it. I have lost her letter, <lb/>I am so glad 'Fairy Led' sold so well she sent me out some copies  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0629_img_2073_4"/>
              which I have been giving to my friends here. By the way you <lb/>never told me what you paid for the picnic basket you ordered <lb/>for Nell Ryland! At present there are very few patients <lb/>in hospital so I didn't need the money so much, &amp; I think you <lb/>had better not bother sending any more cigarettes etc. till I let <lb/>you know. I dare say we shall be full up again later and need <lb/>them but at present everything is very uncertain  I was sorry to hear that Billy Bradshaw had been killed. Now <lb/>that the Ulster Div is in action Belfast will suffer a lot <lb/>This is a stupid letter as now that I am a night bird again <lb/>I have nothing to write about.  Best love dearest, I am glad you had Terry home. <lb/>Is there any chance of Celia getting leave, why shouldn't the girls get <lb/>it as well as the men. <seg type="closer"> Ever your own  <hi rend="underline">Emma</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>