<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4298">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 4 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/14/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4298</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1915-12-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1275">Old Town Hall, Belfast, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4298_img_3660_1"  type="Letter"  url="d1fc42da2dde99b277b0beec0eb1df57.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4298_img_3660_2"  type="Letter"  url="7c92a4e6e6985887c09404e5f6c41421.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4298_img_3660_3"  type="Letter"  url="ef1e0dd7c99d5d0b4649a2a7cbb52c22.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4298_img_3660_4"  type="Letter"  url="f570cc48e5159090a427ed6515b18c36.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4298_img_3660_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Balis</hi><seg type="unclear">Press refund</seg> &amp; Irish Divisions <!-- Lots of indecipherable notes, possibly in short hand, in the margin -->  4th December, 1915.   Rt. Hon. Sir Edward Carson, K. C., M. P., <lb/>5, Eaton Place, <lb/>London, S. W.   <hi rend="underline">Private &amp; Confidential.</hi>   Dear Sir Edward,   At a Meeting held on 12th November of the <lb/>City and County of Dublin Recruiting Committee of Ireland, <lb/>the following resolution was passed:-    "That in the opinion of this Committee <lb/>"an Irish Press Representative should be appoint- <lb/>"ed to accompany the Irish Division so that a <lb/>"full Report of their deeds might receive publicity.   "My committee feel that if arrangements <lb/>"could be made to give publicity to the deeds of the <lb/>"Irish Regiments of which full Reports should appear <lb/>"in the Irish papers, it would be a great stimulus <lb/>"to recruiting".   This was moved by Sir Maurice Dockrell, and <lb/>seconded by Mr. J. C. Percy, practically the only two ;Unionists <lb/>on the Committee, and certainty in <seg type="del">respect</seg> regard to  of Mr. Percy, his <lb/>Unionism is of a very doubtful quantity.   This resolution was forwarded to the War Office, <lb/>and I understand, from strictly private sources, that the War
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4298_img_3660_2"/>
             Sir Edward Carson,   4/12/15.  <lb/>Office passed it on to the Press Committee for their views <lb/>thereon, suggesting that to adopt such a course asked for in <lb/>the resolution would involve similar applications on behalf <lb/>of other Divisions, and suggesting the possibility that under <lb/>the circumstances special instructions might be given to the <lb/>various  press  representatives to call special attention to the doings <lb/>of the Irish Regiments. They further asked the Press Committee <lb/>for an expression of opinion as to the expediency of the whole <lb/>thing. .  I do not know what is the result at the present time. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4298_img_3660_3"/>
             With regard to the resolution And the reference made <lb/>to the Press Committee, this cannot be made public, but what I <lb/>would like to know from you is whether or not it would be <lb/>possible to get any of your friends on the "Daily Telegraph", <lb/>"Morning Post" or "Express" - many of whose <seg type="del">reports</seg> reporters  are very <lb/>friendly to the Ulster Division - to give instructions to their <lb/>reporters that, notwithstanding any instructions they may have
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4298_img_3660_4"/>
             Sir Edward Carson,   4/12/15.  <lb/>from the Press Committee following on the resolution, that <lb/>they should give similar publicity to the doings of the Ulster <lb/>Division.   I would also like to ask your opinion whether or <lb/>not it would be advisable that the Recruiting Committee in <lb/>Belfast should pass a resolution on the lines of that already <lb/>passed in Dublin as if the permission I have mentioned above <lb/>is given in connection with the Irish Divisions, it should <lb/>also be given to the Ulster Divisions.   I do not, however, want to take any step of this <lb/>sort in regard to having a resolution passed, without having <lb/>your sanction and approval.   Yours very truly,    <seg type="unclear">R Dawson Salin</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>