<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2191">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William John Kingston to Sir Robert Chalmers, 8 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William John Kingston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by William John Kingston (1885-1975), a solicitor from Cork to the Under-Secretary of Ireland, Sir Robert Chalmers (1958-1938). Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell , his chief secretary following the Easter Rising in 1916. 
The letter concerns a request by Cork County Council to make amendments to the Order of the  Management of Tramways and Light Railways. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9745</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2191</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1139">William John Kingston</persName>
              <date>1916-06-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2096">Skibbereen, Co. Cork, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2191_img_1637_1"  type="Letter"  url="7c59d2dae2e64cfafcf20d3080fe72e1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2191_img_1637_1"/>
              OFFICES— SKIBBEREEN <lb/> Co Cork  8th day of June 1916   The Under Secretary, <lb/>The Castle,   Sir,   I have been consulted by some rate- <lb/>payers of the Guaranteeing Area of the West <lb/> Carbery Tramway and light Railway Co Ltd. <lb/> They have been informed that an application <lb/> has been made by the Cork County Council <lb/> for an amendment of the order in Council <lb/> under which the light Railway is directed. <lb/> My clients think it would be a favourable <lb/> opportunity to apply for other amendments of <lb/> the same Order, and have consulted me as to how <lb/> the application should be made. They <lb/> understand that the present application is <lb/> being made with the object of providing a <lb/> member of the County Council with a free <lb/> Railway pass, and however commendable and ur- <lb/> gent, this object may be they think that the <lb/> time would be opportune to consider other <lb/> amendments.    Before, however, troubling you <lb/> with any such application, I would wish to <lb/> know if an opportunity would be given for <lb/> the consideration of same.   I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant,   W. J. Kingston 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>