<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1646">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 22 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. Marie was a born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the out break of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British Army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary.
Marie discusses her brother Tommy (1891-?) who is fighting in the war, she also expresses sadness at not hearing anything about her brother Charlie (1895-1915), who had died in December. She goes on to discuss the other nurses, some of whom where sent home. She contemplates going home, stating that seeing the doctors go home has effected the nurses. She goes on to account that there are a group of new patients that have arrive for treatment, continuing to discuss what is happening in the hospital. She then expresses how good it will be to see Tommy when he passes through.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF131</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1646</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-02-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_1"  type="Letter"  url="e677377713c8697a6967a95195570c69.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_2"  type="Letter"  url="7226d8938eacda812676a70dd84bd16c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_3"  type="Letter"  url="fe0b45b7398b30f02cc8937941ddc031.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_4"  type="Letter"  url="213bc644140b5ce7d396efb61668db59.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_5"  type="Letter"  url="276ed005f548ecccb669b7ff2db96a41.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_6"  type="Letter"  url="1a9cb4dd2c59b89e74af022d4bfd6cca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_7"  type="Letter"  url="69d3aeb9de80b8aca52fa543439f2443.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_8"  type="Letter"  url="27f3627d6b267938ddde5b52bdcad52d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_9"  type="Letter"  url="715af755962af3164f4c8303e7e5ff5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_10"  type="Letter"  url="c487a4403c2fe120d4a98bf45053da0b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1646_img_1107_11"  type="Letter"  url="6210d169c9a3cded2a3e2888739f40ac.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">22nd Feb 1916</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   A thousand thanks <lb/>for your letter dated the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>Feb: I am very sorry indeed <lb/>to hear Tommy has been warn- <lb/>ed &amp; sincerely hope it will <lb/>be sometime quit before he is <lb/>sent out I know how much <lb/>you will feel him going <lb/>away again but I am glad <lb/>to say they do not seems <lb/>to be doing much fighting <lb/>out this way &amp; he will be <lb/>so much happier with his <lb/>own regiment. I was very glad <lb/>to see so many <sic>Connaugh</sic> <lb/>Rangers mention in dispatches 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_2"/>
             I think Captain Massy deserved <lb/>all he got. I am disappointed <lb/>not seeing Charlies name, by <lb/>the way I never received Major <lb/>Whytes letters you all mention how <lb/>well he did &amp; that he has been <lb/>recommended for L.S.O but for <lb/>what for I have no idea. I <lb/>suppose that letter has gone <lb/>astray, worse luck. I do wish <lb/>you would hear something different <lb/>soon &amp; that we could get into <lb/>communication with him. It cannot <lb/>be long now before we hear. <lb/>I have not written to Mr. <seg type="unclear">Farrel</seg> <lb/>yet. I never seem to get time <lb/>to set down &amp; write a serious <lb/>letter by the time I keep my <lb/>clothes together etc the time seems <lb/>to pass away &amp; I have done <lb/>nothing I meant to do.   We have been very unsettled
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_3"/>
            lately nobody seems to know <lb/>what is going to happen to M <lb/>Georges. All the Private Sisters <lb/>who are being paid £2-2-0 <lb/>a week have been sent home <lb/>to-day they were terrible sick <lb/>over it &amp; all the Sisters sign- <lb/>ing on for another are <lb/>getting 6 weeks furlow so we <lb/>are quite a small staff but <lb/>still too many for the number <lb/>of patients we have. I have <lb/>for the past couple of days <lb/>been in charge of this ward H.5 <lb/>with only 8 Patients so there was <lb/>no sister with all the changes <lb/>now <sic>ofcourse</sic> we have one again <lb/>as we are a little more <lb/>settled. All the M.O. are getting <lb/>6 weeks leave too so eventually
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_4"/>
             they do not expect to be busy<lb/>for some time.<lb/><lb/>There was a notice put up the<lb/>other day for all V.A.D.'s who<lb/>do not wish to resign for another<lb/>6 months to sign &amp; as we have<lb/>still 3 months to go we thought<lb/>it rather, if our time expired<lb/>now I would not hesitate<lb/>in saying I wanted to go home<lb/>as we are so slack &amp; doing<lb/>nothing. We could do much<lb/>more at home but <sic>ofcourse</sic><lb/>if it were like when I first<lb/>arrived I would consider it<lb/>twice. So I &amp; another girl<lb/>went to Miss Holby ( Matron<lb/>in Chief ) &amp; explained we had<lb/>not made up our minds<lb/>yet &amp; also we had not <seg type="unclear">consented</seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_5"/>
            ed our people she was charming <lb/> &amp; said <sic>ofcourse</sic> I'd wait till <lb/> it came to nearer the time <lb/> &amp; find out what our people <lb/> would like, <sic>ofcourse</sic> most likely <lb/> if things continue as they <lb/> are we shall be sent back <lb/>home without being asked <lb/> What do you think about it ? <lb/> perhaps it would be better for <lb/> me to go home for a bit &amp; <lb/> then try &amp; get out to France <lb/> or some other work in the Sum- <lb/>mer. <sic>Ofcourse</sic> naturally we all <lb/> felt very homesick <sic>to-day</sic> <lb/> seeing all the Leinsters going <lb/> home but at the same time <lb/> I would much sooner finish <lb/> my time out here &amp; then <lb/> go back. a good few of the
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_6"/>
            a lot of V.A.D.'s are going home <lb/> next month their seven months <lb/> being up. So just let me <lb/> know what you would like me <lb/> to do . I <sic>ofcourse</sic> am very <lb/> anxious to see you all again <lb/> but would not like it if they were <lb/> terribly busy to do the shabby <lb/> thing you know my feelings <lb/> I personally think it would <lb/> be better to go home &amp; stay with <lb/> you all for a bit &amp; I can <lb/> always do something later on <lb/> Tell Beatrice I read a most <lb/> interesting &amp; amusing letter <lb/> from her to A. Lily yesterday <lb/> I do wish she would write <lb/> some to me if you could only <lb/> see how it cheered me up <lb/> &amp; made me laugh she would
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_7"/>
             been put on the home that's<lb/>the worst of this place one<lb/>has to be ready for everything<lb/>&amp; anything. They do not consider<lb/>people in the slightest, however<lb/>I hope it will not be for long<lb/>there are a great number of<lb/>new notices up about the<lb/>V.A.D.'s, they are all to be<lb/>treated as Probationers in<lb/>Hospital as an army Sister<lb/>remarked when she read the<lb/>notice, I pity the poor devils<lb/>&amp; others refused to lecture the<lb/>V.A.D's they say we have<lb/>all come out to do our bit<lb/>&amp; let us do it cheerfully<lb/>together, another is that V.A.D's<lb/>are to doing nothing but<lb/>cleaning &amp; any extra nursing 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_8"/>
             write very often. Please thank<lb/>Ethel for her letter dated 12th<lb/>Feb. How constant she is to<lb/>her work. She observes a V.P.<lb/>at the end of the war.<lb/>Tell Bee she need not bother<lb/>sending me the thinning cure<lb/>as I am getting much thinner<lb/>&amp; feel much better for it<lb/>I do not think that extra<lb/>fat was healthy for me as<lb/>I always felt so like as if<lb/>I were blown out &amp; it seemed<lb/>to make me breathless but<lb/>I am really normal now.<lb/>&amp; feel A1.  I saw A Lily on Saturday<lb/>for a few minutes, she<lb/>is very fed up as she has 
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_9"/>
            is to be done by orderlies. <lb/> The notice has not reached <lb/> here yet but I am afraid <lb/> there will be some work <lb/> about it if it does as <lb/> they all say we do not <lb/> care what we do when we <lb/> are busy scrubbing etc. as <lb/> we have done but we will <lb/> not have an orderly handing <lb/> a patient a drink whilst <lb/> he ( the orderly ) is watching us <lb/> scrubbing. However I do not <lb/> think it will come to any <lb/> thing myself &amp; if it does <lb/> well it is evidently the <lb/> way we are wanted to <lb/> help &amp; so be it. 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_10"/>
             It will be very nice seeing <lb/> Tommy on his way back <lb/> He will have all the latest <lb/> news of you dearest Mother. <lb/> I hope it is not true what you <lb/> say about getting old. I hope <lb/> you are taking good care <lb/> of yourself &amp; not worrying <lb/> too much.    Give my fondest love to <lb/> everyone at home. I have <lb/> heard nothing from Gerald <lb/> since the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb. I hope he <lb/> will get leave soon again. <lb/> What has happen to <seg type="unclear">Loclin</seg> <lb/> &amp; Irene I have not heard <lb/> of them for a long time ? <lb/> I shall write to morrow again <lb/> as there is a mail going out
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_1646_img_1107_11"/>
             to-night &amp; another to-morrow<lb/>with every loving thought<lb/>&amp; good wish,   Your most loving &amp;<lb/>grateful daughter    <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>