<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2294">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eleanor Dawson to her niece Louisa Spinks, 26th November 1915.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eleanor Dawson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Eleanor Dawson was the wife of the late Richard Cuming Dawson. Louisa Spinks was the daughter of Dr William Lee Dawson who emigrated to Australia in 1854. Richard and William were brothers. The family corresponded from time to time.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Sharon Brennan, Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2294</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0408">Eleanor Dawson</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1120">Kilronan, Cloghran, Co. Dublin,  Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Louisa Spinks</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2007">Wittlesea, Victoria, Australia</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1933</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_1"  type="Letter"  url="4bad856e6d26791844834bc041cf0db3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_2"  type="Letter"  url="993711379f9c525a6e487ff69f2d2030.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_3"  type="Letter"  url="0a2263f5952215f4e24b9a710394b963.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_4"  type="Letter"  url="0aff7a30b29283399b18a7ca38a931e1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_5"  type="Letter"  url="dc3e46bb43138463ce47b2cd5af39b87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_6"  type="Letter"  url="38f8a3213c3169d1f5ac4975f7f442ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2294_img_1740_7"  type="Letter"  url="80c2133f5391f16c55432f8083355ea2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_1"/>
             Kilronan<lb/>Cloghran   Nov 26/15    My dear Louie   It's such a long<lb/>time since I heard from<lb/>you I only hope you haven't<lb/>been ill, I was thinking to<lb/>day so sat down to write<lb/>at once hoping this will<lb/>reach you by Xmas.  Well to begin, I was very<lb/>ill last Xmas was months<lb/>before I felt quite myself<lb/>again had the doctor<lb/>coming for a long time<lb/>&amp; the nurse for night duty 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_2"/>
             My daughter nursed<lb/>in the day time, she came<lb/>home for her holidays<lb/>&amp; from the day she came<lb/>till she left her time<lb/>l was completely taken<lb/>up &amp; didn't feel so well<lb/>for a long time after she<lb/>went back, but thank God<lb/>I am quite well now.  We are having an awful<lb/>time in Ireland this<lb/>long time, a Mr James Larkin<lb/>who calls himself the leader<lb/>of the working class &amp; has<lb/>gained <seg type="del">imm</seg> immense<lb/>influence over them<lb/>settling what wages they 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_3"/>
             should get &amp; for three<lb/>months the work has been<lb/>stopped on farms &amp; people<lb/>are at their wits ends to know<lb/>what to do, there are strikes<lb/>on all sides &amp; the cross<lb/>channel boats not running<lb/>Dublin is ruined for a time<lb/><seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> there is no knowing<lb/>where the mischief may<lb/>end, there are prayers<lb/>every Sunday in all<lb/>the churches for a peace<lb/>ful ending of this dispute<lb/>the Dublin employers were<lb/>very irate &amp; will not give 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_4"/>
             in &amp; so trade is at a stand<lb/>still, 6 places around here<lb/>been burned out, all their<lb/>years produce so its a sad<lb/>state of things - to pass to<lb/>something brighter we had<lb/>a most lovely summer here<lb/>only the very dry season<lb/>but some things apples<lb/>were very small &amp; scarce the<lb/>May frosts I expect was<lb/>the cause &amp; they are a great<lb/>loss, foreign apples ought<lb/>to be dearer in consequence.<lb/>I hope the season has<lb/>been good for Ernest<lb/>&amp; that he his wife &amp; children 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_5"/>
             are quite well, we live<lb/>very quietly here the<lb/>days are so short but we<lb/>rather like the long night<lb/>up after Xmas the severe<lb/>weather comes there<lb/>were several marriages<lb/>about here, last summer<lb/>but no one belonging to<lb/>me I'm sorry to say.<lb/>So many are going to<lb/>America a cousin of mine<lb/>went out to Canada &amp; his<lb/>mother fretted so much<lb/>after him, she is now gone<lb/>out, but said she would<lb/>come back, I wonder 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_6"/>
             if she ever will,<lb/>but people think nothing<lb/>of going to &amp; from America.<lb/>I haven't seen the Mrs <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>Spinks for a long time<lb/>not since before Mrs<lb/>Moore died for which<lb/>I was very sorry she used<lb/>to come over every two<lb/>or three years to see<lb/>her daughters one of whom<lb/>lives in Germany  Now hoping &amp; wishing<lb/>you Eileen &amp; Charly<lb/>many happy returns<lb/>of the season with love to all 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2294_img_1740_7"/>
             Believe me yours <lb/>very sincerely   Eleanor Dawson  <lb/>All here send their love.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>