<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4376">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from MW O'Reilly to 'A Cara', 16 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M.W. O&#39;Reilly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letters from Volunteer M W O’Reilly to an unidentified friend, written while imprisoned in Knutsford, 1 and 16 June 1916. O&#39;Reilly mentions June Kavanagh. Mentions he has had a visit from his wife and brother so therefore his &#39;cara&#39; is not one of them. It mentions that he might be moved from that prison but he is unsure. Mentions that teachers from Manchester visit them with &#39;all sorts of nice things&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>The Jackie Clarke Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4376</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1028">M.W. O&#39;Reilly</persName>
              <date>1916-06-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0459">Knutsford Prison Cheshire</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4376_img_3730_1"  type="Letter"  url="946e2e40723795801f8f146406c6c9e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4376_img_3730_2"  type="Letter"  url="c6f6f9359f7428454a536d4445606e89.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4376_img_3730_3"  type="Letter"  url="cd509925f7d136ac02e0fc208e480ab3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4376_img_3730_4"  type="Letter"  url="3918ecb938ebe67cc2e4e814936c403a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4376_img_3730_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">Krahford</seg>   June 16 1916,    A Cara a Mor,   I must write and<lb/>thank you for paper which<lb/>I received, I trust you<lb/>are   well and happy.<lb/>Also your mother and<lb/>Sisters and your dear<lb/>nephew give them my<lb/>Kind regards.    All the <seg type="unclear"></seg>  here are<lb/>in the Pink the only<lb/>bother been unable to<lb/>have a walk around  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4376_img_3730_2"/>
             the Beautiful Roads that<lb/>surrounds this place.<lb/>At lease we are informed<lb/>they are Beautiful but have<lb/>not had an opportunity of<lb/>judging for ourselves.<lb/>I am sure however that<lb/>they are not more Beautiful<lb/>than Kilmore, Dear Old<lb/>Kilmore, how pleasant it<lb/>was to have a day out<lb/>Artane way after the<lb/>stuffy City, I wish very<lb/>much I could have a<lb/>day out there now.  However when I come 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4376_img_3730_3"/>
             back I, must take a<lb/>whole long day on<lb/>that way.  Your Friend June Kavanagh<lb/>has left here for Somewhere<lb/>in England! or Wales perhaps.<lb/>I had the pleasure of a<lb/>visit from my wife and<lb/>mother last week and I<lb/>found them both in excellent<lb/>form. I may be going<lb/>from here any time but<lb/>nothing is known at present<lb/>and of course I may not. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4376_img_3730_4"/>
             Should you write me however<lb/>I will receive your letter<lb/>here or elsewhere as all<lb/>letter etc are forwarded after<lb/>those that leave. We have had<lb/>visits from some <seg type="unclear">teachers</seg>  who<lb/>are in Manchester and indeed<lb/>they are most kind, like all  <lb/>I suppose, they bring us all sorts<lb/>of nice things and it will be hard<lb/>luck having to leave them if<lb/>we are changed. With very best<lb/>wishes for your Health.<lb/>and trusting this will find you<lb/>Happy. <!-- can not read what is crossed out --> Believe  <lb/>    Yours very sincerely <lb/>M W OReilly      
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>