<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3308">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A.F. Major to Henry Arthur Wynne, 4 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A.F. Major</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-11742-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3308</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0352">A.F. Major</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0815">Henry Arthur Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3308_img_2722_1"  type="Letter"  url="fcefc05e191292689bec716964ee9304.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3308_img_2722_2"  type="Letter"  url="6405f1c970571c5a50711a59776dac4e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3308_img_2722_1"/>
             Soer General<lb/>Please advise<lb/><seg type="unclear">signature</seg><lb/>8.VII.16  Any furrther communication on this<lb/>subject should be addressed to-  The Secretary,<lb/>War Office,<lb/>Park Buildings,<lb/>St. James's Park,<lb/>London, S.W.,  and the following number quoted.  CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/>11742 -- 8. JUL.<seg type="unclear">1816</seg><lb/>OFFICE<lb/><lb/>War Office,<lb/>Park Buildings,<lb/>St. James's' Park,<lb/>London,  S.W.E/ 128104 / 1. (Accounts 4.)   4th July, 1916.    Sir,   I am directed to forward the following statement of case and the<lb/>accompanying documents relating thereto for your perusal and such action as<lb/>you may consider advisable.  No.8166, Private William Robert Johnston, 1st Battalion, Royal<lb/>Irish Fusiliers, died in France on the 11th December,1915. A sum of<lb/>£21.4.1. (Twenty one pounds, four shillings and one penny) was found to be<lb/>due to his estate from Army Funds and no Will made by him is forthcoming.  The application (marked A) attached claiming the deceased's<lb/>effects and money and bearing the signature Frank Johnston was received in<lb/>the War Office on the 7th February,1916. In response the form of<lb/>application (marked B) was despatched to the applicant on the 15th<lb/>February,1916 and it was received back in the War Office on the 27th March,<lb/>1916 was the information, declaration and certificate now shown therein.  As it appeared from the information given in that form that the<lb/>applicant was entitled to the whole of the deceased's estate as the brother<lb/>and only next of kin of the deceased, the attached Money Order (marked C)<lb/>for £21.4.1. was sent on instructions from this Department by the Command<lb/>Paymaster, Eastern Command, to Mr Frank Johnston on the 13th April. It will<lb/>be observed that the Order was cashed on the 17th idem at Belfast to the<lb/>signature Frank Johnston, the handwriting agreeing with that of the<lb/>signature to the form marked B.  On the 20th April, 1916 the letter (marked D) bearing the<lb/>signature Alexander Johnstone and stating that the writer was entitled to a<lb/>portion of the estate was received in the War Office. Alexander Johnston<lb/><lb/>was   The Chief Crown Solicitor,<lb/>Chief Secretary's Office,<lb/>Dublin Castle,<lb/>Dublin.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3308_img_2722_2"/>
             was requested to give a full statement of all the deceased's brothers and<lb/>sisters and the reply (marked E) was received in this Department on the<lb/>13th May1916. The last mentioned document shows that the late soldier had<lb/>eight brothers and sisters and the children of the deceased sister Rosanna were<lb/>of course, legally entitled to share in the distribution of the amount due<lb/>to the estate.  The case was referred to the Inspector General, Royal Irish<lb/>Constabulary, for investigation,vide copy of War Office letter of 23rd May<lb/>1916, (marked F). His report on the case dated 2nd June,1916, is also<lb/>enclosed (marked G).  I am also to inform you with regard to the statement in the<lb/>document marked D that recovery of any overpayment might be effected from<lb/>an Army allowance issued to Frank Johnston in respect of his son, that it<lb/>has been ascertained that the allowance is being paid to Sarah Johnston,<lb/>presumably his wife. It does not, therefore, appear to this Department<lb/>that recovery could properly be effected from the allowance in question<lb/>even if it were deemed advisable to take any steps to secure the recovery<lb/>of any overpayment.   I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,    AFMajor<lb/>for the Assistant Financial Secretary.   E<hi rend="underline">nclosures.</hi><lb/>A. Frank Johnston's letter of 3rd February 1916.<lb/>B. Form 39 issued 15th February 1916.<lb/>C. Money Order No.122851.<lb/>D. Alexander Johnston's letter 19th April 1916.<lb/>E. Alexander Johnston's letter 11th May 1916.<lb/>F. War Office letter (flimsy) 23rd May 1916.<lb/>G. Constabulary letter 2nd June 1916. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>