<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3538">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert James Rowlette to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, May 10 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert James Rowlette</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter from Robert James Rowlette (1873–1944) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), Robert expresses condolences regarding the death of Hanna&#39;s husband Francis. He writes that, though he did not agree with Francis on many issues, he had a lot of respect for him.

Robert James Rowlette was a medical doctor, politician, and athlete. Rowlette published considerable work in publications such as the Irish Times, the Medical Union&#39;s Journal, and the Medical Press and Circular, the latter of which he edited. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington  suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/1-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3538</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1563">Robert James Rowlette</persName>
              <date>1916-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1091">42, Lower Baggot Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1944</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3538_img_2941_1"  type="Letter"  url="202e17e1df304b674fefcdac2163795e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3538_img_2941_2"  type="Letter"  url="c2a9064db3c3e28fbfd66a157f7cc111.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3538_img_2941_1"/>
             TELEPHONE NO. 2670.   10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916    42, LOWER BAGGOTT STREET,<lb/>DUBLIN.    Dear Mrs Sheehy—Skeffington   I had been hoping tuntil to—day that<lb/>the rumours which were current as to your<lb/>husband's death were untrue, but I find<lb/>now that there is no doubt. I know nothing<lb/>of the circumstances, but there must<lb/>have been some terrible misunderstanding.<lb/>My wife and I wish to offer you our<lb/>sincerest sympathy. Although there<lb/>were probably few points on which your<lb/>husband and I had much agreement,<lb/>there were few even of my acquaintances<lb/>for whose <seg type="unclear"></seg>  and <seg type="unclear"></seg>   I had so<lb/>much respect, or whose intellectual   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3538_img_2941_2"/>
             powers I so much admired. His early <lb/>death is a   less   to <lb/>estimate.   Believe me <lb/>Yours very sincerely <lb/><!-- signature --> Robert J Rowlette 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>