<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5556">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 24 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5556</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-02-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0592">National Health Insurance Commission (Ireland), Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5556_img_652_1"  type="Letter"  url="c3261c1b6f2c4dcd94a3211d6b4691ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5556_img_652_2"  type="Letter"  url="4e80ea89d5895dd6cdc43b286ca18e65.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5556_img_652_1"/>
              No sign of the work easing<lb/>off here but I’ll take a<lb/>few days off next week<lb/>anyhow and to h—with<lb/>everybody.   <hi rend="underline">James</hi>  <!-- Beginning of the letter --> NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION (IRELAND),<lb/>PEMBROKE HOUSE,<lb/>UPPER MOUNT STREET,<lb/>Dublin.    24th Feby, 1916    My dearest girl,   You needn’t have been so penitent about not<lb/>writing to me yesterday. I really didn’t expect to hear from<lb/>you and in any case I know very well that it is not always easy<lb/>to get letters posted in Togherstown. I was very sorry indeed to hear<lb/>that the real cause of your not writing was a recurrence of the<lb/>headache you had at my place. I hope that my poor darling<lb/>wasn’t so bad as she was then. I pitied you very much that<lb/>last evening you had the headache because I could see very well<lb/>that you weren’t really able to sit up. I’m quite sure my mother<lb/>didn’t think you pettish for going to bed: you were quite right to<lb/>go. I was glad to hear that Joe beat the Fays with his pigs —<lb/>for the credit of the family name. I think Christy must have sold<lb/>his too cheap especially if his “piebald” was one of the lot. I’m<lb/>sure the piebald would go much more than £5:10:0 as a curiosity 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5556_img_652_2"/>
             for the waxworks in Henry Street. He’d be a great attraction along<lb/>with the “fat woman” and the “bear lady”. I was very pleased to<lb/>hear of the good opinion that Matty Keanan has of me. If I<lb/>get many more “flowers” thrown at me like that I’ll begin to<lb/>fancy myself too much. I’m beginning to think now that you were<lb/>a fortunate <seg type="del">little</seg><hi rend="underline">big</hi> girl to get hold of such a treasure. So<lb/>you’d better keep your nose very clean and be particularly nice to<lb/>me (and <hi rend="underline">above all</hi> don’t refuse me kisses) or I’ll go back on you.<lb/>So now mind yourself. Glad to hear Tim is getting on so well<lb/>and hope he will continue so. I wrote to Mrs. Seery on Friday to<lb/>let her know I’d be down Saturday evening. Perhaps she would come<lb/>herself to the station to meet us if you suggest it. If not I suppose<lb/>someone else will come. I mean suppose she won't think that the <hi rend="underline">Fays</hi><lb/>are going to meet us and between the two houses we should have<lb/>to walk. I don’t care “tuppence” myself but I don’t suppose you<lb/>would enjoy stumping from Castletown. In fact I’d much prefer walking<lb/>if I had you to myself. I don’t think I’ll write tomorrow as<lb/>probably you’d be gone to the station on Saturday before a letter<lb/>could arrive. I have nothing else to say now except to send my dearest<lb/>and most devoted love as usual. I shall live for the next two days on the<lb/>expectation of Saturday. By the way, I didn’t sleep last night till 2 o’clock thinking about you.  Warmest love again my darling girl   <hi rend="underline">James</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>