<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5325">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Harry Willias to Captain Francis C. Forth, 26 February 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Harry Willias</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A friendly letter discussing recent appointments at Manchester College of Technology, Willias&#39;s son, and Forth&#39;s condition. A newspaper clipping is included, which concerns the recent appointment and the rise in the principal&#39;s salary.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5325</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1408">Harry Willias</persName>
              <date>1919-02-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0820">Manchester College of Technology</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0162">Francis C. Forth</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Last Letters before Death</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5325_img_None_1"  url="1b0efbe7e0cac3623313c0066878886a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5325_img_None_2"  url="27a10a6eabc224751ef63a3583f8137d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5325_img_None_3"  url="446f539ed43298f4c043be156d3e5d4b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5325_img_0_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Personal</hi>  College of Technology<lb/>Manchester   26-2-19    My dear Forth <lb/>Delighted to get your<lb/>letter of the 5th and to know<lb/>that you are none the worse.  It was refreshing to notice<lb/>that your signature had<lb/>lost little of its old swing.  Carry on, old friend.  You were asking about<lb/>Fox's successor. Well, the enclosed<lb/>cutting from the Guardian<lb/>will tell you all about it.  This is the day of<lb/>young men: Professor Turner<lb/>is 29!  I don't suppose he<lb/>knows anything about Textiles.<lb/>But he's a Cambridge man, and,    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5325_img_0_2"/>
             good God, what more do you want?  Did you notice that out<lb/>Chief (who is a very big pot indeed,<lb/>by the way) go the C.B.E.?  And the Committee, bless 'em,<lb/>are going to give him a<lb/>rise of £400. Hurroo!  What it is to be an arm-<lb/>chair stay-at-home warrior.  Excuse my levity, old chap.<lb/>Some day I'll write you a<lb/>personal note about my boy,<lb/>who, incidentally, is a dam<lb/>good poet and a dam<lb/>good musician, but who is<lb/>trying to make money by<lb/>persuading people to buy some.  Thing they don't want but which<lb/>he thinks is good for them.  Ever yours,  Harry Williams. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5325_img_0_3"/>
             MANCHESTER COLLEGE OF  TECHNOLOGY.  THE PRINCIPAL'S SALARY.  At a meeting of the Manchester Education<lb/>Committee yesterday, it was agreed to recom-<lb/>mend the City Council to advance the salary<lb/>of Mr. J. C. Maxwell Garnett, Principal of the<lb/>Municipal College of Technology, from £1,000 to<lb/>£1,400 per annum. Sir Thomas Shann (chair-<lb/>man), in submitting the recommendation, said<lb/>Mr. Garnett had had no advance of salary since<lb/>his appointment, seven years ago.  Councillor Grant (deputy chairman), in<lb/>seconding, said the Manchester College of Tech-<lb/>nology was the largest of its kind in this<lb/>country, except one in London, and in that case<lb/>the salary of the chief was something over<lb/>£2, 000 a year. Sir Henry Miers (Vice Chan-<lb/>cellor of the University) supported the proposal,<lb/>which was passed unanimously.  A New Appointment.  The Committee confirmed the appointment of<lb/>Mr. Arthur James Turner as professor of tex-<lb/>tile technology in the College. Mr. Turner has<lb/>had a distinguished career at Gonville and<lb/>Caius College, Cambridge, where he studied<lb/>natural science and mathematics, obtaining<lb/>first-class honours in the Natural Science<lb/>Tripos, part 1, 1910, a second-class in the<lb/>Mathematics Tripos, part 1, 1911, and first-class<lb/>in the Natural Science Tripos, part II., 1912.<lb/>He was also awarded the degree of B. Sc. with<lb/>first class honours in the University of London<lb/>in 1912. During the latter part of 19112 Mr. Turner<lb/>was engaged in research work in organic<lb/>chemistry at Cambridge, under Professor Pope.<lb/>He later accepted an appointment upon the<lb/>scientific staff of the National Physical Labora-<lb/>tory, where he was chiefly engaged in research<lb/>work on fabrics and dopes for aeronautical<lb/>purposes. Following this he was appointed to<lb/>the charge of the Fabrics Laboratory of the<lb/>Royal Aircraft Establishment, where he has<lb/>been engaged on a number of investigations of<lb/>textile problems, chiefly from the physico-<lb/>chemical point of view. Mr. Turner was also<lb/>engagaed upon researches involving the study of<lb/>the differences of spinning and doubling twists<lb/>throughout a complete range of the various<lb/>materials used in the manufacture of yarns and<lb/>fabrics, and for cotton in particular. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>