<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0779">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 28 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender relates the details of a recent &#39;rumpus&#39; between the Army and the Corps in which he serves. He discusses his loneliness as the only young member of his office. He describes the sights of his current locale, expressing surprise at the &#39;mystery and venerability&#39; of the ruins.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/367</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/779</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0779_img_2313_1"  type="NULL"  url="d75c30b544099f725d7ba4ee4be6f624.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0779_img_2313_2"  type="NULL"  url="3628e5adfb69c0d94fb4d64cd15b9d4a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0779_img_2313_1"/>
                To be posted 28 <seg type="del">July</seg> Oct    My p r   The weather has changed tonight &amp; is dry for once but<lb/> I doubt if it lasts and anyhow the roads will be a long 6<lb/> months I expect before they get rid of their <seg type="unclear">shine</seg>, unless<lb/> we get frost. The <seg type="unclear">salvisan</seg> has arrived at least 10 days<lb/> before it became necessary. Many thanks.  There was a bit of a rumpus. The Army which<lb/> I'm afraid likes to get at our Corps began to complain and<lb/> naturally the blame falls on the only division. I was not<lb/> at all sure the b w would not be the scapegoat but I<lb/> believe the G rather stuck up for me. Anyhow for the moment<lb/> in am in  the  Black books because of an unsuccessful little<lb/> raid which in present circumstances I described as <seg type="del">Comp</seg> Tomfoolery<lb/> both to Gen' G and to a youngster of the Army Staff<lb/> who was sent down to get a report. I was really put <lb/> out and asked him to tell his G people what I thought.  A b w on his hind paws is not a very dangerous <lb/> animal â much more so when standing on his head as<lb/> the p r knows! so I don't expect much will come of it.<lb/> However I hope the Corps will soon get other youngsters to<lb/> to play with. It is rather like being the only boy at a<lb/> a big school with the full teaching staff.  For the first time today I saw something verging on<lb/> the picturesque in the ruins &amp; desolation of these villages.<lb/> The shattered walls of a church â probably an ugly one â showing  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0779_img_2313_2"/>
              up against a black  gold  stormy sunset got a touch of majesty<lb/> &amp; vulnerability (?) which they had never possessed before. It was<lb/> the passing thought of the moment and tomorrow in all<lb/> its stark ghostliness I have not doubt I shall fail to <lb/> see it. Sometimes I have thought I should like to bring<lb/> you to visit my many resting places here but on the<lb/> whole I think not no matter under what 'aspect' this<lb/> place can ever have any attraction for me  No mail has come today owing to the boat not<lb/> going, either mines or submarines I suppose I expect I<lb/> shall get some quite undeserved p r communications later! especially<lb/> if it does not run tomorrow. This will I expect often be<lb/> the case this winter but I hope it not often be on<lb/><seg type="del">Sat</seg> Fridays as you will then miss 2 mails running with<lb/> the Sunday post.  Have written a brief line to young Edward <seg type="closer"> Your   b w <lb/> W B Spender  </seg><seg type="postscript"> We tried again to placate the Powers &amp; were again unsuccessful<lb/> so will have another attempt <seg type="del">wasteful</seg> but it really is rather<lb/> unnecessary toil. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>