<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2179">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John R. Moorhead to Robert Brown, 18 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John R. Moorhead</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by John R. Moorhead (1859 – 1936), crown solicitor for Antrim and Belfast, to Robert Brown.

In this letter, Moorhead is replying to an ‘insolent’ letter which he received from Brown concerning a financial claim. Moorhead states that this is the last time that he will enclose the compensation of £4.4.0 and that he wants nothing further to do with Brown’s claim.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/1205/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2179</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1437">John R. Moorhead</persName>
              <date>1916-01-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0205">30 Rosemary Street, Belfast</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1991">10 Quality Street, Leith, Edinburgh, Scotland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1936</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2179_img_1626_1"  type="Letter"  url="a734716929eb63314d3b1add28c6799c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2179_img_1626_1"/>
             Counties of Antrim &amp;Belfast Crown Solicitor's Office<lb/> <lb/>30 Rosemary Street, <lb/>Belfast.   18th <sic>Janry</sic> 1916  <lb/><hi rend="underline">The King v Henry McCambley</hi>  Sir:-   I am in receipt of yours of the 17th and <hi rend="underline">notwithstanding your <lb/>insolence</hi> I take the trouble again and for the last time to return <lb/>you the Clerk of the Crown's cheque for £4-4-0. In doing so I wish <lb/>to say that if you return it to me again I shall not take any further <lb/>trouble in the mater. If you had had the courtesy to read the <lb/>document before writing me in insolent terms you would have seen that <lb/>the cheque is issued by the Clerk of the Crown and is expressed to be <lb/>for "<hi rend="underline">expenses trouble and loss of time prosecuting in this cause <lb/>pursuant to the statutes in that behalf</hi>". I am informed by the Police <lb/>that your travelling expenses were paid and in my certificate to the <lb/>Clerk of the Crown on which this cheque was based I certified only <lb/>for what I considered to be a reasonable sum to cover hotel expenses <lb/>and trouble and loss of time  " pursuant to the Statute. "  I may <lb/>mention that the statute referred to authorizes an allowance for <lb/>loss of time only to "<hi rend="underline">persons in poor circumstances</hi>" and who have <lb/>actually suffered pecuniary loss'  i.e. loss of earnings or wages.  Assuming you to be a person in <lb/>"poor circumstances" and that you had lost six days' time I certified <lb/>for £4.4.0. I have nothing to do with your claim; I know nothing about <lb/>your claim, and I want to know nothing about your claim, and I have <lb/>already informed you that if you are dissatisfied with the amount <!-- letter is incomplete -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>