<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1348">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nannie Beazley née Hickey to Piaras Béaslaí, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nannie Beazley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Nannie Beazely to her son Piaras Béaslaí (1881–1965). Nannie mentions that she is organising to send portraits (probably photographs) to her son. She writes that the DBC (Dublin Bakery Company) was destroyed during the Rising. She makes reference to a large number of personal acquaintances and to their recent endeavours and activities - such as visits to the Curragh races and to a Lieutenant Jack Clancy who had wounded and to a Maudy who had gone on an operatic tour. She says that the prison which Piaras Béaslaí is held in is located in Portland. She asks if she should send him a suit for when he is leaving. She is generally making preparations for his release.Béaslaí was an English born influential member of the IRB. He joined the Irish Volunteers on their foundation late in 1913. When visiting his parents he smuggled guns to Ireland. In February of 1916 he published the Fàinne, a publication to organise Gaelic speakers.Béaslaí was an officer during the Easter Rising. He was court-martialled and sentenced to five years’ for his part. In prison he wrote and memorised poems about his captivity. This letter is part of a collection of letters by Piaras’ parents, mostly during Béaslai’s internment. After his release he soon became involved in politics.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, NLI33973/5/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1348</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0676">Nannie Beazley</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0676">The place of Piaras Béaslaí incarceration</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1348_img_69_1"  type="Letter"  url="ae285c610c30809390347d99c872179f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1348_img_69_1"/>
                Oct 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   My darling Pierce   Again the time comes round to write to you,<lb/> &amp; the months are stealing by, &amp; hastening on to the time<lb/> of your longed for release. I delayed the portraits because<lb/> Nellie Murphy got some new ones done, &amp; I was to send you<lb/> one, but owing to their non-arrival I just sent on one I had.<lb/> I hope you have got the 4 I sent. Your friend Foley says that<lb/> himself &amp; all of his people are quite well &amp; as busy as usual.<lb/> His brothers &amp; sisters have gone back to the older business address<lb/> as their last business building was destroyed. At your usual<lb/> dining club you are constantly spoken of. Lang says the<lb/> D.B.C. in O'Connell St is destroyed, &amp; he can't trace<lb/> Miss Duggan <seg type="del">Shield.</seg> Florrie Skeehan, &amp; her husband were up at the Curragh<lb/> races, &amp; then came on to Dublin. She has a second baby son â her<lb/> brother Herbert says she promises to be stoater than him. Lang<lb/> met Mabel Beer in Bray recently. She had let her house<lb/> in Kingstown, &amp; was living in Bray. I believe Lieutenant<lb/> Jack Clancy has been wounded, &amp; Maudie has gone to America<lb/> on an operatic tour. Aggie Long was up in Dublin<lb/> this last week, to stand an examination for a part in<lb/> the Clonmel Technical School. I don't know yet<lb/> how she got on. Lang met Vr Long lately in Dublin<lb/> &amp; took her to lunch, &amp; she was very anxious about you<lb/> &amp; says Aunt Ellie prays for you constantly. Dont you<lb/> think I should send you a complete outfit to Portland<lb/> when you are leaving as I have all your clothes here<lb/> even the ones you brought to Portland? I think I have<lb/> most of your belongings â except your jewellery â &amp; every<lb/> thing will be in order for you. I have got your navy &amp;<lb/> your black ones cleaned at Campbell's &amp; all your light<lb/> suits will go in turn. And now, my own boy, I must<lb/> finish as my space is coming to an end. May God keep<lb/> &amp; guard &amp; bless you &amp; may He hasten the day of our<lb/> happy meeting prays <seg type="closer"> your loving  Mother. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>