<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3214">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Bradley to Sir Robert Chalmers, 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Bradley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Bradley to Sir Robert Chalmers regarding broken wall between the Mountjoy Prison and North Circular Road Laundry.

Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938) was appointed under-secretary of Ireland in 1916, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-8758</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3214</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0074">John Bradley</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1645">The Treasury, Whitehall, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3214_img_2636_1"  type="Letter"  url="5d63b18c86c37502dd3cc4e7e9894a17.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3214_img_2636_1"/>
             Any reply to this letter should be addressed to— <lb/>THE SECRETARY, <lb/>TREASURY, <lb/>WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.. <lb/>and the following number quoted. <lb/>6061 <lb/>16   TREASURY CHAMBERS.   20 May 1916.   Sir,   I have laid before the Lords Commissioners of <lb/>His Majesty's Treasury Sir M. Nathan's letter of the 3rd <lb/>March last 3719/16 stating that during a storm in Dublin <lb/>on the night of the 12th November last a portion of the <lb/>wall, 15 feet high, forming the boundary between the <lb/>grounds attached to the Medical Officer's quarters at <lb/>Mountjoy Prison and those of the North Circular Laundry <lb/>Company was entirely blown down for length of 24 yards.   In reply I am to enquire whether the needs of <lb/>the case could not be satisfactorily met at a far less <lb/>cost by the erection of a substantial wooden fence by <lb/>the Laundry Company subject to a contribution of one half <lb/>the cost by the Prisons Board.   I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,    John Bradley   The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   Send copy of this letter to <lb/>Prisons Board for their <lb/>observations. <lb/>I.J.T. <lb/>23.V.16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>