<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0763">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 15 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender expresses anger that his private letters are being used in editorials and sermons. He asks Lillian to give a treat of a pound each to &#39;the 3 children families&#39; to allow them to go on holidays, as he worries that the war is stamping the fun out of the children&#39;s lives. He writes about the Division, mentioning that it is as well that he is leaving it soon, as his newly arrived brother Rex will probably settle in better without him &#39;fussing round&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/345</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/763</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0763_img_2295_1"  type="NULL"  url="15358f775138a181ecac1b969e46e7ea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0763_img_2295_2"  type="NULL"  url="788d4e856149b95b2aad371691da3578.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0763_img_2295_1"/>
                15 July.   My   I am really quite angry at the way <lb/>my private letters are being used. The letters of <lb/>condolence are made into Editorials! Or are being <lb/>used for texts in the Cathedral. I really do not <lb/>understand the feelings of people a their craving <lb/>for publicity.  However I don't think any harm has been <lb/>done (except to dood taste) as nothing I have written <lb/>can be objected to by the Censor, but I dislike <lb/>being brought even anonymously into the lime light, <lb/>&amp; I think the old reserve of the Ulstermen was <lb/>far finer than this sudden burst of advertisement.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0763_img_2295_2"/>
              dreadfully afraid they may be used by our stalwarts as <lb/>a reason for passivity &amp; procrastination in the hope that <lb/>the other side will cook the goose for them.  I am longing to hear of your weekend. It is more <lb/>sunny here so perhaps you may get a <seg type="unclear">bathe</seg>. I am <lb/>only 15 M from the sea!  I should like the 3 children families to have <lb/>a treat from us this holidays if you agree. Probably Â£1-00 <lb/>each would give them a good picnic? &amp; I don't want <lb/>to find that this war is stamping out all the youngster's <lb/>enjoyment in life. What say you?  The G is a bit cross with things lately I'm afraid <lb/>he thinks we are 'out of it' now, in a backwater &amp; <lb/>forgotten. Personally I do not mind as I hope the Div <lb/>may get a chance which it would not have otherwise <lb/>but P with whom I have got on much better lately is <lb/>also getting restive. Perhaps it's as well that I am going <lb/>away tho' I should like to help Rex to settle in, but <lb/>he <seg type="del">could</seg> probably do better without my fussing round. <seg type="closer"> You bw, hoping you have returned <lb/>a very p pr, &amp; that <sic>Siredward</sic> will see you don't <lb/>over work.   WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>