<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3949">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington, 14 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,612/18-29</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3949</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-01-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3949_img_3325_1"  type="Letter"  url="a2d50f1e9ef5899dce79821bf0f643e2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3949_img_3325_1"/>
             Private.   11, Grosveror Place, <lb/>Rathmines, Dublin.   14 - I. - I6.   Dear Madam,   You will, I hope, pardon me writin<seg type="del">h</seg>g to you, although not known <lb/>to you personally; I have known your name for a long time in active <lb/>suffrage work in Belfast, and I know you are interested in the IRISH <lb/>CITIZEN, which I have been running, in the interests of the suffrage <lb/>movement, for nearly three years. As you will have seen, the paper <lb/>is sadly in need of funds just now, the week<seg type="del">b</seg> l y loss, though small, <lb/>having piled up a considerable debt. Of this debt, £100 is owed to <lb/>a bank, from which I borrowed it in September, 1914, in order to meet <lb/>the pressing demands of the printer at that time. The loan is <lb/>guaranteed by three good signatures besides my own; I have paid the <lb/>interest myself, but have not been able to reduce the principal. Now <lb/>one of the guarantors wishes to withdraw her name, because she is in <lb/>favour of conscription, and objects to our opposition to it. The <lb/>other two guarantors are both excellent securities for the amount; <lb/>but in these days banks are extra cautious, and a third signature <lb/>will be required to replace that which is withdrawn. May I ask <lb/>whether you could consent to help in this difficulty by replacing <lb/>the withdrawn guarantor?   If you are prepared to consider the matter, <seg type="del">the</seg> I will give <lb/>you all details, names of the other guarantors, &amp;c, before you final- <lb/>ly decide.   With apologies for troubling you, but feeling sure that you will <lb/>forgive my appeal, even if you cannot respond to it, in the interests <lb/>of the feminist movement,   <hi rend="underline">F.S. Skeffington</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>