<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2224">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenerg Montgomery to Edward Carson, 31 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenerg Montgomery (1844-1924). Montgomery was a landowner and politician. Originally a liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
This letter was written to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a lawyer and a politician. In 1916 he was at the peak of his parliamentary influence. It was in 1916 that he accepted the first lordship of the admiralty from Lloyd George (1863-1945). He held this, one of the most demanding of wartime offices, between December 1916 and July 1917. In addition to this, Carson was also a leading unionist figure in Irish politics. He sanctioned the formation of the paramilitary Ulster Volunteer Force in January 1913; and he helped to found the Ulster provisional government of September 1913.
In this letter Montgomery states that he is enclosing a letter which he wrote &#39;for the sake of blowing off steam&#39; . Montgomery writes that the enclosure should prove useful to show what Irish unionists at home are thinking and that he is considering sending it into the &#34;Times&#34; but he would not like to do anything to increase Carson&#39;s difficulties.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2224</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-05-31</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2224_img_1669_1"  type="Letter"  url="e4aba2fc246ea9ac018a141ebbe361c0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2224_img_1669_1"/>
            Copy  31st May, 1916.   My dear Carson,    I dictated the enclosed chiefly for the sake of <lb/> blowing off steam, but two mutual friends of ours in Dublin <lb/> who saw it expressed a strong wish that I should get it into <lb/> the "Times." I had my doubts, and referred the matter to <lb/> a permanent official in London who holds my views very strongly, <lb/> but who has exceptional opportunities of knowing how the land <lb/> lies. He thinks it would be bad tactics to publish this letter, <lb/> but useful to rub the contents into our friends, or those who <lb/> ought to be our friends. There is nothing the least new to <lb/> you in it, but I send you a couple of copies on the off-chance <lb/> of your finding it useful to show what Irish Unionists at <lb/>home are thinking.    The situation is very ticklish, and none of us would <lb/> like to do or say anything that could possibly increase your <lb/> difficulties.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>