<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1393">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir John Maxwell to Herbert Henry Asquith, 12 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Grenfell Maxwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir John Grenfell Maxwell (1859-1929) to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928). Maxwell writes to advise Asquith on the Bishop of Cork, Dr. Daniel Cohalan, (1858-1952). Dr.Cohalan was later an outspoken critic during the Irish War of Independence, condemning acts of violence on both sides. The letter is a response to questions arising from the killing of Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916), a pacifist. At the time of writing Maxwell doesn&#39;t know the identity of the military officer who was present at the arrest of Sheehy Skeffington but he makes a point to say that it was not Captain Bowen Colthurst (1880-1966). Maxwell says in this letter that, as far as he knows, the death of Sheehy Skeffington was not known at the time of the search. However, it is reported elsewhere that the search was ordered by Colthurst in an effort to find evidence against Sheehy Skeffington which might go towards justification of his actions. The letter also gives number of troops serving in Dublin and refers to an article in the nationalist newspaper, the &#39;Freeman&#39;s Journal&#39;. As Asquith was due in Dublin on the date of the letter, it may have served as a briefing.Herbert Henry Asquith was Liberal Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1908 to 1916. Sir John Henry Grenfell Maxwell was appointed commander in chief of the British forces in Ireland after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. Before 1916, Maxwell briefly held command of British troops in Egypt, where he successfully organised defences against a Turkish attack in February 1915 and presided over the huge expansion of his command as Egypt became a major British imperial military base. In March 1916, having been superseded as general officer commanding in Egypt, he was recalled home when the Easter Rising broke out.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/512</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1393</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1393_img_776_1"  type="Letter"  url="78c1a864b355755045557850273e8693.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1393_img_776_2"  type="Letter"  url="413760fdcc81926e011872a76abe95fb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1393_img_776_1"/>
                May 12. 1916   Dear Mr. Asquith,   The name of the Bishop of Cork is D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><lb/>Daniel Cohalan.  Mr.F.Sheehy Skeffington's house in Dublin <lb/> was searched on Friday the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April, in <lb/> accordance with general instructions <lb/> that the houses of suspects were to be searched <lb/> for arms. Military assistance was given <lb/> to the police for this purpose. It was not done <lb/> by Capt Bowen Colthurst - I am enquiring <lb/> as to what officer was present. As far as <lb/> I know Mr.Sheehy Skeffington's death was <lb/> not known of at the time the search was <lb/> made. I enclose a paper on this gentleman' s<lb/> antecedents.  The number of troops in Ireland irrespective <lb/> of 59<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division is roughly<lb/> 17000 Infantry<lb/> 3149 Cavalry<lb/> 1000 Artillery but these<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1393_img_776_2"/>
              <lb/>are all the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> line troops and draft <lb/> finding units.  Will it be convenient for you to visit <lb/> Richmond Barracks at 2.30 tomorrow <lb/> and afterwards George V hospital as <lb/> I find I have an inspection at 4p.m. <lb/> at Trinity College, Dublin. <seg type="closer"> Yours very truly  J.G.Maxwell. </seg> P.S. I would call your attention to <lb/> the leading article in today's Freeman's <lb/> Journal  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>