<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0012">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James O'Connor to Patrick Dyer, 27 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James O&#39;Connor</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from James O&#39;Connor, a solicitor based on Dame Street in Dublin, to Patrick Dyer. O&#39;Connor writes to enclose a letter from the Chief Crown Solicitor. Dyer had been arrested, presumably under the new Defence of the Realm Act, and the Chief Crown Solicitor&#39;s office had written to inform O&#39;Connor of the date of his hearing. Both letters are included here. Written on the back of both letters is a note from Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947), presumably to his wife Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958). The note refers to family visits, his children and asks that news to passed to the family of a fellow prisoner.Desmond FitzGerald was serving a six month sentence in Mountjoy prison having been convicted under the new Defence of the Realm legislation for making a seditious speech and was in prison with Dyer. He later served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Mountjoy, Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1535</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/12</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0242">James O&#39;Connor</persName>
              <date>1915-11-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0194">57 Dame Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Patrick Dyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1165">Mountjoy Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0012_img_1039_1"  type="Letter"  url="d3a8d896c0daa0550b98d6e496eaf8fc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0012_img_1039_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="a18d9930b6f9be8a8d5bdb44e2c492e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0012_img_1039_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="d2cb88d718c06146fd9818cb4c7e75d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0012_img_1039_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="9ffba550d7b67f2d640e9d0b28841b90.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0012_img_1039_1"/>
                James O'Connor,  Solicitor.  TEL NO 4736.   57 Dame Street,  Dublin.    27th November, 1915.   Dear Sir,    I herewith enclose you a copy letter which came from the Chief <lb/> Crown Solicitor this morning which speaks for itself. <lb/> I shall call to see you at three o'clock on Monday.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  J O'Connor   Patrick Dyer, Esq.,  H.M. Prison,  Mountjoy,  Dublin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0012_img_1039_2"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi> <seg type="head">re Patrick Dyer</seg>   26th November 1915   Dear Sir,   I have ascertained that this case will be <lb/> heard in the Southern Police Court Dublin on <lb/> Tuesday next at 12 o'clock or as soon after that <lb/> hour as the other business will permit.  <seg type="closer"> yours truly <lb/><hi rend="superscript">Signed</hi> M. Kelly    James O'Connor Esq.,  Solicitor,  57 Dame St.,  Dublin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0012_img_1039_3"/>
              Ordinary visit on Monday permits <lb/><hi rend="underline">3</hi> persons for 20 minutes. Ask <lb/> for permission for <hi rend="underline">4</hi> persons <lb/> â my mother,brother, sister, wife â <lb/> for a longer period.   Ask D. Rynd to write to Mrs. E Mac- <lb/> Queen, 98 Hyndford Rd, Bloomfield <lb/> Belfast - am old parishioner of her <lb/> father's â to tell her that her son is <lb/> in Mountjoy for desertion. He would <lb/> like to know if she has received any of <lb/> his allotment, what her circumstances <lb/> are at present. He much regrets the trouble <lb/> he has caused her. He leaves Mountjoy Jan 19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/> &amp; will be taken to Victoria Barracks <lb/> Belfast. If D.S. doesn't get a reply within <lb/> one week she might come to visit the <lb/> prisoner.   I hope Mclave is visited every <lb/> day. Get E. O'Duffy or McCarthy to <lb/> check and oil my bicycle &amp; <hi rend="underline">the other <lb/> plaything </hi>  As much chocolate in the smallest possible <lb/> space. There may be a chance. I have <lb/> received <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the news &amp; <lb/> am delighted &amp; thankful that <seg type="unclear">Demeen</seg> is <seg type="unclear">saved</seg> to <lb/> us, &amp; well again, God bless him.   I am in excellent spirits &amp; health &amp;  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0012_img_1039_4"/>
              count everyone to be perfectly happy &amp; <lb/> Xmas &amp; not to worry about me in the <lb/> least. I have no expectation of getting <lb/> out before March 31 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi>.   I am looking forward to Monday <lb/> all the time. After that it will be to the <lb/> letter &amp; then to the next visit &amp; so on <lb/> till I am out again. I do hope that my <lb/> imprisonment won't damp my dear ones' <lb/> spirits at Xmas. I am in excellent <lb/> form - fatter than I have ever been in <lb/> my life.   A very very happy Xmas to all my <lb/> dear ones. I <sic>shd.</sic> like to be there with them, <lb/> but it can't be helped. I am more thankful <lb/> than I can say that my wee son is spared, <lb/> how small a matter is this little term <lb/> of imprisonment when one thinks <lb/> of that. I hope that as soon as ever <lb/> it is possible, we shall all be together <lb/> in my mother's house. I know my <lb/> mother will like being in Dublin again. <lb/> I imagine that the place she lived in as a <lb/> child will be near Phoenix Park.   My dear ones will be doing me an ill <lb/> turn if they go worry about me <lb/> in stead of being perfectly happy as <lb/> I am thinking of the visit on Monday.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>