<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1411">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 2 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. The lovely weather makes him long for holidays and he&#39;s counting the days to Easter Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters. They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats. James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>Finn Family Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1411</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-04-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1427">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1411_img_815_1"  type="Letter"  url="3b46a58e577cbacc4418de5c2d53e07f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1411_img_815_2"  type="Letter"  url="f4f3a02d58a5681a613d3ee1bcde5f5b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1411_img_815_3"  type="Letter"  url="57bd1b7eab9a306ba1f702a4cb7f5b1c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1411_img_815_1"/>
                39 Belgrave Sq  Dublin    2 April, 1916   My dearest love,   You are awfully good to write <lb/> to me so constantly and especially so when <lb/> you have to do all your own messages. <lb/> Your letters make me very happy so that I <lb/> don't feel the day pass until I am hearing <lb/> from you again. All the same I'm not so <lb/> selfish as to wish you to write to me <hi rend="underline">every</hi><lb/> day so please don't be fretting yourself about <lb/> writing except when you find it convenient. <lb/> I was out walking for a good while to-day but <lb/> my company was not so pleasant as I <lb/> could have had if I had only deferred my <lb/> country visit until this Sunday. I was <lb/> thinking of you all the time and wondering  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1411_img_815_2"/>
              <lb/>what you were doing but I suppose you were <lb/> busy with homework at the time and had <lb/> no time to spare for such a worthless chap as <lb/> me. The weather these days makes you long for <lb/> holidays and to be able to get away from <lb/> the treadmill of the office especially when you <lb/> know what pleasure and happiness await you <lb/> if you could only manage to get the liberty. <lb/>However it's not long now till Easter next <lb/> Thursday fortnight and it won't be long <lb/> passing and six weeks after that will be <lb/> the day of days. I'll start marking them off day <lb/> by day from this on like I used to do at <lb/> school and I'll keep my heart warm and <lb/> my hopes up in the meantime. I'm sure I'll <lb/>l have a lovely time at Easter and on the <lb/> whole I'm not sorry that you are not anxious <lb/> to go to the races. I'd be bound to go down<cb/><lb/> to them, nothing could keep me away and as I <lb/> couldn't for shame sake spend another weekend <lb/> in   so soon I'd only see you for <lb/> a few minutes in a crowd and it would only <lb/> increase my heartache rather than relieve it. It <lb/> will be much better to have you up for a while <lb/> than that and I feel like hugging you now ( I <lb/> wish I could!!) for being such a dear good little <lb/> girl as to agree to come up. My mother will be <lb/> delighted to have you for as long as you'll stay, sure <lb/> it's hardly worth your while going back and your <lb/> own little man will worship you and the ground <lb/> you stand on all the time. By the way when I <lb/> come down at Easter I'd like to bring you something <lb/> just to show my love. Would you like anything <lb/> special? How about a scarf or gloves or something <lb/> of that sort. If you wish it, I can get Nora to <lb/> help me buy and so you could be sure of the <lb/> taste being all right, if I bought myself I'd probably <lb/> make an awful mess of it. Nobody made an April  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1411_img_815_3"/>
              <lb/>fool of me. I wish I had been with you for <lb/> the pleasure of having it done to me but I know <lb/>the June fooling will be the best and sweetest <lb/> in the world. You're quite right in saying that <lb/> you made a January fool of me or perhaps <lb/> hardly a <hi rend="underline">January</hi> one because it was a very long <lb/> time before January that you turned my silly <lb/> head. You have a lot to answer for in that <lb/> way so I hope you will do your full and <lb/> proper wifely duty when you pledge yourself. <seg type="unclear">And</seg><lb/> I know very well you will but I like to jibe <lb/> you about it in any case, and I like to talk <lb/> about  it  or think about it when I'm alone. No <lb/> news at all today except the lovely weather. The <lb/> boys must be killed these days with the rush <lb/> of the opening work so long deferred. Hope they're <lb/> sowing plenty of spuds and oats because we might <lb/> all have to live on them this year. Give my regards <lb/> to your mother, Nans and all and my heart's deepest <lb/> and warmest love for my darling <seg type="closer"> From her loving  James </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>