<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1417">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Julia Evans to Mabel FitzGerald, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Julia Evans</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Julia Evans to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). Mrs. Evans writes to thank Mabel for her &#39;kind assistance in our great distress&#39;. Her husband had been arrested after the Rising and she sympathises with Mabel having learned that Mr FitzGerald is also under arrest. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1573/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1417</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0455">Julia Evans</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0065">22 Harold&#39;s Cross Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1417_img_828_1"  type="Letter"  url="1cc07dea2cdf86078e6ddbf5d28f7655.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1417_img_828_2"  type="Letter"  url="d28483d9c6a0e7934770644c3b38db61.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1417_img_828_1"/>
                22 Harolds Cross Road  Dublin    May 13.1916  <lb/>To Mrs.Desmond Fitzgerald  Dear Madam   I am very thankful <lb/> to you for your kindness in <lb/> assisting me in my trouble. <lb/> I am very sorry to learn <lb/> your husband is also under <lb/> arrest. God grant they may <lb/> soon be released to us. <lb/> Hope your children are getting  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1417_img_828_2"/>
              <lb/>better and may the Lord comfort <lb/> and console you, again <lb/> thanking you for your kind <lb/> assistance in our great distress <seg type="closer"> Respectfully Yours  Julia Evans </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>