<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2688">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Moynihan to his brother, Michael Moynihan, 28 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Moynihan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is written on hearing upon Michael&#39;s imminent departure to the front.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>University College Dublin Collection List P57/190</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2688</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1368">John Moynihan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1137">Tralee, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1459">Michael Moynihan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2688_img_211_1"  type="Letter"  url="1543ea57ed970111e21d97c45e04b94d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2688_img_211_2"  type="Letter"  url="d0bcc89d8a3cbe202dee6cf81be39c44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2688_img_211_3"  type="Letter"  url="24fedc9c40d118a1383ac7879d1a8ede.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2688_img_211_4"  type="Letter"  url="aa89c1d93bd8e3f53b51a5e1391938fb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2688_img_211_1"/>
             Tralee   29 May 1916 <lb/><lb/> My dear Michael,   Evidently, if that rumour, of which<lb/><seg type="del">deleted text</seg> you have told Mother, is true, the decision<lb/>to send your battalion to the front<lb/>must have come sooner than you expected.<lb/>It would be well if you could get that<lb/>leave before going. But we <seg type="del">even</seg> feel,<lb/>and even Mother, notwithstanding her<lb/>fears, feels that in any case you will be<lb/>safe. I have an impression that you are<lb/>not the sort of person to die young, and,<lb/>in addition, a curious confidence in such<lb/>instincts.  I enclose an inflammatory and<lb/>seditious document, which bears a German-<lb/>looking signature. It would seem, on this<lb/>ground, to be the production of an unin-<lb/>terned Hun, and on other, internal evidence,<lb/>to be an effort to draw a namesake<lb/>of yours from his allegiance to the king<lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2688_img_211_2"/>
              and his duty as a soldier. Would it be<lb/>worth while to bring this man's treasonable<lb/>activities to the notice of the Daily Mail<lb/>and the Rebellion Commission.<lb/>J. Moynihan   P.S. You will probably be especially<lb/>interested in that portion of the evidence<lb/>produced before the Hardinge Commission which<lb/>deals with Kerry. County Inspector Hill stated<lb/>that the Kerry Volunteers mobilised and<lb/>then in consequence of some arrests got ner-<lb/>vous and went home. This is, to say the<lb/>least misleading. The facts are that on Good<lb/>Friday Austin Stack and Collins, a Post Office<lb/>official, were arrested; following the arrests<lb/>which were efffected by stratagem the<lb/>Tralee Volunteers mobilised and spent<lb/>some hours parading the town armed<lb/>and at times proceeding at double pace<lb/>and, I believe, giving other indications that<lb/>they were eager for fight. There were not interfered<lb/>with in any way and dispersed<lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2688_img_211_3"/>
              late that night, presumably tired of their<lb/>manoeuvres. On Easter Sunday there was a<lb/>general muster at which there were present<lb/>according to my reckoning from 800 to 2000<lb/>men. This was part of a general scheme<lb/>of Easter manoeuvres all over the country.<lb/>The manoeuvres were cancelled at the last<lb/>moment by Headquarters, but were carried<lb/>out in Tralee owing to the presence of a<lb/>number of country volunteers who in some<lb/>cases marched 30 or 40 miles to be present.<lb/>During all Easter week the country was on<lb/>the verge of an outbreak but partly to the<lb/>wishes of Casement which had been conveyed<lb/>to the local leaders , partly to the im-<lb/>possibility of communication with Headquarters<lb/>and to the uncertainty of what was going on<lb/>in Dublin, partly to other causes, <lb/>nothing happened. But no further<lb/>arrests were made until May 9th (I think),<lb/>after the volunteers had delivered up their<lb/>arms and when there were between one<lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2688_img_211_4"/>
             and two thousand soldiers, including artillery-men,<lb/>in town.<lb/> J.M.  P.S. (still another) If you still wish to<lb/>get the Irish Catholic I shall send it to<lb/>you. I have given up the rag; its<lb/>politics always objectionable are utterly<lb/>insufferable under present conditions. If I<lb/>were to continue reading there is a danger<lb/>that I should develop a definite homicidal<lb/>tendency.  As to Dr. Kane's lectures I<lb/>have no doubt they will be published<lb/>in book later on. I shall have a look<lb/>out and get them for you.  This last P.S was a happy<lb/>thought; in these times it would be mad-<lb/>ness and highly dangerous to the realm<lb/>to allow so much paper go waste. Had<lb/>it not been for the Summer Time Act I<lb/>might have spent another hour filling<lb/>in the margins and the spaces between<lb/>the lines. As a law abiding subject I<lb/>will let you off for this time.   J.M. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>