<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2867">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 27 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

Spender complains of the disturbance to his sleep caused by a painful wisdom tooth and the increasingly noisy front. He despairs at the lack of purpose or consistency in the fighting, and states his growing support for a &#39;benevolent autocracy&#39;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/326</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2867</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-06-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2867_img_2279_1"  type="NULL"  url="cbaacbc32d27e4ef7cb1b3cb557dec48.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2867_img_2279_2"  type="NULL"  url="1077e201f148be6ceebeceee07580028.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2867_img_2279_1"/>
             27 June   My pr   Only a scrap to <lb/>accompany my note to Lil <lb/>which you need not pass on <lb/>if you think it best but not to <lb/>do so. With an old wisdom <lb/>tooth &amp; a <seg type="unclear">head</seg>, &amp; 3 AM <lb/> bed this bw is not quite <lb/>his best, tho' he got a <lb/>new packet of <seg type="unclear">mitcum</seg> <lb/>- sheets - which did him <lb/>good.   I'm very much afraid <lb/> of your being over worked &amp; <lb/>wish some of the others <lb/>could come &amp; help you. I <lb/>think you must try &amp; get <lb/>some regular worker now
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2867_img_2279_2"/>
            &amp; perhaps <seg type="del">some of</seg> Miss Scrum <lb/>might do failing others . I <lb/>will gladly pay expenses.   A great deal of noise <lb/>today which will I suppose <lb/>continue for some time, <lb/>but one is a little disappointed<lb/>by the lack of <lb/>steady purpose, &amp; the changes <lb/>which perpetually occur. <lb/>I believe more &amp; more in <lb/>a benevolent autocracy !    I am very busy &amp; <lb/>shall be for some days <lb/>so you will get nothing <lb/>but scraps.   Your very own   bw <lb/>WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>