<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4268">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 3 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/205</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4268</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4268_img_3633_1"  type="Letter"  url="11bd07ebf98392c30efd6f94c0140b84.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4268_img_3633_2"  type="Letter"  url="9f168199138c3580f1297b275c891b8e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4268_img_3633_3"  type="Letter"  url="69d7317b98f96141576978e5d4d8ee24.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4268_img_3633_4"  type="Letter"  url="183a71764053bd78cc032749c355f81e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4268_img_3633_1"/>
             3 April   My p r   I am writing in the middle of a move &amp; am <lb/> rather glad of the hustle . As you can imagine, this <lb/> waiting period is rather trying for R &amp; for me too <lb/> in consequence as I do feel for him. He is such a <lb/> gentleman &amp; tho' he is not too strong in character — <lb/> he would have done splendidly.  News just come The new man who <lb/> comes here is a Major Place from the 19<hi rend="superscript">th (new)</hi> <lb/> Division where he was GSO2. He was a sapper <lb/> but I do not know what he is like. I fancy a <lb/>good deal younger than myself but I shan't mind <lb/> that if he is really a useful chap. He will have <lb/> been out here 2 or 3 months longer than I have <lb/> been, &amp; has probably seen much more fighting. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4268_img_3633_2"/>
             K has been about these parts and is reported <lb/> to have said that the war will be over in <lb/> August which if true as being his remark is <lb/> certainly astounding as he is not supposed to <lb/> be an optimist, but he may have come straight <lb/> from Verdun &amp; got infected there. If this is the <lb/> case I hope Carson will play up &amp; be quick, othe r<lb/>wise Squiffy will hang on to get the credit !   I wonder where you and I will spend the autumn <lb/> if this proves to be true — looking for houses in the <lb/> West? another furnished house in Ulster ? — or <lb/> staying in town — probably none of the 3. It may <lb/> be advisable for one to have a <seg type="unclear">paid-a-term</seg> in town <lb/> in order to be in touch with what is going on, but <lb/> I expect you &amp; I will want to hide our diminished <lb/> heads somewhere away in the country.   However there's a lot of work to be done first.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4268_img_3633_3"/>
             I enclose a letter from <seg type="del"> </seg> <seg type="unclear">Blakers'</seg> . I suppose I must <lb/> accept yet another Godson in his case tho' I have <lb/>repeatedly refused others. I am so glad he seems to <lb/> have been given a chance at last, &amp; that they <lb/> are doing the right thing in employing him away <lb/> from Europe where there can be no question of <lb/> French mistrust.   I am meeting such a lot of old pals <lb/> mostly Generals including a Divisional Commander <lb/> whom I last called a "dark green landlubber not <lb/> fit to steer Noah's ark"! This was at a sailing <lb/> race in Malta where he  Gen' Couper  fouled me badly. He <lb/> was in the Rifle brigade hence the dark green epithet <lb/> I forget what his terms were to me but something <lb/> much stronger no doubt.   I wish I could see our Army Commander's face <lb/> if I told him that you had been stopping the week end <lb/> with the future prime minister. I fancy it would cause
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4268_img_3633_4"/>
            him an acute pain for the moment !    I don't think our new plan will be so bad in the <lb/> Summer which now really seems in the air, if the <lb/>birds are true prophets. I rather wish I had asked Douglas <lb/> to bring out my medium vests but it was not <lb/> indicated when he left with snow on the ground !     beat the Gen' in his row, &amp; to tell the <lb/> truth the latter has so many enemies now that <lb/> he cannot afford to make any more big ones; <lb/> but for his temper he would have done better as <lb/> there are elements of greatness in him.   I am just handing over to  Col Fuller GSO1 of <lb/> the Division coming to our HQ. I handed over <lb/> to him once before many years ago at the War <lb/> office.   It is a lovely day &amp; the birds are singing <lb/> merrily but I want to hear the songs of another <lb/> litlle animal which is not supposed to be anything <lb/> but a squeak which shows my bad taste.    Your b w   WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>