<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0102">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Lewis Martin, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). The letter refers to Marie&#39;s life and surroundings in her new posting along with the work she is doing there. She is unable to disclose her location but gives her mother clues to guess it. She concludes with a happy birthday message to her mother.Marie was later the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary. At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle until she was called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo, France.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B/F/1/42, B/F/1/42</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/102</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0102_img_1184_1"  type="Letter"  url="c3c1fc8eb3956f87274dcb9cd6d2ce54.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0102_img_1184_2"  type="Letter"  url="c6c8ad21d4484a491d4a897aff004d5a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0102_img_1184_3"  type="Letter"  url="6c61fda9f6337145d966a5d600792c5a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0102_img_1184_4"  type="Letter"  url="0cccbc170bea1e9838c06c8b6a6ebc68.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0102_img_1184_1"/>
              B/F/1/42    No 25 General Hospi.  B. E. F.    <hi rend="underline">18<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> June 1916</hi>   My very dearest Mother.   We arrived here <lb/>last night about 7â30, it is <lb/>a very large Hospital but <lb/>rather quaint, it is a seaâ <lb/>side resort which has been <lb/>taken over by the Military as <lb/>a Hospital, they are sweet <lb/>little Villas &amp; we are billeted <lb/>in some of them also the <lb/>strand is just perfect with <lb/>glorious silver sand â which <lb/>I am enjoying whilst <lb/>writing this short note â I <lb/>do not think we could have <lb/>possibly been sent to a <seg type="unclear">healthier</seg><lb/>spot it is really quite like <lb/>Malta in some ways, there <lb/>are a great number of tents  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0102_img_1184_2"/>
              &amp; altogether we lead a very <lb/>out of door life. I was in the <lb/> ward this morning for a short <lb/>time, it is surgical but do <lb/>not know what sort of cases <lb/>yet but they all look to <lb/>me fairly well &amp; wont be <lb/>here long. Some of the girls <lb/>seem very nice but none of <lb/>them have been here very <lb/>long.  We had a great voyage out <lb/>leaving Charing Cross by mail <lb/>train &amp; came across on <lb/>a mail boat which was <lb/>packed &amp; we all just sat <lb/>on our luggage it was fairly <lb/>rough in parts. After having <lb/>lunch at the Bologne <lb/><seg type="unclear">Lower</seg> Hotel we all went <lb/>for a short walk round <lb/>the town â but did not <lb/>have much time as we  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0102_img_1184_3"/>
              had to be back in <lb/>the hotel at 5 o'ckâ <lb/>to see the matron who <lb/>packed us off hereâ <lb/>I am sending you a <lb/>riddle so as you may <lb/>guess the place I am at. <lb/> 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi> the opposite of soft 2<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">nd</hi></hi> the <lb/>5<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> letter in the Alphabet 3<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> the <lb/>name of the man whose wife <lb/>turned into a pillar of saltâ <lb/>you have got the nameâ <lb/>Before I close this I must <lb/>wish you a happy <lb/>birthday as possible under <lb/>the circumstances &amp; every <lb/>blessing good wish &amp; luck <lb/>I only wish I were at <lb/>home to enjoy it with <lb/>you ââ In a few days <lb/>time I shall be able  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0102_img_1184_4"/>
              to write you a better <lb/>account of every thing <lb/>I am very tired toânight <lb/>&amp; want to get up for <lb/>6â30 Mass toâmorrow <lb/>morning <seg type="unclear">S. V.</seg> so will <lb/>close this, excuse the <lb/>way it is written but <lb/>I am in bed now &amp; <lb/>very sleepâ   With my fondest love <lb/>good wishes &amp; many <lb/>happy returns of the <lb/>dayâ <seg type="closer"> Your most loving <lb/>daughter  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>