<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0121">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Rundle to Mr Campbell, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William John Rundle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William John Rundle (b.1865) to Mr. Campbell. The letter contains the details of Rundle&#39;s whereabouts from Saturday 22 April to 1 May, the weekend prior to, and the week in which, the Easter Rising took place. Rundle states he spent most of his time at his private address or on patrol. Rundle&#39;s record of patrol was given to his local Officer Training Corp unit. The corp, nicknamed the &#39;Gorgeous Wrecks&#39; owing to the &#39;Georgious Rex&#39; badges they wore and their advanced age, were a voluntary training militia.The Georgeous Rex volunteers suffered several casualties, including the death of IRFU president Francis Browning (1868-1916), during the fighting at Mount Street Bridge. Irish Volunteers stationed at 25 Northumberland Road fired upon them as they returned from training exercises in the Wicklow mountains.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/04051916/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/121</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0741">William John Rundle</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr Campbell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0121_img_1205_1"  type="Letter"  url="8741807a890a043004ddd11b9bd08ada.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0121_img_1205_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">R.H. Office</hi>   Mr Campbell,   From Saturday April 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> until <lb/>noon Monday May 1st I was in Bray. <seg type="del">Some</seg> Most <lb/> of the time was spent at my private address <lb/>3 Brennan's Terrace, but each night I went <lb/> on patrol duty for a limited time <seg type="unclear">minding</seg><lb/> the Royal Irish Constabulary. For this please <lb/> refer to the District Inspector, Mr H. Molony. <seg type="closer"> W. J. Rundle,   4th May 1916.  </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S. My services on patrol were given as a member <lb/>of the local GR corps. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>