<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2494">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from C. O'Connell Fitzsimon to D. Windrum Carlisle, 4 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>C. O&#39;Connell Fitzsimon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Christopher O&#39;Connell Fitzsimon (1860 - 1947), a solicitor from Queen&#39;s County. The letter was written by David Windrum Carlisle (b. 1887). Carlisle was a district inspector with the Royal Irish Constabulary. During the First World War he was seconded into the Royal Garrison Artillery until he was invalided out in 1919 after being severely wounded. 

This letter concerns the application of William Phelan for an extension of his six-day early closing licence under the Licensing Act, 1902. Phelan&#39;s notice of application and application form are enclosed with the letter.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-1551-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2494</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0491">C. O&#39;Connell Fitzsimon</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0617">Abbeyleix, County Laois, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">David Windrum Carlisle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0617">Abbeyleix, County Laois, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_1"  type="Letter"  url="c60bf2d73b28624c0d1df0478e599682.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="23130e69d4362a1969254d1267ed44ef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="e8528996bafebbfaa6b3bb9a582b21da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="3aedebd23e89e2d12d6204cfd55c8e99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="826999163b303a3a87b7626d9ba11ff5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="3646872148aad2568b6eba75d5a6ba32.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2494_img_1929_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="f117c4ca4160ece550520225ed6e234b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_1"/>
             ackd 8 July 1916  <lb/> C O'CONNELL FITZSIMON<lb/>SOLICITOR<lb/><lb/>ABBEYLEIX  <lb/> 4th July 1916 <lb/> Dear Sir <lb/>Referring to the application for a six-<lb/>day early-closing licence made on behalf of<lb/>Wm Phelan of Ballinakill to the Justices at<lb/>Abbeyleix Quarter Sessions on the 26th June<lb/>last and which was granted by the Court I<lb/>beg to state that having looked into the<lb/>authorities the applicant Mr Phelan<lb/>instructs me to inform you that he will make<lb/>no use of the certificates or order made in<lb/>his favour but will continue to trade under<lb/>the existing six-day early closing licence<lb/>and he does not propose to apply to the In-<lb/>land Revenue for an extension of the said<lb/>early-closing licence notwithstanding the<lb/>order of the Justices.  <lb/> Yours faithfully <lb/>C O'Connell Fitzsimon<lb/> D. Windrum Caslisle, Esq.<lb/>D.I.R.I.C<lb/>Abbeyleix.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_2"/>
             Notice of Application to Quarter Sessions for Certifi-<lb/>ate for Publican's Licence.  TAKE NOTICE that it is my intention to<lb/>apply at the next General Quarter Sessions of the Peace<lb/>to be held in Abbeyleix in and for the Division of<lb/>Ballinakill and Queen's County on the 26th day of June<lb/>next for a certificate to entitle me to receive a six-<lb/>day ordinary licence to sell beer cider and spirits by<lb/>retail for consumption on the premises at my house<lb/>situate at The Square in the town of Ballinakill<lb/>townland of Ballinakill Parish of Dysartgallen Barony<lb/>of Cullenagh and Queen's County at present licensed for<lb/>such sale in my name under six-day early closing<lb/>licence and my place of abode is The Square Ballinakill<lb/>in the Queen's County  <lb/>Dated this 31st day of May 1916<lb/> William Phelan  Applicant.<lb/>C O'Connell Fitzsimon,<lb/>Solicitor for Applicant Abbeyleix.  <lb/>To:<lb/>Colonel Sir Wm. Hutcheson Poe, Bart., C. B., J. P.,<lb/>Walter J. Murphy, Esq., J. P.<lb/>James Moore Esq., J. P.<lb/>Robert T. FitzGerald, Esq.,<lb/>Clerk of the Crown &amp; Peace,<lb/>Peace Office Maryborough.<lb/>And to:<lb/>David Windrum Carlisle, Esq., D. I. R. I. C., Abbeyleix. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_3"/>
             Abbeyleix Quarter Sessions 26th June 1916<lb/>Before His Honor the Hon D FitzGerald Chairman and the other Justices<lb/>there assembled viz:-, Col Poe, Patrick Maher, John Walsh, James Moore  No. Name of applicant Nature of Licence Decision of Court<lb/>applied for<lb/>4 Phelan William Six day ordinary licence Granted<lb/>Ballinakill D FitzGerald - Chairman of Quarter Session  I certify above to be a true copy of the entry in the<lb/>Licensing Book<lb/>   <lb/><!-- stamp -->CLERK OF THE CROWN AND PEACE<lb/>QUEEN'S COUNTY<lb/>   
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_4"/>
             Notice of Application to Quarter Sessions for<lb/>Certificate for Publican's Licence  <lb/>TAKE NOTICE that it is my intention to apply at the next General Quarter<lb/>Sessions of the Peace to be held at Abbeyleix  in and for the Division of Ballinakill<lb/>and Queen's County on the 26th day of June next,<lb/>for a Certificate to entitle me to receive a six day ordinary<lb/>Licence to Sell<lb/>Beer Cider and Spirits by Retail <seg type="del">at</seg> for consumption on the premises at my<lb/>house situate at the Square i the Town of<lb/>Ballinakillk Townland of Ballinakill<lb/><seg type="del">in the</seg>Parish of Lysartgallen Barony of<lb/>Cullenagh and Queens County at present licensed for such sale in my<lb/>name under a six day early closing licence and my place of abode is<lb/>The Square Ballinakill in the Queens County <seg type="del">and Queen's County</seg><lb/>Dated this 31 st day of May 1916 <seg type="del">190</seg><lb/>William Phelan<lb/>Applicant<lb/>C. O'Connell Fitzsimon Solicitor for Applicant<lb/>Abbeyleix<lb/>To Col Sir Wm Hutcheson Poe, Bart., C. B., J. P.<lb/>W alter J. Murphy Esq J. P.<lb/><seg type="del">JP</seg> James Moore Esq J. P.<lb/>Robert R T FitzGerald Esq., Clerk of the Crown and Peace<lb/><seg type="del">Maryborough</seg> Peace Office Mryborough<lb/>And to David Windrum Carlisle Esq D.I.R.I.C. Abbeyleix. And to the District Inspector Royal Irish Constabulary<lb/>I certify above to be a true copy of notice of application<lb/>lodged with me.<lb/>   <lb/><!-- stamp -->Office of the Crown and Peace<lb/>   <lb/>     
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_5"/>
             Application for Certificate for<lb/>extension of Publicans Licence<lb/><hi rend="underline">granted at Quarter Sessions</hi><lb/>Queens County<lb/>Abbeyleix 27 June 1916.<lb/>I beg to report that at Abbey<lb/>leix Qr. sessions held on yesterday<lb/>before His Honor Co Court Judge<lb/>Fitzgerald and the following<lb/>Magistrates: Sir William Hutcheson<lb/>Poe Bart: Messrs Patrick Maher<lb/>John Walsh and James Moore<lb/>An application was made by<lb/>William Phelan ( Publican ) of<lb/>Ballinakill through his Solr.<lb/>Mr O'Connell Fitzsimons for<lb/>a certificate of extension of the<lb/>six day and Early closing licence<lb/>which he at present holds<lb/>to that of a six day ordinary<lb/>licence.  I opposed the application<lb/>in accordance with Code Sec<lb/>1019 as being contrary to Section<lb/>2 of 2 Ediv: 7 ch: 18 and read<lb/>the decision appearing in the<lb/>The Co Inspector<lb/> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_6"/>
             Irish Constables Guide<lb/>in the case of Dorrian V.<lb/>Greer 1903. 3 N. I. J. R. 302<lb/>as against the granting of<lb/>the Certificate.  I also pointed out that<lb/>this being a certificate for a<lb/>new licence it could not be<lb/>granted at any Quarter Sessions<lb/>but the Annual Licensing Qr<lb/>Sessions to be held in month of<lb/>October.  <lb/>Sir Hutcheson Poe made an<lb/>appeal to the Judge stating that<lb/>his employees nearly all dealt<lb/>with this publican &amp; as they were<lb/>not working according to the<lb/>Daylight Saving Bill they were not<lb/>able to reach this shop on Saturday<lb/>nights sooner than 7 1/2 pm and<lb/>consequently had only half an<lb/>hour to transact business.<lb/>He stated that he was in favour<lb/>of granting the certificate as<lb/>did also the three other local<lb/>Magistrates.<lb/>The County Court<lb/> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2494_img_1929_7"/>
             Judge said that with<lb/>great diffidence and<lb/>reluctance he granted the<lb/>certificate of Extension and<lb/>owing to the short paragraph<lb/>appearing in the Constables<lb/>Guide of the decision of the<lb/>case (Dorrian) V Greer with<lb/>the circumstances of which<lb/>he was not familiar he<lb/>did not think himself justified<lb/>in refusing it.  It would appear that<lb/>this is a case where<lb/>the Magistrates were canvassed<lb/>as they left the Bench<lb/>immediately the case was dis-<lb/>posed of.<lb/><seg type="unclear">M McCarthy</seg><lb/>HC 41886<lb/>for <seg type="unclear">D. Pink</seg> <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>