<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3849">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emily Adelaide Wynne to her mother Alice Katherine Wynne, 18 January 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emily Adelaide Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Emily Wynne (b. 1872 ) to her mother Alice Wynne (1848 - 1928). In addition to their estate in Co. Wicklow the Wynne family ran successful German mining operations from the end of the nineteenth century.

In this letter Emily tells her mother about a little boy she is nursing and remarks on his state of health. Emily also writes about her sadness over the death of a family friend, Jim Stockley, and her efforts to secure vermin powder.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin </repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Wynne family of Co. Wicklow, MS10247/1/1097</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3849</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0670">Emily Adelaide Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-01-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0630">52 Lower Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1267">Alice Katherine Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3849_img_323_1"  type="Letter"  url="ab03ec9f1f379f74fb10b943c2b6edf8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3849_img_323_2"  type="Letter"  url="8857626d199c3e1626492cf0ac7e95fb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3849_img_323_1"/>
             52 Lower Mount Street,   Jany 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   My dearest Muddie,   I thought the boy was a little limp <lb/> this morning which I expect was really <lb/> perhaps the result of his first sitting up <lb/> yesterday. However he cheered up in <lb/> the afternoon &amp; was most exuberant <lb/> this evening. He is getting awfully rampant <lb/> but I was glad that the sister firmly <lb/> vetoed his being up longer, for I am <lb/> sure though he does feel it at <lb/> the moment that he is better not allowed <lb/> to do all he wants to &amp; I think <lb/> he has rather the upper hand <lb/> of Nurse Bow (if that's how she spells <lb/> her name!). He is frightfully <sic>agrieved</sic> <lb/> at tapioca pudding for luncheon but <lb/> had a very nice dinner, soup, fish &amp; <lb/> queen pudding, much enjoyed. We had a <lb/> turn of power patience in the afternoon <lb/> varied by a dissertation on numerals &amp; <lb/> numerical systems, <sic>Abyssinnian</sic> methods <lb/> of multiplication, &amp; a <seg type="unclear">refrulig</seg> electrical <lb/>problem. I did not see any of the attendants
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3849_img_323_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline"></hi>to themselves to ask about probability<lb/>as to leaving. It was a very sad beginning<lb/>to the day seeing the announcement about<lb/>Jim <seg type="unclear">Stockley</seg> in the paper this morning.<lb/>One keeps thinking of poor little Hilda<lb/>&amp; wondering how things go with her. I am<lb/>so glad she has the little son at any<lb/>rate. I think the change of air has<lb/>nearly quite taken away the remains<lb/>of my pain which is very satisfactory.<lb/>I asked for the vermin powder today but<lb/>could not get it. I should think it would<lb/>be best to write to Boots direct or get V.<lb/>to get it. By the by have you tipped<lb/>Mary <seg type="unclear">hire</seg>? or will it be right if I give<lb/>her 2/6? She and M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Turner are so<lb/>very nice &amp; engaging &amp; thoughtful &amp;<lb/>certainly make one very comfortable.<lb/>Ever so much love Mother dearest.<lb/>I hope Father's hand is all right<lb/>by now.      Your very big child     <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">E.A. Wynne</hi></hi> <hi rend="underline"> </hi>  <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">For Mother</hi></hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>