<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3606">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frederick Pethick-Lawrence to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 8 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frederick Pethick-Lawrence</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Frederick Pethick-Lawrence (1871-1961) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) expressing his sympathy regarding the death of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. Lawrence promises he will do his best to do what she has asked of him in a previous letter.

Frederick Pethick-Lawrence was a British Labour politician. A supporter of socialism, pacifism, and women&#39;s suffrage, Lawrence adopted the prefix Pethick following his marriage to Emmeline Pethick (1867-1954), an active socialist and campaigner for women&#39;s rights.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3606</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1024">Frederick Pethick-Lawrence</persName>
              <date>1916-05-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0286">87, Clement&#39;s Inn, W.C.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1961</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3606_img_3006_1"  type="Letter"  url="474ade292f34365c78abb977bbae2df4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3606_img_3006_1"/>
            <!-- Address on the left upper corner of the page -->  ENTRANCE, 3 &amp; 4, CLEMENT'S INN. <lb/>TELEPHONE: 1314 HOLBORN. <lb/>TELEGRAMS: "PETHLAWRO-ESTRAND, LONDON."  <!-- Letter transcription with address on the right-hand side -->  87, CLEMENT'S INN, <lb/>W.C.   May 8, 16   Dear M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> Sheehy Skeffington   You have our very <lb/>deepest sympathy in your <lb/>sorrow. Our hearts are <lb/>lacerated. I will do <lb/>my best to do what you <lb/>ask in your letter.   Yours very sincerely   <seg type="unclear">F</seg> Pethick Lawrence. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>