<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0458">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from S.C. Harrison to Sir Matthew Nathan, 1 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>S.C. Harrison</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A report from S.C. Harrison to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). Harrison is writing to Nathan in connection with the working conditions of factory and mill workers in Belfast. Included in Harrison&#39;s report are interviews with various owners and workers of these mills and factories. Harrison&#39;s report makes it clear that the war is directly affecting working conditions in Belfast, writing that &#39;if the Dardanelles were forced fresh supplies of flax might arrive which would alter the situation...&#39;Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSO 1916/7443/25/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/458</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0115">S.C. Harrison</persName>
              <date>1916-02-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1390">36, Upper Fitzwilliam Street, Dublin, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_1"  type="Letter"  url="b7a7a372c5b78772ca36f315aa4e1af0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_2"  type="Letter"  url="0ca0f9c6a51d5009d061bf33323b5421.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="18c91f8ea22d06b277d82ea558b8f355.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="324c047208f13171adb0403c8c00a36c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="1aa3890e9e1e66155ac355968eed6b5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="e41753fb5f05f0e103af5eaadcff87b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="f87e0f9ce5fc90942b941959fd807f41.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="3c20e0257e181bbfb45f4d5b8c43aed7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="04d87412664dae2ee5bb4971dd2d5186.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_10"  type="Enclosure"  url="fde564ff88d4c3c2a3215bef885790a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_11"  type="Enclosure"  url="c77edebc6eed630f791f527336eaf033.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_12"  type="Enclosure"  url="ad143103de08c153e3b3295f076f75ce.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0458_img_1803_13"  type="Enclosure"  url="2cd3c7d6121e29a1bfcdabfa310996be.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_1"/>
                36. Upper Fitzwilliam Street     1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> February. 1916.    Dear Sir Matthew Nathan   I regret the delay that occurred <lb/> in sending you the statement on the situation <lb/> of the factory &amp; mill workers (women) in Belfast <lb/> at present, — but it was unavoidable.   I have sent you the names &amp; addresses of the <lb/> competent persons who gave me the information, <lb/> so that it will be easy to test the truth of my  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_2"/>
              statements. I earnestly hope you will proceed to do <lb/> so. I shall be well rewarded for any work that <lb/> I have done if I <seg type="del"> can </seg> succeed in bringing the <lb/> facts of the conditions under which these women <lb/> labour to your personal knowledge, for then <lb/> I know you will strive to give them any chance <lb/> of betterment that you can obtain for them.    I am sending a copy of my note of the conversations <lb/> with each person to them  except Mr Mackey, as his contribution was negative   to check my report <lb/> but I believe it is accurate enough to forward without <lb/> waiting for the answers. Any material corrections I will <lb/> forward at once. Once more apologies for the delay  <seg type="closer">  I remain <lb/> Sincerely yours   <hi rend="underline"> S.C. Harrison </hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_3"/>
                To the Right Honble. Sir Mathhew Nathan. K.C..M.G. <lb/> Under Secretary of State for Ireland    <hi rend="underline">Memorandum</hi> on the short hours now being <lb/> worked in the linen mills &amp; factories in Belfast <lb/> &amp; district, with the heavy tasks &amp; low pay <lb/> given in certain classes of war work.    I visited Belfast on the 18. <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>—19. <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January <lb/> 1916, &amp; discussed the situation of the women factory <lb/> &amp; mill hands employed in the manufacture of <lb/> linen, with <lb/> Miss Galway, Secretary of the Textile Operatives <lb/> Association. Avenue Hall, Garfield St. Belfast. <lb/> W. Greig. National Amalgamated Union of Labour <lb/> Avenue Hall, Garfield Street. <lb/> Miss Daunt. Board of Trade Labour Exchange <lb/> W. M <hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dowell. Secretary of the <seg type="unclear">Tenter's</seg> Society. <lb/> 11. Dover Street, Shankill Road. <lb/> W. Dawson Gordon. Secretary of the Flax Roughers &amp; <lb/><seg type="unclear">Servers</seg>. Engineer's Hall, College Street. <lb/> W. Mackey, of   James Mackey &amp; Sons' Factory <lb/> Springfield Road, Belfast <lb/> &amp; with about a dozen numbers of the textile operations <lb/> association who met me for the purpose.    I told each &amp; all that I had come to get  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_4"/>
              facts from them to lay before the Government. That <lb/> I was to be held personally responsible for the truth <lb/> of the statements I should make; that the facts <lb/> would be investigated to test them, on behalf of <lb/> the Government.    18. <hi rend="superscript">th </hi>January <hi rend="underline">Miss Galway</hi> informed me that in <hi rend="underline">June 1915</hi>, a <lb/> Joint Deputation of Flax Roughers (men), dressers <lb/> &amp; textile operatives waited on the Flax Spinners <lb/> Association at the Chamber of Commerce, — <lb/> Chairman W. Garrett Campbell, Secretary, W. Wilson — <lb/> Joint Deputation to Employers to ask for an increase of wages to meet the increased <lb/> cost of living.   This demand was refused on the ground of the lack <lb/> of raw material. If the Dardanelles were forced <lb/> fresh supplies of flax might arrive which would alter <lb/> the situation, but, in the absence of this relief, in addition <lb/> to the short time that had been worked for sixteen months, <lb/> they might have to close down some of the machinery <lb/> now working   In June no linen workers were working more than <lb/> 40 hours per week, i.e. 15 hours short, amounting to <lb/> a reduction of 20 per cent in output.   About 28,000 men, women &amp; children were employed in 1906. 95 per cent are women or girls  In answer to a question as to the hours being worked <lb/> &amp; the number of women employed at present, Miss <lb/> Galway advised one to see Secretary of the <seg type="unclear">Tenter's</seg>  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_5"/>
              Miss Galway (continued.) Society, Every tenter is paid according to the output <lb/> of the looms for which he is responsible, each week <lb/> he has to report to the Sec. of his union what looms <lb/> have been stopped or started. The tenters are mechanics <lb/> &amp; each one is responsible for a share (about 60) of the <lb/> looms at which the women work, to see that the <lb/> machines are in order &amp; that the cloth made is up <lb/> to standard.   Miss Galway infomed me that munition work <lb/> for women was just about to be started in Belfast. <lb/> A notice was put up on Wednesday the 12. <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January <lb/> at James Mackey &amp; Sons factory, Springfield Road, <lb/> saying that women desiring munition work should <lb/> apply by letter only. This factory &amp; <sic>Coombe</sic><lb/> Barbour's on the Falls Road are called 'black shops' <lb/> by the workers because they do not pay trade union <lb/> rates except perhaps to a few engineers, &amp; on this <lb/> ground it was regretted that Government work <lb/> had been given to them. Miss Galway had <lb/> advised some of her members, who are on very short <lb/> time, to write applying for work, &amp; said we should <lb/> hear from them in the evening what the result had <lb/> been.   <hi rend="underline">W. Greig</hi>, National Amalgamated Union of Labour— <lb/> deplored the fact that the Government work was given to  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_6"/>
              W. Greig. (continued) three 'black shops'. He spoke of the new Government <lb/> factory being opened at gretna, &amp; pointed out that <lb/> there are acres of unoccupied land close to 'the island' <lb/> on the Belfast Harbour Estate on the Co. Down side, <lb/> which would be a convenient site for a government <lb/> factory, - here where so many good factory hands are <lb/> short of work. Fifty or sixty trams come from <lb/> all parts of the city to 'the island' every morning <lb/> about 6.30 a.m.    Miss Daunt <hi rend="underline">Miss Daunt</hi> of the Labour Exchange, said that in <lb/> spite of the short time being worked in the linen mills <lb/> &amp; factories few women registered, as they <seg type="del">dared</seg> would not <lb/> risk the loss of the low wages they were earning <lb/> with the present high cost of living.   W. M <hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dowell, Secretary of the Teuters Society, <lb/> 11 Dover Street, Shankill Road. <lb/> told me that a tenter has 28 or 34 weavers under his <lb/> control, &amp; is paid 1 <hi rend="superscript">s</hi>/5 <hi rend="superscript"> superscript text </hi> in the £1 on the wages earned <lb/> by them. The tenters are now getting 35/- <lb/> instead of 50/- per week, (or a reduction of 30 per cent). <lb/> He gave a list of the factories in Belfast &amp; district, <lb/> (attached hereto) 34 in number — 2 are working overtime <hi rend="superscript">xx</hi> (the Grove, &amp; Highfield.) <lb/> 18 are down as full time, but I understand that even <lb/><hi rend="superscript">xx</hi> these factories are said to have complained of want of workers, <lb/> but I am told that they neither applied to the Labour Exchange or advertised for them.  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_7"/>
              W. McDowell (continued) in these cases a number of looms are stopped; <lb/> 2 are working full time in one branch of works <lb/> &amp; short time for the others; <lb/> 12 are on short time, - from 45 to 27 hours' <lb/> 12 factories on short time. (out of the usual 55 hours week), ' &amp; not 75 per' <lb/> 'cent. of the machinery going, &amp; still they say' <lb/> 'they can't spare any labours!'   One employer, outside the district, told W. M <hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Dowell <lb/> that by working three weeks out of every four on <lb/> three quarter time his material might last seven <lb/> months.   As tenters have no connection with mills he ad- <lb/> vised me to see W. Dawson Gordon of the Flax <lb/> Roughers Association   <hi rend="underline">W. Dawson Gordan.</hi> Enquirer's Hall, College Street. <lb/> said that Miss Galway's figure was correct when <lb/> 19 out of 24 mills on short time. she said that only five out of the 24 mills <lb/> in the Belfast district were working full time. <lb/> These are Mr. Jaffe's, Cogry , <seg type="unclear">Derrymount</seg><lb/> Edenderry &amp; Blackstaff mills. <lb/> Flax workers earn an average of 25/- per week. <lb/> Women (spinners) on full time would earn from <lb/> 12/- to 13/-. Wages have gone down;- <lb/> Where 80 spindles used to be worked for a certain <lb/> wage, they now have to work 180 for a very few  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_8"/>
              W.Dawson Gordan (continued) shillings more. Even one of the better employers <lb/> like John Fulton &amp; Co. are lowering their pay:— <lb/> certain work on khaki shirts that was paid at <lb/> 2/8 per day has lately been reduced to 2/4 <hi rend="superscript"> superscript text </hi>.    The same story was told me when I met <lb/> some dozen members of the Textile Operatives <lb/> falling wages &amp; rising prices Union in the evening. <lb/> Material for tents is paid at from 2/4 to 3/6 per <lb/> 'cut' of 130 yards. It is very heavy work &amp; <lb/> bad pay. A widow, an experienced worker told <lb/> me her daughter could not stand it, &amp; as she herself <lb/> was out of work at the time, she went in to finish <lb/> the job. The flax or material used was so bad it <lb/> constantly was breaking &amp; delayed the work greatly. <lb/> The looms break down under this heavy work:- <lb/> the girls are 'slaughtered' by it, &amp; get no more <lb/> pay for it; — 'that is the reason weavers cannot be <lb/> got sometimes.   At Agnes Street Factory this mother was paid 4/8 <lb/> for 126 yards 42 ins. wide of aeroplane linens — <lb/> Ten years ago at York Street Mill she would have <lb/> got 9/- for what they get 4/8 now. She was <lb/> able to make four 'cuts' in three weeks — i.e <lb/> 504 yards for 18/8 or 6 <hi rend="superscript"> / </hi>/2 <hi rend="superscript">3/4</hi> a week — <lb/> Camp cloth, they said should be paid 4/- to 5/-  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_9"/>
              per cut or 'set wages' of 17/6 per week.   19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>January   <hi rend="underline">W. Mackey</hi> of   James Mackey &amp; Sons, Springfield Rd. <lb/> Next morning I went to the factory which <lb/> had invited women to apply for munition work. <lb/> On the door posts I read that volunteers for munition <lb/> work were invited to apply by letter. I entered &amp; <lb/> asked to see the Manager. I was courteously <lb/> informed that I should apply by letter, but on ex- <lb/> plaining that I was not coming on my own behalf, <lb/> but was desirous to see that Manager &amp; learn something <lb/> about the work, I was asked to wait.   Eventually I was ushered into a room &amp; saw a gentle- <lb/> man who, I was told later, must have been M <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Mackey. <lb/> He repeated that the rule was to apply by letter, &amp; when I <lb/> explained that I was interested to hear that munition <lb/> work was being started for women in Belfast as I knew <lb/> the need there was for work for the womens factory &amp; <lb/> mill workers, he at once assured me I was mistaken: <lb/> — that there was no lack of work for any women who <lb/> wished to work &amp; did not drink.   I told him my experience was different, - that I knew <lb/> women worked in Belfast for very low wages &amp; were <lb/> now in fear of even shorter hours owing to the shortage <lb/> of flax.   W. Mackey said that no doubt I would not credit it,  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_10"/>
              but that at Beardmore's factory in Glasgow, the <lb/> best work was done by women with University degrees <lb/> who came in their motor cars. I assured him I <lb/> had no difficulty in believing that people well <lb/> clothed &amp; fed &amp; educated did the best work, &amp; if <lb/> the employers in Belfast would try paying their <lb/> women workers enough to enable them to be properly <lb/> clothed &amp; fed &amp; educated, they would find what <lb/> much better work they could do. This was the <lb/> experience where there were Trade Boards. <lb/> I said I had come to get facts to lay before the <lb/> Government, as there were at least two sides to <lb/> every question.   After a minutes silence he raised his head &amp; said he <lb/> thought it would be no use to discuss matters further. <lb/> I agreed &amp; asked if I could see the works, he <seg type="unclear">dismissed</seg>. <lb/> He added that they would start in about a weeks' <lb/> time, &amp; that there was nothing he could show <lb/> me that day.   Thinking of the women I had seen the night <lb/> before &amp; of their cruel struggle for existence, — the <lb/> mill hands die early, mercifully:- I wished I <lb/> could bring the well-off women to see what they are <lb/> doing in competing for these poor women's crusts.   
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_11"/>
               Is it impossible to get the Government to see <lb/> that instead of forbidding the increase of wages <lb/> they should forbid the lowering of them, while <lb/> food is rapidly reaching famine prices for the <lb/> workers &amp; the poor?.    I must add that, although I have heard it <lb/><seg type="unclear">suggested</seg> on several occasions that the women of <lb/> Belfast suffer particularly from the prejudice <lb/> &amp; obstruction of the men, I have found no con- <lb/> firmation of this theory. I found no trace of <lb/> it in talking to the men &amp; when I asked the women <lb/> they said there was not the slightest ground for <lb/> such a suggestion. their only criticism was <lb/> this, - that men who are convinced have union- <lb/> ists do not urge the women workers in their families <lb/> to organise themselves, - which they   con- <lb/> sider they ought to do.  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to remain <lb/> Faithfully yours   <hi rend="underline">S.C. Harrison.</hi>   31 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi>January 1916.     36. Upper Fitzwilliam Street.   Dublin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_12"/>
               A list of union member names A list of union member names  
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_0458_img_1803_13"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>