<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2386">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph MacDonagh to Louise Gavan Duffy regarding subscriptions for the Irish National Aid Association</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph MacDonagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Joseph MacDonagh suggests means for raising money for the Irish National Aid; he advocates asking the central council of the G.A.A. to adopt a tax scheme in favour of the Irish National Aid.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 24,376 /1; Collection List 131</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2386</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1538">Joseph MacDonagh</persName>
              <date>1916-06-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0759">Friar St., Thurles</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Susan Duffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0817">10 Exchequer Street</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2386_img_183_1"  type="Letter"  url="078a41482e5fb9b0fb1773323bff1b9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2386_img_183_2"  type="Letter"  url="018a0fc78cdfd2abe2f8c0a687354e67.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2386_img_183_3"  type="Letter"  url="6550ccb88d88caa6c11ebaf93fe4fdfc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2386_img_183_1"/>
             Friar St. Thurles.   2.6.1916.   Dear Miss Gavan Duffy,    Seeing that you are one <lb/> of the secretaries of the Irish National<lb/> Aid Association, I am taking the<lb/> liberty of writing to you.     I shall be most happy<lb/> to do any thing I can to help the<lb/> association. Owing to my employment<lb/> in the Excise I am not at liberty<lb/> to openly canvass for subscriptions;<lb/> but any clerical work or collecting<lb/> among my friends I shall be very<lb/> ready to undertake. If you will
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2386_img_183_2"/>
            send me fifty weekly subscription<lb/> books, I think I shall be able to<lb/> "place" all or most of them. I regard<lb/> the weekly subscription idea as the<lb/> most likely to bring in the necessary <lb/> money, &amp; it will also do good <lb/> from a national point of view.    There is a suggestion I <lb/> would like to make which may not have<lb/> been put forward already. It is<lb/> unlikely that the Gaelic Athletic<lb/> Association will have to contribute<lb/> any thing to the Entertainments Tax. <lb/> If that is so, I think it would be<lb/> an easy matter to get the Central <lb/> Council of the G.A.A. to adopt the tax <lb/> scheme in favour of your Aid <lb/> Association. This is how the thing is<lb/>  worked for the Revenue In the<lb/> large central offices such as Dublin &amp;<lb/> Limerick there are rolls of tickets of 1000<lb/> each for sale. The proprietors of theatres<lb/> <seg type="unclear">ste</seg> pay 1000 pennies for each roll<lb/> (where the tax is 1d) &amp; sell each<lb/> ticket for 7d. Of course there are other<lb/> rolls of 2d tickets for admission<lb/> tickets exceeding 6.d. This scheme could<lb/> easily be adapted to suit your Ass'n.<lb/> You could <seg type="del">buy</seg> have the tickets manufactured<lb/> &amp; the various county committees of<lb/> the G.A.A. by order of the Central Council<lb/> would have to buy them from you, paying <lb/> 1d. or 2d for each ticket (1d. not exceeding<lb/> 6d. &amp; 2d. otherwise). You could afford<lb/> to give the paper free &amp; still make a lot<lb/> of money. A very poor year would <lb/> amount to at least £1200.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2386_img_183_3"/>
            The time is rife now I think for a simultaneous<lb/> collection some Sunday all over Ireland<lb/> with an annual collection on every St.<lb/> Patrick's Day in the future.    Reverting to the G.A.A. idea,<lb/> I know some of the leading G.A.A. officials.    I often heard my brother (Thomas)<lb/> speaking of you. My second brother who<lb/> managed the Irish Theatre for Ed. Martyn<lb/> is a present in Knutsford. He is<lb/> unmarried. My brother's widow &amp;<lb/> children come down here tomorrow<lb/> to stay with me for a time.   Your's sincerely,  Joseph MacDonagh  Miss L. Gavan Duffy,<lb/> 10 Exchequer St. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>