<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1917">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John F. Smyth to Robert Chalmers, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John F. Smyth</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from a Monaghan based solicitor John F. Smyth to the Under Secretary Sir Robert Chalmers (1858–1938). After the Easter rising of 1916 Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), his chief secretary. Smyth is writhing on behalf of Miss Kate Rooney, and is enclosing a petition from Miss Rooney for a Temporary License for her premises in Castleblayney, Monaghan.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8165</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1917</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0850">John F. Smyth</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0464">Castleblayney, County Monaghan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1917_img_1368_1"  type="Letter"  url="0f3a2eff69d509e87af0fd700bf48c2c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1917_img_1368_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="5133a51c69a3db60d737c9be5befeb4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1917_img_1368_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="42442388f522b701a36b40c97ca7c5ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1917_img_1368_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="0b5b1246030b2429853df38b445f4e17.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1917_img_1368_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="3ad808678d81e2c0a8ed31def832a1d8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1917_img_1368_1"/>
             Castleblayney, <lb/>Co. Monaghan .  13th May, 1916.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">James Rooney Deceased.</hi>  Sir,   I beg to enclose Petition of Miss Kate Rooney for a Temporary <lb/>Licence for her premises in Main Street, Castleblayney from 30th <lb/>May to 3rd October next.   I shall feel obliged by the matter receiving early attention <lb/>so that the Licence may be received by the 30th inst, and so enable <lb/>Miss Rooney to continue to carry on the Licensed business as here— <lb/>tofore and keep the trade to the premises.    I am Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   John F. Smyth   The Under Secretary, <lb/>The Castle, <lb/>Dublin. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1917_img_1368_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">James Rooney</hi> <hi rend="underline">Deceased</hi> <hi rend="underline">Petition</hi> <hi rend="underline">of</hi> <hi rend="underline">Kate Rooney</hi>  <hi rend="underline">John F. Smyth</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Solicitor for Petitioner</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">3 St Andrew Street</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Dublin and Castleblayney</hi> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1917_img_1368_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">To</hi> His Excellency the Lord <lb/>Lieutenant General and General <lb/>Governor of Ireland.   <hi rend="underline">The Humble Petition</hi> of Kate Rooney <lb/>of Main Street, Castleblayney in the <lb/>County of Monaghan, Publican and <lb/>Spinster <hi rend="underline">showeth</hi>   That James Rooney was the owner <lb/>of Licensed premises situate in Main <lb/>Street, in the town of Castleblayney <lb/>in the parish of Muckno, Barony of <lb/>Cremorne, and County of Monaghan.   That the said James Rooney died <lb/>on the 19th day of March 1916, having <lb/>previously duly executed his Will <lb/>whereby he bequeathed the said premises <lb/>to his sister your Petitioner subject <lb/>to the payment of his debts funeral <lb/>and testamentary expenses in said <lb/> Will mentioned.   That the Executors named in said <lb/>Will have taken proceedings to prove <lb/>the said Will.   That your Petitioner at Petty <lb/>Sessions held at Castleblayney on <lb/>the 4<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> April 1916 obtained a Pro- <lb/>visional transfer of the said Licence <lb/>until the Quarter Sessions for the <lb/>District after the expiration of one <lb/>month from that date, which Quarter <lb/>Sessions will be held on the 30th <lb/> May 1916.   That the Licence Duty £12:5:3 <lb/>has been paid to the Collector of <lb/>Customs and Excise Dundalk
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1917_img_1368_4"/>
            in respect of the said premises up to the <lb/>30th September 1916.   That by an oversight Notice of <lb/>Application for a transfer of said <lb/>Licence from said James Rooney <lb/>deceased to me was not served twenty <lb/>one days prior to the Quarter Sessions <lb/> to be held on the 30th inst, and in <lb/> consequence thereof your Petitioner <lb/> will be unable to obtain such transfer <lb/> at the said Quarter Sessions.   That your Petitioner will apply <lb/> at the next Quarter Sessions to be <lb/>held in October next for a transfer <lb/> of said Licence.   That your Petitioner has resided <lb/>with her brother the said James <lb/>Rooney deceased all her lifetime and <lb/>has for upwards of thirty years <lb/> assisted him in the management <lb/> and carrying on of said business <lb/> which has been established for <lb/>upwards of Fifty years.   That the said business is your <lb/>Petitioners and only means of livelihood <lb/>and it is for the benefit of your <lb/>Petitioner that the said premises <lb/>should be kept open from the <lb/>Quarter Sessions on the 30th May until <lb/>the next Quarter Sessions on the 3rd <lb/>October 1916, so that the trade there- <lb/>to may not be diverted from the <lb/>premises.   Your Petitioner therefore humbly <lb/>prays that it may please your <lb/>Excellency to grant to your Petitioner
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1917_img_1368_5"/>
            <lb/>a temporary Licence for the said <lb/>premises from 30th May until the <lb/>3rd October 1916 the date of the <lb/>next Quarter Sessions for the District. <lb/>And your Petitioner will ever pray   Kate Rooney 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>