<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0921">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James McDonnell to Lady Clonbrock,16 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James McDonnell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from a prisoner of war, James McDonnell, Connaught Rangers, to Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). McDonnell is incarcerated in Bulgaria at the time of this letter. He writes to thank her for the parcel he received from the Irishwomen&#39;s Association and requests that they send him a pair of boots as his are worn out. McDonnell has been a prisoner of war since December 1915. Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.W</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 35,796 /14 (13) (Collection List 54), MS 35,796 /14 (13) (Collection List 54)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/921</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0948">James McDonnell</persName>
              <date>1916-08-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1780">Bulgaria</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lady Clonbrock (Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton)</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0921_img_263_1"  type="Letter"  url="6fa7a9228cc47031d6088b81d8534d66.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0921_img_263_2"  type="Letter"  url="c924062d2741d30d333333570efe583c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0921_img_263_3"  type="Letter"  url="3d76d8a4ff001231079e0c336bee4504.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0921_img_263_1"/>
                Bulgaria    Aug 30 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 16    Dear Madam   I got no clothing <sic>sence</sic><lb/> I was captured the Irish <lb/> Women sent me 2 <lb/> shirts socks and some <lb/><sic>parcles</sic> of Food stuff <lb/>I want to tell you <lb/> I have no Boots on <lb/> my feet I take 9 size  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0921_img_263_2"/>
              <lb/>I was taken prisoner <lb/> on the 7 December <lb/> 1915 my boots is <sic>wore</sic><lb/>I am from Ballinasloe <lb/> I would be thankful <lb/> to you to send me <lb/> one <hi rend="underline">pair of Boots</hi> <seg type="closer">598 Pte  James McDonnell <lb/>Connaught Rangers <lb/>Prisoner of War Philoppolis <lb/>Bulgaria </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0921_img_263_3"/>
              Mc Donnell <lb/>Prisoner.  <lb/>wants boots <lb/>wrote to I.W.A <lb/>Sep: 19. 1916   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>