<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3381">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Ernsley Blackwell to Sir Robert Chalmers, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sir Ernsley Blackwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Ernley Robertson Hay Blackwell, lawyer and civil servant, was the chief legal advisor to the Cabinet.  Blackwell authorised the circulation of Roger Casement&#39;s (1864-1916) black diaries during his prosecution.  Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10671-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3381</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0880">Sir Ernsley Blackwell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0170">Home Office, Whitehall, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3381_img_2794_1"  type="Letter"  url="09f4c2b6817e0b102ceea44cbc12ca8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3381_img_2794_1"/>
             COPY  Prison Commission,   9th June, 1916.    Sir,   I have the honour to report for the information of<lb/>the Secretary of State that a question has arisen with<lb/>regard to the classification of the Sinn Fein rebels now<lb/>located in the English Convict Prisons, many of whom where in<lb/>the first instance sentenced to death which was subsequently<lb/>commuted to Penal Servitude. The question as to whether<lb/>their offence constitutes a felony or misdemeanour is not<lb/>clear, and the Directors will be glad to receive the<lb/>Secretary of State's instructions in the matter. Two of<lb/>the Order of Courts are enclosed (a) where the sentence<lb/>first passed was death and (b) where penal servitude was<lb/>the original order <sic>.....</sic>   I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,<lb/>(Sd) E. Ruggles Brise <lb/>The Under Secretary of State,<lb/>&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>