<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1892">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Joseph Sutherland to Herbert Henry Asquith, 27 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Joseph Sutherland </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from John Joseph Sutherland (b.1868) to Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), the prime minister of Britain. The letter is an application for the position of lord magistrate of Cork. He also refers Asquith to Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926), the assistant under-secretary. Sutherland encloses various recommendations including one from Maurice Healy (1859-1923), Irish Nationalist politician, who wishes Sutherland great luck in his application. The bishop of Cork, Thomas Alphonsus O&#39;Callaghan (1839-1916) and arch-deacon also provide recommendations.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5612/9324</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1892</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0650">John Joseph Sutherland </persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1184">49 Leinster Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_1"  type="Letter"  url="6e8695b10acb8c8fe89a354fb665405f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_2"  type="Letter"  url="149475dce84d587a05294a5add54670d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="a9f235b5f893da75c201a8c857f50587.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="bc2808157116a125cb0c250d1371fcb8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="30d20f86d3f198a0b0fc8bf3548a4e32.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="3eab658cab6985eb0a7c87b77c064523.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1892_img_1344_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="1c9e73a9db6d4a6d0fbc80da5c6dd5a8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_1"/>
             Ack. and inform that <lb/>the vacancy for a Res. Insptr <lb/>at Queenstown has been filled <lb/>by the transfer of <seg type="del">Mr. Fallon thereto</seg>. <lb/> a R.M. from another county.  <lb/>Done 5/6   49 Leinster Road  <lb/><seg type="del">29, CLARE STREET,</seg> <lb/>C<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>. DUBLIN.   27.5.16   Dear Prime Minister  <lb/>As Head of <lb/>the Irish Government.  I beg to apply for the <lb/>Post of Resident Magistrate <lb/>for the County of Cork <lb/>(Headquarters Queenstown)   I enclose recommendations.   I also refer you to <lb/>the Lord Chancellor, Attorney
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_2"/>
            General &amp; Solicitor General <lb/>for Ireland also to Sir <lb/>Edward O'Farrell.   I am Dear Prime Minister <lb/>Yours faithfully   John J. Sutherland 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_3"/>
             Copy   My dear Sutherland   I have much <lb/>pleasure in saying that <lb/>having known you for <lb/>many years in the Munster <lb/>Circuit I believe you are <lb/>possessed of all the necessary <lb/>qualifications for such <lb/>an appointment as a Resident <lb/>Magistrate.   In addition to your legal <lb/>attainments your knowledge <lb/>of the Country and of the people <lb/>&amp; your high personal character <lb/>to which every member
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_4"/>
            of the circuit will bear testimony <lb/>should materially assist in <lb/>recommending you to those <lb/>authorities in whose hands <lb/>lie the disposal of such appointment.   Yours sincerely   Seymour Bushe  <lb/>(K.C.) <lb/>Senior Crown Prosecutor
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_5"/>
             Copy   Dear Mr. Sutherland   I have the greatest <lb/> pleasure in wishing you <lb/> success in your candidature <lb/> for the position of R.M.   Having known you for <lb/>many years it would <lb/>give me the greatest pleasure <lb/>to learn of your appointment <lb/>to a position which I am <lb/>sure you would fill with <lb/>credit &amp; success.   Yours faithfully   Maurice Healy  <lb/>(M.P.)
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_6"/>
             Copy   The Palace   Cork   Mr JJ Sutherland is seeking <lb/>the position of Resident <lb/>Magistrate and I warmly <lb/>recommend him. He <lb/>is a Barrister at law <lb/>of the Munster Circuit.   I believe his appointment <lb/>would give satisfaction in Cork.   +T.A. O'Callaghan  <hi rend="underline">Bishop of Cork</hi>
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1892_img_1344_7"/>
             Sir   I beg to recommend for <lb/>the position of Resident Magistrate <lb/>Mr JJ Sutherland until lately <lb/>a parishioner of mine but now <lb/>residing in Dublin. He is <lb/>an upright, honourable &amp; <lb/>conscientious gentleman. He <lb/>is a practising Barrister <lb/>of over 12 years standing <lb/>&amp; married. I am well acquainted <lb/>with him &amp; can testify that <lb/>his judgements would not be <lb/>influenced by fear or <sic>favor</sic>   Hoping you may see your <lb/>way to give him the appointment.   I am <lb/>With great respect <lb/>Yours faithfully   John Cotter P.P . <lb/>Archdeacon of Cork
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>