<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0110">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to Mary Martin, 7 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892–1975) to her mother Mary Martin. In the letter, Marie expresses joy at receiving her mother&#39;s letter as she had not been able to get her family off her mind and expresses her wish to be at home. Marie goes on the write that she will not write much as she is feeling depressed. She recounts a tennis tournament that took place between the nurses and officers on the previous Saturday. She writes of her work in the gas poisoning tent, her brother Laurence John &#39;Jack&#39;, who is unwell and other family members.Marie was a born in Dublin and trained as a nurse at the outbreak of World War I. Two of Marie&#39;s brothers joined the British army at this time, one of whom was killed in action. Marie served as a nurse in Malta, Leeds and France, and later set up the Medical Missionaries of Mary</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>Medical Missionaries of Mary, B/F/1/60/1916/09/07</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/110</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-09-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0361">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0110_img_1192_1"  type="Letter"  url="d83efd7a3d0e234cc86fcc0d607141f2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0110_img_1192_2"  type="Letter"  url="750029b1d1c9dafa6bb9c771a037f8b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0110_img_1192_3"  type="Letter"  url="03e8bbf8b3bf33060b897b25b0e5cea0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0110_img_1192_4"  type="Letter"  url="e60144456c937c020f4e22901677f694.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0110_img_1192_5"  type="Letter"  url="770794240cbc5c81eb9006d158be34b7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0110_img_1192_1"/>
                7-9-16   My very dearest Mother,   I was never so <sic>relieve</sic> as to <lb/>get your letter to-day &amp; to hear you <lb/>are all fairly well for the last few <lb/>days I have not been able to get <lb/>you all off my mind &amp; last night <lb/>I had such a horrible dream of <lb/>you being ill it was so realistic <lb/>I woke up crying &amp; could not get <lb/>to sleep wondering how you all were <lb/>I just longed to be at home &amp; am <lb/>longing for the day. But things <lb/>are brighter again now after your <lb/>letter &amp; I have also had one <lb/>from Tommy which cheered me <lb/>up to hear he is alright again <lb/><sic>Ienclose</sic> it in this you will be <lb/>glad to read, it is too bad <lb/>Dickâs getting laid up again. <lb/>Yes it is splendid if Greece  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0110_img_1192_2"/>
              really does join in with us â any <lb/>thing to end this war, how I <lb/>long for that day. I shall not <lb/>write very much to-day as I am <lb/>feeling rather depressed so would <lb/>only write the wrong kind of <lb/>letter.  Did I ever tell you we had a <lb/>Tennis Tournament on Saturday last <lb/>with the Officers from the Bombing <lb/>School which is quite near here <lb/>it was really a great success &amp; <lb/>they all seemed to enjoy it very <lb/>much. Yesterday I had my half <lb/>day so went up to see Paul who <lb/>has gone to Lady Griffiths for a weeks <lb/>chance she was rather knocked <lb/> up &amp; needs a change.  I am glad to say I am feeling <lb/>very well now &amp; hope to continue <lb/>to do so. I shall have to get  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0110_img_1192_3"/>
              you to send me out some warmer <lb/>combination fairly soon as it is <lb/>getting very cold here also a few <lb/>white tight bodices as mine have <lb/>gone into ribbons with the heat. <lb/>Also would you send me a black <lb/>South Western as we get so wet <lb/>walking between the Tents in fact <lb/>sometimes it is nearly necessary <lb/>to wear them inside.  We have filled up again but <lb/>we are not nearly so busy as <lb/>we were &amp; are able to get our <lb/>regulars off time I am still <lb/>in the Gas Poisoning Tents &amp; find <lb/>it very interesting work our M. U. <lb/>is so good &amp; conscientious over <lb/>his work &amp; has made a special <lb/>study on how to treat thes[e] gas <lb/>cases.  Did F. Eaton want you for any <lb/>thing important when he rang you  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0110_img_1192_4"/>
              up. I sincerely hope Violet will <lb/>brook much better after her change <lb/>it is toobad about poor Uncle <lb/>Frank I must try &amp; write to <lb/>him some day soon. I also hope <lb/>you were able to get to some <lb/>decision about Jack _ it really is <lb/>more difficult to know what is the <lb/>best.  I tell you what I should love <lb/>to see &amp; that is a copy of <lb/>Muaros dispatches in which Charlie <lb/>is mentioned as I never saw <lb/>it.  Also if the Photos are home of <lb/>me will you send me out two <lb/>you might send one to Mrs Garttan <lb/>I think she would like one instead <lb/>of the awful old one she has of <lb/>me I shall write &amp; tell her to tear <lb/>the old one up. With my fondest  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0110_img_1192_5"/>
              love to every one at home <lb/>a big kiss to Desmond &amp; <lb/>Andrew Tell Bea to write <lb/><sic>oftener</sic> even if it is only a <lb/>car to say how every thing <lb/>is. &amp; what she is doing.  Do you know if Granny ever <lb/>got my letter. I am afraid I <lb/>shall never be forgiven there <lb/>however it does not really worry <lb/>me I like her just the same &amp; <lb/>am very sorry to hear she is <lb/>laid up &amp; hope she is better. <lb/>Must close now I am very <lb/>tired. With every loving thought <lb/>good wish &amp; luck. <seg type="closer"> From your most loving &amp; grateful <lb/>daughter  Marie </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>