<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3601">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to Edythe Fitzgerald, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland (RCPI) to Edythe Fitzgerald expressing their deep sense of loss following the death of their colleague, Edythe&#39;s husband, Dr Charles Edward Fitzgerald (1853-1916).
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-168</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3601</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0650">Royal College of Physicians, 6 Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0674">Edythe Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0236">27 Upper Merrion Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3601_img_3000_1"  type="Letter"  url="80d15d2b89d28df0406f025c5b04e70e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3601_img_3000_1"/>
             THE ROYAL COLLEGE OF PHYSICIANS OF IRELAND, <lb/>6 Kildare street, Dublin.   3rd JUNE, 1916.   Mrs.FitzGerald, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Madam,   I am directed by the President and Fellows of this <lb/>College to forward you a copy of the following resolution <lb/>which was carried in silence at yesterday's meeting : <lb/>RESOLVED : "That the President and Fellows of the Royal <lb/>College of Physicians of Ireland desire to record their <lb/>deep sense of the loss sustained by their College, by the <lb/>Medical Profession and by the public at large in the death <lb/>of their distinguished and beloved colleague Dr.Charles <lb/>Edward FitzGerald, Ex-President of the College; and the <lb/>President and Fellows hereby tender an expression of <lb/>heartfelt sympathy to Mrs FitzGerald and the other members <lb/>of his family in their bereavement."   I remain, Dear Madam, <lb/>Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>