<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3420">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kathleen Teebay, Stafford, England to James Ryan, 7 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Teebay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.
Kathleen Teebay had come to know Ryan while he was imprisoned in Stafford, where she lived, and she became friendly with many of the other inmates. Ryan had been released from prison when the letter was written. Teebay refers to Miss Pearse and Mrs Pearse, sister and mother of Patrick Pearse (executed after the Rising) and notes that she was given a book that had belonged to Pearse from St. Enda&#39;s, Rathfarnham, the school he had founded. It also describes the wife of Darrell Figgis, arrested after the Rising, as a &#39;great agitator&#39; and refers to others involved in the republican movement, including Michael Collins.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/47</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3420</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1016">Kathleen Teebay</persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1157">41 Wolverhampton Road, Stafford, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3420_img_283_1"  type="Letter"  url="2d8ec1a932b3af5fc452459d11147ebc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3420_img_283_2"  type="Letter"  url="c2527e2ca77c778b70409f0b7a436549.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3420_img_283_3"  type="Letter"  url="123d1e78d9f540d718f8c0a437967835.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3420_img_283_4"  type="Letter"  url="9363e872e01523a439cca676fc6dce34.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3420_img_283_1"/>
             41 Wolverhampton Rd <lb/>Stafford.   Sat: 7.10.16   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Ryan,   Thanks very much <lb/>for your letter. I am sure you <lb/>must feel a little sad that your <lb/>holiday is over but perhaps it has <lb/>been almost long enough.   I was awfully glad to hear Miss <lb/>Cregan is still in Ireland. I think <lb/>she would have been brokenhearted <lb/>to come so far away. I may be going <lb/>to London for a short stay next month &amp; <lb/>I was going to ask her to come &amp; see me <lb/>then if she cared <sic>too</sic> - However I wish <lb/> you would give me her address as <lb/>I promised to get her some pc's &amp; they
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3420_img_283_2"/>
            have only just arrived.   All friends here are terribly <lb/>sorry for the boys in camp because <lb/>they are having such a dreadful time. <lb/>We do wish they would bring them <lb/>back for the winter. F<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Moore heard from <lb/> M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Collins lately but it was not very cheerful. <lb/>Jo did not hear from Mert for a long time <lb/>until just lately &amp; she says his letters <lb/>were stopped because he tried to tell her <lb/>about it. The last time I heard from <lb/>Miss Pearse she had not heard either - <lb/>so perhaps it is the same explanation. <lb/>Jo sends me some of the cuttings from the <lb/>papers, I  will  forward to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> D. Figgis <lb/>because she is a great agitator. Of <lb/>course most of her energies up to the <lb/>present have been concerned with <lb/>Reading. Jo has not been to Wales <lb/>yet but I am always urging her to <lb/>do so because when she does she has <lb/>promised to <seg type="del">go</seg> come in here &amp; stay with me - <lb/>&amp; we have an awfully warm corner <lb/>for her - but it is rather a long way for her <lb/>now as she is not returning to Liverpool. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3420_img_283_3"/>
             Do you remember Denis Daly <lb/>perjuring himself by saying he could <lb/>not write first because he did not know <lb/>how to begin or end &amp; had no previous <lb/>experience to go upon. Well the <lb/>initial difficulty has evidently <lb/>proved too much for him so I have <lb/>kept up rather a desultory one sided <lb/>correspondence. I really must write <lb/> him again about some of the <lb/> "Kerryisms" in hopes it may cheer <lb/> him - it is difficult to imagine him <lb/> in the dumps. They nick-named <lb/> me "Why so" down there &amp; teased <lb/> me dreadfully, so if he had been <lb/> there as well I should hardly <lb/> have survived.   Well - your friends were <lb/> awfully good to me in Dublin. <lb/> I really did intend to write you <lb/>before &amp; tell you  all about it  so please forgive <lb/> delay. I went to see M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Pearse a <lb/> few times - she is quite close to you now, <lb/> isn't she? They gave me a book belonging
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3420_img_283_4"/>
            to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Pearse. R.I.P out of his study at <lb/> Rathfarnham - &amp; some other keepsakes <lb/> &amp; I am certain I shall treasure them <lb/> more than anything. I am glad that <lb/> I may be going to see her again soon.   I am coming to Dublin at the <lb/>end of October. Jo has a sister <lb/> who is a professor in a College there, <lb/> She has only been a little while &amp; finds it rather lonely. She wants me <lb/> to stay with her so I am almost <lb/> certain to be there - at any rate <lb/> over the weekend - so I hope I <lb/> see you. I heard that the <lb/> moustache has gone &amp; that you <lb/> looked a ruffian at Stafford &amp; <lb/> I would not know you now you <lb/> are civilized - Perhaps so but I would <lb/> have known your sister - she is so <lb/> like you.   Goodbye now. I remain, <lb/>Yours very sincerely   Kathleen Teebay. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>