<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1776">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to Thomas Henry Grattan Esmonde, 8 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Andrew Philip Magill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by  Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941) to Thomas Henry Grattan Esmonde (1862-1935). Magill was a civil servant and held the position of private secretary for successive chief secretaries of Ireland until his transfer to the Northern Irish Civil Service in 1921. Esmonde was a landowner and politician. The letter acknowledges Esmonde&#39;s recommendation that John Robert O&#39;Connell (1868-1943) be appointed chief crown solicitor and that O&#39;Connell&#39;s claims will be considered before any decision is made.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1776</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date>1916-04-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0418">Thomas Esmonde</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0921">Wexford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1776_img_1231_1"  type="Letter"  url="bf5c85adc3f71bc5c97dd73b39a854e0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1776_img_1231_1"/>
             Copy   8th April, 1916.   Dear Sir Thomas Esmonde,   I am desired by Mr. Birrell to acknowledge the <lb/>receipt of your letter of 7th instant, recommending <lb/>Sir John R. O'Connell for appointment as Chief Crown <lb/>Solicitor for Ireland, and to say that his claims will <lb/>be fully considered before an appointment is made.   Yours faithfully,  <lb/>(Sd.) A.P.M. <lb/>Under Secretary <lb/>A.P.M. <lb/>8/4/16 <lb/>Sir Thomas H. Grattan Esmonde, Bart., M.P.,  Ballynastragh, Inch, Co.Wexford 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>