<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0475">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Elder to the Under Secretary, 30 June, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Elder</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Robert Elder to the Undersecretary. Elder writes to apply for the position of Clerk of Crown and Peace for Co. Westmeath. In this letter he outlines his professional experience which includes his appointment to Commissioner of the Oaths in Westmeath.Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/11170</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/475</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1114">Robert Elder</persName>
              <date>1916-06-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1888">Athlone, Co. Westmeath, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Under Secretary for Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0475_img_1829_1"  type="Letter"  url="3accd5ac479b03877ab71c0aa3cca157.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0475_img_1829_1"/>
                ROBERT ELDER,  Solicitor.  Dublin Office,  69 &amp; 70 Dame Street.  Telegrams: 'Elder, Athlone.'  Telephone N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 9.   Notary Public.  Comm<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> for Oaths.    30 June 1916   Dear Sir,   I beg to apply for the vacant Clerk of the Crown and<lb/> Peaceship for the County of Westmeath. I was admitted a Solicitor<lb/> in 1903 and have since practised at Athlone and I have recently<lb/> been appointed by the Lord Chancellor a Notary Public and a <lb/> Commissioner for Oaths for the County of Westmeath. I should<lb/> feel obliged therefore if you would kindly bring my application<lb/> under the notice of the proper authority. <seg type="closer"> I am,<lb/> Your obedient servant,  <hi rend="underline">Robert Elder</hi>   The Under Secretary,  The Castle,   Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>