<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1059">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to Samuel Davidson, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his father, Samuel Cleland (1846-1921). James writes to thank his father for his congratulations on James&#39; engagement. James cautions that news of the engagement should be kept within the family until he returns. James notes that allotment of leave has decreased, suggesting that final preparations for the battle of the Somme are in motion. He briefly mentions the death of British Secretary of State for War, Lord Kitchener (1850-1916), describing it as a great blow.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.Sir Samuel Cleland Davidson was an Irish inventor and founder of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast. During the First World War the Sirocco Engineering Works manufactured and exported equipment for cooling, drying, dust collecting, heating, ventilating, pneumatic conveyance for the Royal and Merchant Navy.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>PRONI-D3642-B-8-53, PRONI-D3642-B-8-53</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1059</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1149">Samuel Cleland Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1121">SeaCourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1059_img_3153_1"  type="Letter"  url="c0d1a9c82c41c0703ec86db93c8a9146.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1059_img_3153_2"  type="Letter"  url="313c69ddf9a2c7efb164b4f4dca50274.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1059_img_3153_3"  type="Letter"  url="9d23946ae7fb89df0fda2cde742f7f17.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1059_img_3153_4"  type="Envelope"  url="61ba7450ce76b5759b6f146edc8f47c1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1059_img_3153_1"/>
                9/6/16   My Dear Father    Just a few <lb/>lines to thank you for <lb/>your letter of congratulations <lb/>&amp; to tell you how much <lb/>I appreciated it.    I fell sure Eileen &amp; <lb/>I will be very happy <lb/>together if only this <lb/>War was safely over, <lb/>for we have the advantage <lb/>of a long friendship &amp; <lb/>so many tastes, in <lb/>common. We <lb/>had neither of us quite <lb/>realised till recently <lb/>how we felt towards <lb/>one another. I told <lb/>Eileen my feelings  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1059_img_3153_2"/>
              before leaving but there <lb/>was no engagement <lb/>as I thought it better <lb/>that things should <lb/>not go further till <lb/>after the War. However <lb/>we soon found that <lb/>this was not possible <lb/>&amp; you know the rest, <lb/>only I do want our <lb/>engagement kept <lb/>strictly private till <lb/>I get home again. <lb/>I am afraid however <lb/>there is little prospect <lb/>of leave for some time. <lb/>The allotment has <lb/>not only been curtailed <lb/>but shortened as well <lb/>&amp; there is every indication <lb/>of its being cancelled  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1059_img_3153_3"/>
              completely before <lb/>long for things are <lb/>now moving quickly. <lb/>It is a great blow to <lb/>the Army losing Kitchener <lb/>at such a critical time. <lb/>We are still in the line <lb/>&amp; attached to a different Bde <lb/>as our Bde has gone back. <lb/>I don't expect we shall be <lb/>relieved at all as our <lb/>own Bde will soon be <lb/>returning but of course <lb/>one never knows. <seg type="closer"> Hoping you &amp; all are <lb/>well. <lb/>Your affect son  Jim </seg> The change of Brigade does not <lb/>alter the address as it is only <lb/>a temporary matter.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1059_img_3153_4"/>
              On Active Service <lb/>Written 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June recd 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  S.C Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co Down  Ireland   9 June 1916  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>