<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0571">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Duffy &amp; Co. to the Chief Secretary for Ireland, 4 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Duffy &amp;amp; Co. Ltd</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from James Duffy &amp;amp; Co. Ltd. to Henry Edward Duke (1855–1939), Chief Secretary for Ireland, acknowledging the receipt of a £40 settlement of the business’ claim for compensation in respect of damages sustained during the course of the Easter Rising, 1916.After the Easter rising British Prime Minister Herbert Asquith experienced considerable difficulty in finding a chief secretary for Ireland. Duke eventually accepted the position, although it was generally recognised as a poisoned chalice; he was formally appointed on 31 July 1916. Duke had little previous contact with Ireland, but displayed considerable diligence in mastering his brief, paying intense attention to official correspondence and undertaking a tour of large areas of Ireland in September 1916 to see the situation for himself.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5620/13528</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/571</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0638">James Duffy &amp;amp; Co. Ltd</persName>
              <date>1916-08-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0127">38 Westmoreland Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Henry Edward Duke</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0571_img_1966_1"  type="Letter"  url="a3a784aa45a926cbc920544a42e5e82a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0571_img_1966_1"/>
                38, Westmoreland S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>  Dublin    4th August 1916.    The Chief Secretary for Ireland,  Property Losses (Ireland) Committee,  Dublin Castle.    Printing  and  Binding Works,  61 &amp;62, G<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>Strand S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> &amp; 70 Jervis S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>   Dear Sir,   We beg to acknowledge cheque for Â£40-0-0 in full discharge<lb/> of our claim Â£41-10-6 for Damages incurred during the disturbances<lb/> between April 27th and May 1st. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully, <lb/> James Duffy &amp; Co Ltd </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>