<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0193">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Daulat Ram Kalia, March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Daulat Ram Kalia</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Daulat Ram Kalia, an Indian student. Kalia is writing in the hope that his letter will be brought to the attention of the Viceroy of Ireland, Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimbrone (1873-1939). Kalia was writing to complain about the newspaper &#39;The Eye-Opener&#39;. The paper caused some controversy due to an article it published with the heading &#39;Black Peril&#39; which attacked Indian students. The paper claims that &#39;coloured people&#39; were savage and that any white person seen in their company was a disgrace. Kalia asks the lord lieutenant to act against the offensive paper.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5575/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/193</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0290">Daulat Ram Kalia</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0154">21 Synge Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_1"  type="Letter"  url="45b4c7172d75dfcbb50294ef9706a908.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_2"  type="Letter"  url="dba650292cdf11ce41f0039381a78148.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_3"  type="Letter"  url="6459f4c59e82cab516e5b88aecff1389.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_4"  type="Letter"  url="a6fb532ca0e6628c26a8abd3064814f4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_5"  type="Letter"  url="06b02a90fda7b540d649bc8547c51b8f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_6"  type="Letter"  url="be83e97d9b2df05b169640a128a19912.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0193_img_1333_7"  type="Letter"  url="e4240847124fc69ed37c07c60e2c1f92.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_1"/>
               Dear Sir,   I shall feel much obliged <lb/> if you will care to lay the following lines <lb/> before His Excellency the Viceroy of Ireland.   1. The Eye- Opener, a recently started newspaper <lb/> of Dublin, has in its two last issues <lb/> written on the 'Black peril' in Dublin. <lb/> The writings are marked in the enclosed <lb/> copies &amp; speak for themselves.   2. The general impression of the language <lb/> on an unprejudiced mind is that it is <lb/> calculated to produce feelings of ill- <lb/> will &amp; hatred between too classes of His <lb/> Majesty's subjects - <seg type="unclear">in</seg> the white &amp; the <lb/> coloured people. The <seg type="unclear">Dundrum put</seg> on  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_2"/>
              page 3rd of the issue of 25.3.16 considers <lb/> it a disgrace for a white person to be seen <lb/> in the company of a coloured one. Not <lb/> only this but the words of the said <lb/> publication on Friday last had the <lb/> words 'Black Peril' on the in glowing <lb/> &amp; big type &amp; thus provoking every coloured man.   3. The publication in question really offended <lb/> the coloured class so for that they held <lb/> a meeting on Saturday last to consider <lb/> what measures should be taken <lb/> to put a stop to such offensive and <lb/> provocative language as has been <lb/> offending in the said publication. In <lb/> the meeting the indignation was <lb/> great &amp; surely the wounded feelings  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_3"/>
              seemed to hope for a remedy.   4. It is also worth mentioning that the <lb/> 'abundance of coloured gentlemen' finds <lb/> its only interpretation in the incidence <lb/> of the Indian students here, who all want to <lb/> come to a considerable <seg type="unclear">result</seg>.   5. It is simply shocking to see that <lb/> there law abiding subjects of His Majesty <lb/> are being <seg type="unclear">labelled</seg> with such references <lb/> which are nothing short of an attempt <lb/> to <seg type="unclear">outrage</seg> their feelings of decency. If they <lb/> deserved anything here it was sympathy <lb/> &amp; hospitality so that they had  left  this <lb/> beautiful town with happy memories &amp; <lb/> not an abusive language like the one <lb/> under influence.   6. The Govt: of India is doing its best to prompt <lb/> feelings of sympathy between the rulers <lb/> &amp; the ruled &amp; of everything possible is being <lb/> done to bring about cordial relations  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_4"/>
              between the Europeans &amp; the Indians. In <lb/> London where the Indian students are <lb/> found in hundreds the Govt: is looking <lb/> after their comforts, amusements the <lb/><seg type="unclear">religion</seg> &amp; the students go back to <lb/> their country full of the feelings of gratitude <lb/> towards their foreign rulers. Instead <lb/> of of anything of the kind the paper in question <lb/> has thought fit to hold them up to ridi- <lb/> cule, contempt and hatred. The editor may <lb/> have his motives, doubt or distrust he <lb/> knows well, but he should remain <lb/> within the bounds of law &amp; refrain <lb/> from using language which incites a community <lb/> as a whole. Who would on earth think <lb/> that every meeting of a coloured gentleman <lb/> &amp; a white lady is for unmoral purposes! Does <lb/> the editor want that they their should be un <lb/> social influence between two classes of <lb/> His Majesty's subjects? Is it consistent <lb/> with the policy of the European which <lb/> has made its <seg type="unclear">protection</seg> such a  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_5"/>
              namely of races! Surely the editor <lb/> is doing a mischief which is doing an <lb/> incalculable harm &amp; in his guise to <lb/> attempt to play a social reformer he <lb/> is offending &amp; wounding the feelings <lb/> of a race which comes to about 3/4 of <lb/> His Majesty's subjects. Again in view <lb/> of what India is doing for the war &amp; <lb/> in the <seg type="unclear">interest</seg> of the Empire it is <lb/> hardly admirable that those responsible <lb/> for the running of the 'eye -opener' should <lb/> be allowed to condemn us with impunit- <lb/> y.   7. The writing in question in my humble <lb/> opinion amounts to seditious libel on <lb/> a class (coloured class as opposed to white) <lb/> &amp; it is hoped His Excellency will <lb/> surely take steps in the matter-   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_6"/>
              8. During the regime of Lord Hardinge <lb/> in India as <seg type="unclear">towns</seg> were <seg type="unclear">formed</seg> by the <lb/> Govt: <hi rend="superscript">to</hi> establish wholesome relations <lb/> between the rulers &amp; the ruled &amp; Lord <lb/> Hardinge's name has become a <lb/> household word in India for his <lb/> sympathy &amp; love for the Indians. In <lb/> countenance of the same token we <lb/> bring hope that - Lord Chelmsford <lb/> our new viceroy will be able to migrate <lb/> with his generous policy the plant which <lb/> Lord Hardinge has sown there. His Excellency <lb/> Lord Wimborne being related to our <lb/> new viceroy we hope that he wanted <lb/> to look to this just complaint of <lb/> the subject  consented  to his brother in law  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0193_img_1333_7"/>
              which has been made to him <lb/> in the interest of justice &amp; good <lb/> administration &amp; above all <lb/> in the interest of the European <lb/> one which the sun does not <lb/><seg type="del">set</seg> set.  <seg type="closer"> With deepest respect - to His Excellency <lb/> of <seg type="unclear">Ireland</seg>. <lb/> Your very obedient servant   D.R.Kalia. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>