<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4157">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 9 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/51</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4157</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4157_img_3530_1"  type="Letter"  url="342b267cf488c865db74018959108549.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4157_img_3530_2"  type="Letter"  url="ccd8ad66c4c579619d058acdcf3b54c9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4157_img_3530_1"/>
             9 Nov 15   My dear pr   Your news of your happy visit at Elsie's is happy <lb/>reading &amp; I am grateful to them for giving you so nice a holiday <lb/>I am glad the youngsters remember me, &amp; hope they <seg type="del">shall</seg>will <lb/>get to know their new — fairly new still if rather old <lb/>&amp; shabby — uncle before many years are past.   About DON you write a lot of his attitude to you, <lb/>but what a growly surly wolf is much more interested in is <lb/>your attitude to him. Does he replace poor Julia, in <lb/>Your ...as well as in your affections, or does he remove <lb/>my shoes which are then declared as too old  fro me, possibly <seg type="unclear">reward offered</seg> &amp;does he <lb/>monopolise my best &amp; warmest rugs. In fact you have <lb/>roused the wolf's curiosity over the little beastie which of <lb/>course he would not deign to show. I suppose you haven't <lb/>paid the dog tax? He ought to keep you exercised &amp; <lb/>out of taxies &amp; other mischief, unless he says no busses <lb/>for me only taxies thanks!   Russel is up &amp; much better so I shall not have <lb/>to rouse the Gen' out of his postprandial slumbers as I did <lb/>last night. I thought he would be interested in hearing that our old  <lb/>artillery was coming to us &amp; our Terriers going to leave us, but
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4157_img_3530_2"/>
            all I got out of him, was "well I don't see what I can do." <lb/>I felt inclined to say "wake up &amp; take a little interest" but didn't.   I was out this morning with 108 th <seg type="unclear">Bdc</seg> bombing class,&amp; <lb/>saw their new battalion at work — nothing very wonderful.— <lb/>HP turned up &amp; he really expects a Division I believe. It is <lb/>almost incredible, but if you look ponderous &amp; hold your tongue <lb/>you can impose on a good many people.   There has been a rare rumpus with the chaplains. <lb/>Canon King has taken this line that he is not Senior Chap- <lb/>lain but <seg type="unclear">Singleton</seg>insists on sending his orders through him, <lb/>&amp; the Presbyterians have gone on strike! I fancy the RC <lb/>element has complicated matters. The whole mismanage- <lb/>ment is a pity, but in any case these P.Ministers are <lb/>a little difficiles.   Clyde Valley has been a little lame those last few <lb/>days but M'Gill is busy with hot bandages thinks he will <lb/>cure her without expert advice &amp; it is as well to let him <lb/><seg type="unclear">try</seg>. Fanny still goes strong &amp; has won the affectionate <lb/>admiration of Richardson's mare, which is tolerated by Fanny <lb/>without enthusiasm, &amp; which is most amusing to watch. <lb/>It is a case of a complete infatuation almost as complete&amp; <lb/>as incomprehensible as that of the b w for a little p r.   Still your b w    W.BSpender   It wouldn't be much use my being home as you <lb/>can't receive any good <seg type="unclear">marks</seg>now! Hows the cold? 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>