<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6735">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alice Stopford Green to John Quinn, 27 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alice Stopford Green</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Alice Stopford Green (1847–1929) to John Quinn (1870-1924), discussing the execution of Rodger Casement. Stopford Green was a historian and an Irish nationalist, who had a close connection with Sir Roger Casement, working with him to form the Congo Reform Association in 1904. John Quinn was a lawyer in New York, the son of Irish immigrants who maintained close ties with Ireland during his life through his patronage of the arts. In this letter, Stopford Green thanks Quinn for writing to her. From the details of the letter, it appears that Stopford Green was receiving messages from Quinn for Casement in prison. Stopford Green also asks that Quinn suspend all judgement about Casement following the rumours regarding his supposed controversial journals. These were the infamous &#39;Black Diaries&#39;, allegedly written by Casement. She has further information, but believes it best not to discuss them now.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>John Quinn Papers, Box 7, f.4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6735</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date>1916-08-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0183">36 Grosvenor Road, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1279">John Quinn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0945">31 Nassau Street, New York, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1929</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6735_img_None_1"  url="phpfwBQKW.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6735_img_0_1"/>
              36 Grosvenor Road.<lb/>London. S.W.   2. N. 17   Aug. 27.    My dear Mr. Quinn.   I thank you for sending me the<lb/>cable, now so long ago. Alas, I could not<lb/>give your message – it was on the day it was<lb/>sent, and before it arrived, that my last<lb/>visit was paid. But he knew that friends<lb/>thought of him and would remember him,<lb/>and this was his consolation &amp; encouragement.  I have many grave and deeply<lb/>interesting things to tell you, but it is of<lb/>no use to attempt to write them now –<lb/>I can only ask you to suspend all judgements<lb/>until a better time comes. There has been some<lb/>more horror than exultation at the cause of events.  I am yours sincerely   Alice Stopford Green  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>