<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0429">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William S. McKee to Frederick Hugh Crawford, 24 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William S. McKee</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from William S McKee (b. 1836) to Colonel Frederick Hugh Crawford (1861-1952) McKee has recently left the employment at A. Crawford &amp;amp; Sons and clearly Crawford has continued to send him his full salary. McKee writes to thank him for the money but protests at Crawford&#39;s generosity.Born in in Belfast, County Antrim, to a Methodist family, Frederick Hugh Crawford was an engineer, soldier and a gun runner. He smuggled German guns into Larne, Bangor and Donaghadee in 1914 for the Ulster Volunteer Force. William McKee was the long time manager of A. Crawford &amp;amp; Sons starch manufacturers, a firm founded by Crawford&#39;s grandfather.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Crawford Papers, D/1700/5/17/1/129</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/429</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0176">William S. McKee</persName>
              <date>1916-03-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0241">Mossvale, Bangor, County Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0900">Frederick Hugh Crawford</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0790">Wilson Street, Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0429_img_1747_1"  type="Letter"  url="3eef3e4368068889269236655e7c475c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0429_img_1747_2"  type="Letter"  url="824e43845d9118ed8a27642a905b31df.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0429_img_1747_3"  type="Letter"  url="9a66572f18aafb46aed7fb73713b7a59.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0429_img_1747_4"  type="Photograph"  url="30067dd9c25c96122dc25ed59c46ab27.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0429_img_1747_1"/>
               MOSSVALE,   BANGOR,  CO. DOWN    March 24/16   Dear Col. Crawford   I yesterday received from Ernest<lb/>my usual weekly drawing,<lb/>&amp; must thank you for your goodness<lb/>in telling him to pay this amount<lb/>to me whether at the office or not.  I know this is only in keeping<lb/>with all the kindness you have<lb/><sic>shewn</sic> me, both before &amp; since<lb/>your father died, but as I am<lb/>fully aware that any business you have, can be carried on<lb/>perfectly well without me 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0429_img_1747_2"/>
              I feel it would not be fair <lb/> to take this money in view of <lb/> your present financial difficulties. <lb/> Ernest is really doing all the <lb/> work &amp; will naturally &amp; fairly <lb/> expect more salary than he now <lb/> has &amp; as I will be perfectly <lb/> satisfied &amp; content with half <lb/> my usual wages, you can at <lb/> once give him an advance without <lb/> in the least increasing the office <lb/> expenses in any way.   I need hardly say that it <lb/> is most painful for me to be <lb/> obliged to give up my position in the old firm, after such a long <lb/> and pleasant service. With all <lb/> the several members of the firm I <lb/> have always had the happiest relations <lb/> and I feel I owe them more than <lb/> it would ever be possible for me <lb/> to repay, if I were to live for a century <lb/> longer. I cannot however get <lb/> over the fact that I am now in <lb/> my 80 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year &amp; that I no longer <lb/> feel that I am fit to take on <lb/> great responsibilities in connection <lb/> with business. I am not given <lb/> to complaining about my health <lb/> but I must say that I never felt <lb/> any winter so severely as this one, <lb/> and I am almost certain that <lb/> only for your kindness in giving <lb/> me shorter hours &amp; a whole Saturday  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0429_img_1747_3"/>
              holiday, I would not have <lb/> been able to hold out so long. <lb/> I need hardly say that anything <lb/> it is in my power to do for you <lb/> or the firm in any way, I shall <lb/> always be ready to do. I am <lb/> counting on feeling better when <lb/> the weather improves &amp; when <lb/> I will be able to take more <lb/> outside exercise than is now <lb/> possible.  <seg type="closer"> With kind regards <lb/> Ever yours truly   W. S. McKee  </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0429_img_1747_4"/>
               Bangor 25 Mar 16 <lb/><hi rend="underline">Private</hi>    Colonel F. H. Crawford,  A Crawford &amp; Son,  Wilson St.,  Belfast.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>