<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2736">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his parents, Harford and Sara Montgomery, 18 November, 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Montgomery from the front to his parents detailing his daily life and difficult conditions in the trenches, particularly for the men in the company under William&#39;s command.

The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2736</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1915-11-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Harford Hugh Montgomery and Sara Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2095">Monacherra, Malone Park,Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_1"  type="Letter"  url="ef6bf5eb91596b7b2afce2b7368df35a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_2"  type="Letter"  url="1c8ef6865904f43561fb81a3718f2072.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_3"  type="Letter"  url="94282df1a0458ee3cf6c51416240a706.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_4"  type="Letter"  url="90f862a733eb783154749deb6f6490c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_5"  type="Letter"  url="37937381032b0a53a1a40d44f65a0046.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_6"  type="Letter"  url="61e563849ec5611100593e442dca147b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_7"  type="Letter"  url="f7510efc0efa843c041142b82339b444.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_8"  type="Letter"  url="4a7c2d29c96a43619f834816378be891.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_9"  type="Letter"  url="20a1e21523db67dc04e8973c1a73706c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2736_img_2156_10"  type="Letter"  url="8f2cfc20719666358d267d286e53ce5a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_1"/>
              In the Field     18.11.15.    My dear Father &amp; Mother /   / I am in the very <lb/> best of health &amp; form. Since I wrote <lb/> you last, I have had the honour <lb/>of commanding my own Company <lb/> in occupation of a portion of the <lb/> British Front Line for a week.     My men did splendidly and <lb/> I am  very   proud of them. Father <lb/> you people at home, even if you <lb/>are gifted with vivid imagination <lb/> can have no idea of what a poor <lb/> line of trenches entail in the <lb/> way of suffering on the men. <lb/> And again you have no idea of what <lb/> the human animal can with <lb/> training &amp; discipline be taught <lb/> to endure. I   had   probably the lowest <lb/> type of men in the battalion as <lb/> far as ordinary standards go <lb/> (<hi rend="underline">not</hi> for quotation at the Rotary club) <lb/> I always said that they would <lb/> never be regimental soldiers but that <lb/> I didn't care where I took them &amp; <lb/> that they would never fail me in the field. <lb/> They have justified that contention &amp; <lb/> A Coy, which was formerly the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_2"/>
            black sheep, is today the flower of the <lb/>flock in the C.O.s opinion with <lb/>Horaces' Coy a very good next. <lb/>Horace's was always considered the <lb/>best Coy. &amp; he is easily the best <lb/>Coy. Cmdr. But my knowledge of <lb/>engineering &amp; tool handling is getting <lb/>scope now. Trenches are all <lb/>engineering. <sic>some</sic> of it not at all <lb/>elementary. Conditions in the line <lb/>we took over were so bad that some <lb/>of my men never got lying down <lb/>at all for a week. No dugout, not <lb/>even mine, was waterproof &amp; it <lb/>rained 5 days &amp; 4 nights. There <lb/>were 6 " of mud on the floors of <lb/>all the mens <seg type="del">trenches</seg> dugouts &amp; <lb/>some of the Sapheads had two <lb/>feet of water &amp; a foot of mud <lb/>in them. 3 of my listening posts <lb/>(2 men in each 2 hours each) had <lb/>to stand in the mud &amp; water <lb/>mixture &amp; <hi rend="underline">listen for our lives</hi> <lb/>all week. With no change of clothes <lb/>no place to sleep except sitting <lb/>or standing &amp; very little fuel <lb/>&amp; practically no light. These <lb/>listening posts are <hi rend="underline">very</hi> close to
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_3"/>
            the German lines &amp; run out about <lb/>100 yards in front of our own line <lb/>usually in front of the wire. <lb/>They are lonely places &amp; occasionally <lb/>men are lost in them as the <lb/>result of successful bombing <lb/>parties of Germans <seg type="del">getting</seg> who work <lb/>close up &amp; blow the whole post to <lb/>Hades or heaven with a couple of <lb/>bombs. I always say to myself every <lb/>time I visit a listening post that <lb/>I must take my revolver or a couple <lb/>of bombs next time.   Maynard Sinclair (about 19 years old) <lb/>is my second in command at present <lb/>but I fear he is going to be taken <lb/>from me my Brigade H.Q. This would <lb/>be a good big lift for him &amp; he <lb/>would be in the place where <lb/>D.S.Os go. He is a grand boy <lb/>&amp; the makings of a fine soldier   On my week in the trenches <lb/>I only had 3 men went sick <lb/><seg type="del">some</seg>all the others had over 20 &amp; <lb/>one had over 50. Pretty good but <lb/>wants a lot of nursing with a <lb/>rough tongue &amp; the very judicious <lb/>dosing with raw spirit. I have
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_4"/>
            seen men <hi rend="underline">marching asleep</hi>. A <lb/>most astonishing sight. They <lb/>have all the symptoms of ordinary <lb/>sleep walkers. When I think of what <lb/>my fellows have stood &amp; will have to <lb/>stand again &amp; I think of some of the <lb/>people at home who do nothing I <lb/>go mad. And the cheeriness of the <lb/>fellows is marvellous. Beautiful <lb/>and I have heard them described <lb/>as the scum of the Shankill road, <lb/>by people not fit to clean their <lb/>very dirty boots. We have had very <lb/>heavy snow &amp; frost, but are in very <lb/>comfortable billets at present &amp; have <lb/>some fuel. so everything is rosy.    Company cmdg. on the line is <lb/>a job carrying with it great <lb/>responsibility &amp; great power. For instance <lb/>I would say more or less casually to <lb/>Downing at afternoon tea time — <lb/>William I want you to go out on <lb/>Patrol tonight to ascertain the <lb/>strength of the German wire in <lb/>front. Make all arrangements &amp; choose <lb/>your men please. You will go out <lb/>by No 1 listening post = will work <lb/>left. No 1 machine gun will <lb/>afford you support by traversing from
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_5"/>
            the post to the right. Advise the gun <lb/>as to time of going out &amp; report return <lb/>to me. I am not allowed to go out <lb/>on patrol mother will be glad to <lb/>hear. Being too valuable as a Coy <lb/>Cmdr. funny isn't it?   My Aunt Olivia would say I <lb/>am spoiled in the trenches. It is a <lb/>pretty imposing show I must admit. <lb/>I have a dug out well behind the <lb/>line to which I must retire in <lb/>case we are attacked or heavily <lb/>shelled except for purpose of <lb/>steadying the men. I have a servant <lb/>there, 3 signallers one always with <lb/>instrument on his head. 2 orderlies <lb/>and an observer &amp; behind the <lb/>line my horse and groom. Our <lb/>officers mess of six also possesses <lb/>two cooks who with the six servants <lb/>do nothing else but look after us.    I am in direct communication with <lb/>a battery of artillery which I can <lb/>turn out at my own sweet will. <lb/>It is a most beautiful sight to <lb/>see our shells landing clear <lb/>into the enemy/s trenches or <lb/>bursting over them, or landing into <lb/>a village they occupy &amp; the <lb/>houses collapsing. It is <hi rend="underline">most</hi> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_6"/>
            exciting &amp; the men at work always <lb/> want to down tools &amp; go &amp; look at <lb/> it much the same as they go to <lb/> a football match. We don't of course <lb/> have it all our own way. And the <lb/> Bosches have the range of our trenches <lb/> just as accurately as we have <lb/>theirs. Sleep in the trenches for <lb/> a CoyComdr at night is one of the <lb/> many things he does without <lb/> unless he has great luck &amp; <lb/> things are very quiet. He never <lb/> takes off his clothes or boots to <lb/> lie down. And should only change <lb/> his boots &amp; socks during the <lb/> day time. I generally get about <lb/> 3 hours sleep at a time &amp; that <lb/> comes mostly about every 18 hours. <lb/> I have heard men say the <lb/> strain of command tells on them <lb/> very severely. Now that I <hi rend="underline">know </hi> <lb/> that seeing casualties &amp; fire <lb/> do not upset me I have got <lb/> confidence in myself &amp; up to now <lb/> have kept cool. It is very <lb/>extraordinary to note the effect <lb/> of fire on different people.   Almost all my previous real <lb/> bad eggs, specially drunks, have
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_7"/>
            turned out well. I met one of <seg type="unclear">them </seg> <lb/> the other day in a communicating <lb/> trench <seg type="del">&amp; asked</seg> He was wet to the <lb/>waist &amp; mud to the eyes &amp; hadn't <lb/> had food for 14 hours &amp; it was <lb/> pouring rain &amp; asked him how <lb/> he liked the life — He replied <lb/> shortly &amp; with his eyes shining _ I <lb/> just love it Sir &amp; then he <lb/> laughed &amp; said I never could <lb/> stand that bloody Barrack <lb/>sodgering. He couldnt either, he <lb/> spent 6 months of it in jail. <lb/> I have another awful bad <lb/> character whom I have had to see <lb/> undergo Field Punishment N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>1 <lb/> who bears no malice &amp; is in fact <lb/> thirsting for a melodramatic <lb/> opportunity to save my life <lb/> simply because months ago <lb/> when everyone kicked him <lb/> I spoke seriously &amp; with kindness <lb/> to him &amp; gave him a shilling <lb/> when he hadnt had pay for <lb/> months. The little blighter never forgot <lb/>it. His curse is drink. But he cant <lb/> get that now except under very <lb/> strict supervision. You should see <lb/> me at the ungodly hour of 5 AM
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_8"/>
            every morning when in the trenches <lb/> doling out tots of rum. It is one of <lb/> my duties to sit on the rum supply. <lb/> It is never handled in my Coy <lb/>unless an officer is present. I <lb/> am terrified of the stuff as it <lb/> means 10 years penal servitude <lb/> for any man who gets too much.   The men are very funny about <lb/> it. One said to me the other <lb/> day when I was dishing it out <lb/> "Sir just turn your back &amp; let your <lb/> orderly lay down that for &amp; <lb/> in half an hour we will be <lb/> in the German trenches". It is <lb/> gorgeous stuff. I have used it <lb/> hot to revive even the almost <lb/> dead. I found a fellow collapsed <lb/> on his post one night during <lb/> my rounds still clinging to <lb/> his rifle watching his front <lb/> but unable to stand, burning <lb/> with fever, &amp; cold as ice. I <lb/> had him relieved &amp; well beaten <lb/> took him to my dug out. Fed <lb/> him rum hot &amp; bread in <lb/> front of my stove &amp; drove <lb/> him out to work again with a <lb/> shovel. He was quite all right
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_9"/>
            next morning except that his feet <lb/> and legs were swollen a bit.   I had another strong man who had <lb/> awful feet coming along the road <lb/> following trench relief<hi rend="underline">crying</hi> as <lb/> he fell out because he was <lb/> disgracing his company. I was <lb/> commanding my coy from the rear <lb/> at this time just on the look out <lb/> for such as he. I flailed him <lb/> with my tongue, fed him <lb/> neat whiskey from my flask <lb/> &amp; ordered him back into the <lb/> ranks. He went &amp; completed the <lb/> march in the ranks. His feet <lb/> were bleeding. But I got him home. <lb/> That was what I was there for. Before <lb/> I came out the men hated me <lb/> now they don't because I am so hard <lb/> with them that they trust me. I <lb/> feed them kindness in small rare <lb/> doses. And I never tell them I am <lb/> pleased with them. They generally <lb/> know when I am displeased with <lb/> them. Coy. Commanding is necessarily <lb/> in war a brutal occupation. This <lb/> side of the business would suit <lb/> Bodel but the exposure wouldnt.   I think it is time I drew to a close
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_2736_img_2156_10"/>
            I would just love a packet or two of <lb/> Macfarlane &amp; Lang's oatcakes &amp; some <lb/> more of that good honey.   Please show this to Emmie, but <lb/> please please don't make speeches about <lb/> it.   With love    <seg type="unclear">WAMontgomery</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>