<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4234">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/71</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4234</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4234_img_3602_1"  type="Letter"  url="97ceed23e306032ab45e6a153f4f4e5b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4234_img_3602_2"  type="Letter"  url="c0869ae2c9f27f371c529ca6b877b6c3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4234_img_3602_1"/>
             Nov. 22.   I think the b w is distincly jealous of the squirrel, when <lb/> he sees how the p r makes up to him -the pampered little mendicant! <lb/> but all the same he would much like to see the 2 together. Would the squirrel <lb/> disappear if the b w came along with the p r ? I notice you have no doubt <lb/> that it is a "Mr", perhaps there are several little Mrs looking on with poor <lb/> litlle wrinkled noses. However when the B W comes their time will come, <lb/> &amp; then Mr Squirrel perhaps will give up his flirtation with a p r &amp; think <lb/> more of the domestic virtues of his....? (toploft is the nearest term I can <lb/>get to his own hearth).   I am afraid I may not have given you quite enough informa <lb/> tion about the Div' train for your Committee, but if you have taken my <lb/> advice &amp; have written to the OC ( not to any one by name) this will <lb/> not matter. The Div' train which is now concentrated is likely to <lb/> be divided up over a fairly wide area so that each <seg type="del">man</seg> company  will have <lb/> to be dealt with as a separate unit, but if you have written to the <lb/> OC Div' train &amp; not to each of the OC Cos A<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">SC</seg></hi>this will not have <lb/> mattered in the "past", but will later not work.   I am wondering if you have decided to go over to Ireland, rather <lb/> a miserable little p r I'm afraid if so, also whether the Agency is going to be <lb/> opened. Even this will require a certain amount of funds.    The men seem to be fully provided with cardigan waistcoats <lb/> &amp; all the clothing they can carry except perhaps socks &amp; mittens? But <lb/> the local unit committees can let you know things. I expect they will ask <lb/> for cigarettes (woodbines) but as they get a fairly large issue I should not "give" <lb/> them tho' I see no objection to your becoming an agency as tobacconists.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4234_img_3602_2"/>
             ask Mrs K S whether she objects <lb/> to having Tobacconist &amp; wholesale dealer written up outside her front door. Proba- <lb/>bly she would quite agree If her name were put first &amp; that of the <lb/> Duchess 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> &amp; Lady C's last!    I think as far as one can tell at present that we shall have <lb/> moved to our new district by the end of the month, &amp; it is the intention <lb/> for us to stop there for at least 6 weeks, but one really never knows more than <lb/> 1 day ahead.   Richardson is very  much  annoyed because COC has treating his <lb/> expert knowledge on musketry as if it was that of an infant, &amp; told him <lb/> to refer to Barnett. As R was head of a Musketry school &amp; Barnett <lb/> a territorial pot hunter you can imagine that <seg type="del">th</seg>he does not like it. <lb/> This is Gen N all over he looks upon his subordinates as so many <lb/> children &amp; lets them know it.    No more prattling now but my dear love to Mater <lb/> &amp; old Jess, &amp; ... to ...   Your b w    WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>