<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4276">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to family, 9 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his family.  Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/213</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4276</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4276_img_3640_1"  type="Letter"  url="d3e23b9187c100bc0637271fa4ef9092.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4276_img_3640_2"  type="Letter"  url="9a80c793c44e117f4ee4269d213510a6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4276_img_3640_3"  type="Letter"  url="8d6fab00a6ccd5b728b817f72b343e58.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4276_img_3640_4"  type="Letter"  url="cace2a5661ad55c0dd46fbb355457f18.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4276_img_3640_5"  type="Letter"  url="8a942579ae57a2c0cbf8abc342ffb484.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4276_img_3640_1"/>
             <seg type="del">Mater<lb/>Mab<lb/>Edmund</seg><lb/>Rex   <hi rend="underline">Please return finally to Lil</hi>   9 April   My dear Folks.   Douglas brought me a most exciting <lb/>budget with news of Sir E &amp; all manner <lb/>of things. I am sorry that Edmund was unable <lb/>to get an interview with him, tho' I can <lb/>imagine what a strain these interviews must be <lb/>on a leading man. I am delighted that <lb/>Ed has decided to support him in the WMN <lb/>&amp; if he knew all that I should like to tell <lb/>him  but must not  he would be even more determined in <lb/>his views.   Bonar Law whom I look upon as a most
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4276_img_3640_2"/>
            <lb/>honourable man is I think a little narrow <lb/>minded and limited in vision, probably a most <lb/>useful head of one of the great departments, but <lb/>not a Leader.   Pearson, especially if he has to feel the <lb/>tonic of sacrifice, as I believe is the case now that <lb/>he is resolved to give up law has all the qualities <lb/>of leadership except one &amp; that is robust health, <lb/>but many a great man has succeeded in spite <lb/>of this — Wolfe Caesar — .   Of my own news I have not very much <lb/>to tell. We have left our lordly chateau but <lb/>I am not so badly off in my labourer's <lb/>cottage &amp; our office is not bad at all, &amp; the <lb/>Spring weather of course gives quite a different <lb/>aspect to life &amp; one can sit by an open window.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4276_img_3640_3"/>
             Lt Col Place — Russsell's successor as GSO1 — <lb/> has arrived. He is a sapper <seg type="del">best</seg> &amp; I think has <lb/> both brains &amp; determination so it is probably <lb/> best for the Division that he should be here.   I have just got Mater's letter saying <lb/> she is giving us a gift of £25 each, &amp; really <lb/> it is wonderful in these times. Her purse seems <lb/> to be a real Widows' cruse thanks to her <lb/> care &amp; management. Both Lily &amp; I give <lb/> our most grateful thanks &amp; I hope Mater <lb/> will approve of its being used for Government <lb/> Loan purposes, into which all my pay is being put.   I calculate that the Government will take <lb/> rather more than half one's income this next <lb/> year — as the excess profits tax will take a very <lb/> large portion of the rubber dividends &amp; the 25%
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4276_img_3640_4"/>
            <lb/>income tax comes in on top, but thanks to Mater's <lb/> help in the past &amp; Lily's care now we can manage <lb/> more than comfortably &amp; can I hope still give our <lb/> tenth to charity. Later on rubber will not do so <lb/> well and we shall also have no pay <seg type="del">but</seg>so that <lb/> is why we do not intend to live beyond our future <lb/> — even if there were any inducements to do so <lb/> which there are not —.    There was a very determined attack this <lb/> week upon our lines and on the Division <lb/> next door, and for the 3rd time the Ulstermen <lb/> held their own whilst those  Divisions on our flank <lb/> let the enemy in though only for a short time <lb/> before they were turned out again. As the <lb/> battalion concerned was our most doubtful <lb/> one it is satisfactory to feel that they have upheld <lb/> the moral of the Division, but they are certain-
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4276_img_3640_5"/>
            <lb/>ly a good lot. It will not do to boast &amp; under <lb/> certain unfair conditions they may fail, but <lb/> I am sure that no other troops in the British <lb/> Army could do more.   It is wonderful how the French villagers <lb/> can cultivate their land with the whole <lb/> of their villages full of British troops — how full <lb/> you can imagine when a village of 800 inhabi <lb/>tants has got 3000 men extra living in it ! 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>