<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5795">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay 20 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
The letter discusses rumors of Home Rule</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5795</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5795_img_893_1"  type="Letter"  url="34eacb22ba243cb7c940d78c4357d498.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5795_img_893_2"  type="Letter"  url="d932ea581e5c06127c091514a9b4429e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5795_img_893_3"  type="Letter"  url="7eb2f7b962e67037498f5a9e4624d23c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5795_img_893_1"/>
             20th May, 1916.   My darling May,   I have very little to say to you <lb/>to-day except the things that I suppose you <lb/>are tired of hearing and that you can <lb/>guess at even when I don't tell you. I <lb/>need only say <seg type="del"> </seg> that score that every <lb/>day that brings me nearer to the 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/>June makes me more impatient for the moment <lb/>when I can have you for myself. I hope <lb/>you got the watch all right this <lb/>morning and that it will give better <lb/>satisfaction than I fear the donor ever will
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5795_img_893_2"/>
             give you. By the way, will you please<lb/>keep safely the box in which I sent you<lb/>the watch. It is not of very much intrinsic<lb/>value as you can see but my mother<lb/>attaches a great deal of sentimental value<lb/>to it and wishes to have it back. You<lb/>needn't send it back, I can bring it<lb/>back with me on the eventful day. I<lb/>have been inquiring again about the holiday<lb/>arrangements on the Great Southern and<lb/>think they will be all right by the time<lb/>our little hurroo comes off. Things here<lb/>are settling down more and more every  day. The papers are still full of a settlement<lb/>of the Home Rule question and I hear on<lb/>very good authority indeed that it is a<lb/>settled thing that Home Rule is to come<lb/>into operation without delay. That will mean<lb/>big changes and you might see your little<lb/>man Prime Minister yet. Jokes apart I believe<lb/>there will be very interesting happenings in<lb/>Ireland in the course of the next few<lb/>months and I don't think they will be to<lb/>the disadvantage of the country generally.<lb/>We haven't heard or seen anything of<lb/>Johnnie since he left for Cork. Mrs Seery<lb/>was saying if he came back he would stop<lb/>a night with us so I am hoping for the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5795_img_893_3"/>
             fact that we haven't seen him that<lb/>he has got on well. Tell Mrs Seery that<lb/>I got my wee kit all right and that<lb/>I intend to wear it for my wedding.<lb/>I think it's good enough for a country wedding<lb/>I don't see what better I can get unless I turn<lb/>out in a morning coat and a silk hat.<lb/>What do you think? If you would prefer<lb/>me to get something darker and smarter, I<lb/>will do so with pleasure. No news since<lb/>from the O'Connors, but their cousins, Eddie Con<lb/>and his father have been deported to England.<lb/>I expect you heard us talk of the Cons.<lb/>I send you my warmest and most<lb/>devoted love as ever.<lb/> Your loving<lb/>James 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>