<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6637">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ellen Daly to Kate Allman, 28 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ellen Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Mother of Charlie Daly, Ellen Daly is mourning Charlie&#39;s death. She supports their family friend, Kate Allman&#39;s decision to return to the convent to become a nun. 1 page</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>P41 Charlie Daly Collection, Location MG2 B6 S4, Fond 10: &#34;Correspondence of Kate Allman&#34;, Sub-Fond 3 &#34;Correspondence between Kate Allman and the Charlie Daly&#39;s Siblings&#34;</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6637</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1168">Ellen Daly</persName>
              <date>1923-03-28</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0800">Kate Allman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1605">Convent of Mercy, Waterford, Co. Waterford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1964</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6637_img_None_1"  url="phpgtlWn2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6637_img_0_1"/>
             841/10/3/3/2   Thursday    Dear Katty   Oh how hard it is to write when<lb/>ones heart is sore. God holy will be done<lb/>Oh Katty what a thunderbolt when we thought<lb/>our darling was safe he was too good for<lb/>this mean world &amp; is gone to a happier home<lb/>well prepared to meet his <seg type="unclear">? ?</seg> but left<lb/>sad hearts in this miserable world my<lb/>darling had no secrets from me even to<lb/>the last. I will treasure them during my<lb/>life. Well Katty I am delighted you have<lb/>left the outside world. If you ever come<lb/>home if, God, spares my life I will go to see you<lb/>your nice letters were very consoling.<lb/>Katty excuse me I can't write any more<lb/>my heart is too full.  <lb/> God Bless <seg type="unclear">? ?</seg> you is the<lb/><seg type="unclear">?</seg> of your ever loving friend<lb/>Ellen   <seg type="unclear">? letter</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>