<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1512">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Printed copy of letter from Henry Lemass, solicitor, to Herbert Henry Asquith, 13 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Lemass</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Henry Lemass, Solicitor. The writer expresses Mrs.Sheehy-Skeffington&#39;s &#39;profound dissatisfaction&#39; with the limited information disclosed at the Court-Martial of Captain J.C. Bowen-Colthurst (for the murder of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington and others) and goes on to cite particular details as the basis for her dissatisfaction. Lemass also asks when the promised Public Inquiry is to be held. The letter questions the suitability of English Counsel for the Prosecution and expresses other concerns about the way the process has been conducted. This copy was enclosed in a letter (MS6837/25/3), dated 16 June 1916, from Lemass to John Dillon, MP. That letter has also survived.Lemass acted for Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in matters relating to her husband&#39;s murder on 26 April 1916, and subsequent events. Herbert Henry Asquith, (1852 – 1928) served as the Liberal Prime Minister of the United Kingdom from 1908 to 1916. Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916), a pacifist, feminist, and suffragist had been arrested on 25 April 1916, along with two others by Captain J.C. Bowen-Colthurst (1880-1966), an Anglo-Irish officer of the Royal Irish Regiment. On 26 April all three were summarily executed by firing squad at Portobello Barracks. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full detail emerged. John Dillon, (1851-1927) was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs.Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, Ms. 6837/25/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1512</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0457">Henry Lemass</persName>
              <date>1916-06-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0359">Parliament Chambers, 31 Parliament Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0582">Herbert Henry Asquith</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0715">10 Downing Street, London S.W., England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1512_img_970_1"  type="Letter"  url="805c5b5da4c9df6c6f20356549da7d31.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1512_img_970_1"/>
                31 PARLIAMENT STREET, DUBLIN,    June 13th, 1916.   SIR   As solicitor for Mrs. Sheehy Skeffington - for whose husband's murder, on 26th April, <lb/> Captain Bowen Colthurst has been adjudged guilty - I have the honour to inquire when the <lb/> promised Public Inquiry will be held?   My client is profoundly dissatisfied with the limited information afforded at the Court- <lb/>martial, when the insanity of the acused was suggested.   While she abhors the idea that fresh blood should be spilt, my client is equally resolute <lb/> that the truth should be known, so that the people of the three Kingdoms may determine whether <lb/>the same measure of justice has been meted out to all parties affected by the rebellion.   That there were circumstances giving rise to anxiety connected with the recent trial will <lb/>be evident from the following facts: -   Lieutenant Wylie, K.C. who had prosecuted to conviction other men recently executed, <lb/>was released from this Courtmartial and an English Counsel, not fully acquainted with the facts <lb/> or imperfectly instructed, was appointed. Although no plea of inability to plead was entered <lb/> for the accused, the question of his sanity was raised from the outset. Yet the manner in which <lb/> he effected the arrest of the other murdered men (Messrs Dickson and McIntyre) was not proved, <lb/> nor the process by which he selected them for execution from amongst eight prisoners. Never <lb/>theless, it was within the knowledge of the Military Authorities that Messrs, Dickson and <lb/> McIntyre were taken into custody on the premises of Alderman James Kelly, ex-High Sheriff, by <lb/> the accused, under the idea that the shop belonged to Alderman Thomas Kelly, a person of <lb/> wholly different politics. They also knew that Colthurst threw a bomb into the premises and <lb/> subsequently 'planted' Mr. Dickson's trunk therein to give rise to the suspicion that Mr. <lb/>Dickson had been harboured by Alderman James Kelly who was also lodged in Portobello <lb/> Barracks. Nor was the Court informed that two sisters of Mrs. Skeffington, viz: Mrs Kettle <lb/> (wife of Lieutenant Kettle), and Mrs, Culhane (widow of a public official lately deceased) called <lb/>at Portobello Barracks on Friday, 28th April, after the murders, and, on inquiring for their <lb/> brother, Lieutenant Sheehy, were put under arrest and brought before Captain Colthurst, and <lb/>that he denied all knowledge of Mr. Skeffington and was perfectly calm and collected in his <lb/>demeanour and falsehoods. Similarly, the tribunal was not made aware that on the evening <lb/>after his examination of these ladies, Captain Colthurst ordered a search of Mrs.Skeffington's <lb/>house; that his soldiers first fired into her dwelling, and then, producing a key taken from the <lb/> body of the murdered man, opened his locked room and removed documents to try to furnish the <lb/>accused with ex post facto justification for his crime. The second raid on the widow's house by <lb/>Colthurst's orders on the following Monday, as well as the fact that one of the soldiers who took <lb/>part in it was the Sergeant left in charge of Dickson's trunk at Alderman James Kelly's, was <lb/>also left unmentioned. There was an equally significant silence as to the protests of the murder- <lb/>ed men on the morning of their execution, and as to the accused's refusal of spiritual solace to <lb/>them in their last moments.The Courtmartial were likewise unaware that Captain Colthurst <lb/> was allowed to remain at large by his superiors until the 6th May- nearly a fortnight after the <lb/>murders - while the non-production of Major Sir Francis Vane, his Senior Officer, disabled it <lb/> from learning that on the 1st may (a week after the murders) the accused was promoted to the <lb/> charge of the Defence of Portobello Barracks. His conduct on shooting the lad, Coade, on <lb/> Rathmines Road previous to the three murders, was not introduced, although Coade's father <lb/>immediately lodged information at the Barracks. None of the soldiers who formed the firing <lb/> party was called to speak as to the nature of the accused's commands and demeanour, or explain <lb/> how Mr. Skeffington came to be taken from a locked cell without authority. The added <lb/> tragedy which led to a second squad of soldiers being called out to fire at the prostrate body of <lb/>Mr. Skeffington would not have become known (although proved at the private preliminary <lb/> inquiry) but for the candour of the noble President of the tribunal, Lord Cheylesmore. As for <lb/>the attempt to fasten complicity with the rebellion on Mr. Skeffington by the production of a <lb/>document published previously by Alderman Thomas Kelly (which deceased, as a journalist, <lb/> kept in his house) - it stands in strange contrast with the silence preserved concerning the <lb/> innocence of the other slaughtered men and the Court was not even told who or what they were. <lb/> The admission of this document after Adjutant Morgan, who produced it, had sworn that it was <lb/>not found on Mr. Skeffington, may have been due to inadvertenance, but the cunning of the un- <lb/>truthful endorsement on it by the accused to the effect that it was found on the body, seemed <lb/>to call for observation on the issue of sanity, as corroboration of the fact that Captain Colthurst <lb/> from the date when he knew the murders were discovered, was engaged in the manufacture of <lb/>evidence to palliate his guilt.   I therefore have to ask that in view of the promised Inquiry you will make arrangements <lb/> with the Military Authorities to have in attendance thereat, in addition to the witnesses called on <lb/>behalf of the prosecution at the late Courtmartial, the following persons: - <lb/>1. âThe soldiers under command of Lieutenant Wilson when Mr. Skeffington was marched out <lb/>of his cell into the street to serve as a hostage. <lb/>2. âThe soldiers who composed the first and second firing parties. <lb/>3. âLieutenant Colonel McCammond who was in command of the Royal Irish Rifles. <lb/>4. â Major Sir Francis Vane, 2nd in Command. <lb/>5. âLieutenant Tooley and Lieutenant Gibbon. <lb/>6. âThe officers and soldiers who were sent after the murder to search Mrs. Skeffington's resi- <lb/>dence on two occasions - especially Sergeant Claxton.   Of course, the names, regiment and regimental number of all the proposed witnesses <lb/> should be supplied to me some days before the Inquiry, unless the Government undertake to call <lb/>them for examination.   I should also be furnished the Notes of the preliminary Inquiry which the Courtmartial <lb/> were supplied with. In addition I request that all documents, etc., taken from the person of <lb/> Mr. Skeffington, or seized at his residence, should be returned, and if this is refused that copies <lb/>should be supplied to me.   I should likewise be afforded an opportunity of examining and taking copies of any reports <lb/>or entries dealing with the circumstances attending the arrest or execution of Mr. Skeffington, <lb/> or the searches at his residence.   I shall feel obliged by an intimation of an early decision. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant   HENRY LEMASS.   To,  THE RIGHT HON. H. H. ASQUITH, K.C., M.P.,  Prime Minister,  10 Downing Street, London, S.W.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>