<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1335">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 11 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) concerning the watch James had ordered from Hopkins for Fay and their upcoming marriage. James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1335</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0487">National Health Insurance Commission, Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Irelans</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1335_img_664_1"  type="Letter"  url="66bb8f2d2f582d0a3c4454e792211603.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1335_img_664_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0dbcfe381fbe05542b0fc3aadaabb4f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1335_img_664_1"/>
               for two people to live together day <lb/>in day out without little <lb/>quarrels (I suppose even you and I <lb/>will quarrel sometimes — I know I <lb/>have a rather sullen temper) but <lb/>I think you are both too sweet— <lb/>tempered to be out for very long. With <lb/>God’s blessing we will all live happy <lb/>and contented together and when <lb/>I get out of temper, I hope I will always <lb/>think of the sweet trustfulness and <lb/>confidence so freely shown to me by the <lb/>dear girl who gave herself to me in <lb/>the first flower of her youth and <lb/>beauty. Now that may sound a <lb/>bit high flowing but it is all, my <lb/>darling, true and sincere and <lb/>heartfelt. Glad to hear that <lb/>Christy is doing so well. <lb/>Give my regards to your <lb/>mother, Nano and all. <lb/>I send you a thousand kisses <lb/>and warmest and most <lb/>heartfelt love. <lb/>Yours for ever &amp; ever <lb/>James     NATIONAL HEALTH COMMISSION (IRELAND),  PEMBROKE HOUSE,  UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN.    11th March,1916.   My ever dearest darling,   I was more disgusted and disappointed this <lb/>morning than I can explain when I saw from your letter that <lb/>you had not received the watch. Hopkins people made it up in a <lb/>box in my presence on Thursday and sealed it for dispatch <hi rend="underline">at once</hi><lb/>to the post. They wouldn’t let me take it myself as they assured me <lb/>that it would go off <hi rend="underline">without delay</hi>. This was at 3 o’clock and I <lb/>can’t understand why you should not have got it yesterday morning without <lb/>fail especially as it was registered. I trust however it has turned up <lb/>this morning. I was so anxious <hi rend="underline">yesterday</hi> that there should be no hitch <lb/>that when I got your letter saying you had been invited to Mary Kelly’s <lb/>I called up O’Leary, the manager, on the telephone and questioned him <lb/>closely as to whether the watch had <hi rend="underline">certainly</hi> gone off all right on <lb/>Thursday. I am very much annoyed over it, especially as I wanted to <lb/>give you the pleasure of the surprise in getting it a day sooner than you <lb/>had expected. I hope I may have a note from you in the morning to say <lb/>that it arrived all right. You say that you are anxious to have the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1335_img_664_2"/>
              watch for a reason that I can guess. Well you can understand how anxious <lb/>I am that you should have it for the very same reason, that I love <lb/>my dearest girl above and far beyond anything else in this world. I’m not <lb/>ashamed to say that to you although you seem to be shy of saying the same. <lb/>Still I hope that it is true although you don’t say it. Thanks, love for the <lb/>kisses. You wouldn’t ask “who is good in the holy season to send them”. I know <lb/>very well that my dear sweet girl is always good so that I hope you won’t <lb/>expect me to take too seriously the references to loaded consciences and <lb/>sin and all the rest of it. I imagine the priest must have a job to <lb/>keep from laughing sometimes when he hears your “sins”.  I was very much amused to hear about the rush of marriages <lb/>in Mitchelstown. I don’t imagine our case would have been so bad if <lb/>we had suddenly taken the sweet madness of getting married last week. <lb/>Anyhow the hurry and little difficulties of that sort add to the pleasant <lb/>romance and the dear happiness of carrying off your own little wife <lb/>almost by main force and marrying her out of hand. The more I think <lb/>of it, the more I’m sorry I didn’t do it so there’s no use your trying <lb/>to frighten me by horrible examples from Mitchelstown. I taxed my mother <lb/>with what you told me about Father Moran and she only laughed so I <lb/>don’t think she is inclined to be too downhearted over our marriage. I feel <lb/>quite sure that you and she will get on famously and will grow to like <lb/>each other more the more you see of each other. Of course it’s not always easy  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>