<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0195">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas B. Garvey to Robert Chalmers, 31 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas B. Garvey</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Thomas B. Garvey to Robert Chalmers (1958-1938), the under-secretary for Ireland. The letter is written over a month after the 1916 Easter Rising and concerns the activity of Sinn Fein members in Kerry. The letter describes the astonishment of Loyalists that there has been a military presence in the area yet few arrests. It states that Sinn Fein have been quite active in the area, although not publicly. It goes on to state that Sinn Fein had planned to cut telephone wires and occupy the post office. Garvey also states that Sinn Fein still have guns in the area. The letter goes on the name various Sinn Fein members and their activities. Garvey also states that at the funeral of one member 100 Sinn Fein members marched in a military fashion. Garvey finally states that a local hotel owner William Leslie (b. 1864) will corroborate his statement. Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9274</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/195</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0891">Thomas B. Garvey</persName>
              <date>1916-05-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1894">Bridge Street, Cahersiveen, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0195_img_1335_1"  type="Letter"  url="e4c6cfa7d13acc2cbfb4be12041c3350.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0195_img_1335_2"  type="Letter"  url="7251b936e2cb4af464904b95ae53bcf7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0195_img_1335_3"  type="Letter"  url="c12ad8076c661f8a05b9c6775e12b845.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0195_img_1335_1"/>
              'Very Confidential.'    Bridge St.  Cahirciveen    31/5/16    To the Right Honourable  The Under-Secretary  Dublin Castle   Sir/   The loyal inhabitants of this town are astounded <lb/> why 800 military were sent here on 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> inst. <hi rend="underline">and left</hi><lb/> on 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst. without arresting any Sinn Féin traitors. <lb/> The traitors of this  town  were the most demonstrative in Kerry, <lb/> and this is exemplified by the evidence of Co. Inspector <lb/> Hill before the Commission. Though they did not make <lb/> any open demonstration against recruiting, they did <lb/> everything possible secretly to discourage recruiting, <lb/> and for a considerable time past the Recruiting <lb/> Sergeant has been unable to obtain any recruits.  There was great unrest in this town and neigh- <lb/>bourhood on 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ult. on that night or on the follow- <lb/> ing morning the Sinn Feíners intended to cut all the telegraph <lb/> wires, tear up the railway line, take possession of the <lb/> P. O., and Police Barracks, and if possible blow up the <lb/> Cable Stations at Waterville, Valentia, and Ballinskelligs. <lb/> Knowing the critical state of affairs the District Inspector <lb/> brought a force of military into the town late in the evening <lb/> and their presence had the effect of nipping the <lb/> insurrection in the bud. For his action on that <lb/> occasion he deserves great credit, but his subsequent <lb/> conduct does not redound very much to same. <lb/> The military were withdrawn on evening of 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>ult., <lb/> and on 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst., Mr James Leslie of Cahirciveen, <lb/> publican and agent for Messrs Guinness's porter <lb/> rumoured through the town that none of the Cahirciveen <lb/> Sinn Feiners would be arrested as he had squared the <lb/> matter with District Inspector Hicks, and subsequent <lb/> events have proved this. Mr Leslie is no Sinn Feíner, <lb/> but if arrests had been made, there were threats  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0195_img_1335_2"/>
              <lb/> by the Sinn Feíners that as agent for Messrs <lb/> Guinness he would be boycotted. Mr Leslie is a man <lb/> of influence in the town, though a few years ago he <lb/> was imprisoned under the Bankruptcy Laws for fraud.  Out of 53 rifles the Sinn Feíners had <lb/> parading the streets only 34 were given up to the <lb/> police, the National Volunteers have 2 of them, and 17 <lb/> are unaccounted for. They have also a number of <lb/> Colt automatic Pistols, but none of those have <lb/> been given up. The loyal inhabitants have lost <lb/>all confidence Dist Inspector Hicks and <lb/>Head Constable Howe. It is well-known that the <lb/> latter had a leniency towards the traitors, and <lb/> this is attributed to the fact that his son is <lb/> Manager of the Co-operative Store here, and that <lb/> he is about to retire shortly having about <lb/> 39 years' service. The sooner these officers are <lb/> transferred the better it will be for the peace <lb/> of the district. The following is a list of extreme <lb/> Sinn Feíners here: — <lb/> Capt. James J OShea (Publican &amp; Shoemaker) Main St. Cahirciveen. <lb/> Lieut Jeremiah OReardon (Butcher) Do <lb/> Denis J. O'Connell (Publican &amp; M. C. C.) Do <lb/> John Reidy (Chemist) Do <lb/> Michael M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Carthy (Publican) Newmarket St. Do <lb/> Sergt Major Daniel ODonoghue (Cart Maker) ... Quay St Do <lb/> John Kellegher (Tailor) ... Railway St Do <lb/> Lieut. John Conway (Shoemaker) ... High St Do <lb/> Corporal Patrick Connor (Do) West New St Do <lb/> Michael Walsh (Gaelic League Organiser) Carham Road Do <lb/> Michael Keating (R. D. C.) Coomduff Do   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0195_img_1335_3"/>
              Michael Keating R. D. C. took no part in the parades, but <lb/> he delivered strong Sinn Feín speeches at the meetings <lb/> of the District Council. O'Reardon &amp; Walsh were organising <lb/> in Tralee the week the Germans were expected to land <lb/> arms there; and Donoghue was organizing in Castle- <lb/> island. Since the insurrection Capt. James J OShea <lb/> has named his public-house – 'Liberty Hall.' Most of the <lb/> abovenamed were manoeuvring in the Galtee Mountains <lb/> last Summer. This treasonable organisation was formed <lb/> here in 1913 by a National Teacher named Jeremiah OConnell, <lb/> but he was later on prevented from continuing  his  activities at <lb/> the head of same by the Commissioners.  The Sinn Feín organization here is looked upon as a <lb/> dangerous secret society. It has connection with the A. O. H. <lb/> (Irish American Alliance) and Clann-Na-Gael.; and loyalists <lb/> are puzzled why arrests were made in Tralee, Killarney, <lb/> Dingle, Listowel, and Castleisland, and none in Cahirciveen. <lb/> While arms and ammunition are in the possession of the traitors, <lb/> the lives of loyalists are not safe.. A District Inspector <lb/> and Head Constable who will perform their duties without <lb/> fear or favour should be sent here at once. Four traitors <lb/> named Daly, Clifford, Connell, &amp; Donoghue from this locality, <lb/> some of <sic>whome</sic>, were only a short time in Dublin before the <lb/> rebellion were arrested there and deported to England, and Cornelius <lb/> Keating was drowned in the Motor Car accident at <seg type="unclear">Killorghin</seg><lb/> Those were not half so extreme as some of the Characters <lb/> who are at large here. On the occasion of Cornelius <lb/> Keating's funeral here about 100 Sinn Feíners marched in <lb/> military order to the place of burial.  You can make any use  you  please of this information <lb/> provided my name is not revealed to the District Inspector <lb/> here. Mr W. J. Leslie J. P., Railway Hôtel Cahirciveen will <lb/> corroborate most of this statement. <seg type="closer"> I am, your obedient Servant  T. B. Garvey <lb/> R. D. C. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>