<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5827">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from G.H. Mercer to the Secretary, Department of Recruiting for Ireland, 4 March 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>G.H. Mercer</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from G.H. Mercer, private secretary in the Royal Irish Constabulary (RIC) Office, Dublin Castle to the secretary in the Department of Recruiting for Ireland. The department oversaw the recruitment of Irishmen to the British army to fight in the Great War, or World War I.
The letter encloses a circular regarding the establishment of a school for non-commissioned officers from the RIC in which a course of 6-8 weeks will be provided. Candidates successfully completing the course would, subject to approval, go on to the rank of sergeant.
The letter advises that the inspector general of the RIC has accepted 150 of the 194 applicants for the course.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Erskine Childers Papers, Collection List No 161; Ms. 15,175</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5827</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1285">G.H. Mercer</persName>
              <date>1916-03-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2049">Royal Irish Constabulary Office, Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Secretary, Department of Recruiting for Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5827_img_928_1"  type="Letter"  url="0013be902f5544a2f9258fc9d9408977.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5827_img_928_2"  type="Letter"  url="2a9f1669e0a07fd261707655d1b2b3b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5827_img_928_3"  type="Letter"  url="bfb46533b420090e7b6281566bd690e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5827_img_928_4"  type="Letter"  url="8f5a308778824ce64b7599940375dd65.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5827_img_928_1"/>
             (Copy)   R.I. Constabulary Office, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   4/3/16   Dear Sir,   With reference to our conversation on the telephone <lb/> yesterday I now send you a copy of the circular that was issued <lb/> with regard to the formation of a school of instruction for <lb/> N.C.O's from the R.I.C. in consultation with the Military <lb/> Authorities. The latter subsequently decided to take 150 of <lb/> our men - instead of the 100 referred to in the circular.   In response to the circular, 199 men volunteered, of <lb/> whom 5 subsequently withdrew their names. From the remaining <lb/> 194, the number allotted to the class, viz: 150 have been <lb/> selected by the I.G. and they will join on Monday next.   Yours very truly  <lb/>(signed)  G. H. Mercer,  <lb/>Private Secretary. <lb/>The Secretary, <lb/>Department of Recruiting for Ireland.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5827_img_928_2"/>
             (Copy)   Royal Irish Constabulary Office, Dublin Castle,   22nd. February 1916  <lb/><hi rend="underline">IMMEDIATE</hi> <lb/><hi rend="underline">SCHOOL OF INSTRUCTION FOR NON-COMMISSIONED OFFICERS.</hi>  County Inspector,   A School of Instruction for non-commissioned officers <lb/> in the Army will open at Portobello Barracks, Dublin, on <lb/> or about 2nd. March, and I am glad to be able to inform you <lb/> that the Military Authorities are willing to admit up to <lb/> one hundred men of the Royal Irish Constabulary for a <lb/>course of instruction lasting from 6 to 8 weeks.   The men so admitted would retain their status as members <lb/> of the Force while at the School. At the end of the <lb/> course, or earlier if specially recommended, those who have <lb/> attained the necessary standard would be in enlisted in the <lb/>Army for general service and be posted as Sergeants to <lb/> Irish units, while any who are not considered qualified <lb/> for such rank would return to Constabulary duty.   The men while at the School would be supplied with <lb/> quarters and bedding in Barracks. Rations would be issued <lb/> to them at a cost of approximately 1/3-per day, and it is <lb/> possible that a small charge for Barrack Damages might be <lb/> presented to them.   Please inform your County Force accordingly and submit, <lb/> with the least possible delay, the list of men who desire to <lb/> take advantage of this opportunity of joining the School <lb/> and to enlist in the army as Sergeants if considered qualified. <lb/> The list should give the man's name, registered number, rank, <lb/> age, length of service in the Force, and state whether he is <lb/> married or single. Opposite each name should be given your <lb/> carefully considered opinion and that of the District <lb/> Inspector, as to the fitness of the candidate for non- <lb/>commissioned rank in the Army. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5827_img_928_3"/>
             If more than 100 men volunteer, a selection will be <lb/> made by me of the candidates who are considered most <lb/> suitable.  (Signed)  NEVILLE CHAMBERLAIN.  <lb/>Inspector General.
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5827_img_928_4"/>
             Recruiting <lb/>in <lb/><hi rend="underline">R.I.C.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>