<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1570">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Arthur Munro to Mabel FitzGerald, 24 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Arthur Munro</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from C.A. Munro, governor of Mountjoy prison, to Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947).
This letter was written while Desmond FitzGerald was serving a six month sentence in Mountjoy prison having been convicted under the new Defence of the Realm legislation for making a seditious speech. He later served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Mountjoy, Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.
Munro writes about a proposed visit by Mabel to her husband that will be of &#39;strictly business nature&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1534</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1570</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0487">Charles Arthur Munro</persName>
              <date>1915-11-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1165">Mountjoy Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1402">2 Loretto Villas, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1570_img_1038_1"  type="Letter"  url="6bd65020b931cba38f50455f03df1207.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1570_img_1038_2"  type="Letter"  url="840d06acf893e76619aa3529d26ad75e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1570_img_1038_1"/>
             H.M. Prison,<lb/> Mountjoy.   24th Nov. 15   Dear Madam   With reference to your <lb/> letter of 21st last. I am to inform<lb/> you that when I have looked through <lb/> the M.S.S. left by you I will notify <lb/> you as to when you can see your <lb/> husband. As this visit is of a <lb/> strictly business nature I repeat
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1570_img_1038_2"/>
            that it will not be permissible <lb/> for you to bring your little son on the<lb/> occasion of the interview.   Yours faithfully C.T. Munro   Mrs. Fitzgerald<lb/> 2 Loretto Villas<lb/> Bray 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>