<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5854">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Anne MacDonnell to Lady Clonbrock, 21 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Anne MacDonnell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Anne MacDonnell, honorary secretary of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton). The Irish Women&#39;s Association was set up to provide aid and assistance to Irish regiments and to Irish members of the British army who were being held in prisoner of war camps.
MacDonnell writes about two prisoners of war who are &#39;giving a great deal of trouble&#39;. The men are being held in Bulgaria and are writing &#39;innumerable begging letters&#39;. She also writes about the transfer of items to men serving in Mesopotamia.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No 54; Ms. 35,796</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5854</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1071">Anne MacDonnell</persName>
              <date>1916-09-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0515">Kensington Palace, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5854_img_952_1"  type="Letter"  url="8efecacde876001e85186ef93e58d6ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5854_img_952_2"  type="Letter"  url="7965c6eddc97676d95fd4de678b77a5a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5854_img_952_1"/>
             Correct 426.1.7 <lb/>400 — <lb/>7-17-6   The Irish Women's Association <lb/>(to aid Irish Regiments and Prisoners of War) <lb/>Kensington Palace, <lb/>London W.   September 21st 1916   Dear Lady Clonbrock,   Pte. Hore and French are <lb/> giving a very great deal of trouble. They <lb/>are excellently provided for in every way, but <lb/>they are writing innumerable begging letters. <lb/>We hold quantities of their <sic>acknwoledgments</sic> - <lb/>they are really in no need of further assistance <lb/>whatsoever,   598 Pte. James Macdonald is acknowledging <lb/> his food parcels most profusely and has also <lb/> acknowledged <seg type="del">all</seg>  a  clothing parcels.   I am sorry to say that the begging of our <lb/> men in Bulgaria is assuming alarming proportions, <lb/>so much so that the British officer <lb/> in charge of them has asked us not to send <lb/> them anything that they ask for over and above <lb/> their usual parcels, unless he countersigns <lb/> the application. He has been sent money and <lb/> has fitted every man out with boots. This <lb/>applies to the Prisoners in Philippopolis. <lb/> I will send a pair of boots to Macdonald at once. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5854_img_952_2"/>
            (2)  We are in constant, almost daily communication with the <lb/>R.A.C.D. about the outfit for the men in Bulgaria - so far <lb/>they will not issue it - but we are trying very hard to make them do so.   I wired to Miss Hynes telling her the the 1st Battalion <lb/>in Mesopotamia have written acknowledging the things sent out <lb/> from here by your order. They took a very long time to arrive, <lb/> but they have arrived - which is really very extraordinary as <lb/> we are told on all sides that it is almost impossible for any <lb/>things to arrive with our men in Mesopotamia. However, the <lb/>Rangers have got theirs and it is rather a triumph. I do not <lb/>know whether the triumph applies to us, or to the Military <lb/>Forwarding Officer, or to the Goddess of Chance!   For your <hi rend="underline">private information only</hi> I may tell you that <lb/> the I. W. A. will, we have every reason to believe, stand by itself. <lb/>The powers that be are kind enough to acknowledge that <lb/>we are capable of standing on our own legs.   Mother and I have been away for a fortnight but that is <lb/>not a very long time.   Yours very sincerely,   A. MacDonnell  <lb/>Hon. Secretary
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>