<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5297">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to William Tyrrell Sr., 27 December 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

The present letter is sent from the Lewis Gun School. Willie received a parcel on the 24th and a letter on the 25th. He has accumulated so much kit that it takes two men to carry it. He had goose for Christmas dinner and sampled the soldiers rationed plum pudding which he found satisfactory. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5297</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-12-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Tyrrell Sr.</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5297_img_None_1"  url="84049c1d0c72d20b0a09908db5e204ad.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5297_img_None_2"  url="2680589699826564b34e38a64cafc17f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5297_img_0_1"/>
              27/12/17    My dear Daddy,   Here I am at the Lewis Gun School and<lb/>living in the height of luxury. The weather is still<lb/>cold with deep snow on the grounds and it is again<lb/>snowing. I will be here until 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Jan. so you<lb/>need not change the address on my letters.<lb/>I will be back again before they would be<lb/>here. The cakes were absolutely delicious<lb/>and so was every thing in those three<lb/>splendid parcels which came just the day<lb/>before xmas. Mamy's letter enclosing<lb/>Mr Boohey's card arrived on Xmas day.  There is really not a word of news.<lb/>We had a very quiet and very happy<lb/>Xmas day but unfortunately it snowed<lb/>all day. We were to have a batallion<lb/>dinner but it could not be arranged 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5297_img_0_2"/>
             so we just had our own company messes.<lb/>We procured an excellent goose. The men<lb/>all got splendid dinners too. The ration<lb/>plum pudding was <seg type="del">as</seg> very good. We had<lb/>some of it too.  My kit has now reached such an<lb/>enormous size that it takes two men to<lb/>carry it. I will really have to send a lot<lb/>of stuff home as our allowance is 35 lbs.  I have a quantity of stuff which I do not<lb/>require so i will get it away at the first<lb/>opportunity.  I am not as near C. Davison as I thought<lb/>I would be so I doubt whether I will see him.<lb/>It would mean a train journey and I<lb/>am not sure that I could get away.  I will write you tomorrow when I know<lb/>more about this place. I only got here at 11 last<lb/>night. With very best love to all   Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>