<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1444">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John T. Quinan to Edward O'Farrell, 3 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John T. Quinan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from John T. Quinan, the Estates Commissioner to Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926) the assistant under secretary for Ireland. The letter regards a memorial from Peter Molloy (1868-?) to the Lord Lieutenant, Ivory Guest (1873-1939). It accounts the estate in which Molloy is living being bought by the Estate Commissioners under the Land Act of 1903. It states and enclosure which is attached which is an extract from a report on the estate. It goes on to account that a house provided to another tenant was in worse condition than that of Molloy&#39;s. It ends stating that Molloy should be informed that the resale of his house was carried put by the Estates Commissioners. The attachment accounts Molloy&#39;s income and personal details. It ends accounting that Molloy and his wife, Annie&#39;s 1873-?) current living arrangements are due to choice as she holds a teaching positions.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/4057</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1444</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0224">John T. Quinan</persName>
              <date>1916-03-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0196">Estate Commissioner&#39;s Office, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1444_img_869_1"  type="Letter"  url="79ec764237f837a281af87f282484c2f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1444_img_869_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="f0a577cd22206d174489b461d5b98bd9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1444_img_869_3"  type="Letter"  url="dd3c221d70c6306aff200427332bda06.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1444_img_869_1"/>
              2684/16 <lb/>Estate of The Irish Land Commission, <lb/>formerly Estate of Sir William <hi rend="underline">Mahon, County Galway</hi>, E C 6979  Assistant Under Secretary,   I return Peter Molloy's Memorial to His Excellency <lb/>the Lord Lieutenant with reference to the division of the un- <lb/>tenanted lands on the above Estate which was forwarded by you <lb/>for report.   The Estate was purchased by the Estates Commission- <lb/>ers under Section 6 of the Irish Land Act 1903, and they direct <lb/>me to enclose the accompanying extracts from a Report which <lb/>they have obtained from their Inspector, and to say that the <lb/>house referred to by Mr Molloy was allotted to a tenant on the <lb/>Estate whose house was in a far worse condition than Molloy's <lb/>and that as regards the cess-pools complained of, Commiss- <lb/>ioners are taking steps to have the matter remedied.   I am to suggest, for His Excellency's consideration, <lb/>that Molloy might be informed that the resale of the this Estate <lb/>was carried out by the Estates Commissioners in the exercise of <lb/>the discretion conferred on the them and  H.E. <seg type="unclear">regrets</seg> therefore   that the matter is not one <lb/>in which <seg type="del">His Excellency</seg> he  can interfere.  <seg type="closer"> John T. Quinan:   Estates Commissioners' Officies,  DUBLIN:    3rd March, 1916.  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1444_img_869_2"/>
              ESTATE OF SIR WILLIAM <lb/>COUNTY GALWAY <lb/>RE MEMORIAL OF PETER MOLLOY TO THE LORD <lb/>LIEUTENTANT. <lb/>Extract from the Report of the Estates Commisioners' <lb/>Inspector. <lb/>'''''''''''''''''''''  <hi rend="underline">Mr. Hogan</hi>   Molloy's circumstances are as follows:- <lb/>His holding consists of land as follows:- <lb/>Area 9a Or 32p. <lb/>Purchase Money Â£65. <lb/>Valuation Â£5.15. 0.   Family. <lb/>Self and wife. (Married for years and no <lb/>children. His wife is a first class National <lb/>School Teacher receiving at least Â£70 per <lb/>annum and Molloy himself is a police <lb/>pensioner receiving Â£25 per annum.   Now on the scheme for division of untenanted lands on the <lb/>Estate there are roughly about 100 tenants provided for <lb/>whose valuation range from 15/- to Â£7 and their average <lb/>valuation is Â£3.10.0   Com  p aring the impoverished condition of these tenants with <lb/>that of Molloy enjoying a receipt of Â£100 per year by way <lb/>of income with no family to provide for, and in occupation <lb/>of a holding of greater value than the majority of those <lb/>held by tenants on the estate, I think I was justified in  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1444_img_869_3"/>
              deciding not to recommend Molloy to the Commissioners <lb/>for favourable consideration in the division of lands on <lb/>the Mahon Estate.   Regarding Molloy's complaint about the bad condition of <lb/>his house and its unsanitary condition I would point out <lb/>to the Commissioners that considering Molloy's means and <lb/>the position held by his wife in the district it was a <lb/>matter of choice for Molloy himself whether he continued <lb/>to live under such conditions as he describes.   Further his indifference to the conditions of his premises <lb/>was, in addition to the other vital objections which I <lb/>have already stated, a very substantial reason in addition <lb/>against a favourable recommendation.   In conclusion I wish to state that I never discussed <lb/>Molloy's case with any other tenant or body of tenantry <lb/>and I have no recollection of ever having received a letter <lb/>from him.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  Signed. James C. Tynan   8/2/16  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>