<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1329">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 20 Feb 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) expressing the difficulties he has writing and sending letters. James also refers about work and writing to Mrs Seery.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1329</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-02-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0557">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0622">Togherstown,Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1329_img_648_1"  type="Letter"  url="b5427e8e7086322913444e8a07a3600c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1329_img_648_2"  type="Letter"  url="73474724df9a805057dc80fc9be094c5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1329_img_648_3"  type="Letter"  url="5e1f71615a6cd63da920723bb2c6367f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1329_img_648_1"/>
              as usual here not like <lb/>the country where something <lb/>is always happening. Dublin <lb/>life is much duller I think <lb/>or maybe it is I'm a dull <lb/>dog myself. Well goodbye <lb/>now my dearest love with <lb/>warmest love until I see <lb/>you. <lb/>Your loving <lb/>James    39 Belgrave Square,  Rathmines,  Dublin.   My Darling May,   You won't get this letter <lb/>tomorrow so you will have to live on <lb/>the fat of the letter you get to day (I hope <lb/>you got it by the way) until Tuesday. I ought <lb/>to have written to day in time for post but <lb/>I got lazy after dinner (gluttony I expect) and <lb/>so put off writing until it was too late. <lb/>The post by the way goes very early from here <lb/>now (owing to war economies like everything <lb/>else) — about 4 o'clock so one has to be <lb/>very brisk to get to the post at all on Sundays.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1329_img_648_2"/>
              I expect that's why the letter you posted <lb/>home this day fortnight (how long ago it <lb/>seems) didn't reach in time. The fact it's <lb/>a struggle for me any day to write to you <lb/>during the day at the office as I am constantly <lb/>being interrupted by callers, men coming to <lb/>submit cases for decision &amp;c &amp;c, and if <lb/>I defer it until the rush is over it is too <lb/>late. So now admit I a good little man <lb/>to write so regularly especially as I have always <lb/>been a rotten hand at writing letters. I <lb/>always envy the people who can dash off <lb/>pleasant chatty entertaining letters without <lb/>any apparent trouble. Both Nora and Moll <lb/>are great at that job, so is Baby Finn (my <lb/>cousin) and you're a a very good hand at it yourself too. Whereas in my case after I <lb/>have exhausted the 'taking my pen in hand to write to <lb/>you these few lines hoping you are well' <lb/>and then fall back on the weather I'm <lb/>stumped. I gave your message about the <lb/>prayer book to Nora. She has been running around <lb/>like a clucking hen for the past week or so <lb/>since she lost it. I cleared you character with <lb/>her but I think she's blaming Mrs. Seery now. <lb/>Anyhow she's quite sure it's between you it is, so <lb/>you'd both better bring your own payer books the <lb/>next time you come up. Glad to hear you're <lb/>not losing your religion anyway. The unfortunate <lb/>somebody you refer to is thinking the day will never <lb/>come when you take him in charge. You'll have <lb/>a heavy handful I'm afraid, but not as heavy I <lb/>hope as Rose Duffy. The more you wipe your boots <lb/>on some girls, the more they love you. It's a curious  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1329_img_648_3"/>
              kind of temperament I must say. There ought to be <lb/>a limit to forbearance in such a case as Jim <lb/>Duffy's. Well love, I think the work in the office <lb/>will ease off this week all right and I'll <lb/>probably be able to get a few days off next week. If <lb/>you are going to Mullingar on Saturday I suppose you <lb/>would prefer me to wait until that day. Either <lb/>Friday or Saturday will probably be all the same to <lb/>me. Thanks for tip about Mrs Seery but I hadn't <lb/>forgotten to write to her. Shall do so tomorrow <lb/>and she will have on Monday same time as you <lb/>have this. Moll was in to day for a few hours <lb/>from Kingstown. She is charmed with both the office <lb/>and her lodgings and will I'm sure be very happy. <lb/>I suppose you have hardly had time to hear from Tim <lb/>yet. Give my regards to your mother, Nano and the <lb/>boys. Hope my namesake pulled off the first prize <lb/>at the ploughing for the credit of the family name. As <lb/>usual I have no news at all. Everything goes on  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>