<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5298">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to Robert Tyrrell, 24 December 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

In the present letter, Willie expresses gratitude for his Christmas parcels. He purports that he had the most of all the men. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5298</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-12-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5298_img_None_1"  url="269231457ac1e49db9970dd1867a9a86.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5298_img_None_2"  url="5db404d42db37babd2ada0c2adc10b82.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5298_img_None_3"  url="7721877a284e4984b645b84bec10d91e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5298_img_0_1"/>
              24/12/17    My dear Bobby   Thank you very much indeed<lb/>for the splendid photograph. It is<lb/>very good indeed of you and<lb/>is exactly what I wanted. You<lb/>were great to think of such a thing.  Well this is Xmas eve and I am<lb/>sitting before a huge fire eating toffee<lb/>which came in one of those magnificent<lb/>parvels. I got three large ones last<lb/>night late. One containing apples, one<lb/>some delicious SOS cakes, and the<lb/>other delicious odds and ends. Invited<lb/>Moore to tea to have some cakes and<lb/>he thought they were delicious too.  Really the amount of parcels you<lb/>all sent is enormous and you<lb/>have no idea what a treat they are,<lb/>because we are not near any places<lb/>where we can buy things and of 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5298_img_0_2"/>
             course everything is scarce in<lb/>such weather in the country. It is<lb/>wonderful how very quickly all the<lb/>mails came. The apples were in<lb/>perfect condition and really a<lb/>great treat. Every one has been<lb/>getting parcels but no one got<lb/>half as many as I did and none<lb/>of them nearly so nice. I have<lb/>just sampled the big cake and<lb/>it is just like everything else.<lb/>absolutely <seg type="unclear">lof hole</seg>. I wish I had<lb/>Garrett here to eat a chunk of it.  I hope you are getting some<lb/>shooting though if your weather<lb/>is like ours it will be bad<lb/>for it. There is a thaw on<lb/>tonight but I think it is only<lb/>a temporary one.  I have to keep shifting away 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5298_img_0_3"/>
             from the fire as I am getting<lb/>roasted.  I got a good letter last night<lb/>too from Minnie which she<lb/>said would not arrive until<lb/>long after Xmas.  I cannot think of anything<lb/>else to say so I will shut up<lb/>with very best love to all   Your <seg type="unclear">affie</seg> brother     Willie <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>