<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6684">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Sturge Moore to WB Yeats, 6 November 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Sturge Moore</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Harry Ransom Center, The University of Texas at Austin</repository>
                  <collection>William Butler Yeats Collection; II. Correspondence, 1891-1938, Outgoing. Box 8. Folder: Letters 2: Correspondence with Moore, Thomas Sturge. Moore to Yeats (1 of 2) </collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6684</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0794">Thomas Sturge Moore</persName>
              <date>1923-11-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1622">Steep, Petersfield, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1561">W.B. Yeats</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1944</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6684_img_None_1"  url="phpn259YE.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6684_img_None_2"  url="phpOxWhSc.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6684_img_None_3"  url="phpcdaOLK.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6684_img_0_1"/>
              Hillcroft<lb/>Steep<lb/>Petersfield, Hants    6/11/23    Dear Yeats   I was very pleased to have<lb/>your letter but very sorry learn<lb/>that your eyes are troubling you<lb/>again and hope that they may<lb/>soon recover once more.  I am<lb/>glad you like so much of my<lb/>Judas as you have been able to<lb/>read we have not been able to<lb/>make out quite all the words<lb/>in your letter, I think in many<lb/>ways that shorter poems are<lb/>a better thing to produce than<lb/>long ones quite apart from<lb/>the fact that they have a wider    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6684_img_0_2"/>
             public so few people can give the time<lb/>and patience necessary to become<lb/>really acquainted with a long poem<lb/>and though they perhaps give that to<lb/>only one in 10 or 12 of the short pieces<lb/>of the poet they prefer, he at least becomes<lb/>more definite for them than the author<lb/>of a poem they only tried to read and<lb/>meant to return to but didnt.  I never feel really like writing poetry<lb/>now untill I have worked up a whole<lb/>atmosphere, and so I must be long for<lb/>lack of power to be short.  I enclose a letter from one of the<lb/>demonstrators at the School of<lb/>Medicine of the London University<lb/>These young women who mean to<lb/>be doctors are amazingly devoted<lb/>to poetry and give up half their<lb/>lunch hour once a week to read<lb/>it together.<lb/>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6684_img_0_3"/>
             They are a very sympathetic audience and<lb/>if you could spare time when you are<lb/>in London some time to go and<lb/>read to them or talk to them they<lb/>would be very delighted &amp; count it<lb/>no end of an honour.  They are quite simple and unpretentious<lb/>and far more enthusiastic than critical<lb/>you will see that De la Mare has been<lb/>and I went.  I am glad to hear that Mrs Yeats<lb/>is waking up the Cuala Industries<lb/>and hope you are all well.   Yours ever<lb/>T.S. Moore   P.S. Could you just let me have a P.C.<lb/>to say if there is any chance of your being<lb/>able to accede to their request  and when  so that<lb/>I can let our friend know.       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>