<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1131">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Under Secretary of State for the Home Office to the Under Secretary for Ireland, 10 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from the Under Secretary of State for the Home Office, Sir Edward Troup (1857-1941) to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). The letter encloses a copy of a letter sent from the Home Office to Professor B.J. Collingwood regarding an application he had made to be allowed to transfer a license giving him permission to conduct experiments on living animals in Ireland. It points out that a previous letter to Collingwood had contained incorrect information and was forwarded in error. Notes regarding actions to be taken are handwritten at the bottom of the letter. The enclosed letter informs Collingwood that his license cannot be transferred and that he should procure fresh certificates for Ireland, submit them to the Irish Government and return his old licenses to be cancelled.Sir Edward Troup served as permanent Under Secretary of State from 1908 - 1922. Mathew Nathan had become under-secretary in 1914 under Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). After the Easter Rising 1916, Nathan resigned as under-secretary due to his misjudgement and failure to stop the Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, CSO RP/5596/1916/671/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1131</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-01-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0658">Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1131_img_365_1"  type="Letter"  url="2106516313d1b3b54ca4e40a7413aacb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1131_img_365_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="8d6dbc3b8a2d8723553289796434e41e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1131_img_365_1"/>
              The Under Secretary of State for the Home <lb/> Department presents his compliments to the Under Secretary, <lb/> Dublin Castle, and begs to forward, herewith, the enclosed <lb/> copy of a letter which has been addressed to Professor <lb/> B.J.Collingwood respecting the transfer to Ireland of his <lb/> licence and certificates to perform experiments on living <lb/> animals. The enclosure to the official letter of the 7th <lb/> instant is incorrect, and was forwarded in error.  <seg type="closer">  Whitehall,    10th January 1916  </seg> I Note annex <lb/> II Await any application from <lb/> Prof Collingwood; <lb/> III Resubmit on 1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> March <lb/> E.Work <lb/><hi rend="underline">11-1-16</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1131_img_365_2"/>
                10th January,1916.   Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 30th ultimo, I am <lb/> directed by the Secretary of State to inform you that <lb/> licences and certificates under the Act 39 &amp; 40 Vic. cap.77 <lb/> cannot be transferred from Great Britain to Ireland, and <lb/> that if you desire to perform experiments in Ireland under <lb/> the licence granted to you by the Chief Secretary, you should <lb/> procure fresh certificates and submit them to the <lb/> Irish Government.   Your English licence is accordingly revoked and <lb/> Certificates A1 and E1 disallowed as from the 31st ultimo. <lb/> This will obviate the necessity of your name appearing in <lb/> the Annual Return for England for 1916, and will save you the <lb/> inconvenience of being called upon to furnish any further <lb/> Return of experiments to the Home Office.   I am to request that your licence may be returned to <lb/> this office in order that it may be cancelled.  <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/> Sir, <lb/> Your obedient servant    Professor B.J. Collingwood, M.D.,  Adelaide House,  Earlsfort Terrace,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>