<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5318">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Earls  to J. H. Reynolds, 11 March 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Earls</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Encloses two newspaper notices of Captain Forth&#39;s death. Requests that Reynolds sends notices to academic journals.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5318</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0494">John Earls</persName>
              <date>1919-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1851">Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0847">J. H. Reynolds</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2080">Glyn Malden, 38, Woodfield Road, Cheadle Hulme, Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5318_img_None_1"  url="a80d2c32ea15339fa9492d9d56dca644.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5318_img_0_1"/>
              11th March, 1919    J.H. Reynolds,<lb/>Glyn Malden<lb/>38, Woodfield Road,<lb/>CHEADLE HULME,<lb/>Cheshire.    Dear Sir,   Your letter of the 8th inst. has been duly received.<lb/>I understood from Mr. Vincent Forth that he was sending<lb/>you a copy of a local paper. However, as you did not get it<lb/>I have forwarded you two papers containing notices about Captain<lb/>Forth and his work.  I quite agree with all you say regarding him. I have<lb/>been closely associated with him in his work here for the past<lb/>eight years and during the time he was absent from the Institute<lb/>on military service I acted for him here, as I have also been<lb/>doing since he underwent the surgical operation at the end of<lb/>August last. He often spoke of you and of his associated with<lb/>you in Manchester and I know that he held you in very high esteem.  With regard to the question of perpetuating his memory - <lb/>no steps have yet been taken in this direction. I shall, however,<lb/>be pleased to let you know as soon as anything of this kind has<lb/>been decided. Sir James Henderson, the former Chairman of<lb/>the Library and Technical Instruction Committee, died in  May, 1914 .<lb/>The present Chairman of the Committee is -    Alderman S. T. Mercier, J.P<lb/>Riverside Mills,<lb/>Lagan View Street,<lb/>Belfast   I think that some notice of Captain Forth's death should<lb/>be sent to some of the educational journals as Nature,<lb/>Education, etc. and it occurs to me to suggest that you might<lb/>perhaps undertake to do this. It could not I am sure be in<lb/>better hands. With regard to his work in Belfast, you could<lb/>obtain sufficient information from the articles in the newspapers<lb/>which I have forwarded to you.   I am,    Yours faithfully,    J Earls    Vice-Principal     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>