<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1202">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr William Keary to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 12 October 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W. Keary</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Keary (1881-1958) to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) regarding outstanding bills, and an apology for the problems that he may have caused the Father Provincial.Fr. Thomas V Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/26, IJA/CHPI/21/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1202</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0303">W. Keary</persName>
              <date>1918-10-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1202_img_3884_1"  type="Letter"  url="872aa38b7fa38bd1cf5948b193cb09d7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1202_img_3884_1"/>
                Saturday 12-10-18   Dear Fr. Provincial P.C.   Your letters with enclosures <lb/>arrived yesterday.  I shall do all I can to settle the bills &amp;c and <lb/>shall let you know when I have finished <lb/>with them. I fear however that your Reverence <lb/>must have patience; for we are 'in the blue' at <lb/>present, and shall be going further and further <lb/>away from civilization for some time to come.  Concerning that cheque which Fr. Fitzgibbon <lb/>wrote out in <hi rend="underline">pencil</hi>, I shall write first for <lb/>the pencilled cheque, before sending one in <hi rend="underline">ink</hi>. <lb/>When I have squared everything I shall <lb/>let you know whether I owe you anything, or <lb/>you owe me.  I am sorry you should have been caused all <lb/>this trouble, which, had I not been on leave at <lb/>the time, might have been easily done by me.  If there is any other 'knotty' points which I might <lb/>be of use to you in settling, please let me know. <seg type="closer"> Yours very respectfully in xt.   W. Keary. S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>