<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5592">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Desmond FitzGerald to Mabel FitzGerald, 30 December 1915  </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Desmond FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947) to his wife  Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958).
Desmond FitzGerald had served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.
This letter was written while Desmond was held in Mountjoy. He refers largely to family. friends and daily life, in particular his mother. He also asks for news on colleagues and refers to George Bernard Shaw and Cathal Brugha among others.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1540/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5592</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0538">Desmond FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1915-12-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0259">H. M. Prison, Mountjoy, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5592_img_686_1"  type="Letter"  url="6e027c8d569eda8cb729e2b54907d3d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5592_img_686_2"  type="Letter"  url="a61e302a36066989467c4ab9c4d9c47b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5592_img_686_3"  type="Letter"  url="f596f1c821d056fd864e70e228f5e2cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5592_img_686_4"  type="Letter"  url="6eead4b3fb8d4a24651275e978049876.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5592_img_686_1"/>
              PC. 26/12/15<lb/><lb/>P80/1540(1) <lb/><hi rend="underline"><lb/>Form 21.</hi> In Replying to this Letter, please Address the Envelope as follows:—<lb/>A. D. Number 1817 Name Thos. D. Fitzgerald<lb/>2988/1902 Stage III H. M. Prison, Mountjoy.  The following regulation as to communications, by visit or letter, between<lb/>prisoners and their friends, are notified for the information of their correspondents.  The permission to write and receive letters is given to prisoners for the pur—<lb/>pose of enabling them to keep a connection with their respectable friends and not<lb/>that they may be kept informed of public events.  All letters are read by the Prison Authorities. They must be legibly written<lb/>and not crossed. Any which are of any objectionable tendency, either to or from<lb/>prisoners, or containing slang, or improper expressions, will be suppressed.  Prisoners are permitted to receive and to write a letter at intervals, which<lb/>depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry and good conduct; but<lb/>matters of special importance to a prisoner may be communicated at any time by<lb/>letter (prepaid) to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof if expedient.  In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving and writing a letter may be<lb/>forfeited for a time.  Money, Books, Postage Stamps, Food Tobacco, Clothes, &amp;c., should not be<lb/>sent to prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received at the<lb/>Prison for that purpose.  Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce any<lb/>article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine or imprisonment, and any prisoner<lb/>concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.  Prisoners' friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorised persons, to send<lb/>money, &amp;c., to them privately, under pretence that they can apply it for the benefit<lb/>of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such persons endeavour to<lb/>obtain money for themselves. Any letter containing such an application, received<lb/>by the friends of a prisoner, should be at once forwarded by them to the Governor.  Prisoners are allowed to receive visits from their friends, according to rules,<lb/>at intervals which depend on their stage.  When visits are due to prisoners, notification will be sent to the friends whom<lb/>they desire to visit them.  (6209) Wt.2774—7.10,000.7/15.A.T.&amp; Co., Ltd.(Sch. 139.) 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5592_img_686_2"/>
              , <seg type="unclear">CAM</seg>    I am departing from our arrangement and writing first, as,<lb/>on consideration I find it answers best. I was so thrilled and so delighted<lb/>and so moved to see all my dear ones in the wee room together, that my<lb/>mind was bemused, and I forgot whatever I had to say. Also this letter<lb/>is for all <seg type="del">or</seg> of you, and I want it to reach you while Kate and<lb/>my dear mother are still there. Write to me <seg type="del">me</seg> when they go, let them<lb/>both write, and incorporate their letters. <hi rend="underline">Type</hi> your letter, and <hi rend="underline">all</hi><lb/>letters. You may know how wonderful it was for me to see you all. My dear<lb/>mother whom I hadn't seen for <hi rend="underline">so</hi> long. I was so glad to see her looking<lb/>so well and in such good spirits. I know she will enjoy herself<lb/>in Soretto Villas. It is rather a grief to me to miss their stay there, but if I had<lb/>been free they wouldn't have come, and I am looking forward to our<lb/>trip to them. You know how much that will mean to me. You might warn<lb/>my mother not to be too persistent in singing your praises when she goes<lb/>to see the twins. It may tend to get on Lottie's nerves. My mother might<lb/>like to go to see if there is any trace of the house she lived in as a<lb/>child. I shd. like to see it myself. You asked me if I wanted anything.<lb/>I forgot to say, bootlaces, a card of <seg type="unclear">balshelars</seg> buttons, and a<lb/>couple of studs (back &amp; front) I don't need them immediately, but it<lb/>is well to forestall the want. Also leave in some money for me. It<lb/>will be kept in the <seg type="del">f</seg> office for me. There is always the possibility<lb/>that I might need to send a wire. Or I might be released a few days<lb/>before my time expires as Dyer &amp; Pym were. And if my dear one shouldn't be<lb/>there to meet me, I shall want to have tram fares, and the price of<lb/>champagne &amp; oysters — and a few chocolates. It was a pity about<lb/><hi rend="underline">Miss Leáin</hi> but circumstances were particularly untoward.<lb/>Send her to M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> P. where she may still be useful. I was glad Dwyer<lb/>went to you. I didn't gather whether he stayed the night, and over<lb/>Christmas. Tell me all about <seg type="del">her</seg> his visit when you write. Also a<lb/>full account of all visits. O'Rahilly's, O'Connors — and all the rest of them.<lb/>Also I shall like to hear all about Flora. It is hard luck on Ciss that<lb/>she has her staying with her, but I shall like to hear how she got on<lb/>in Berlin. Is her husband still over there, Is he interned and how<lb/>was she and how is he treated. I am glad you got the charming letter<lb/>The writer was a very particular friend of mine as he probably told you<lb/>write nicely him, and send him the book. Have you heard from G.B. Shaw?<lb/>Or from Lizzie or College Green House at all? Tell Blythe, <hi rend="underline">Seán</hi>, Eimar,<lb/>O'Rahilly, &amp;c that I want their news. Let it be incorporated. Also a full<lb/>account of the Kerry turkey &amp; all Kerry news. I am sorry that T.O'Donnell<lb/>objects to my <seg type="unclear">patronymic</seg>. I hope to make it <seg type="del">to</seg> MacGearailt someday.<lb/>It is a coincidense that Lord F. FitzG. was sent to Bray and Tom<lb/>Huggard to Dingle. Get all London League news from France, and all local<lb/>news from Kate — news of J. Lane. Cissie Gogarty &amp;c, &amp; incorporate<lb/>you will of course convey my homage to M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> Somers — M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> MacCarthy<lb/>&amp;c &amp; incorporate all Bray news. I know the family will enjoy their stay, and<lb/>my absence need  not  worry them <seg type="del">and I</seg> as it won't be long to the great reunion<lb/>at Easter. About the moving — don't forget the bicycle condition attaching<lb/>to it — I suppose you will not want to be too near the centre of the city because<lb/>of the children. Don't undertake to beg a rent as it is a pity to pay out a  Letters must be legibly written 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5592_img_686_3"/>
             December 30<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> 1915  Date  lot of money for that. I am sorry that the brunt of the removal will again fall on you<lb/>though rather glad that you are the one to choose the house. The poor old<lb/>furniture gets an awful amount of knocking about. I hope the removal won't be<lb/>too expensive. I am sorry the family aren't enthusiastic about Piaraisin<lb/>but I am sure they will be before they go. I can't conceive of anything more delight—<lb/>ful &amp; lovable than the wee son. Of course they always loved Dem. How<lb/>thankfuI I am that the darling is spared &amp; is so well, God bless him. I shall be inter—<lb/>ested to get his present, though I doubt if it will satisfy a much felt need<lb/>as did his last present to me. Tell him his daddy thinks of him &amp; prays for him.<lb/>I offered my communions on Xmas &amp; the next day, Sunday, for my dear ones gathered<lb/>in 2 Loretto Villas. I thought my mother Kate &amp; France all looked well. I know you<lb/>will take great care of my dear mother while she is there, you know how<lb/>inexpressably dear she is to me. As I said before it is a grief to me to miss Christmas<lb/>in Bray, but the great reunion is very Thrilling to think about. By the way<lb/>burning or smoking   is a singularly objectionable habit, — the one thing that<lb/>tends to irritate me, as you know. I am sure that France will agree that the<lb/>  under you atones for the   under me at Kilmolin. He will have<lb/>to <seg type="del">be</seg> explain the matter <seg type="del">the</seg> to his friend Crowley. The house where Kate stayed<lb/>in Bray is at the Top of high St. about the begining of the Killarney Road. It is<lb/>called The Cottage, and is shut off from the road. Have you received the papers from<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Moloney. If not, apply to him again and if he then refuses, let me know &amp; I<lb/>will ask for permission to write to him formally authorising him to give all belongings<lb/>both to you and to me, back to you. By the way on the memorable occasion of my<lb/>trip home I heard nothing but the continual crash of china in the kitchen. Was<lb/>anything left unbroken? Warn Eileen &amp; Maggie, that the man in the <seg type="del">next</seg> cell to mine<lb/>is doing 2 months for breaking delph. I gathered from you that M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> O'Shea had<lb/>written to you. Look up all the letters you received extract such items of news as are<lb/>likely to interest me — subject to conditions on page I. Remove all slang and<lb/>impropriety. There are many humourous incidents here wh. I am afraid I shall<lb/>have forgotten <seg type="del">&amp;</seg> before I leave here. <seg type="del">By the way</seg> there is one prisoner here with a<lb/>charming face — very reminiscent of Conroy's. There is another — not a star man<lb/>— whose face is like a caricature of Marroussia's. By the way write to<lb/>Margarita, if you have her last address. You can easily explain delay<lb/>by the deportation. Is there any sign of Miss Allen <seg type="del">  </seg> about? As my mother<lb/>&amp; France were surprised at my unshaven condition, I wonder what they would<lb/>have said had they seen me before I had the clips. I hope Deirdre will perform<lb/>that commission promptly. You see I am so little put about my gaol that I<lb/>can still be worried <seg type="del">the</seg> by other people's troubles. It will be you business<lb/>as boss of cumann na mban to see that MacCabe is looked after. I hope he<lb/>so, <seg type="del">  </seg><lb/><seg type="del">  </seg> I get great satisfaction out of Lecky. I am in Vol 2. By the way, among<lb/>the victorians I have been reading was John Halifax, gentleman. Sentimentalist<lb/><seg type="unclear">but</seg> with much charm, and much more sincerity &amp; real emotion than one<lb/>would expect. I am not reading of of Wilkie Collins. Read Barchester Towers<lb/>if you come across it. It might have been written with the last decade<lb/>— by Henry James — extraordinarily amusing. It and the plum duff<lb/>made a really enjoyable Xmas for me. I really laughed at it. Perhaps<lb/>the close confinement tends to make me more easily amused. I remember<lb/>how the mother abbess of the Poor Clares at Arundel used to be convulsed<lb/>at the most <seg type="unclear">famous</seg> jokes that Kate and I told through the grating.<lb/>By the way have you met Pearse? Remember me to T. MacDonagh if you<lb/>see him. Also incorporate MacCarthy &amp; <seg type="unclear">Pardin</seg> G Ryan, if they<lb/>care to be incorporated. I have now your letter to look forward to,<lb/>then the next visit &amp; so on till I am with you once more. And I can<lb/>dream about the great reunion at Easter. I hope you sent my present<lb/>to Gerald. I hope to get a full account of      on the ruled lines and not crossed. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5592_img_686_4"/>
             Dem's Tree. I hope he has been good at it. What children came?<lb/><seg type="del">gap/></seg><lb/><seg type="del">gap/></seg><lb/>It is hard luck on Plunkett to have us move so soon. See that the<lb/>removal is carried out carefully so as not to injure the paper<lb/>in the rooms that were recently done up. Tell Eileen to say<lb/>the prayers with Dem. He used to know the  ,   m  <lb/> , &amp; the  . She might teach him such others as are<lb/>used by the children in Kerry. Remember me to the Miss<lb/>Griffins when you see them, also Campbells, Geoghegan, Higgins<lb/>Tannam, J. Kenny, Richard in Cleary's (Bacon counter) and all<lb/>others. Have you heard from Austin Stack at all? If you think<lb/>well of it you might write to Lespinasse — His last address<lb/>was, 55, Rue des Abbesses — or to his father's address — There is<lb/>a letter or visiting card <seg type="del">to</seg> somewhere among my papers with<lb/>his address — Mons. Georges Lespinasse. I should like<lb/>my mother and Kate to hear the 'Battle of Stepney'. Did you know<lb/>that the day of the visit I had been in prison as long as Blythe? I hope that<lb/>France has got back safely and unmolested by submarines. I hope he<lb/>enjoyed his trip it is a pity it had to be so short for him. It will<lb/>be very exciting to me to come out to a new house. I think that apart<lb/>from other considerations it is well for you to have the moving<lb/>done while I am still here. The reason will be obvious to you.<lb/>Did you tell my mother M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> Reddin's remark at the picture show. It<lb/><seg type="del">  </seg> is the sort of thing my mother likes to hear. By the way did you<lb/>ever <sic>meett</sic> that Miss O'Connor who was at Rooney's, &amp; who lives next door<lb/>but one to you? I hope you neighbours are nice to my dear one.<lb/>Is M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> H. very sympathetic? I hope Eileen is improving Dem's<lb/>Irish. It really seemed to me to be improved that night I was<lb/>home, even when he was half delirious. I wish I had a map of<lb/>Dublin, so as to have some <seg type="del">of</seg> idea of the various districts in which<lb/>we are to live. Is Deirdre making any sort of hit in her theatrical<lb/>career? Have you been to the theatre or to any <seg type="del">or</seg> concerts or other<lb/>entertainments? Do you remember the 'turn', at the Bray Picture<lb/>house that Eimer &amp; I thought was amusing. I must say that the<lb/>caricature had a great deal more <seg type="del">the</seg> truth in it than I thought at<lb/>the time. I expect you will get this on new year's day. I wish my<lb/>dear ones all a <seg type="unclear">Blovez</seg> mad. That brings   to my mind.<lb/>I wonder how she is getting on poor soul. I dont imagine things are<lb/>very flourishing with her. Have you seen Eilis Ward &amp; Maggie Smith<lb/>there was a mi—ádh on their visit. Do you ever see C. <sic>Brugh</sic>? This page<lb/>is drawing to an end, &amp; I know that when I have finished I shall have so<lb/>much more to say. I shall look forward to a great letter from you.<lb/>And I shall begin to look for it about a week after you get this. Did<lb/>you get 'The Mikolo' from Sean. If he had mislaid it, their is a<lb/>ms copy, not typed, I suppose with Dem's illness you weren't able to<lb/>do much in the way of negotiating those other mss. Did you hear from the<lb/><seg type="unclear">Naturins</seg> at Xmas? I saw Mr Webb here the other day. He is apparently<lb/>Protestant chaplain. He didn't see me, and couldn't have spoken had<lb/>he wanted to. About your next visit, bring Blythe or Sean or Eimar or<lb/>Dolly — after all the third party gets very little say, as you have so<lb/>much to say to me and I to you. Have as good a time as you can. Go to everything<lb/>you can manage. Has there been anything interesting at the theatres? Have<lb/>you heard from P.S.H. I hope his married life runs smoothly. I am<lb/>about to read the 'Egoist'. It will last me over the week and <seg type="unclear">Whendoos Pyris<lb/>Secties Erigma</seg> appear. I wish it luck. And when his new organ? I<lb/>shall hope to appear in that myself. Have you heard any more from Mrs<lb/>Rita FitzGerald? When you are choosing the house, use your own<lb/>judgement, and suit your own taste in the matter. I shall not<lb/> <seg type="unclear">doubt</seg> I shall come out so affectionate and so very unquarrelsome<lb/>that I shall be quite convinced that everything you do and have done<lb/>is perfect. I pity my poor dear having all the packing to do. But it shd. be a<lb/>much simpler matter than the last. Let your letter be very comprehensive.<lb/>Tell my mother that I am very fond of her, and looking forward to the great<lb/>reunion. I look for news from dear Kate incorporated. Tell Dem I am<lb/>going to be a very kind daddy but I hope he will make it easy for me by being<lb/>good. Bless him &amp;  .  Goodbye my darling.   Desmond Fitzgerald          
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>