<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1788">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cecil Harmsworth to Augustine Birrell, 31 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cecil Harmsworth</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Cecil Harmsworth (1869-1948) and addressed Augustine Birrell (1850-1933).
 Birrell was appointed chief secretary in January 1907. In 1916 he resigned as he willingly accepted the political responsibility for the outbreak of the Rising in 1916. 
Harmsworth as well as being a British politician was also the 1st Baron of Harmsworth.
In this letter Hamrworth recommends John Robert O&#39;Connell (1868-1943) for the vacant position of chief crown solicitor. Harmsworth mentions that they studied together as undergraduates at Trinity College Dublin and that everything he knows of him is in his favour.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1788</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1018">Cecil Harmsworth</persName>
              <date>1916-03-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1948</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1788_img_1243_1"  type="Letter"  url="3e2e57db6b6b0aa301bebd717120ce52.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1788_img_1243_2"  type="Letter"  url="d2b9ec8afa44290f3c8b379b307089ac.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1788_img_1243_1"/>
             28, Montagu Square.W.   31<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> March <lb/>1916   My dear M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Birrell   Sir J.R. O'Connell <lb/>tells me that he is a <lb/>candidate for a vacant <lb/>office of Chief Crown <lb/>Solicitor for Ireland. I <lb/>have known Sir JR O'Connell <lb/>since we were undergraduates <lb/>together in Trinity College <lb/>Dublin &amp; everything I know <lb/>of him is in his favour.   I am very reluctant <lb/>to "butt in" in a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1788_img_1243_2"/>
            situation that knowing <lb/>something of the difficulties <lb/>that surround <seg type="unclear">our</seg> Crown <lb/>appointment under a <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> <lb/>government, I can well <lb/>believe to be extremely <lb/>embarrassing, &amp; I discharge <lb/>a moral bound duty <lb/>in testifying so in Sir JR <lb/>O'Connell's <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> qual- <lb/>ifications for the post   Believe me <lb/><seg type="unclear">yours very sincerly</seg>   Celine Harmsworth 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>