<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0528">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas MacDonagh to Alice Furlong, 3 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas MacDonagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Thomas MacDonagh (1878 - 1916) to Alice Furlong (1871 - 1946). MacDonagh writes in order to request Miss Furlong&#39;s permission to print her poetry in his newly published book of studies in Irish and Anglo-Irish literature. MacDonagh also expresses admiration for Furlong&#39;s work and informs her that he will be using the first edition of the poem.Thomas MacDonagh was a poet, playwright and teacher. MacDonagh was a leading member of the Dublin Brigade of the Irish Volunteers and was one of the principle organisers of the Easter Rising. He was also one of the seven signatories of the Proclamation of the Irish Republic. He was executed by firing-squad on 3 May 1916. Alice Furlong was born at Knocklaiquin Lodge, near Rathfarnham, Co. Dublin, one of four daughters of James Walter Furlong, the sports editor of a Dublin newspaper. She was a poet and a writer, and was regarded as an influential contributor to the Irish literary revival. She was also a political activist; she was a founder member and vice-president of the nationalist women&#39;s group Inghinidhe na hÉireann, established in 1900.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br. Allen Collection, IE/AL/1915/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/528</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1464">Thomas MacDonagh</persName>
              <date>1915-11-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0362">29 Oakley Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Furlong</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0528_img_1901_1"  type="Letter"  url="233dec85100138febef19e2b64b23666.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0528_img_1901_2"  type="Letter"  url="343b0ede60cff3fd67e6d343903bc30d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0528_img_1901_3"  type="Letter"  url="053e26c9607d44b6912585473a21b75c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0528_img_1901_1"/>
                29 Oakley Road  Dublin     3.xi.1915   Dear Miss Furlong,   I hope you have <lb/>not quite forgotten me and that <lb/>you will recognise my name. I <lb/>have written and am now publishing <lb/>a book of studies in Irish and <lb/>Anglo Irish Literature, and am at <lb/>present adding to it a citation <lb/>of thirty poems illustration of what <lb/> I call the Irish mode. I <seg type="del">am</seg> was  not <lb/>using any copyright work, and so <lb/>not asking the permission of authors <lb/>to use their work till Mr Joseph a  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0528_img_1901_2"/>
              Plunkett on looking over my proofs <lb/>insisted on my asking you for permission <lb/>to use your <seg type="unclear"><hi rend="underline">Tu'ad</hi></seg>. As all the rest <lb/>of the book is printed <seg type="unclear">corrected</seg><lb/>finished I have printed your <lb/>poem and now ask you to <lb/><seg type="unclear">hurry</seg>. If you cannot give me <lb/> permission to use it I can cut it <lb/> out still. If you give me <seg type="del">the</seg> permission <lb/> I can offer you with my <lb/>thanks nothing better than a copy <lb/>of the book when it is ready   I may say that even before Plunkett <lb/>put me under bonds to do this I <lb/>admired the poem. It was the thirty <lb/> eighth, and last in order of pages of the <lb/>good poems in Gregory's bad anthology <lb/>in my thinking  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0528_img_1901_3"/>
              You will notice that I have inserted <lb/>the 'cloak' of your first version, omitted <lb/>in Gregory's book. I hope you will <lb/>let it stand. You need not <lb/>annotate it. I am writing notes <lb/>at the end of the book.   <seg type="unclear">With many good wishes</seg> <seg type="closer"> Yours,  Thomas MacDonagh </seg> D J O'Donoghue has given me your <lb/> address.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>