<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4182">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin, November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother, Maria Duffin (1854-1954).

Celia Duffin, born in 1888, was one of Adam and Maria Duffin&#39;s nine children. She attended the Cheltenham Ladies College. She served in the Voluntary Aid Detachment (V.A.D.) during the First World War. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#34;Escape Poem&#34; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell &amp; Co. Ltd in 1929. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4182</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0548">England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4182_img_3555_1"  type="Letter"  url="67fdca7bb7d43c3528382f10d3d09b06.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4182_img_3555_2"  type="Letter"  url="99ffa32edcac74f5df1487d61a901b32.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4182_img_3555_3"  type="Letter"  url="03625896236cb64bd2fe6b8b5b4cd88f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4182_img_3555_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Sunday</hi> <lb/>Nov. 1915   Dearest Mamma   Thank you ever so much for the <lb/>handkerchiefs and your nice long letter, the <lb/>handkerchiefs are darling, far too dainty for <lb/>here, the only little bit of dress I sport <lb/>here, as I am seldom out of uniform ex- <lb/>cept on my half days. I have had <lb/>my evening off to-night, and as usual have <lb/>found a good many odds and ends to do, <lb/>washing to count and mending, and have <lb/>just been making myself supper of <lb/>bread and milk, toasted bun and ginger <lb/>biscuits. You must be kept busy <lb/>writing us all letters. I suppose Ruth is in- <lb/>stated at the hostel. I wonder how she <lb/>will get on with the girls. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4182_img_3555_2"/>
             I was sorry not to see Terry before he went, I <lb/>am glad he is going out on the staff, and <lb/>that it is France not the Dardanelles. It is <lb/>really something to be thankful for.   I am going to the <seg type="unclear">Sanelts</seg> on Wednesday <lb/>night, and will spend Thursday there as I <lb/>am having my October day off that day.   I had a card form Mrs. MacLeod, so <lb/>must go to see her some day when I have <lb/>time. I have promised to spend my next <lb/>half day with the <seg type="unclear">Tillinilp</seg> at Sydenham Hill — <lb/>I always seem to have lots of people to go <lb/>to, and only wish I had more time.   I spent last half day with Mrs. Harker, <lb/>Hampstead is much more party town than I <lb/>imagined, I always thought it was was further <lb/>out.. I always go by bus instead of <lb/>train; it takes longer of course, but I like <lb/>seeing about me. One of the girls came a good <lb/>part of the way with me. I find Mrs Calde- <lb/>cott in this house is a cousin of the <lb/>Charleys; she comes from Dundalk—   Mrs Cecil Smith was asking especially <lb/>about you, and wanted to know if you <lb/>looked as young as ever, I thought her a <lb/>good bit changed and rather sad— <lb/>this afternoon I spent, cleaning out the <lb/>doctor's cupboard, arranging all the flowers <lb/>as it was visitors day, sewing a new <lb/>cover for the sterilised water jug, and <lb/>getting teas. The busy time is after <lb/>tea when all the treatment begins, especially <lb/>if it is a concert night, and the men don't <lb/>come back from the Recreation room till <lb/>late. They always have concerts twice or <lb/>thrice a week, arranged by different people. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4182_img_3555_3"/>
             We get a good many who haven't been to the <lb/>front yet, who come to have adenoids or <lb/>tonsils removed as soon as they join the <lb/>army. Some of them are just like schoolboys, <lb/>I am sure one boy we have at present <lb/>isn't more than fifteen. The Australians <lb/>are very breezy people and great talkers, <lb/>and not nearly so disciplined as <lb/>our men, we have had a good many <lb/>of them lately.   I have found some rather nice things in <lb/>the new Irish volume Ruth sent me for <lb/>my birthday, it is better than Padrig <lb/>Gregory's collection. I am going to send <lb/>Emma low regulation collars for her birthday, <lb/>the foreign detachments are now allowed to <lb/>wear them, and I am sure she will <lb/>be thankful for them in the heat.   Best love <lb/>Ever your own   Celia 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>