<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4630">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to John Pentland Mahaffy, 5 November 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

John Pentland Mahaffy (1839-1919) wrote much on the history of Trinity College Dublin and was appointed Vice-Provost in 1913.  He served as Provost of Trinity College Dublin from November 1914 until his death in 1919.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-55</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4630</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0649">Thomas Kirkpatrick </persName>
              <date>1918-11-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Pentland Mahaffy</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1853">Trinity College, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4630_img_3970_1"  type="Letter"  url="5bc0324bc8ab4ae00cbfe9ed55d38a80.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4630_img_3970_2"  type="Letter"  url="fe3b5d955a53f491606bf14202c3ec39.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4630_img_3970_1"/>
             5th November, 1918.///   The Registrar, <lb/>Trinity College, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I am requested by the President and Fellows of the <lb/>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to write to you <lb/>with reference to the King's Professorship of the Institutes <lb/>of Medicine in the School of Physic which has become vacant <lb/>owing to the presumed death of the late Sir William Henry <lb/>Thompson on October 10, 1918.    As you are aware the vacant Professorship must be <lb/>advertised for three months before elections can be held.    The President and Fellows are anxious to know what <lb/>arrangements the Board of Trinity College would wish to <lb/>be made for the discharge of the late Professor's duties <lb/>till the appointment of his successor.   Further, does the Board of Trinit College desire <lb/>that the elections should be held at the earliest possible
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4630_img_3970_2"/>
            date, or that such election should be pestponed for the <lb/>present?   The next meeting of the College will be held on <lb/>on Friday, December 6, and I shall be glad to lay the views <lb/>of the Board before the President and Fellows on that <lb/>date.   Yours faithfully,   <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>