<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1544">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Armstrong to Lady Clonbrock, 23 February, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs Armstrong</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Emma Armstrong to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Lady Clonbrock was a prominent member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, founded in 1915 to provide aid and comfort to Irish prisoners of war.
This letter concerns wounded WW1 soldiers. While they are initially on a high rate of pension, the writer advises that cut are imminent and she is hoping that a local relief fund will give supplementary assistance.
She discusses a number of individuals, describing their injuries (mostly amputees), their current pensions and the likely reductions, their suitability/willingness to work. Some apparently have problems with alcohol and some have overcome these problems. Some may be suitable for farm work and the writer suggests that others might be trained in basket making and re-caning chairs in order to supplement their income but  &#34;it will be difficult to get them to do anything&#34;. She has been told that if these men are brought together in Dublin for training they would be likely to go on a &#39;drinking burst&#39;.
A note on the letter, presumably added by Lady Clonbrock, suggests that the wounded men were from Ballinasloe, Co. Galway.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/10/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1544</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0123">Mrs Armstrong</persName>
              <date>1916-02-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1456">Lavistown House, Kilkenny, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1544_img_1011_1"  type="Letter"  url="0fac89b6153fba30786952b40ff33e87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1544_img_1011_2"  type="Letter"  url="fc167be77a9cfe4319ab0c0161a3d107.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1544_img_1011_3"  type="Letter"  url="2f3075079c2a633ab4666993d05f95cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1544_img_1011_4"  type="Letter"  url="a9f15c58d24c333219fc1d4761f928da.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1544_img_1011_5"  type="Letter"  url="fe3d8aeb00f7d1db21fa3a8e48adef53.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1544_img_1011_6"  type="Letter"  url="72447b655ccca90200f27b6d9f2f176c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1544_img_1011_1"/>
             Lavistown House, <lb/>Kilkenny.   Feb 23<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rd</hi></hi> 1916   Dear Lady Clonbrock   I am so sorry I could not answer <lb/>your letter sooner — about the wounded <lb/>soldiers — as the letter only reached me here <lb/>this morning — For the moment I think <lb/>all the men are well off — as their high <lb/>rate of pensions run for several months <lb/>yet — I am not sure but I imagine <lb/>when the gov<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">t</hi></hi> appoints their Local Committees <lb/>of the <seg type="unclear">had</seg> Relief Fund that they will be able <lb/>to give supplementary help where necessary <lb/>but you would know more of this than I do <lb/> (C Ranger)  <hi rend="underline">Griffin</hi> - has 25/- a week for dry months <lb/>&amp; he reduced to 10/6 — he told me that <lb/>at present until his stump gets harder <lb/> he cannot wear the leg for long at time —
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1544_img_1011_2"/>
            he wants to get employment as a groom but <lb/>I don't know if he would be able of course he <lb/>could not ride but I suppose he could groom <lb/>a horse &amp; wash a trap alright - he used to <lb/>be a hack-car driver — he used to <lb/>drink badly but I believe has been keeping <lb/>quite steady since he came back with his leg <lb/>he has a half blind old mother dependent on <lb/>him — she is a protestant he <seg type="unclear">became</seg> RC some <lb/>years ago —    <hi rend="underline">Burke John — Irish Guards</hi> is also back with <lb/>his leg which he some times  <seg type="del">wears</seg> wears he still <lb/>has 25/- I have never seen him drunk but I <lb/>believe he drinks a great deal of it his <seg type="unclear">req</seg> <lb/> paper had been called in just before I left him <lb/> so I don't know what alteration they are making <lb/>in his case. There was a new 25/- a week book <lb/>at the post office so I suppose he will have it <lb/>for some time yet —  he lives with his Father and Mother  Father is a steady hard working man   <hi rend="underline">Murray</hi> J. C Ranger leg cut off <hi rend="underline">at the hip</hi>
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1544_img_1011_3"/>
            has absolutely <hi rend="underline">no stump</hi> and I think it would <lb/>be quite impossible to give him an artificial <lb/>leg — he is a present drawing 37/6 for himself <lb/>wife &amp; 5 children — — at the end of the year <lb/>from the <seg type="unclear">hine</seg> that was granted to him. He <lb/>is to be reduced to 14/- for himself &amp; wife &amp; 1/3 <lb/> for each child while under age for life — <lb/>I think that  this higher rate  will <seg type="unclear">ruce</seg> for <seg type="unclear">some</seg> months still.   If it were possible to get him &amp; perhaps <lb/>the <seg type="unclear">n</seg> two more - taught to make baskets &amp; <lb/>re-cane chairs they might supplement their <lb/>pensions - but I am afraid it will be <lb/>very difficult to get them to do anything  I asked Colonel Dobbs if we could get them <lb/>taught at <seg type="unclear">GG Luver minut S </seg> if we sent them <lb/>up &amp; he said he thought it would not be <lb/>much good - as when in <seg type="unclear">Codguy</seg> in Dublin <lb/>they generally went on a drunken burst it <lb/>did no good. There is another man
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1544_img_1011_4"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Influence CR.</hi> with a dangling useless <lb/>leg he would not let them amputate (he <lb/>had it wounded in S Africa &amp; then he re-joined <lb/>&amp; it got bad - digging trenches etc - down <lb/>about cork - he has wife &amp; 3 or 4 children at <lb/>first he had 25/- then it was reduced to 16/ - I <lb/>think it is to be reduced more - they are rather <lb/>given to drink - but were better lately - if he <lb/> &amp; Murray would take up basket work - or if <lb/>we could get Burke &amp; he taught some kind <lb/>other work - fitting screws in something of kind <lb/>he might take to it -    Caddwell C Ranger the man with the shattered <lb/> ankle - was taken into King George V <lb/>hospital &amp; was operated on about a month ago <lb/> I saw him in hospital last month - he <lb/> said the doctors said he would be able to <lb/> move his ankle alright - his leg will <lb/> be shorter - but he can wear a thicker boot.
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1544_img_1011_5"/>
            he is a most respectable man - and lives at <lb/>Derrymullen - your side of Ballinasloe Station <lb/>he says he is sure he will be able to do <lb/>farm work allright &amp; stay in - he has <lb/>a brother serving in the Army &amp; one working for <lb/>him <seg type="unclear">Harper</seg> - unless he has joined by this <lb/>He is drawing £1 a week at present will <lb/>go on for 7 or 8 months more I think - <lb/>There is one other man with an artificial <lb/>leg named Wylie a protestant - his father <lb/>is a farmer - he has 25/- for six months <lb/>&amp; be reduced to 10/6 at which he is <seg type="unclear">turin</seg> <lb/>he used to be a drunken <seg type="unclear">man</seg> &amp; was <lb/>dismissed from the Asylum <seg type="del">wheh</seg> where he <lb/>was an attendant - I am sure if he <lb/> chooses he will be <lb/> able to work on the farm <lb/>but I fear he won't if he can help it    John Purvell the man you gave me <lb/>the order for for Newcastle was to go there
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1544_img_1011_6"/>
             1916. March <lb/>Wounded <lb/>Men - <lb/> Ballinasloe   yesterday so I hope he has gone - <lb/>he is being sent by the Co Galway <seg type="unclear">head</seg> <lb/> Health Committee - Mr Orpen referred me <lb/> to them - holding your order over until <lb/>we saw - I must apologise for <lb/>having troubled you for a second order <lb/>&amp; not make use of it - I will be careful <lb/> in the future - I have also discussed <lb/> that if a soldier applies within 3 months <lb/> of discharge there is practically no <lb/> difficulty in getting them sanatorium <lb/> treatment - my husband had been bad <lb/>with rheumatism <seg type="unclear">&amp; I</seg> had bad Sciatica over <lb/>Xmas - so we went to Dublin for electric <lb/> treatment &amp; then we came here for <lb/> a few days &amp; will be home on Saturday <lb/> &amp; I hope to come &amp; call after March 1<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">st</hi></hi> <lb/> (Roscommon Fair ) Believe me    Yours very sincerely   Emma Armstrong 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>