<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3782">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charlotte Shaw to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 22 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charlotte Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charlotte Shaw (1857-1943) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding Louise Bennett and financing an Irish delegate as a representative of Irish women at the International Committee for Permanent Peace. Shaw recalls providing Skeffington with financial assistance to send one or more Irishwomen to the Hague Congress. Seeing the delegates were prevented from going due to government interference Shaw queries whether any of that money remains. Before signing off Shaw requests more information about Louise Bennett and in a postscript informs Skeffington that &#39;The Citizen&#39; is a constant source of satisfaction to her. 

Charlotte Shaw (née Payne-Townshend) was an Irish political activist and wife of playwright George Bernard Shaw (1856-1950). As a member of the Fabian Society Charlotte was a dedicated socialist and advocator of women&#39;s rights.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papaers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,608/8-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3782</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1213">Charlotte Shaw</persName>
              <date>1915-11-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1299">10 Adelphi Terrace, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3782_img_3167_1"  type="Letter"  url="1e1b5a94eaaa2d0acbc30bd0f52ea259.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3782_img_3167_1"/>
             <seg type="del">AYOT ST. LAWRENCE, WELWYN, HERTS. <lb/>STATION. WHEATHAMPSTEAD, G.N.R.2¼ MILES. <lb/>TELGRAMS: BERNARD SHAW, CODICOTE.</seg>   22 Nov. 1915   10 ADELPHI TERRACE.W.C   Dear Miss Skeffington   Miss Louise Bennett has written to me asking me to assist to finance <lb/>an Irish delegate to serve as a representative of Irish Women on the International <lb/>Committee for Permanent Peace.   I am strongly in favor of the movement, &amp; also in favor of <lb/>Ireland being represented.   You may remember that some time ago you wrote to ask me to <lb/>finance one or more Irishwomen going to the Hague Congress — out <lb/>of which this movement has arisen. The delegates were prevented from going <lb/>by Government interference. Now what about the money I subscribed? Is any, <lb/>or all of it; available for this occasion? Or how was it?   Will you tell me about Miss Louise Bennett. Her name is very familiar to me <lb/>as a Suffragist &amp; in other ways. What exactly is she doing? Is she working with <lb/>you on the Citizen?   With best remembrances, &amp; cordial greetngs to you &amp;and your husband <lb/>Sincerely yours   C.F. Shaw   "The Citizen" is a constant source of satisfaction to me! 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>