<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0154">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from 'a loyal subject' to Lord Wimborne, 30 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from an anonymous, loyal subject, to Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, the Lord Wimborne (1873-1939). The writer states that there are hundreds of RIC (Royal Irish Constabulary) pensioners who would be willing to relieve men serving on light posts so that the younger men may do duties elsewhere during the war. He mentions that such pensioners are usually engaged in civil employment as their pensions are inadequate to keep them.Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7684/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/154</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-04-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0050">Belfast, County Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0154_img_1280_1"  type="Letter"  url="f44dcd9bacb35ce02e99b84f2cff5207.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0154_img_1280_1"/>
                Belfast    30th April 1916   To The Lord Lieutenant of Ireland,   May it please your excellency to allow me <lb/>who for obvious reasons must remain anonymous, <lb/>to respectfully bring under your notice the fact <lb/> that there are hundreds <hi rend="underline">of R.I.C. pensioners</hi><lb/>fit and willing to rehire men serving on light <lb/>posts - stores, offices &amp; sundry street duties - <lb/> so as to allow the younger men to do <lb/> duties elsewhere during the war.  Such pensioners are as a rule engaged <lb/> in civil employment, as their pensions are <lb/> utterly inadequate to keep them, more especially <lb/> in these bad times.  Should you consider this matter favourably <lb/>the employers of these men should be asked to <lb/>keep the places of these pensioners open for them, <lb/>otherwise they would be slow to volunteer.  Each man to get the pay of his former Rank <lb/>without reduction of pension. <seg type="closer"> I am your excellency's humble servt. <lb/>A loyalist, <hi rend="underline">Anxious</hi> to help. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>