<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2478">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Elizabeth Dunlap Simpson Fadzen from her aunt and uncle,  M-S Greer, 13 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M-S Greer</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter to Elizabeth Dunlap Simpson Fadzen from her aunt and uncle. Her relatives inform her of the untimely death of a their son, Arthur, who died during the Gallipoli campaign, likely during the first battle of Krithia which took place on the 28th of April 1915. They write of their painful loss and the relief that their other sons, Herbert and Sammie, are safe. Her aunt and uncle close the letter with some family tidings and enclose a photograph. 

A note from the collection owner: &#39;This is a letter that&#39;s been in our family for generations, written from relatives in Ireland to those in America during the early part of 1916.  It is especially touching in the details regarding the war and the family losses suffered during it.  It is a treasured part of our familial genealogical research, as it gives the context of the time so eloquently. The portrait posted with these is of the recipient, Elizabeth Dunlap Simpson Fadzen.&#39;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Fadzen Family Collection, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2478</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1542">M-S Greer</persName>
              <date>1916-03-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1949">Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Dunlap Simpson Fadzen</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1809">Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2478_img_1914_1"  type="Letter"  url="a4ae40823816869820cc6d127ba4d521.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2478_img_1914_2"  type="Letter"  url="b68f7a090d59231a88aee1b2babdfb93.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2478_img_1914_3"  type="Photograph"  url="46ab5689119b36e2f0806ec2ee9eb9b2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2478_img_1914_1"/>
             excuse <lb/>bad writing   159 Donegal Rd <seg type="del">Ble</seg>  Belfast.    March-<seg type="unclear">10</seg>-1916.   Dear Niece.   In answer to your ever welcome <lb/> letter which I received and was glad to hear <lb/> from it that you and husband and family <lb/> was well as it leaves us all at present <lb/> there is not many of us now did you not <lb/> hear about Arthur being killed he was 8 years <lb/> in India He <sic>brough</sic> them home a year <lb/> last January and he got home for 5 days <lb/> and went back to <seg type="del">Elan</seg>  England  to a place called <lb/> Rugby <sic>the</sic> <sic>cept</sic> them there to 16 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  of March and <lb/> <sic>the</sic> landed on the Dardinelles on 25  <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  of <lb/> April and Arthur was killed on 28  <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  of <lb/> April the war office notifying us that it was <lb/> the 14 of May but we found out that it <seg type="del">wa</seg> <lb/> was 28 April. Lizzie Dear it was it was very hard <lb/> You may <sic>gess</sic> what this war means to me <lb/> but I am <sic>thinkfull</sic> that Sammy did <lb/>not go so I have just Sammy and Herbert     Maggie and boys are well the last word I <lb/> got <sic>the</sic> are at home and working away <lb/> <sic>yous</sic> are <sic>allright</sic> that your country is not <lb/> in the war there is very fine young men <lb/> about Belfast now that is not soldiers
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2478_img_1914_2"/>
             2  <lb/>so god knows how many will be left <lb/> there is a good many down as it is     Willie Dunlop is out in France this <seg type="del">m</seg> <lb/> year and a half and is <sic>allright</sic> so far <lb/> so some is lucky.     Dear Lizzie I <sic>though</sic> <lb/> you had forgotten <sic>a bout</sic> me but I <lb/> see you have not so I am sending you <lb/> one of my photo I got taking at Xmas <lb/> I have none of Arthurs now or I would <lb/> send you one I sent Mrs Dunlop one and <lb/> she never answered it so I do not know <lb/> <sic>wheather</sic> she got it or not I must <sic>wright</sic> <lb/> and see and how is Minnie doing and <lb/> are <sic>the</sic> all well I heard about Mr and Mrs <lb/> Coope being dead and that the <sic>chirdren</sic> were <lb/> going to sell the house and go <sic>farder</sic> <lb/> back to where the brother lives it was <lb/> Mrs Ellis told me your Uncle Dave is still <lb/> living with Mrs Dunlop it is a <sic>pitty</sic> <lb/> Tom huper so ill it is very hard on <lb/> him. I suppose you have  good  family round you <lb/> I am sure Willy Simpson is got a big boy     now I think I will close till I hear <lb/> from you    with love from all your <lb/> loving Aunt and <seg type="del">Unlce</seg> Uncle   M - S Greer 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2478_img_1914_3"/>
            <!-- Large photograph in oval frame. There is no indication of this person's identity. maybe it's the picture that the Aunt sent to her Niece ? -->
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>