<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4273">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 8 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/210</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4273</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4273_img_3638_1"  type="Letter"  url="1c4067ae77d11a00c871ae34c3e0f0c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4273_img_3638_2"  type="Letter"  url="604f78165dd8bdb6082a7173c586e56a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4273_img_3638_3"  type="Letter"  url="a34d897c41dc402cf3bf74e3b679b97e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4273_img_3638_1"/>
             8 April   My p r    Very sorry for your heads but glad <lb/> you were doing the sensible thing.    I hope to get a letter by Douglas <lb/> tomorrow. I hope I <seg type="unclear">don't</seg>have to growl at <lb/> any unnecessary things he has persuaded you <lb/> to send back !    There is a lot of work on &amp; I <lb/> to not see how I can propose going away <lb/> &amp; should not like to get a snub <lb/> about it. I hear all leave is to stop
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4273_img_3638_2"/>
            <lb/>from May 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> so it looks pretty hopeless <lb/> in any case.   Very little news. Papers very interesting <lb/> in showing what a hold Carson has on the <lb/> house, &amp; what a grip of essentials but Bonar <lb/> Law's speech rather shows that he is not <lb/> willing to be a party to shutting down the <lb/> present amalgamated Government which <lb/> I am sorry for. Surely all men must <lb/>realize that Squiffy is past work now.   Postman is waiting.   I had a nice walk in the sun
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4273_img_3638_3"/>
            <lb/>but wanted    Your b w  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>