<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1382">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Kilmainham, to the Chief Crown Solicitor, 26 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Kilmainham</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by the Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Kilmainham, to the chief crown solicitor. Sir Henry Arthur Wynne (1867-1943), was appointed to the vacant position of chief crown solicitor following the death of Sir Malachy Kelly (1851-1916,) after his death in March 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3785</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1382</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0263">Administrative Area Officer, Royal Hospital Kilmainham</persName>
              <date>1916-03-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0027">Royal Hospital, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0509">Malachy Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1382_img_747_1"  type="Letter"  url="b17dda6ee17d8315292e11bcec01d822.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1382_img_747_1"/>
              Ref. No. 92. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Subject. Injury to Ptk. Sheehan.</hi>  A.A.O. Ireland,  Royal Hospital,  Dublin.    26th March, 1916.    The Chief Crown Solicitor,  Dublin Castle.   Sir,   In further reference to yours of 16/3/16 with <lb/>regard to Patrick Sheehan, I find that this man is totally <lb/>incapacitated from work with a fractured fibula.   I have instructed the District Purchasing Officer, Cork <lb/>during the period of such incapacity to pay him a sum not <lb/>exceeding 50% of his weekly earnings, such weekly payments <lb/>not to exceed £1.   I have also instructed the D.P.O.S. Cork to have <lb/>this man re-examined periodically with a view to ascertain- <lb/>ing when he will be able to resume work.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully,   GM Colonel, <lb/>Administrative Area Officer.  <lb/>M.R. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>