<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5277">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 4, September, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell is at the front lines but in an area with no trenches, &#34;just a series of posts etc.&#34;. They sleep during the day and wake with the dark. He is excited to receive some new underwear which are on the way. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5277</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-09-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5277_img_None_1"  url="b041b948d47de7729ab2f9f3a877363f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5277_img_None_2"  url="1e7d6c64e36d380896a588d0e22b783b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5277_img_0_1"/>
              4 Sept 1917    My dearest Daddy   Just a line to let you know that<lb/>all is well. I was delighted to get<lb/>a letter from Minnie last night altho'<lb/>she had not much news. I am very<lb/>glad that Mrs Howe was going down<lb/>to see you. I am sure you will all<lb/>like her. Your are having a great<lb/>run of visit(or)s now.  We are like nightingales here - We be<lb/>low and can't move all day but wake<lb/>up as soon as it begins to get dark.<lb/>We have really got out of trench<lb/>warfare here. We have no proper<lb/>trenches at all but just a series<lb/>of posts etc. There are no trenches<lb/>in front of us either and we can<lb/>see for about two miles with glasses.<lb/>I expect the papers and your<lb/>parcel will come up after dark too 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5277_img_0_2"/>
             I am quite excited about my<lb/>new underwear.  Minnie gave<lb/>me a wonderful description of the <lb/>colour.  Anyway I am sure they<lb/>will be A1.  Colour makes no<lb/>odds.  You can quite understand<lb/>the lack of news I am sure so<lb/>I will shut up with best love<lb/>to all from   Yours most affec Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>