<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6660">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard Hazleton to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 14 March 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard Hazleton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter Richard Hazleton discusses Joseph Cyrillus Walsh&#39;s relation to a man named Moloney (possibly William J. Maloney), as well as his views of the Irish political party Sinn Féin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>Walsh, J. C. Papers. Letters: Hazleton, Richard 1918</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6660</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0458">Richard Hazleton</persName>
              <date>1918-03-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1737">Congress Hotel, Chicago, Illinois, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6660_img_None_1"  url="php7csjXh.jpeg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6660_img_None_2"  url="phpVMbVOs.jpeg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6660_img_0_1"/>
              Congress Hotel,    Chicago, Illinois.    14th March, 1918.       My dear J.C:   I have just received your letter of yesterday<lb/>and can only send you a short note in answer to it as I<lb/>have to leave town in a few minutes for an outside en-<lb/>gagement. I am glad you wrote me so fully and frankly.<lb/>I was with you enough in New York to get to understand<lb/>your point of view, which so closely approximates to my<lb/>own in many respects as regards the situation in Ireland<lb/>that I would like to be able to give you my views on<lb/>the issues you raise in your letter.  First, as to Moloney, I beg of you to hold his<lb/>hand if you can. I do not know him well enough<seg type="del">x</seg> to judge<lb/>him, but I have great respect for your judgement, and I<lb/>know that you regard him as valuable. The impression I<lb/>got was one of great ability, with an exaggerated self-<lb/>importance and a taste for intrigue. Forgive this if it<lb/>is wrong. M., I think, loves to dabble in High Politics.<lb/>So would I if I had the time, but I am too busy in the<lb/>humbler details of politics. But I would like to see you<lb/>hold his hand because I believe that the developments in<lb/>the Irish situation will be very rapid now, and it wont be<lb/>long before it will be possible for all of us to come to<lb/>a much clearer perception of where we stand.  The trouble with M. is that he does not see<lb/>that T.P. and I are only in a very minor way at the<lb/>moment dealin<seg type="del">g</seg> with policy. We are here to get money<lb/>without which we need'nt trouble to discuss policy, for if<lb/>we fail there will be only the one policy --- that of our<lb/>opponents. If Moloney thinks that desirable then he has a<lb/>perfect right to go out and attack us, but if not,he<lb/>must really make some allowance for the needs of the<lb/>situation so long as we are doing the effective thing to<lb/>get the money and so long as we dont go wrong on<lb/>fundamentals. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6660_img_0_2"/>
             2.  I gather that M. considers it entirely wrong<lb/>to attack Sinn Fein. But does he confine that limitation<lb/>to this country? Does he think we ought not to <seg type="del">confine</seg><lb/>fight them in Ireland? The reason I am not a Sinn Feiner<lb/>is that so long as there is a chance of saving the<lb/>Constitutional movement I believe it is worth saving. But<lb/>to do that I must fight Sinn Fein. Such support as we<lb/>have been able to get in this country has been as a result<lb/>of the war policy of the Constitutional movement, and I am<lb/>wholly with T.P. in the attitude that it would be fatal<lb/>to do or say anything which would lead people to think that<lb/>our attitude on th<seg type="del">a</seg>t point had undergone any change. I<lb/>think there is room for accomodation as to whether the<lb/>point of accentuation in this country ought to be <seg type="del">xx</seg><lb/>the attack on Sinn Fein or not. I would be perfectly <seg type="del">xxx</seg><lb/>prepared to discuss the wisdom of putting the soft pedal<lb/>on that here, while I see that there can be on relaxation<lb/>of the battle in Ireland. Also I think that Dillon's<lb/>leadership will show a sound way to put the British Gov-<lb/>ernment in the wrong in case of the failure of the Con-<lb/>vention and their failure to take hold of the situation<lb/>in the right way. I am confident he will give us all a<lb/>rallying cry in that event, which can be taken up here<lb/>without conflict with our fundamental position on the<lb/>war. I have the utmost confidence in his soundness of<lb/>judgement, and in the prospect of a bold and de-<lb/>termined lead from him. His arm has been paralised for<lb/>a long time back, but in his new position he will be<lb/>able to give effect to his ideas, particularly as he has<lb/>Devlin with him and the element in tne Party that counts<lb/>for anything. Therefore, in spite of the apparent black-<lb/>ness of the position at the moment, I am fully of hope,<lb/>and feel perfectly certain that this is the very last<lb/>moment that ought to be chosen by any friend of ours<lb/>to make break. I am sure T.P. would agree with all that<lb/>I have said. He has emphasised one side of the position,<lb/>probably to your displeasure as well as Moloney's, but<lb/>I am sure you will agree that he has done it with the sole<lb/>object of furthering the purpose we share in common. I<lb/>expect him back to-morrow, and do not yet know if I<lb/>will accompany him to the West, but I want to keep in<lb/>touch with you.      Yours always sincerely,    <hi rend="underline">Richard Hazleton</hi>   Reprocessing Ireland 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>