<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5268">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 15, April, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>References the Battle of Vimy Ridge. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5268</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-04-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5268_img_None_1"  url="2356117f8895bdeebc487272abd98404.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5268_img_None_2"  url="dafe302f64cc948743257259913b04f7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5268_img_0_1"/>
             14   15 April 1917    My dear Mamy   I have just received Minnies long<lb/>letter of 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> which I was delighted to get. I<lb/>had not got any <seg type="del">fo</seg> since Thursday until<lb/>today. The weather here is alternately<lb/>bad and good. today happens to be<lb/>very wet. There is not much to be<lb/>done today except write letters. We<lb/>were at church at ten and have<lb/>nothing to do for the rest of the day.  I went into a big town yesterday<lb/>afternoon just to look round. Have<lb/>some tea and come back again.  There was a cinema show on Friday<lb/>night but the films were not up to<lb/>much and some bright fellow started<lb/>making a row like animals and in<lb/>a minute every one in the room 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5268_img_0_2"/>
             was trying to imitate animals.  I   The finish was one man imitating<lb/>a pig's last moments. The C.O, who<lb/>was there was highly amused.  There is certainly great war<lb/>news now. Some fools are talking<lb/>about the hum arranging the retreats etc.  <seg type="del">t</seg> it is not a a cass of what he<lb/>will do but a case <seg type="del">who</seg> of what<lb/>he has jolly well got to do or<lb/>be reminded by good sharp steel.  There is no doubt that he is<lb/>being very hard pressed. I see he<lb/>says he retired according to plan from<lb/>Vinny. some plan !!! He did not say<lb/>who made the plan.  I was very sorry to see in the<lb/>casualty list about <seg type="unclear">Four Taving</seg>. I<lb/>saw it the day I got Daddy's<lb/>letter telling of it. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>