<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5395">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Matthew J. Farrell to Father Bernard, 29 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Matthew J. Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Matthew J. Farrell writes to his cousin, Father Bernard, asking him to write a letter in support of his  application to join The Royal Welsh Fusiliers by writing to the Colonel, Major Lawrence. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NLI10561/6/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5395</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1187">Matthew J. Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-01-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Father Bernard</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1782">Grange, Co.Sligo, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5395_img_468_1"  type="Letter"  url="d52a4750aa916704323699e9631acc60.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5395_img_468_2"  type="Letter"  url="8426feb052fb55acf0bc25d44b2f964b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5395_img_468_3"  type="Envelope"  url="5c9fb58632eb8ced3133d685beb602e8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5395_img_468_1"/>
            <!-- note written upside down at top of letter --> address to get Colonel to <lb/>write to - The Commandant, <lb/> Cadet School, <lb/> G.H.Q., B.E.F.   Cadet School <lb/>G.H.Q. <lb/>B.E.Force   29.1.16   Dear Father Bernard   I suppose you have <lb/> already received my last letter. I am working <lb/> very hard here at present, and expect to be <lb/> able to get through all right after 4 or 5 weeks.   We were only going to do 4 weeks <lb/>training first, but they have prolonged the <lb/>course to another two weeks.   Our Instructor (Captain Finch - Cheshire <lb/>Regiment) told us a few days ago if we <lb/> wanted to get any particular Regiment <lb/>to write immediately to Colonel of that Regiment <lb/>and tell him to apply immediately for us <lb/>to above address <hi rend="underline">The Commandant, Cadet School, <lb/> G.H.Q., B.E.F.</hi> For information the Commandant <lb/> is (Major Lawrence - Royal Welsh Fusiliers).   It would also be very advisable <lb/>if he would say a few words in favour <lb/>of me, as they expect great efficiency of late <lb/>from all Cadet Students. This order applies <lb/> principally to all Territorial Regiments. <seg type="del">However</seg>   Is it a Territorial Unit, The <lb/>Tyneside Irish? However it does not
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5395_img_468_2"/>
            matter much <seg type="del">where</seg>whether it is a regular unit <lb/> or not. The latest order is that in order <lb/>to get into any Territorial or special Regiment <lb/> you have to get Colonel of unit to apply <lb/>for you <hi rend="underline">immediately</hi>, in order to fill <lb/> in required forms. If this is not <lb/>done you will be sent to any Regiment <lb/>where there is a vacancy.   So I earnestly hope that you <lb/>will <sic>loose</sic> no time whatever in writing <lb/>immediately to either of these Colonels <lb/><hi rend="underline">Colonel Moore</hi> or <hi rend="underline">Esmonde</hi> or any other <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Colonel</hi> you may know in order to <lb/>apply for me. It does not matter to <lb/>me what Regiment I go to if you <lb/>know the Colonel of it. One thing I <lb/>would like of course to be in some <lb/>Catholic Unit.   Once more I beg to remind you <lb/>of getting this done immediately as <lb/> I trust you will have no difficulty <lb/> whatsoever, judging from your influence.   Trusting you are quite well, and <lb/>wishing you every good wish.   I am Dear Father Bernard <lb/>Your fond Cousin   Matthew J. Farrell  <hi rend="underline">Pte Matthew J. Farrell</hi>, <lb/>No.2 Division
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5395_img_468_3"/>
             Rev.Father Crehan C.C., <lb/>Grange, <lb/>Co.Sligo, <lb/> Ireland 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>