<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1828">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur Joseph Dease to his mother Lady Emily Dease, 18 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur Joseph Dease</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Arthur Dease was born in Celbridge County Kildare in 1871. He was the son of Colonel Sir Gerald Richard Dease (d1903) and Emily Throckmorton (d1929). Gerald and Emily married in 1863. Arthur&#39;s father, had a distinguished career, being amongst other things Chamberlain to various Lord&#39;s Lieutenant of Ireland and also a Director and former Governor of The Bank of Ireland. 

Arthur served as a volunteer ambulance driver in France during WW1 from January 1915 to December 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>www.arthursletters.com</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1828</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1089">Arthur Joseph Dease</persName>
              <date>1916-07-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Emily Dease</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0305">Celbridge, County Kildare, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1965</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1828_img_1283_1"  type="Letter"  url="729cdf9a9a697a7b17bda104a463b75f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1828_img_1283_2"  type="Letter"  url="2fd0785cf410fa82fb7946800e580a46.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1828_img_1283_3"  type="Letter"  url="5ebace5cefc55bd87ffd787cbbd8622a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1828_img_1283_4"  type="Letter"  url="7e886edbfc6a8139f838a924ff1892aa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1828_img_1283_5"  type="Envelope"  url="224baa7b4cd8ab216cc53401831812ee.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1828_img_1283_1"/>
             S.S.a.3   July 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> /16   My Dear Mother,  <seg type="unclear">yrs</seg> of july 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; enclosures, also <lb/> <seg type="unclear">... paper</seg> sent on, all came yesterday morning <lb/> Quite imaginary , I fancy, rumours that no letters <lb/> were being sent to France, like so many other <lb/> rumours, pure imagination, any way as far as concerns <lb/> our people. I don't know about visiting forces, but <lb/> probably their letters go just the same time here on <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Sunday</seg> after 3 <seg type="unclear">like</seg> at my last place. Above also here, <lb/> a small town of some 5000 inhabitants, quite <lb/> pretty spot on the <seg type="unclear">Moselle</seg>. I fancy will be here only <lb/> till next Sunday, but don't know. Fine now &amp; quite <lb/> warm today. I have a nice large room over a jeweller's <lb/> shop &amp; the <seg type="unclear">landlady</seg> brings me up my <seg type="foreign">petit dejeuner</seg> every <lb/> morning, for which &amp; the room I pay 12f50 a week! <lb/> My <seg type="unclear">sharer</seg> &amp; I <seg type="unclear">feed</seg> together at a little cafe in <lb/> the town, the patron &amp; his wife feed at the other end of <lb/> our table at <seg type="foreign">dejeuner</seg> &amp; she waits on us &amp; eats <lb/> between times &amp; he &amp; she get up at intervals to <lb/> attend to various soldier customers who keeps stopping <lb/> in for their wine . All this makes a little change <lb/> from living all together &amp; the <seg type="unclear">many (at times) stresses</seg>, which <lb/> one gets rather tired of. My sharer, a very nice <lb/> steady fellow, was in the army, what a difference army training makes, such a different <seg type="unclear">respectable</seg> <lb/> type to the average sharer with no army training. I
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1828_img_1283_2"/>
            <lb/>was sorry in a way to leave. When we were there I found <lb/> at the hotel, nice people I made friends with &amp; at one <lb/> <seg type="unclear">garage</seg> too, they would not charge my sharer any thing <lb/> for his room! How too funny <seg type="unclear">Josie Corbally</seg> marrying <lb/> Herbert <seg type="unclear">Nimmi</seg> <hi rend="underline">where</hi> did they meet. He came out <lb/> to us last August for 6 months, but just after I left <lb/> Gerard over to go to Paris in <seg type="unclear">Nov</seg> He broke his <lb/> leg tobogganning &amp; was in hospital there for a time <lb/> &amp; then <seg type="unclear">convalesced</seg> home. I lunched with him at <lb/> the <seg type="unclear">North</seg> Club in March &amp; within a day or two <lb/> of <seg type="unclear">Josie</seg> lunching with me at Jules! I wonder if <lb/>they knew one another then. He is not a bad chap <lb/> about 48 rather fussy &amp; I fancy probably £1000 to <lb/> £1200 a year, I say this as a mere guess. He <lb/> told me he intended to live in England in future. <lb/> I think they are quite a well known family in <lb/> N.I., Wales, stations etc. &amp; he has a married sister <lb/> in England. I should say <hi rend="underline">very</hi> Prot. of the <seg type="unclear">Sydney sort</seg> <lb/> I know, but I may be wrong. I confess I can't <lb/> understand Josie marrying him, however it is <lb/> not more curious than many other marriages we <lb/> all know of. Personally I should not care for the <lb/> job of being <seg type="unclear">Mrs Nimmi</seg>, but I'm sure he <lb/> is probably a good, kind hearted soul &amp; after all <lb/> Josie was not just 21 last week! <seg type="unclear">Right</seg> thing for <lb/> her to marry &amp; settle down, probably tired of <lb/> wandering about staying with people &amp; with a, <lb/> I fear, large crop of young widows coming on, <lb/> girls can't be too particular if they want husbands. <lb/> I have written to congratulate both. She is a very good
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1828_img_1283_3"/>
            sort &amp; I hope she is very happy with her Herbert. I wonder <lb/> where they will be married. I imagine any thing R.C. <lb/> will be <hi rend="underline">very</hi> novel to him. I had no idea you <lb/> were 75 on 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July, I never knew any family birthday <lb/> &amp; never did, stupid of me, but being so many <lb/> years away I suppose I forgot them if I ever knew <lb/> them. I'm glad you are going to <seg type="unclear">Thu..</seg> today for <lb/> a bit &amp; I suppose Turbotstown too if they are there. <lb/>Better go later to England so you can stay a month <lb/> at least once you are there, or 6 wks. Coughton for 2 or <lb/> 3 wks, Southend &amp; Aunt M. &amp; no doubt they will meet <lb/> you at Euston. A line from Sean, he has been <lb/> staying with PJ, Alice is or was in Ireland. <lb/> Good news from all fronts this morning. Yes, our <lb/> casualty lists are, I fear many, but it has to be <lb/> if ever the war is to end. You can imagine what <lb/> it has been in this country amongst the millions <lb/> fighting here for nearly 2 years! Trise's letter was <lb/> interesting, her news of Aunt M. was not very <lb/> good. I suppose she may go on for some considerable <lb/> time, on the other hand she may go off fairly <lb/> suddenly. Thanks for Hayes bill. I will send him <lb/> a chq. soon. My world always seems better &amp; happier <lb/> away from home! Yes, I think I have got all your <lb/> letters. Rifle Brigade does sound rather expensive esp. <lb/> for most, poor Maurice &amp; regt. would be nice <lb/> &amp; not so expensive; they go in for being so hard up <lb/> I don't know why so keen on an expensive regt. <lb/> However after war I fancy a lot of that will <lb/> change all referral Rifle Brigade I suppose are killed
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1828_img_1283_4"/>
            I don't suppose such extravagant habits will be <lb/> possible with most <seg type="unclear">formation</seg> &amp; <seg type="unclear">formally</seg> with army <lb/> of the future. I should not suppose there would be <lb/> much difficulty in fitting into Rifle Brigade or any <lb/>other boys now a days.   It is quiet here &amp; one is not bombarded by aeroplanes <lb/> which is an advantage, we had 3 bombardments <lb/> in the three weeks I was at the last place. They <lb/> have taken to bombarding one at night &amp; fly <lb/> quite low, you can hear them very plainly <lb/> but hard to see. Has Mr. de Munck got a job yet. <lb/> I wonder if Augustus did or was able to do any thing <lb/> for him. Yes, I fear it has been a wet june <lb/> in England &amp; Ireland. Here very wet. Probably we <lb/> shall have a lovely Autumn.    I hope Rudolph is all right, they must be always <lb/> anxious about him. Our new army seems to have <lb/> done splendidly, lots of praise in French papers about <lb/> it. The Russian recovery is wonderful.     Josie is sure to take her Rimmi over to Donadea <lb/> &amp; he will be shown to Maud &amp; to   <lb/> perhaps you will see him. Ireland seems very <lb/> unsettled. What <hi rend="underline">are</hi> they going to do with the <lb/> wretched country, why on earth they could <lb/> not leave it alone &amp; never introduce a Home <lb/> Rule Bill. W will become a sort of mild <seg type="unclear">m...</seg> <lb/> I suppose,cheerful!>   <seg type="unclear">Vast love <lb/>.......... son</seg>   <hi rend="underline">Arthur</hi>   One or two nasty <seg type="unclear">f.... of d.........</seg> <lb/> make me rather doubt if <lb/>I shall be able to stay <lb/>winter out here. <lb/><seg type="unclear">.....</seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1828_img_1283_5"/>
             A. J. Dease <lb/>S.S.A.3   <seg type="unclear"> M....A.... 25/7</seg>   Turbotstown <lb/>Coole <lb/>Co Westmeath   I.M.   Lady Dease <lb/><seg type="del">Celbridge</seg> <lb/><hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>   16+16=32   <hi rend="underline">Irelande.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>