<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3271">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Basil Blackwood, 17 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.A.R. Cruise</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-2757</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3271</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1347">W.A.R. Cruise</persName>
              <date>1916-05-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0645">The Hibernian Fire &amp;amp; General Insurance Co, Ltd., 49 Dame Street, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1034">Basil Blackwood</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3271_img_2688_1"  type="Letter"  url="290a102c2ffa457dc1c268c2e29a3f4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3271_img_2688_2"  type="Letter"  url="219a6a86f7733fb81bfa955c9e84a2ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3271_img_2688_1"/>
             TELEPHONE No. 165<lb/>TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS<lb/>FORLA DUBLIN   2757    The Hibernia Fire &amp; General<lb/>Insurance Company, Ltd<lb/>HEAD OFFICES,<lb/>49, Dame Street,<lb/>Dublin.    17th May/1916.   GENERAL MANAGER &amp; SECRETARY<lb/>W.A.R. CRUISE, J.P   Lord Basil Blackwood,<lb/>Private Secretary, to His Excellency the LordLieutenant,    Sir,   I understand that the Government propose, in connection with<lb/>the question of compensation for those who have sustained losses in the<lb/>recent revolt in Dublin, to appoint a committee to advise on the details<lb/>of administration.  I desire to offer my services in any way that they may be<lb/>thought useful in this matter.  I may add that I am General Manager of the Hibernian Fire &amp;<lb/>General Insurance Company, Limited, and I am also a member — the only<lb/>member from Ireland — of the Fire Office s  Committee in London, the<lb/>governing body which deals with all questions relating to the principles,<lb/>terms ,  and interpretation of all Fire Insurance claims.  At the request of the recent meeting of traders affected,<lb/>presided over by Mr W. M. Murphy, I was requested to cross over to London<lb/>and convene a meeting of the Fire Office s  Committee, to discuss the Dublin<lb/>claims, which I accordingly did.  I may also add that in a letter on this subject which I wrote 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3271_img_2688_2"/>
             TELEPHONE No. 165<lb/>TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS<lb/>FORLA DUBLIN   The Hibernia Fire &amp; General<lb/>Insurance Company, Ltd<lb/>HEAD OFFICES,<lb/>49, Dame Street,<lb/>Dublin.   GENERAL MANAGER &amp; SECRETARY<lb/>W.A.R. CRUISE, J.P  <lb/>—2—<lb/>me to give you his name as a reference to my character and position.<lb/>I am crossing to London for the next meeting of the Fire Office<lb/>Committee, at which the Dublin situation will be discussed, and<lb/>if you would think well of giving me an interview for a <sic>fewminutes</sic><lb/>I shall be very pleased to wait on you at your convenience.   Yours very truly,<lb/><!-- signature --> <hi rend="underline">GENERAL MANAGER &amp; SECRETARY</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>