<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0425">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maude Dawson to her cousin Louisa Spinks, 9 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maude Dawson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Maude Dawson (1881 - 1933) was the daughter of Richard Cuming Dawson (1822 - 1886) and Eleanor Dawson (née Waters) (1835 - 1921). Her brother, Richard Cecil (Dick) Dawson (1865 - 1955), was a noted racehorse trainer. Louisa&#39;s father, Dr William Lee Dawson, had emigrated to Australia in 1854. The family corresponded from time to time.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Sharon Brennan Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/425</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1044">Maude Dawson</persName>
              <date>1916-06-09T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1927">Cloghran, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Louisa Spinks</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0743">Whittlesea, Victoria, Australia</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0425_img_1739_1"  type="Letter"  url="7c28ff687026e02c78db271f4f339ba0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0425_img_1739_2"  type="Letter"  url="0c09aca5b138ebb78b4bc728eb9c484e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0425_img_1739_3"  type="Letter"  url="8dbdcaed34acdca486d26a61cd349684.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0425_img_1739_4"  type="Letter"  url="24aba1d21267fe2268edc838a9e7eab9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0425_img_1739_5"  type="Letter"  url="f8611ab46979cbb6108c9eb72d32b96e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0425_img_1739_1"/>
                Cloghran  Co. Dublin    9.6.16   My dear Louisa    You will be glad to hear we have <lb/> had one of your nephews, Ernest, here, we all <lb/> liked him so much &amp; were very sorry indeed <lb/> when he had to return to duty, as we <lb/> did not think he was at all fit; the last <lb/> time we had a letter he seemed to be very <lb/> busy &amp; in much better health, but oh <lb/> the severe weather they had this year <lb/> how they stood it I cant imagine, frost <lb/> &amp; snow nearly every day for weeks at <lb/> a time, he was to have come over to see <lb/> us but have not heard from him for <lb/> some time, the rebellion here might <lb/> have prevented him, as people from <lb/> England were not allowed over &amp;  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0425_img_1739_2"/>
              vice versa, was it not a most unlucky <lb/> thing to have happened Ireland just as <lb/> this time too, see what German money <lb/> &amp; influence can do, it should never <lb/> have been allowed to happen, I am sure <lb/> you were sorry too when you heard, being <lb/> in the Co Dublin we were in the thick <lb/> of it &amp; never knew what might happen <lb/> next, hearing the big guns going all day <lb/> &amp; far into the night, then very early <lb/> morning commencing again, the flare <lb/> of the fires from the city, we imagined <lb/> half Dublin was demolished, Sam <lb/> drove in<seg type="del">to</seg> most days but was never <lb/> allowed in certain parts of the city,  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0425_img_1739_3"/>
              &amp; did not see the ruins of Sackville St <lb/> till the week after the Sinn Feiners <lb/> surrendered, it made us feel very very <lb/> sad when we saw everything, thank <lb/> God they were squashed so quickly, <lb/> if they had kept on for another <lb/> week I dont think many of us would <lb/> be alive to day; the week after Mother <lb/> was very ill our Doctor said it was <lb/> the result of the rebellion as it was <lb/> a nervous attack, she is wonderful <lb/> how she manages to pull through &amp; <lb/> pick up so quickly she is so cheery <lb/> when well, &amp; always busyâ   Freddie <seg type="unclear">Sueyd</seg> whom I told you about a <lb/> nephew, had to have an operation <lb/> for appendicitis, complications ensued  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0425_img_1739_4"/>
              so he has been nearly 3 months in hospital <lb/> poor boy, he is reduced to skin &amp; bone, <lb/> but is now on the way to recovery, we <lb/> expect him here soon, he is engaged <lb/> to a Romanian girl, whom they say <lb/> is very rich, Ernest met her at <seg type="unclear">Clarcecion</seg><lb/> Ollie has not come near as yet I hope <lb/> he is safe &amp; well &amp; that he will surprise <lb/> us one <seg type="unclear">of these days</seg>, we feel very <lb/> proud indeed of our cousins, I always <lb/> told Earnest I felt 2 in. taller when <lb/> he was with me. I hope you &amp; Eileen <lb/> are very well a change will have done <lb/> her good, this is your winter now is <lb/> it not? we have rain here every day <lb/> when it should be nice &amp; warm.   I could not manage the snaps for you  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0425_img_1739_5"/>
              as the last I took someone must have <lb/> opened the kodak so they were all <lb/> spoiled, but shall send you some <lb/> later on when the sisters come home <lb/> for their hols., we have to be very quiet <lb/> now, everyone wears clothes years old, such <lb/> a lot of frumps one sees every where!!! <lb/> I wonder when it  this war  will be decided, human <lb/> life seems to be of no account in these <lb/> days, the losses in this naval engagement <lb/> &amp; now <sic>por</sic> Kitchener  gone  is <sic>apalling</sic>.   I think this is a very dismal letter to <lb/> send so far but one reads &amp; talks war <lb/> all the time here â all send their dear <lb/> love. <seg type="closer"> Yrs ever  Maude. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>