<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3483">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Angela "Witchie" to her uncle, Tomás Mac Curtain, 1 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Angela</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Angela writes to her uncle from the Brigidine Convent in Kilkenny where she was a student. She writes with general news and informs him that both she and the nuns pray for him on a daily basis.
 
Tomás MacCurtain (1884–1920), republican, was born Thomas Curtin in Ballyknockane, Co. Cork, on 20 March 1884. MacCurtain was a founder member of the Cork executive of the Irish Volunteers, and in the time leading up to the 1916 Rising, he travelled the county organising new Volunteer units. MacCurtain was arrested in Cork in May 1916, and sent to Dublin before being deported to Wakefield prison on 30 May. On 10 June he was moved to Frongoch in north Wales and on 11 July to Reading gaol, where he remained until his release in December 1916. He continued to lead the Cork Volunteers despite being imprisoned on other occasions in 1917. On 30 January 1920 he became the first Sinn Féin lord mayor of Cork. On 20 March 1920,  MacCurtain was shot dead in his bedroom a major escalation in the spiral of violence that marked the last year of the war of independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork Public Museum</repository>
                  <collection>T. Mac Curtain Collection, L1966.167 D9.7 </collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3483</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0700">Angela</persName>
              <date>1916-10-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1841">Brigidine Convent, Goresbridge, Kilkenny, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0338">Tomás Mac Curtain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1457">Reading Gaol, Berkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3483_img_2891_1"  type="Letter"  url="84f56493c02bcd4e9ac672e1398c8487.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3483_img_2891_2"  type="Letter"  url="e7a009c9720a51700c3bf2bc62a0e03d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3483_img_2891_3"  type="Letter"  url="d6b8149d5c3c9b279bbdb3c3202f44c3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3483_img_2891_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear"> Brigidine Convent,<lb/>Goresbriidge,<lb/>Co. Kilkenny, </seg><lb/> 1st Octobber 1916   [Questinable reading.]<lb/> Oct 5/1916    My dearest uncle Tom,  <lb/><lb/>Many thanks for your lovely<lb/>letter. It was a real joy for me. I haven’t<lb/>heard from home since I came back.  Siobhan is very well. You may be sure<lb/>this is the best place for her, as she is so<lb/>wild. She encloses a letter and a tooth<lb/>which she pulled out a few days ago.  Mother General will be here on Tuesday<lb/>night and on Wednesday will be cele-<lb/>brated the Diamond jubilee of Mother<lb/>Agnes, we expect to have a delightful day.  You didn’t tell me how you were.<lb/>I trust you are keeping quite well. I<lb/>think of you very often and I pray<lb/>for you every morning at Holy Mass<lb/>and after Holy Communion. You will<lb/>have a special share today. The nuns<lb/>all pray for you every day. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3483_img_2891_2"/>
             You shall be glad to know I have<lb/>been promoted to a higher class this<lb/>year. I am in sub junior grade. The<lb/>programme is very stiff, but I hope to<lb/>(hope) be able for it by June exams. I have<lb/>not room for the box, but shall enclose<lb/>the tooth in paper.  I shall write to you soon again.  Best love from all the nuns, and also<lb/>from myself.   I remain dear uncle,<lb/>your loving niece,<lb/>Angela.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3483_img_2891_3"/>
             Dear Mr Curtin<lb/>There will<lb/>bring joy to<lb/>your heart<lb/><seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> is getting<lb/>ever so good<lb/>Very sincerely your<lb/>M. Kevin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>