<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3140">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to her mother, November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Olive to her mother, telling her about Celia, her sister who was suspected of having mumps and is in quarantine. She then informs her mother that it is only a flu and that she will be back on duty in a few days. Celia&#39;s address is 5 Eastfield Gardens, Landsworth, whcih is not an Irish address</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>D2109/9/4/B/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3140</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0772">2 Tablot Square, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3140_img_2559_1"  type="Letter"  url="7891fbd89fec4c5fac36b48e7b3ec033.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3140_img_2559_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/B   2 Tablot Square    Wed:Nov 1915    Dearest Mamma   Just a line to tell you that Celia<lb/>has influenza. She worried she could not<lb/>smell me yesterday. This morning a note<lb/>came saying she had mumps, &amp;<lb/>was summoned to quarantine. I have just been<lb/>telephoning the hospital &amp; a nice person<lb/>came and said it was the <sic>“flue”</sic> and she was getting<lb/>on well &amp; would be back on duty in a<lb/>few days! I’ve not gone to see her because<lb/>of this reason. I thought I ought not to<lb/>chance catching it off her. I have just<lb/>written to Celia, telling her to let me know<lb/>if she wants anything. And I will send her<lb/>some flowers and fruit. Her address is<lb/>5 Eastfield Gardens, Landsworth.  l am so relieved it is not mumps,<lb/>just off to see Iris &amp; then off to<lb/>Eastmine.   Your loving,<lb/>Olive  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>