<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3962">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Staines to Alfred Byrne, 11 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Staines</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Michael Staines, on the behalf of Irish prisoners in Frongoch, to Alfred Byrne concernin the living conditions of Irish prisoners interned in Frongoch. According to the letter the living conditions in Frongoch are not suitable for human habitation and are causing health problems for some of the men.

Frongoch Internment Camp in Wales was a makeshift prison used for the internment of approximately 1,800 Irishmen in the wake of the Easter Rising, 1916. It was to become known as the &#39;University of Revolution&#39; due to the influential effect it had on its inmates.

Michael Staines (1885 - 1955) was a member of the Irish Republican Brotherhood, Garda commissioner and senator. During the Rising he served as Quartermaster in the GPO for which he was detained in Frongoch.  He remained active during the War of Independence and continued in politics up until the 1940s.

 Alfred Byrne (1882-1956) was first elected an MP in the 1915 by-election as a nationalist candidate for the Irish Parliamentary Party. Although opposed to the Easter Rising, he spent 1916 lobbying on behalf of the interned prisoners. Before the Rising he was also a vociferous anti-conscription campaigner. He would later serve as a TD in Dáil Éireann.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Art Ó Briain Papers, Collection List No. 150; Ms 8429/19-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3962</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0758">Michael Staines</persName>
              <date>1916-10-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1405">Alfred Byrne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0077">House of Commons, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1955</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3962_img_3337_1"  type="Letter"  url="864c548a6a839282fca8428642ba1067.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3962_img_3337_2"  type="Letter"  url="aea133a7e8a1161693305424bb794fed.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3962_img_3337_1"/>
             Copy.  <hi rend="underline">B.C.B. 12/10/16.</hi>   26th Aug. <lb/> 11th Oct. 1916.   To Alfred Byrne M.P.,   House of Commons.    A chara,   We, the undersigned, being the duly elected Camp Leaders<lb/>are desirous of drawing your attention to several grave complaints<lb/>concerning the conditions of our internment here.  As doubtless you are aware the Irish prisoners are housed<lb/>here in grain lofts which were never intended for human habitation,<lb/>some of them not even possessing windows, being lighted and ventil—<lb/>ated only by a few skylights. According to Government measurement<lb/>the grain lofts at present in occupation are supposed to accom m odate<lb/>185, 200, 300, and 60 prisoners respectively but we feel sure<lb/>that all impartial persons having any knowledge of hygiene or<lb/>sanitation will agree with us that they are really unfit for<lb/>human habitation, and their injurious offensiveness in this respect<lb/>is considerably aggravated by the fact that two lavatories are<lb/>established inside the grain lofts. Men arise in the morning with<lb/>what is well known to us as that tired Frongoch feeling; and the<lb/>debilitating effect of the sleeping in these grain lofts have been<lb/>established beyond all doubt by the number of men who have fainted<lb/>on the early morning parade. There are quite a number of prisoners<lb/>suffering from lung trouble sleeping amidst the other prisoners<lb/>and when these prisoners have been sent sick in the ordinary course<lb/>of procedure they have been certified as alright; but when these<lb/>men are brought specially before the doctor by the Camp Leader he<lb/>admits on re-examination that these men are suffering from lung<lb/>trouble. It is absolutely iniquitous that these unfortunate<lb/>prisoners should be compelled to live in such grain lofts amidst<lb/>hundreds of other men.  On the 26th August last an application was made by the   Item No 1 A look for B  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3962_img_3337_2"/>
             Camp Leader for a transference of the whole body of prisoners to<lb/>what is known as the North Camp (wooden huts) on the grounds that<lb/>it was more healthy and comfortable than the old distillery<lb/>buildings which constitute the South Camp; this application was<lb/>brutally ignored. Another application for a transfer was made<lb/>on 11th October but the Commandant stated that he could not move<lb/>us without an Order from Home Office.  We should like to know if this refusal to transfer us<lb/>arose from a desire on the part of the authorities to ruin the<lb/>men's constitution by keeping them in the unhygenic and insanitary<lb/>surroundings of the South Camp.   Signed (5)   <lb/>P.S. It is rumoured this morning (11th inst.) that this<lb/>transfer to the North Camp is about to be granted to us. We<lb/>should like very much to know the reason why it should not be<lb/>granted to us on the 26th August instead of leaving it to this<lb/>late hour of the day when many of the men's health has already<lb/>become affected.  We are enclosing a copy of a letter to Mr. Ginnell which<lb/>was posted to him on the 10th inst. and we should be very glad if<lb/>you would deal with it, as no doubt, Mr Ginnell would have dealt<lb/>with it had he been at liberty.   M.S. <lb/> ?Michael Staines  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>