<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1106">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Sheehy Skeffington to Margaret McCoubrey, 10 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Sheehy Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878-1916), journalist, was a prominent feminist, activist and co-founder of the Irish Women&#39;s Franchise league in 1908. In 1912, he and his wife, Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), founded the suffragist newspaper The Irish Citizen. A staunch pacifist and nationalist, Sheehy Skeffington opposed Irish involvement in the Great War. During the Easter Rising, he attempted to organise a civilian defence force to prevent looting and saved the life of a British officer under fire. Arrested on the evening of Tuesday 25 April 1916, Sheehy Skeffington and two other civilians were shot by firing squad on the morning of Wednesday 26 April.&#39;Margaret McCoubrey (1880-1956) was a suffragette, pacifist and Labour activist. She was committed to helping women, children and the working class with local, national and international causes.&#39;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47;, Ms 33,612/18-34</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1106</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1551">Francis Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-01-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0720">11 Grosvenor Place, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0264">Margaret McCoubrey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1106_img_3326_1"  type="Letter"  url="9112914c4bfe3cae312a50a3307bed61.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1106_img_3326_1"/>
              Private.    11 Grosvenor Place,  Rathmines, Dublin    10—I.—16.   Dear Mrs. McCoubrey,   In September, 1914, I raised a bank loan of Â£100 to meet part of <lb/>the debt on the IRISH CITIZEN. This loan was guaranteed by three <lb/>good signatures in addition to my own. I have since met the inter- <lb/>est, but have been unable to reduce the principal. Now one of the <lb/>guarantors wishes to withdraw her name, because she <sic>supperss</sic> conscrip- <lb/>tion and objects to our opposition to it. The other two guarantors <lb/>are both perfectly good securities for the amount; but in these days <lb/> of financial <sic>stringenenyy</sic> the bank will require a third name to replace <lb/> the one which is withdrawn.  —My chief anxiety at the moment is to find someone to undertake <lb/>this responsibility. As I know you are intimate with Miss Lindsay <lb/>I write to ask you if there would be any chance of <hi rend="underline">her</hi> agreeing to <lb/>do so? I am not asking you to <sic>appraoch</sic> her yourself on the matter; <lb/>but simply asking your opinion as to whether you think it would be <lb/>advisable to approach her, and, if so, as to the best means of doing <lb/>so. I know I can re l <seg type="del">p</seg>y on your <sic>freindship</sic> and discretion in the mat- <lb/>ter.  With best wishes for the New Year, <sic>andcongratulations</sic> on keep- <lb/>ing the flag flying in the North in the face of so many difficulties <seg type="closer"> F.S.Skeffington </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>