<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0795">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 12 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender instructs Lillian on how much she may reveal to a friend about his position and responsibilities in the war office. He tells her of a recent visit by the King to the office, but says that he kept in the background to avoid discussion of his own &#39;lurid past&#39;.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/384</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/795</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0795_img_2336_1"  type="NULL"  url="9d67af1032eff98e29de8693637bb55c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0795_img_2336_2"  type="NULL"  url="95c36ad3ce6d0820a7b25ae90abd759c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0795_img_2336_3"  type="NULL"  url="9d67af1032eff98e29de8693637bb55c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0795_img_2336_1"/>
                12 Aug   My pr   Am waiting for Gen Butler so can begin a <lb/>letter, tho' I badly want to get back to my own <lb/>office. You have certainly done wonders in winning <lb/>Mrs Blacker so completely. No, Mulholland is by no <lb/>means Dunleath's <sic>sons</sic>, but rather a bounder, with <lb/>whom I had trouble in old YCV days tho' we <lb/>more or less made things up later.  He was Col Chichester's adjutant!  I forgot whether <lb/>Haye was in the 37 or the 38<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. The <hi rend="underline">former</hi> did well <lb/>I believe. No don't give details of my work, especially <lb/>in view of future feelings except to say that I am <lb/>employed on  new  confidential work of an important charac- <lb/>ter of which you have not got details. This is indeed the <lb/>case now as I do not like to write further.  I have nearly daily interviews <lb/>with the CGS.   The King came round today but the bw kept <lb/>discretely in the background, which you will agree was indi- <lb/>cated under the circumstances, I think. I do not know <lb/>if the King would have minded but others might if he <lb/>asked awkward questions about one's lurid past. He  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0795_img_2336_2"/>
              looked very much better again &amp; is said to be cheered <lb/>up by the news. <seg type="unclear">Wigram</seg> came to lunch looking <lb/>pale I thought. He must have had an inkling that he <lb/>knew my face but was not quite sure of it, so drew <lb/>a <seg type="unclear">bow</seg> at a venture and asked if any one knew where <lb/>the Ulster Division was stationed. When I replied he <lb/>must have known he had drawn a winner &amp; said <lb/>something about seeing Sir George. I so so well understand <lb/>the feelings of any one whose husband is in the firing <lb/>line towards those whose lines lie back here. You <lb/>would feel it too old thing this' no rabbit's claws would <lb/>show themselves. I suppose rabbits have claws to burrow <lb/>with but think the pr never had any or perhaps has <lb/>lost them since she has a bw to burrow for her, tho' <lb/>I now recollect that the pr has had to burrow out <lb/>most of their homes poor thing. â I had written thing<hi rend="underline">s</hi><lb/>in the plural by a horrible mistake! â Its too hot to <lb/>walk now so I must return to my office to <seg type="unclear">grind</seg> if <lb/>I am not to stay in all day. BW did not have such a <lb/>bad time as you think old thing. He used to <seg type="unclear">fret</seg> but it was largely continued at top of first page   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0795_img_2336_3"/>
               At top top of the page  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>