<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3602">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alfreda Baker to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 14 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alfreda Baker</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Alfreda Baker (1897-1984)  to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) to extend her condolences for the murder of Francis Sheehy Skeffington. Although Hanna&#39;s full forename is &#34;Johanna,&#34; she referred to herself as &#34;Hanna&#34; and it appears that Alfreda simply abbreviated the name to &#34;Joan&#34; instead. 

Alfreda Helen Baker was a consulting surgeon who graduated from Queen&#39;s University Belfast.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946)  suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,605/1-35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3602</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0299">Alfreda Baker</persName>
              <date>1916-05-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1448">Trevena, Knock, Co. Mayo, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1984</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3602_img_3001_1"  type="Letter"  url="21f09d17c383153d9d23168a8cf4f7ea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3602_img_3001_2"  type="Letter"  url="dc3b4426a088bbe1edb357fa5d9a1aec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3602_img_3001_3"  type="Letter"  url="5d86d0ef39e8503b4f52e624c0e4dba2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3602_img_3001_4"  type="Letter"  url="013a211681899e41eee59a6f06874ebc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3602_img_3001_1"/>
             Trevena<lb/>Knock   May 14 : 16    Joan dear   A wee note to tell you<lb/>how very, very much you are in<lb/>my thoughts. I have been ill<lb/>since Friday, a sort of bronchial<lb/>attack, but faint attacks<lb/>bothered me last night, and<lb/>so I have stayed in bed all<lb/>day<seg type="del">s</seg>, until 8 o'clock, and am<lb/>now resting in an armchair.   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3602_img_3001_2"/>
             My dear, I have seen your<lb/>letter to the Press — oh! <hi rend="underline">what</hi><lb/>suffering you have been through.<lb/>I am most anxious to know how<lb/>you and little Owen are, and<lb/>where you are. Before I wrote<lb/>to you my first letter — this is<lb/>my third, I mention it in case<lb/>they should not have reached<lb/>you — I had written to my friend<lb/>Miss Garrett, of Norfolk College,<lb/>and I heard on Friday from<lb/>her, that she had been past your<lb/>house, not liking to introude on<lb/>you, yet anxious — and that<lb/>the lower window panes were 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3602_img_3001_3"/>
             out, &amp; boarded up in the spaces, <lb/>but she did not know why.   If you are living at home, <lb/>have you a maid, now?   Your whole account is too <lb/>awful. I can't really think <lb/>it all out, you have indeed had <lb/><seg type="unclear">where</seg> more than one human's <lb/>share. What work lies before <lb/>you, I wonder?   I have written to Mrs Tickell <lb/>for news of you, but have not <lb/>heard yet. I am a bit tor— <lb/>mented by the thought that you <lb/>may not get letters.   Can you read? and what about <lb/>sleep? are the nights bad? 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3602_img_3001_4"/>
             Fond love, dear <lb/>from yours affectionately <lb/>Alfreda 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>