<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6386">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Victoria Mary Tyrrell 25, July, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell is experiencing rain at the from and describes the sound of artillery fire as &#34;artificial&#34; lightening. This letter also discusses matters at home.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6386</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-07-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Victoria Mary Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6386_img_None_1"  url="6fb781c242597a5b4c72dc2abfe0621a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6386_img_None_2"  url="581c2161cde5f57bf6d375da8633c443.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6386_img_None_3"  url="86926d84663cf993d85f749f8727e449.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6386_img_0_1"/>
              25 July 1917    My dear Minnie   No time to write in french today and <lb/>besides it would be very difficult as<lb/>there are lots of fellows round all<lb/>talking to me at the same time.  Well<lb/>by the time you get this you and<lb/>Bobby will be home and I am sure<lb/>greatly delighted at it.  We moved yesterday night back about<lb/>10 miles and are again in tents.  We<lb/>had a distinctly lively time in the last<lb/>place as a lot of queer things used to<lb/>drop near and make a noise when<lb/>they dropped too.  I wonder what they<lb/>could have been.  We were very<lb/>lucky as none actually came into the <lb/>camp.  We were out all night on<lb/>working parties.  Today it is raining very heavilIy<lb/>worse luck.  I hope that it will not<lb/>continue but it has all the appearance<lb/>of it.  We can hear two sorts of 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6386_img_0_2"/>
             thunder, real and artificial.  The people in this country are not<lb/>nearly so friendly as over the border<lb/>They never want to give us<lb/>anything or help in any way. They<lb/>sometimes take the handle off the<lb/>pumps but of course we soon<lb/>stop that. However we get on A1<lb/>and enjoy ourselves quite well.  Yesterday the dust was awful<lb/>when we were marching. Today it<lb/>is mud. I hope the weather is<lb/>not going to break now after<lb/>all the fine weather we had.  We have not had any bad rain<lb/>since early April now. At a good<lb/>hour be it spoken!  The books in the last parcel<lb/>were A1 and most useful as you<lb/>see we just read all day when not<lb/>asleep.  When is Mr Bookey coming down<lb/>to see you. It will be great if you<lb/>get a  <seg type="unclear"></seg>  clown also 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6386_img_0_3"/>
             I suppose she is nice and young too<lb/>isnt it a pity I am not there?  I think Mrs Hone must be at the<lb/>Curragh by now as she said the<lb/>middle of July. Write and ask her<lb/>you know her permanent address<lb/>Carrinhaunes House, Carrinhaunes Co<lb/>Dublin. I have been thinking about it<lb/>and really it would be easier for<lb/>her to get down from Dublin as it would<lb/>be a very long drive. She was only<lb/>to stay at Curragh for 6 weeks. I am<lb/>writing to her today.  I suppose you will be a regular old<lb/>woman now and put up your<lb/>bunch of tow in a knot since you<lb/>have left school.  No news but will write soon<lb/>again but not every day as I have<lb/>nothing to write about.   With very best love to all from<lb/>Your most affec brother<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>