<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5527">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Monteith to Roger Casement, 2 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Monteith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Robert Monteith (1880-1956) to Roger Casement (1864-1916) from Limberg, where there was a prisoner of war camp holding a large number of Irish POWs. Moneith was the Commander of the Irish Brigade, appointed by Casement. 
Casement spent eighteen months in total in Germany attempting to secure German support for an uprising in Ireland and raising an ultimately unsuccessful brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps. By April 1916, he had become become disillusioned with German assistance and marginalized from the plans for the Rising. He believed there should be no rising without sufficient German support and when he realised that it was going ahead with only a small supply of German arms, he traveled to Ireland to prevent it from taking place. The Germans supplied a submarine to transport Casement, Monteith and Sergeant Beverly (Daniel Bailey) to Ireland but Casement and Beverly were captured after they landed in Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Casement was hanged for treason in London in August 1916.
This letter details Monteith&#39;s work in attempting to recruit Irish POW&#39;s to the Irish Brigade, the making of his uniform and the role of Michael Kehoe, a member of the Irish Brigade.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sir Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15; Ms. 13,085/24/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5527</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0377">Robert Monteith</persName>
              <date>1915-11-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1956</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5527_img_623_1"  type="Letter"  url="704668144e7741857544dd418de1a67a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5527_img_623_2"  type="Letter"  url="0b69dc58c9406b1aaf2d3578f3a807dc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5527_img_623_1"/>
              R in Berlin <lb/>4 Nov/15   Limburg.   2.XI.15.   Dear Sir Roger    Your letter of yesterday to hand <lb/> this evening — I have not spoken to anyone of the <lb/> messenger up to the present, &amp; will take care not <lb/> to mention his name on any future occasion —    Regarding Kehoe I am rather in doubt <lb/> in this matter, I have learned that there are other <lb/> attractions in Limburg for the Sergt Major besides <lb/> recruiting, but as he might be able to help <lb/> things along, I think it would be best to send <lb/> him down. I will make sure that he carries out <lb/> his share of the work —    Up to the present we have nothing to show <lb/>for our work, I have interviewed 70 men about <lb/> 10 of whom I intend to see again. The first <lb/> 25 men were inclined to be a little rusty and
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5527_img_623_2"/>
            insolent, but I managed to smooth their ruffled <lb/> feathers and part with them on good terms, the <lb/> men whom I saw today were in a far <lb/> better frame of mind and reasoned out the <lb/> matter squarely, and I think we stand to get <lb/> 8 or 10 of them —   Regarding the uniform, my reason for <lb/> asking you to send it down, was to avoid the <lb/> expense of having a second one made up <lb/> until we knew it was necessary. However I have <lb/>arranged with a local military tailor to have one <lb/> made, and, I know you will understand me <lb/> Sir Roger, when I say that I cannot think of <lb/> saddling you with the expense of my clothing or <lb/>equipment.    I do not really require anything at present - <lb/>one or two small things required by the N.C.O.S. I <lb/> purchased, and I will hand up the bill when I <lb/>return, these articles were necessary and I thought <lb/> it right to get them —   Faithfully Yours   <hi rend="underline">R. Monteith</hi>   PS. <lb/>Please do not send Kehoe down until <lb/>Monday next. <lb/> <hi rend="underline">RM</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>