<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1513">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis Vane of Hutton to Sir Reginald Brade, 5 October 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is Vane&#39;s reply to a letter of 3 October from the War Office. He understands that, despite his record as a recruiting officer in Ireland and various positive comments and commendations from senior officers, he is &#39;no longer an officer&#39;. He feels that his reporting of the murders of Sheehy-Skeffington, Dixon, and McIntyre, and his refusal to condone them, and his efforts to &#39;allay the feeling of anger&#39; in Ireland, was beneficial to the reputation of the army and of H.M Government.He asks for an explanation from the Army Council of &#39;the reasons which led them to relegate me to unemployment&#39; in view of the many commendations he received.Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane (1861-1934) was in command of Portobello Barracks during the Easter Rising. When he learned about activities of Captain J.C. Bowen-Colthurst he reported the matter to his superiors but, sensing a cover-up, went to London and reported to Lord Kitchener and Maurice Bonham Carter, private secretary to the prime minister. Although Bowen-Colthurst was court-martialed and found guilty, the outcome for Vane was that he was &#39;retired&#39; from the military. John Dillon (1851-1927) was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs.Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, Ms. 6837/27/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1513</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1025">Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1916-10-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0916">National Liberal Club, London S.W., England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Reginald Brade</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0553">War Office, London, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1513_img_971_1"  type="Letter"  url="7f21e87052f9c01c1fadce413fc2c371.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1513_img_971_2"  type="Letter"  url="c1dd6d6c60c945b4665782e77046c3c7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1513_img_971_1"/>
              Copy of reply to War Office letter 3rd, Oct, 1916. <lb/>29004/22 (C.I.)   Sir Reginald Brade K.C.B. War Office    National Liberal Club  S.W.    5th October, 1916.   Sir,   I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your <lb/> letter dated 3rd inst.   I am, therefore, to understand that I am at present <lb/>'no longer an officer', in spite of the fact that for an <lb/>action on the 27th April last, I was recommended for distin<lb rend="hyphen"/>guished service in the field in command of men by the Briga<lb rend="hyphen"/>dier, who was present. Moreover, for the command of the <lb/> Defences, Portobello Barracks, during the week of the Rising, <lb/>I was personally commended and thanked for this work and for <lb/> the reorganisation of these posts, by the Officer Commanding <lb/> the Troops.   I beg to call the attention of the Army Council further <lb/> to the fact that in reporting the murders of Messrs. Skeffing<lb rend="hyphen"/>ton, Dickson, and McIntyre, and refusing to condone these <lb/> murders, I performed valuable service for the Honour of the <lb/>Army and for the reputation of H. M's Government in Ireland. <lb/> This personal report of mine was carried through correctly. <lb/> On the 1st May, six days after the illegal shootings, having <lb/> remonstrated with the then Commanding Officer for placing <lb/> Captain Bowen Colthurst in command of the Defences, he at the <lb/> time being under accusation of murder, I proceeded in due se<lb rend="hyphen"/>quence to report to the Irish Command, Park Gate. There <lb/> receiving no assurance that the latter officer was to be placed <lb/>under restraint, I proceeded to London and reported the facts <lb/> to the Rt. Hon <hi rend="superscript">ble</hi> H. J. Tennant, late Parliamentary Secretary, <lb/> W. O., (2nd May) and to the late Earl Kitchener, (3rd May). <lb/>Mr Tennant in writing thanked me for this action, and Lord  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1513_img_971_2"/>
              Kitchener, in the presence of Mr Bonham Carter, stated that <lb/>I had acted quite rightly. Lord Kitchener in my presence <lb/> dictated the telegram ordering Captain Bowen Colthurst to be <lb/> placed under arrest, which in fact was not carried out until <lb/> the 6th May - exactly ten days after the crimes had been com<lb rend="hyphen"/>mitted.   At the time of the occurrence of the Rebellion I was <lb/> engaged in recruiting in Ireland, and at once volunteered my <lb/> services for the suppression of the Rising. I was gazetted <lb/>on the 31st March and posted by Garrison Order for duty during <lb/>the Rebellion 24th April.   May I point out that nothing has occurred to show that <lb/> I failed in my duty as a recruiting officer and on the con<lb rend="hyphen"/>trary so far as efficency in that work is concerned, it may <lb/> be noted that at my own expense I raised 500 recruits in <lb/> London between 24th August and 5th Sept., 1914. In addition <lb/> there are the above reports proving my efficiency in the field.   It is well known throughout Ireland that I did not <lb/>spare myself in attempting to allay the feeling of anger which <lb/> had arisen when the facts of the murders became known, by ren<lb rend="hyphen"/>dering every assistance in my power to the widow of the mur<lb rend="hyphen"/>dered man, and by making it known widely that the crimes were <lb/>unauthorised.   In these circumstances I must, therefore, ask you to <lb/>convey to the Army Council my desire for an explanation of the <lb/> reasons which led them to relegate me to unemployment on the <lb/> 30th June, seeing that then I had only recently performed <lb/> duties which earned me the recommendation of a Brigadier, <lb/>of strong commendation of the Officer Commanding at Portobel<lb rend="hyphen"/>lo Barracks and the thanks of Lord Kitchener, of Mr. Tennant, <lb/> and of the Private Secretary to the Prime Minister.  <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant,   Captain, late Major R.M.F. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>