<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3518">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to the Under Secretary of Ireland, 5 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to the under secretary of Ireland approving the changes under Section 2 of the Poisons and Pharmacy Act, 1908, regulating the sale of Carbolic Acid for the uses of Agriculture and Horticulture, in line with similar regulations in held Great Britain. 

At the time this letter was written Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) was serving as the under secretary for Ireland. Nathan took up the position in 1914 but offered his resignation in 1916 following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. He was replaced by Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-143</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3518</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-02-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3518_img_2923_1"  type="Letter"  url="b1fde93c4a6741c422337ab54c642b50.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3518_img_2923_1"/>
             5th FEBRUARY 16.   The Under Secretary, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   No.<hi rend="underline">1595.</hi>   Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 31st. January, above <lb/>quoted I am requested by the President and Fellows of <lb/>the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to forward <lb/>you a copy of the following resolution passed at a <lb/>meeting of the College held yesterday the 4th inst.:- <lb/>RESOLVED : "that the College approves of the proposal <lb/>to make an order in Council under Section 2 (1) of the <lb/>Poisons and Pharmacy Act,1908, regulating the sale of <lb/>Carbolic Acid, Ac., for the purposes of Agriculture and <lb/>Horticulture, bringing the sale of these drugs under <lb/>similar regulations to those which obtain in Great Britain.   I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>