<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1150">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 24 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to the Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867-1941) regarding Shaw&#39;s responsibilities at work and his time schedule. Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/5, IJA/CHPI/54/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1150</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-05-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1150_img_3827_1"  type="Letter"  url="8ad2881d89d1a137522a5aeab1876ea1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1150_img_3827_1"/>
                24 May 1916   Dear Reverend Father Provincial P. C.   I am getting on well in my new quarters. I have <lb/>fewer to look after in the way of patients, but more in the way of <lb/>staff and orderlies than I had in No. 3 Gen. Hosp. The work here is more <lb/>satisfactory, therefore, in the sense that it can be practically all done <lb/>in the Church. Our village church is a very nice one, indeed, and possesses the <lb/>advantage of having a high alter visible to the congregation. I say Mass every <lb/>weekâday morning at 6.30, and some of the men come to Holy Communion; and <lb/>on Sunday at 9.15 when our congregation is very respectable, and will be even <lb/>more so when we are better organised. We have a good number of Catholics <lb/>considering there is no Irish or purely Catholic unit in the vicinity, but only <lb/>scraps, and make â ups, Army Service Corps, R. A. M. C. <seg type="unclear">etc</seg>. My Commanding Officer <lb/>is a Catholic. He is Lieut â Col. Brogden, and, he told me a few nights ago, <lb/>an old Crescent boy! I go down to the Church again for Benediction on <lb/>Sunday at 5.30. The men sing, and we have Rosary beforehand. I shall <lb/>give them a ten â minute address, also, as they used to have it from my <lb/>predecessor, who left about a fortnight before I came. I am in the Church <lb/>again, on week â days from 5.30 p. m to about 6.45, when I say <seg type="unclear">Matins</seg> &amp; <lb/>Lauds, and hear Confessions. There are a number of villages scattered about <lb/>here, with possibilities in my line, so I don't imagine I shall be occupied <lb/>solely with my immediate surroundings. I hear now and then from F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Fitzgibbon. <lb/>He is at present in close proximity to F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Frank Browne, and they have met a <lb/>couple of times. My nearest confrere is a Father Isidore M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Cann, a <lb/>Jesuit boy of Garnet Hill, Glasgow. He is about three miles away, and was <lb/>over here once. We get a full view of artillery bombardments, star â shells, &amp; <lb/>aeroplane work from here. Is F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Roche still with the H. L. I. Field Ambulance <lb/>I would write to him if you send me his address. I am sure there is <lb/>great work going on in Milltown with <seg type="unclear">repetitions</seg> in full swing!!  I recommend myself in your Reverences Masses and prayers. <seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely in Christ,  Francis M. Shaw S,J. C.F. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>