<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1289">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from C. Spencer Smith to Gertrude Bannister, 31 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>C. Spencer Smith</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from C. Spencer Smith of Queen Anne&#39;s School in London to Gertrude Bannister (later Parry), a cousin of Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter refers to arrangements to terminate Bannister&#39;s employment in the school and the writer asks that she send a copy of the notice announcing her resignation.The letter was written while Casement was imprisoned after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. Bannister was heavily involved in raising public support for Casement during his trial for treason.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15, Ms. 13,075 /1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1289</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0895">C. Spencer Smith</persName>
              <date>1916-07-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0318">53 Palace Street, Victoria Street, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1365">Gertrude Bannister</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1289_img_500_1"  type="Letter"  url="6b20f20cd0d4bc29e8a927597a6a8823.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1289_img_500_1"/>
                CLERK &amp; RECEIVER'S OFFICE: 53, PALACE STREET,  VICTORIA STREET, S.W.    31st July 1916   Dear Miss Bannister    I am sending a formal reply to your letter, &amp; also <lb/> a note from the Chairman which may go some way to satisfy you.    There was some delay in sending my previous letter off as your address was <lb/> unknown until obtained from Miss Holmes, &amp; I was not present here when <lb/> it was dispatched. It appears that the notice was not booked and <lb/> as it is desirable for me to have a copy it would much oblige me if <lb/> you would send me one - or return the original on promise of return.  <seg type="closer"> I am faithfully yours  <hi rend="underline">C.Spencer Smith</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>