<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5286">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Tyrrell Jr. to William Tyrrell Sr, 22 October 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Tyrrell Jr.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letters of William Upton Tyrrell (&#39;Willie&#39;) to his father William J.H. Tyrrell, mother Elizabeth, sister Minnie and brother Robert are a notable example of wartime correspondence. The letters - nearly 200 in total - are mostly written by William to his family while in active service with the Royal Irish Rifles in France. Willie discusses his life and the lives of other soldiers in the trenches, as well as life at Ballindoolin, the family estate.

The family name &#39;Tyrrell&#39; is sometimes misspelled &#39;Tyrell&#39; in correspondence to the family.

Summary of the present letter:

Willie is in the trenches. He describes an encounter with a German soldier at the front lines saying, &#34;he had a rather serious reverse&#34;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5286</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0431">William Tyrrell Jr.</persName>
              <date>1917-10-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Tyrrell Sr.</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5286_img_None_1"  url="ea0324ef248eee6ff5aa8bdb5002d15f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5286_img_None_2"  url="9f872f443b7c24fe7ee107cbf901e903.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5286_img_0_1"/>
              Monday 22/10/17    My dearest Daddy   I was dellghted to get your<lb/>long letter of 16th yesterday.<lb/>Weather here is very fine and<lb/>everything is very quiet. We<lb/>expect to go out of the trenches in<lb/>another two days.  You say that the rebels are<lb/>saying we have had a reverse.<lb/>Well no one out here has heard<lb/>a word of it and I think we ought<lb/>to know. When I was up in the<lb/>front line this morning we spotted<lb/>a boche looking over the parapet<lb/>&amp; I am afraid he had a rather<lb/>serious reverse.  No news and I will write soon<lb/>again. I have some rather amusing<lb/>things to tell you but cannot<lb/>mention them for a few days 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5286_img_0_2"/>
             no news<lb/>Best love<lb/> Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie   <hi rend="underline"></hi>Of course I will give<lb/>something towards a wedding<lb/>present for the <seg type="unclear">Pofe</seg> How<lb/>much should I give.  Will<lb/>10/- or £1 do. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>