<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1671">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward (Ned) Lysaght to Diarmid Coffey, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ned Lysaght</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Ned Lysaght (later MacLysaght) (1887-1986) was born in England but became an enthusiastic member of the Gaelic League and was politically radicalised by the Easter Rising. Although he never became a member, he was openly sympathetic to Sinn Féin. He later became a senator in the Irish Free State.
Diarmid Coffey (1888-1964) joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914 and became secretary of the Irish National Volunteers after the organisation split in 1915 (it was the other group who participated in the Rising). He later served as assistant clerk of the Seanad.
In the letter, Lysaght addresses his proposed solution to the &#39;Ulster difficulty&#39;. A Home Rule Act for Ireland had been postponed by the outbreak of World War I but was bitterly opposed by Ulster Unionists and considered insufficient by advanced nationalists. MacLysaght encloses typed notes on a proposal that he believes will meet the objections of Ulster Unionists and nationalists, while avoiding the partition of the country, which was considered, though not formalised, under the Home Rule Act. The letter comes a month after the execution of the leaders of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Coffey &amp; Chenevic Trench Papers, Collection List No 153; Ms. 46,307/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1671</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0480">Ned Lysaght</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1340">Knocksullish, Scariff, County Clare</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0284">Diarmid Coffey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1870">5 Harcourt Terrace, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1986</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_1"  type="Letter"  url="30f5c9550bc77dcaebc9e6b3eea1407b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="e728b6858bd430447148df7105a298fa.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="8ce71e007275c75761b7e8e151367fb0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="42e51cd5f387e1cdd8361603ade50dd5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="c34b06a57f50b567eb124d29ee9e76e5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="3260f64a027036d9212f48a3da8a1b1a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1671_img_113_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="55fea3f23076f3a2cd59ecef054e792d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_1"/>
             Knocksullish,<lb/>Scariff, Co. Clare.   18 June 1916    Dear Coffey,   Enclosed is an outline of a plan for settling the Ulster difficulty.<lb/>I feel that it is rather presumptuous for an unknown man to set out to<lb/>find a solution, but as far as I can see the idea of Irishmen who are<lb/>not party politicians are <sic>unco-ordinated</sic> and for the moment inarticulate.<lb/>I have received some very interesting comments on my plan already, and I<lb/>feel that a combination of the best points of each would be more likely<lb/>to produce a real settlement than anything else.  Perhaps the simplest idea is that of Mr. G.W. Russell (A.E.) who, in a<lb/>long letter dealing with Ireland's relation to Europe as well as her in-<lb/>ternal relations, suggests that we should return to the King, Lords and<lb/>Commons of Ireland, the House of Lords having an absolute veto, as the<lb/>British house had before the Parliament Act. This, he feels, would be<lb/>the simplest and most efficient safeguard to Protestant and Unionist in-<lb/>terests and at the same time would tend to make our upper classes more<lb/>Irish and to keep them in the country, he thinks that the system of<lb/>representation I have suggested for the Lower House could be adopted to-<lb/>gether with a House of Peers. I have little doubt but that this would<lb/>be accepted with delight by Nationalist Ireland; I daresay the Ulster<lb/>Unionists might accept it too.  I may add that all my correspondents are unanimous in disliking<lb/>the policy of exclusion and in emphasizing the essential need of colon-<lb/>ial self-government (advocated by the Round Table group).  I hope to publish the various letters I receive in the form of a<lb/>pamphlet, as a contribution of non-party Irishmen towards a solution.  The question I am dealing with hardly affects the matter of tempor-<lb/>ary exclusion (except in so far as any bad arrangement might prejudice<lb/>the future) I want to get something as a permanent basis,   Yours   <hi rend="underline"><lb/>Ned Lysaght</hi>    D.Coffey, Esq.,<lb/>5 Harcourt Tce,<lb/>Dublin.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_2"/>
             It is agreed that a golden opportunity for the settlement<lb/>of the Irish problem has come. Our affairs are in process<lb/>of being settled by men who were elected as our represen<lb/>tatives six years ago. Since 1910 many striking events<lb/>have occurred each of sufficient importance to Ireland to<lb/>have justified a general election. In fact, the opinion<lb/>of independ<seg type="del">a</seg> e nt men, whose views on what is for the good of<lb/>Ireland are not blinded by their views of what is good for<lb/>some particular party, is now unheeded and almost unheard.<lb/>I write this letter as a non-party man, interested in the<lb/>future of my country, but without special qualification of<lb/>any kind to speak.  It seems to me that eight salient facts stand out :<lb/>First : It is admitted that the old regime is impossible.<lb/>Second : Nationalist Ireland objects to the dismemberment<lb/>of Ireland by the exclusion of Ulster or any part of it.<lb/>Third : Ulster Unionists object to being in the power (as they<lb/>put it) of an Irish parliament.<lb/>Fourth : Southern Unionists are on the whole prepared to give<lb/>Home Rule a fair trial.<lb/>Fifth : Even in the four Counties there is a very considerable<lb/>Nationalist minority, to coerce which would be as unfair<lb/>as to coerce Unionist Ulster.<lb/>Sixth : War taxation has proved that Ireland is not bankrupt.<lb/>We contribute something like 26 millions now to the<lb/>Imperial Exchequer; before the was Irish expenditure<lb/>was, I think, 11 millions. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_3"/>
             Seventh : The dual control set up by the Home Rule act is likely to<lb/>lead to friction, as dual control invariably does.  Eight : The fuller and more generous the measure of self government,<lb/>the more likely is Ireland to take a willing place in the<lb/>British Empire. I believe this myself and South Africa<lb/>would help to prove it; but possibly it might be regarded<lb/>by some as a not uncontroversial statement.  To evolve a scheme which will take account of these facts and meet<lb/>them in the work which has to be done.  I claim no merit of originality for the following plan: I venture,<lb/>however, to put it forward because it seems to me to fulfill the<lb/>required conditions. But I do so rather in the hopes of its forming<lb/>the basis for better suggestions, than as a cut—and—dried proposal for<lb/>settlement.  The essential features of it are —:<lb/>1. A Parliament for all Ireland.<lb/>2. A Council or Parliament for all Ulster to deal with purely Ulster<lb/>affairs.<lb/>3. Financial autonomy.<lb/>4. No Irish members in the British Parliament.<lb/>5. Both Ireland and Ulster to be represented as Units on such Imperial<lb/>Council of the self governing states of the British Empire as we<lb/>may reasonably assume will be formed after the war.<lb/>6. The Ulster Council or Parliament to have a veto in respect of<lb/>any law not passed through the Irish Parliament by a certain major—<lb/>ity.<lb/>(2) 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_4"/>
             (say 3/5 of the Lower House and a bare majority of the Upper) as regards<lb/>the application of that law to the Province of Ulster.<lb/>7. The Ulster Council or Parliament to have the right of appeal to<lb/>the Imperial Council in respect of any law, irrespective of the<lb/>majority by which it was passed, against its application to the<lb/>Province of Ulster.<lb/>8. Election to the Lower House on a basis of population and by<lb/>proportional representation.<lb/>9. Selection of Upper House by process of election by various public<lb/>bodies and institutions in the Country from among their own<lb/>members, and ex officio by the tenure of certain ecclesiastical<lb/>and public Offices.  Items 8 and 9 require a little elaboration even in the comparatively<lb/>short outline of this kind, to show their force and object. The object<lb/>of No. 8. is to provide minority representation. In order to do<lb/>so the larger the constituency the better, but anything larger than a<lb/>single county or city would be <sic>unwidely</sic>. Possibly, even, it might<lb/>be necessary to divide the larger counties into two, but for<lb/>the purpose of my present calculations I have not done so. I would<lb/>suggest one member to roughly every 30,000 persons and I would concede<lb/>one member also to all towns over 12,000 inhabitants in order to<lb/>increase both urban and Ulster representatives; in effect it would<lb/>add Lurgan, Newry, Dundalk, Drogheda, Portadown, Wexford and<lb/>Galway to the constituencies. Not counting University members,<lb/>which should be returned by both Trinity and the National University,<lb/>we would then have a House of 143. 52 would be from Ulster, 91 from<lb/>(3) 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_5"/>
             the rest of Ireland. Of these 40 would be returned by cities and<lb/>towns, 22 from Ulster, 18 from other provinces. It will thus be<lb/>seen at a glance that a combination of Ulster and urban votes would<lb/>amount to 74 or a majority of 5. When it is remembered that Ulster,<lb/>which means generally industrial, interests could not be prejudiced by<lb/>any law not carried by a majority of 29 (i.e. a 3/5 majority) in a<lb/>full House, it will be seen that the facts of the case provide<lb/>better safeguards to Ulster than the paper safeguards which have<lb/>been so much despised. It is true that parts of Ulster would go<lb/>against Ulster interests, as we are now considering them, but I have no<lb/>doubt that it would be more than counterbalanced by conflicting inter—<lb/>ests among other parties— for no one imagines that the pledge—bound<lb/>discipline of a single Irish Party can continue in a native Parlia—<lb/>ment— and by the affect of proportional representation, I believe<lb/>this in itself would prove a very check on any persecution<lb/>which, I think quite erroneously, is feared by the minority. By<lb/>having large constituencies we greatly increase the likelihood of<lb/>the best minority representation being returned. Thus Dublin and<lb/>Belfast would each return 13 members, Co. Cork and Co. Down 10, Co.<lb/>Tipperary and Co. Tyrone 5 each, and so on down to the single member<lb/>constituencies such as Co. Leitrim. Co. Carlow, Derry, Limerick,<lb/>and Waterford and other towns I mentioned. These practical safe—<lb/>guards apply as well in religious as in industrial matters and a<lb/>senate of a judicial and steady kind would provide additional security.<lb/>I do not propose now to go into details on this point, but by way of<lb/>(4) 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_6"/>
             suggestion I would propose that the members of such institutions as<lb/>the R.D.S., the I.A.O.S., the Royal Hibernian Academy, the College<lb/>Surgeons and Physicians and so on should each choose one member, or<lb/>alternatively their presidents might be members ex officio; each<lb/>county Council could return one or two members; chambers of commerce,<lb/>ecclesiastical interests could provide representatives in the same way.<lb/>Commerce, transport, <seg type="del">and</seg> agricultur e <seg type="del">al</seg> industry, science and the churches<lb/>would thus have direct representation without the possible waywardness<lb/>of popular election; and this would I take it, be no negation of<lb/>democracy in as much as it has never been proposed to give the Upper<lb/>House greater power than that of suggesting amendments and retarding<lb/>legislation which it considers unlikely to reflect the will of the<lb/>country.  Is it too late for Irishmen to attempt something constructive in solv—<lb/>ing the problem of their own future? The best Irish measures passed<lb/>in late years have come from the brains of Irishmen. Is the Home Rule<lb/>Act with which so few were honestly satisfied, inevitably to be taken<lb/>as the basis of settlement now? It cannot be so taken, I hold, if<lb/>the settlement is to be a permanent one.  (5) 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1671_img_113_7"/>
            BALLYCLARE BOND <seg type="unclear">25, 26 New Ireland R</seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>