<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0471">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles E. Fair to the acting Chief Secretary for Ireland, 21 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles E. Fair</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles E. Fair to the acting Chief Secretary for Ireland. Fair refers to his application for the vacant post of Clerk of Crown and Peace for County Westmeath which he submitted the previous week, enclosing two letters of testimony in support of his candidature and says that he will be sending more in due course.The office of Chief Secretary for Ireland was vacated by Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) on 3 May 1916. Birrell&#39;s replacement, Sir Henry Duke (1855-1939), took up the position from 31 July 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/10509</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/471</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0416">Charles E. Fair</persName>
              <date>1916-06-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1099">Athlone, County Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Chief Secretary (Acting)</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0471_img_1818_1"  type="Letter"  url="c519bcfc7091ac76ac1b227089d98052.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0471_img_1818_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="ccb4705a5bea51399d402c0ced7b9660.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0471_img_1818_3"  type="Letter"  url="5f6122e5971cf23919905b1d9e24e2a4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0471_img_1818_1"/>
                ATHLONE,    <hi rend="underline">21st day of June, 1916.</hi>   Sir,-   I trust my Application forwarded to you last <lb/>week for Appointment of Clerk of the Crown and <lb/>Peace for County Westmeath has safely reached <lb/>you.  I now enclose a couple of Testim- <lb/>onials from the managers of the Bank of Ireland <lb/>and Provincial Bank here.  I hope to forward further Testim- <lb/>onials from The Right <sic>Honble</sic> Lord Castlemaine <lb/>and The Provost of Trinity College Dublin in <lb/>due course, <seg type="closer"> I have the honor to be, <lb/>Your obedient servant,  Charles. E. Fair   The Chief Secretary (Acting),-  Dublin Castle.  </seg> I Add to file <lb/>II Ack. <lb/>III A.D.  E.o.f <lb/>22:6:16.  II Done <seg type="unclear">RC</seg> 22/6 <lb/>II Respd  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0471_img_1818_2"/>
                Bank of Ireland Office  Athlone    <hi rend="underline">21st June 1916</hi>    I hereby Certify that I have known <lb/>Mr <sic>Char</sic> E O' Fair for the past <lb/>four years. During that time <lb/>and I believe for many years <lb/>previously Mr Fair has carried on <lb/>a large general Business as a Solicitor <lb/>and Land Agent in this town.  Since that year 1913, when he <lb/>Succeeded to the business of the late <lb/>Mr P. Rob Kelly, he has acted as <lb/>local solicitor to this Bank, and <lb/>during this time he has throughly <lb/>satisfied the Bank Directors and <lb/>myself.  In my option Mr Fair is <lb/>thoroughly competend to perform <lb/>the duties of Clerk of the Crown <lb/>and Peace for County Westmeath <lb/>if appointed to that office. <seg type="closer"> <seg type="unclear">O'Donovan</seg>  agent. <lb/>Bank of Ireland</seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0471_img_1818_3"/>
                Provincial Bank of Ireland  Limited  Athlone    21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June. 1916.    I have known Mr Charles E. Fair, for almost <lb/>the past six years ; and he has conducted the local <lb/>business of this Bank for 20 years.  During the period of my management, <lb/>and I believe previously, he has always done so to the <lb/>satisfaction of my predecessors, myself, and the Bank's <lb/>Directors.  In my opinion Mr. Fair is thoroughly <lb/>Competent, and well qualified to perform the duties <lb/>of Clerk of the Crown and Peace, for County Westmeath <lb/>if appointed to that office. <seg type="closer"> <seg type="unclear">W.F.</seg> Pearson,  Manager.</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>