<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1455">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay 23 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancee Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June and the letters were written between them during that period. He lived in Dublin, she lived in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. He tells how he &#39;had his eye on her&#39; for a long time but waited until she was old enough. Throughout the series of letters you can see how their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters and how her confidence grows.The series is not complete; it is interrupted by visits to each other’s homes and by obviously missing letters. They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child, my father. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him: this explains their survival. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats, so that she ended up quite comfortable off!James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him, trying to demand he be carried in to meetings. Neither May nor James were politically active though, like many in the Civil Service, James was obviously somewhat activated, learning Irish, probably Gaelic League, and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in it. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.This letter is about their wedding arrangements and disappointment about home rule</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1455</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-23T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1455_img_895_1"  type="Letter"  url="923d8459d4b0716521216f291ef3a224.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1455_img_895_2"  type="Letter"  url="e92601c050a6576487a6a7529ffdad10.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1455_img_895_1"/>
                23 May, 1916.   My dearest love,   I'm not going to write you <lb/>much toâday for I haven't got a <lb/>minute hardly to spare but I don't like <lb/>to let the day pass without letting you <lb/>know I have been thinking of you. <lb/>I got your letter all right and <lb/>was interested in the details of the wedding <lb/>dress although I can't say that I <lb/>understand them very clearly. All the <lb/>same I expect I'll be able to tell you  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1455_img_895_2"/>
              <lb/>pretty decidedly whether I like it or not <lb/>so God help you if it is not becoming. <lb/>I'm sure all the same that my dearest <lb/>girl will look very well. I wish to <lb/>goodness I could hope that I will look <lb/>something like the sort of bridegroom that <lb/>you ought to have. I know very well that <lb/>everyone that sees us together will be saying <lb/>to themselves 'What could that nice young <lb/>girl have seen in that ould cod to induce <lb/>her to marry him'. I was amused with <lb/>your account of the bould Johnnie and <lb/>his news from Cork. He's a cool sort <cb/><lb/>all right and I wouldn't be much <lb/>surprised if he forgot Mrs Seery's <lb/>goodness to him very quickly if he once <lb/>got back into a safe job again. <lb/>However I suppose that's only human <lb/>nature and I expect I should be as <lb/>ungrateful myself as the next one. <lb/>It doesn't do for people in glass houses <lb/>to throw stone. I was delighted to hear <lb/>about Louis but the father took the good <lb/>out of it like the British Government <lb/>and Home Rule. Must shut up, no <lb/>more time. Warmest and dearest love <lb/>to my own good little girl. <seg type="closer"> From her loving  James </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>