<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2656">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. Duffin to Celia Duffin, 2 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A. Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

Celia Duffin was a VAD with the 3rd London General Hospital in Wandsworth which opened in 1914. She was an accomplished poet, publishing, amongst other volumes, a book of poetry with her sister Ruth.

In this letter the writer tells Celia that her Aunt Margaret is dying. An operation revealed &#39;deep-seated trouble&#39; and says that she may have been saved a long and painful illness.  T</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/22</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2656</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0124">A. Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1376">Ulster Club, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2656_img_2080_1"  type="Letter"  url="52263923d9d30135991ddf3f48c7896e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2656_img_2080_2"  type="Letter"  url="35d06305ddfef9a3f61f783e84d861b2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2656_img_2080_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/C  Ulster Club<lb/>Belfast.   2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> March. 1916.    Dearest Celia   I have bad news for you. I<lb/>fear dear Aunt Margaret is dying.<lb/>She was to have been at<lb/><seg type="unclear">Dundrum</seg> for tea on Saturday,<lb/>but felt ill and went to bed &amp;<lb/>on Monday had to go to the<lb/>Nursing Home for a very<lb/>serious operation, which  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2656_img_2080_2"/>
             <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>Poor thing it may be that she<lb/>has <seg type="unclear"></seg>a long and<lb/>painful illness the end of<lb/>which was inevitable.<lb/>Poor Marjorie will be home<lb/>in the morning. It is very<lb/>terrible for her.  <lb/>I can think of nothing else.   Your loving<lb/>A.Duffin  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>