<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1157">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Francis M. Shaw to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 18 July 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Francis M. Shaw (1881-1924) to Father Provincial Thomas V. Nolan (1867-1941) regarding his work on the hospital ship &#39;Delta&#39; and the Catholics who he met there.Francis, or Frank, Shaw SJ was born in Ennis, county Clare. He was ordained on 31 July 1916 at Milltown Park, Dublin. Fr Shaw joined the war early in 1916, working in the 16th General Field Hospital at Le Tréporte. In 1917, possibly due to his nationalistic views, Fr Shaw was dispatched to India, and later to Mesopotamia.Fr. Thomas V. Nolan was the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus (1912-1922) and was a member of the Distribution Committee which looked after the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who arrived in Ireland as a consequence of the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/54/15, IJA/CHPI/54/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1157</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1473">Francis Shaw</persName>
              <date>1917-07-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1459">Bombay, India</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr Thomas V Nolan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1157_img_3834_1"  type="Letter"  url="820fcb66b5072d67c5e302968f68c8f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1157_img_3834_2"  type="Letter"  url="c875fe0abe4dc68c19f8c217d631e24e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1157_img_3834_3"  type="Letter"  url="2964a290dd2b6deaa87a7d7cc67ab5a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1157_img_3834_1"/>
                Archbishop's House,  WODEHOUSE ROAD FORT.  BOMBAY.    18 July 1917.   My dear F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Provincial, P.C.   I hope you got my last <lb/>from Bombay with cheque enclosed. <lb/>(Â£50) It will be of more use to you <lb/>than to the Mediterranean fishes.  I have just completed my first <lb/>trip on the Hospital Ship 'Delta'. <lb/>I had a good number of Catholics <lb/>on board coming back â Indians, <lb/>Burmans, Irish, English, West <lb/>Africans. It was very hot up <lb/>Gulf way, but the sea is as flat <lb/>as a pancake, and Mass is <lb/>possible everyday. I only lost <lb/>two Masses on the way up, and <lb/>I don't think I need have lost  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1157_img_3834_2"/>
              them. However I thought it <lb/>better not to run the risk. I <lb/>asked you to tell F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Farley I <lb/>had 20 Masses for him for <lb/>June. Please tell him I <lb/>have 20 also for July. These <lb/>numbers take into account the <lb/>4 suffrage masses for F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> J. <lb/>Maher &amp; B<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Mahon â I have <lb/>said 20 clear for him each <lb/>of the two months â or shall <lb/>have if God spares me to the <lb/>end of July.  I gave F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Hartigan a special <lb/>remembrance on 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> last. I <lb/>was not up the Gulf at the time.  F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> O' Mahony's boat is on our <lb/>run also. They were anchored <lb/>near us for a few days, but <lb/>not near enough to communicate.  He ought to be in Bombay today <lb/>or tomorrow. I sleep on the <lb/>ship, though the Fathers here <lb/>want me to stay here; but many <lb/>of my crew are Catholics and <lb/>they can have Mass on board <lb/>when I am there. The Indians <lb/>are very good Catholics â <lb/>especially the Goanese â <lb/>and these latter make up <lb/>the great bulk of the stewards <lb/>on boats out this way &amp; on <lb/>P &amp; O &amp; British India Steamers.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1157_img_3834_3"/>
              I am fortunate in being on the <lb/>Hospital ship, above all being <lb/>so often here, as I can do a <lb/>lot of work in collecting sermon <lb/>and retreat matter. I get <lb/>an odd bit of news about <lb/>Ireland in various papers <lb/>but have had no letters from <lb/>home since I left. Two â <lb/>certainly one â recent mails from <lb/>England to these parts are at <lb/>the bottom of the sea. Any <lb/>of the last status news will be <lb/>more than welcome.  I commend myself to your <lb/>Reverence's masses and prayers <lb/>and hope soon to be able to <lb/>lose myself again in the holy <lb/>obscurity of the Island of Saints. <seg type="closer"> Francis M. Shaw S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>