<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1258">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Noble Plunkett to Geraldine Plunkett Dillon, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Noble Plunkett</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A Letter from Count George Noble Plunkett (1851-1948) to his daughter Geraldine (b. 1891). The letter was sent from Richmond Barracks where Plunkett was being held at the time. He requests food, makes reference to a visit by Geraldine that &#39;lifted his heart&#39; and the &#39;joy&#39; of being clean. He also asks that she communicates with her mother, who had also been arrested.Count Plunkett was a nationalist and a papal count. He had been sworn in to the IRB by his son, Joseph Mary Plunkett (1887-1916), before the Rising and arrested afterwards. Count Plunkett was elected as an MP in 1918 and was elected a member of the first Dáil.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Geraldine Plunkett Dillon Collection, BMH CD/5/8/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1258</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0116">George Noble Plunkett</persName>
              <date>1916-03-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0909">Block F, Richmond Barracks, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Geraldine Plunkett Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1697">13 Belgrave Road, Rathfarnham, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1258_img_448_1"  type="Letter"  url="f5bc52931a8f4f68c70454cdb3dd86e5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1258_img_448_2"  type="Envelope"  url="46199cd8dd501fa80d704c629ca8bff0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1258_img_448_1"/>
                Richmond Barracks  Top Guard Room, Block F    Saturday, 13<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> May 1916   My dear Gerry   Some sandwiches,<lb/> and apples or oranges would be<lb/> a Godsend to me. Also  a small tumbler little mirror,  some matches,  &amp;<lb/> stamps.   God bless you all. You lifted up<lb/> my heart today. <seg type="closer"> With all my love to all, <lb/> Your loving,  Father. </seg> O the luxury of feeling clean!<lb/> (In body as well as spirit.) Perhaps you could now communicate<lb/> with Mammy, even if you could<lb/> not see her yet. I gave the name of Mr. Mathews<lb/> (of Denning's) as my solicitor today.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1258_img_448_2"/>
                Mrs. Geraldine Dillon  13 Belgrave Road  Rathmines  Co. Dublin    C.R.G. Heath<lb/> 2/6 SF  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>