<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5543">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 11 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
The letter refers to local gossip and also James&#39;s role with the National Health Insurance Commission.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5543</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-02-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0592">National Health Insurance Commission (Ireland), Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0273">Togherstown, Co Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5543_img_639_1"  type="Letter"  url="2d3936bd388ee093e232a3f9212c353c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5543_img_639_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5598ed7309609f73965387c85058c85.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5543_img_639_3"  type="Letter"  url="72fdb3d9fa89630d77d01078b748342f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5543_img_639_1"/>
             NATIONAL HEALTH COMMiSSION (IRELAND),<lb/>PEMBROKE HOUSE,<lb/>UPPER MOUNT STREET,<lb/>DUBLIN.   11th Feby, 1916. <lb/> My darling May,   Your letter received this<lb/>morning as expected. Fortunately I have<lb/>no need to watch out for the beautiful<lb/>figure of Mrs Lonican who I have no<lb/>doubt is praying for me for all the<lb/>extra work I am putting on herself and<lb/>her good man. However let’s hope that<lb/>the extra work won’t be for too long and<lb/>that one of these fine days we’ll be in<lb/>the position of not needing to write<lb/>letters to each other, unless it is across the 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5543_img_639_2"/>
            breakfast table. I was interested to hear of <lb/>Mrs Kelly’s good wishes. She may not be so <lb/>bad as she seems all the same. I think <lb/>I told you about Jim - he never said <lb/>anything either when I told him and yet <lb/>I know very well he wished me all <lb/>good luck. Some people are like that and <lb/>maybe she’s one of them. Saw a note from <lb/>Mrs Seery this morning. It seems that <lb/>Mrs Kiernan wrote to her the day before <lb/>with the news of John Duffy’s marriage but <lb/>the letter didn’t reach. I hope we won’t <lb/>have such a queer marriage when we <lb/>go off the hooks. Glad to hear everybody <lb/>thought you so much improved by your <lb/>stay in the town and hope you will do <lb/>as well when you come permanently. <lb/>Perhaps the present improvement is due to <lb/>the fact that you were so lazy in <lb/>the mornings and that it will pass off <lb/>now that you have to earn your <lb/>crust again. Talking of crusts, I’m <lb/>earning mine these days. We have just <lb/>had what they call a Departmental <lb/>Committee appointed to consider the simplification <lb/>of the Insurance Act. The most of the <lb/>inquiries turn on questions of accounting <lb/>on which I am the Irish expert. Result <lb/>is that your darling little man is nearly
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5543_img_639_3"/>
            killed. However I have weathered worse storms <lb/>than the present one and hope to keep my <lb/>end up all right and to do credit to the <lb/>Irish Commission. Glad to hear you have <lb/>been giving theatrical recitals to the boys <lb/>and that they enjoyed them. I'm going <lb/>to the Abbey tonight with my mother &amp; Moll <lb/>and will be thinking of you. Wish you <lb/>were with me but will see you any how in <lb/>a fortnight. Tell Mrs Seery to keep the <lb/>bed warm till then (Johnnie I suppose will <lb/>do so anyhow). I will enquire about J. <lb/>one of these days if he doesn't hear but he <lb/>had better let me know whether he would be <lb/>willing to come up or not. Remember me <lb/>to all at home and in Lockardstown . I send <lb/>you my dearest love and every warm wish of my heart. <lb/> Ever your loving  <lb/> James. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>