<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0200">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from M. Kennedy to the Chief Secretary for Ireland, 31 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>M. Kinsella </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from M. Kennedy to the chief secretary for Ireland warning of another rising involving Sinn Féin. He writes that the rebels have no shortage of arms and that he believes that considering the rebellion, warnings about rebel activity is probably not paid much attention to.While the letter is addressed to the chief secretary, there was no active chief secretary at the time this letter was written. This is due to the fact that Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) resigned on 3 May 1916 following his administrational failure during the 1916 Rising and his successor, Henry Duke (1855-1939), did not formally accept the position until 31 June 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9278</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/200</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0607">M. Kinsella </persName>
              <date>1916-05-31</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1507">Walton House, Regents Park, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Chief Secretary for Ireland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0200_img_1343_1"  type="Letter"  url="b4c830e40610c880bba53f1fd5eb9533.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0200_img_1343_1"/>
               Pre-printed telephone number - diagonal <lb/>TELEPHONE <lb/>VICTORIA 6074 Pre-printed address <lb/> PARLIAMENT MANSIONS, <lb/>ORCHARD STREET, <lb/>WESTMINSTER. S.W.    <hi rend="underline">Temporary address</hi>  Walton House  Longford St  Regents Park  N.W    May 31.16    Chief Secretary Irish Office   Sir,   I consider it my <lb/>duty to notify you of <lb/>the following, con- <lb/>veyed a letter to a <lb/>friend of mine, (a <lb/> member of the United <lb/>Service Club) by his <lb/>cousin in Dublin.  This gentleman writes <lb/> 1)  that another outbreak <lb/>of the Sinn Fein is expected at Whitsun, <lb/> 2)  that the rebels have <lb/> no shortage of <lb/>hidden arms and <lb/> 3)  that the Rebellion <lb/>is temporarily scotched <lb/>but smouldering still. <lb/> In the opinion of these gentlemen the <lb/>Army Act should <lb/>be re-enforced.  Doubtless you <lb/>have many reports <lb/>but, the recent <lb/> rebellion does not <lb/>lead one to think <lb/>that warnings are <lb/> paid any <seg type="unclear">heed to</seg>.   I have taken <lb/>the precaution of <lb/>posting a similar <lb/>letter to a member <lb/> of the cabinet. <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully <lb/> <hi rend="underline">M. Kennedy</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>