<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0163">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Matthew Nathan to Sir Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain, 1 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939). In the letter Nathan is requesting that Chamberlain forward him reports concerning the whereabouts of every member of Chamberlain&#39;s staff in Dublin from the 22 April to 1 May. Nathan remarks that these accounts should be verified as far as it it is in Chamberlain&#39;s power to do so and added to with any comments Chamberlain sees fit.Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising. The letter was addressed to the Inspector General, Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain (1856-1944). Chamberlain held the position from 1900 until his resignation in July 1916, making him the second longest serving inspector general in the force&#39;s history.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7767/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/163</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0205">Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain</persName>
              <date>1916-05-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0528">Chief Secretary&#39;s Office, Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0163_img_1293_1"  type="Letter"  url="4ef1e687095a21aa08f53df24d016f45.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0163_img_1293_1"/>
                Chief Secretary's Office,  Dublin Castle.    1st May, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Lord Lieutenant to request <lb/>that a full statement should be made by every member <lb/> of your staff employed in Dublin of his movements and <lb/>occupations during each day and of his places of sojourn <lb/> each night between noon on Saturday, April 22nd and noon <lb/>on Monday May 1st, and that these statements, verified <lb/> in as far as it is in your power to do this, should be <lb/>sent in to me before noon on Saturday, May 6th, with any <lb/> comments you may think fit to make with regard to them. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/> Your obedient servant, <lb/> Matthew Nathan. <lb/>Inspector General <lb/>R.I.C. Office</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>