<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0003">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. John McCarthy to Mrs. Sarah Kelly, 2nd May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John McCarthy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter written by Fr. John McCarthy, (b.1875)Leadville, Colorado, U.S.A. on 2nd May 1916 to Mrs. Sarah Kelly (1857-1920) (addressed &#39;Mrs. P.J. Kelly&#39; as Sarah was widow of Peter J. Kelly), The Octagon, Westport, Co. Mayo. The writer enclosed a &#39;draught for £20 on account&#39;, part-payment of a debt owed to Mrs. Kelly for goods supplied him. M Fr. McCarthy asks after &#39;Miss Mary&#39; in the letter; she was Mary McEvilly, an aunt who lived with Mrs. Kelly &amp;amp; family.His worries about sending &#39;money across the seas these times&#39; most likely relate to transatlantic travel upsets caused by the World War, although McCarthy may also have been unsure about postal services within Ireland following the Easter Rising. Mrs. Kelly was running the business which had been founded by her late husband: wholesale &amp;amp; retail grocery, spirit importation, bonding &amp;amp; wholesaling, etc. Fr. McCarthy had been a customer in Kelly&#39;s since at least 1902 (according to the business records) and had been a curate in Westport and later Aughagower; he went to America in c.1908. In Kelly&#39;s business records, his cheque is recorded as having been received &#39;from America&#39; on 25th May 1916, so the letter may have taken over 3 weeks to arrive in Westport, perhaps because it had been opened by the censor (see envelope). His debt was cleared in 1943, almost 40 years after it had been amassed.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kelly Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0450">John McCarthy</persName>
              <date>1916-05-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1262">Leadville, Colorado, U.S.A.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs. Sarah Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1061">Westport, County Mayo, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0003_img_1023_1"  type="NULL"  url="2ee96d2fb01db460d9db0edbf86424f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0003_img_1023_2"  type="NULL"  url="5db661ae2e6d97135f16446248d37a32.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0003_img_1023_3"  type="NULL"  url="a9033611acccc8d90a1aaf76c85ec039.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0003_img_1023_4"  type="NULL"  url="f6bb512e6f49d52abb32b6e08ed05e43.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0003_img_1023_1"/>
                Annunciation Church  Leadville  Colo. U.S.A.    May 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>, 1916   Dear Mrs. Kelly   I received your letter some<lb/> time ago &amp; was glad to learn yourself<lb/><seg type="unclear">Miss Mary</seg> &amp; all members of family were<lb/> well. I enclose draught for<lb/> Â£20 on account. On receipt please drop<lb/> me a card of acknowledgement. It is risky<lb/> to send money across the seas these times,<lb/> as if the letter is lost I will take a<lb/> long time to recover the money<lb/> again, For that reason I hope you  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0003_img_1023_2"/>
              will drop a line should the letter reach<lb/> you safely. With kind regards to<lb/> yourself Miss Mary &amp;all. <seg type="closer"> Yrs sincerely  Father Mc Carthy </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0003_img_1023_3"/>
              <seg type="del">After 5 days, return to</seg>  John McCarthy<lb/>  <seg type="unclear">Bon 325</seg>  LEADVILLE, COLO. <hi rend="superscript">u.04</hi>  Mrs P.J Kelly  The Octagon  Westport  Co.Mayo  Ireland    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0003_img_1023_4"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>