<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4040">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hanoria Shanahan to the Lord Lieutenant, Lord Wimborne, 8 January 1916 </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hanoria Shanahan </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A handwritten petition by Hanoria Shanahan to carry on her business as publican and grocer in a building close to her premises in Portmagee, Co. Kerry which had been destroyed by fire in November 1915.

Lord Wimborne (1873 –1939) was Lord Lieutenant, a largely ceremonial role, from 1915 until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers 1916, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5623-646</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4040</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0583">Hanoria Shanahan </persName>
              <date>1916-01-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1344">Portmagee, Co. Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Wimborne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4040_img_3422_1"  type="Letter"  url="a8b99e0d6903a07429bca802847a51cb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4040_img_3422_1"/>
            <hi rend="underline">Petition</hi>  To His Excellency<lb/>Lord Wimbourne<lb/>Lord <hi rend="underline">Lieutenant</hi> of Ireland   I pray your Excellency to give me permission to carry on my<lb/>business as publican and grocer in a small house not twenty<lb/>yards from the destroyed premises.  I pray your excellency to consider my case as most charitable,<lb/>and enable me to support my young family of seven children<lb/>(the eldest of which is not 13 years), until I am enabled<lb/>to build my house.  I pray your excellency to consider my request so<lb/>deserving, that the charitable public are providing me<lb/>the means of sustenance and the restoration of my little<lb/><seg type="unclear">trade</seg>for the sake of the helpless family.  I pray your Excellency not to refuse but to grant — the<lb/>petition of a heart broken widow, and may the Almighty<lb/>and just lord grant you all the requests you ask of Him<lb/>in these troublesome times is my humble prayer.  Hanoria Shanahan   Portmagee Calterry     8.1.16   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>