<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5716">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 5 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
James is relieved to finally have May&#39;s letter but she is not coming up to Dublin before Easter. He may have to go to Westmeath and meet her at the races.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5716</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-04-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2081">Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5716_img_818_1"  type="Letter"  url="5438a29bb1d5de3e4b056bf530ee7124.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5716_img_818_2"  type="Letter"  url="392d673bbb486afa72adc6f8d26679ad.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5716_img_818_1"/>
             NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION (IRELAND)<lb/>PEMBROKE HOUSE<lb/>UPPER MOUNT STREET<lb/>DUBLIN   5th April, 1916.    My darling May,   I have several things to say to you today and I am afraid<lb/>I haven’t much time but I’ll try to get everything off my chest. First I was<lb/>delighted to get your letter. I have had my tongue hanging out for the last couple<lb/>of days looking out for a line from you and my heart has been down in my boots<lb/>every morning when I got a disappointment. I am grieved that my poor darling<lb/>has been knocked up I was just thinking as much when I didn’t hear yesterday<lb/>but I hope sincerely that you are on the mend now. About coming up to town<lb/>I’m <hi rend="underline">awfully</hi> disappointed that you won’t come. Of course I know very well when our<lb/>marriage was coming off and how near Easter was to it but I don’t see why that<lb/>should stop you. As regards people saying that I was backing out, I had the idea<lb/>that perhaps you would come back with me at Easter and I don’t see how, if you<lb/>could be induced to do that, <seg type="del">how</seg> the peoples tongues could wag but perhaps<lb/>coming back in my company would be a highly improper and outrageous thing to do.<lb/>I’m afraid I’m not very clear on nice points of good conduct and morals such as<lb/>that. As to the races I must go now since you have made up your mind to<lb/>go but I certainly don’t feel inclined to spend the money merely for the fleeting<lb/>pleasure of a look at you in a crowd so I think I’ll brazen it out with<lb/>Mrs Seery and come down on Saturday evening next <hi rend="underline">unless you forbid me.</hi> I’m writing 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5716_img_818_2"/>
             to her now to feel my way and if she gives me any encouragement I feel more<lb/>than inclined to go and chance your displeasure. I’m more than half ashamed<lb/>to trouble her though and I’m afraid both you and your mother and herself will<lb/>think I’m mad. <sic>Praps</sic> I am I should not wonder indeed if I were when I<lb/>think soberly of the luck I have had. Now I want you like a darling to<lb/>write me a line by return (I’ll have it on Friday) to say whether you would be very<lb/>much displeased if I came down for the week end and go to the races with you<lb/>rather than go down straight on Monday to Mullingar. I’d simply hate to see you<lb/>at the races and not be able to steal a kiss or get a word in private with you<lb/>without people looking on and criticising. So will you please let me come down, love.<lb/>I’ll get Nora to help me buy something nice in the way of a glove but<lb/><hi rend="underline">let me know your size by Friday</hi> so that I can bring them with me. I<lb/>have very little news since I wrote to you yesterday you anything<lb/>I knew. The Accountant will not be back till Monday probably but he<lb/>will be in time to take over things for me. You mustn’t worry on that<lb/>score. I can always manage a day or two that way when I want. Remember<lb/>me to all and tell your mother not to be too hard on me for coming<lb/>down so soon but I can’t help it. Warmest and most enduring love for<lb/>my dearest and best   From your loving <lb/> <hi rend="underline">James</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>