<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5232">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate Allman to May Daly, 15 April 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate Allman</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/10/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5232</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0800">Kate Allman</persName>
              <date>1923-04-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0589">Mercy Convent, Waterford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0946">May Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5232_img_None_1"  url="667d4cc6323e3eb6a924b8fe65d81dd4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5232_img_None_2"  url="638aaf2cfb21e8fd175b04b6fd3dc50d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5232_img_None_3"  url="d22ab7b7fed22b7f646312ae0648db85.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5232_img_None_4"  url="927f5162bee2bd69eaf922adf256a6e9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5232_img_0_1"/>
              P41/10/2/3    Mercy Convent,<lb/>Waterford    15<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> April, '23    <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">May a chara mo chroide</seg></seg>   <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">Go raibh mile maith agat</seg></seg> for your<lb/>long letter which I received in due time also<lb/>your mother's. I was anxiously awaiting it but May<lb/>it made me very sad. Your cross indeed is a<lb/>heavy one your fondest &amp; dearest brother Taken from<lb/>you when you were certain That he was quite<lb/>safe and looking forward to his returning home<lb/>but May my dear he has returned to <seg type="unclear">his</seg><lb/>eternal home where  pain  trouble &amp; sorrow can<lb/>touch him no more. His last letter to you<lb/>where he said he'd be home when the flowers<lb/>were in full bloom Touched me very much - he is<lb/>a blooming flower himself now in the presence of<lb/>the Queen of Flowers. One thing May that has<lb/>stuck in my memory about Charlie. Do you remember<lb/>the evening yourself himself &amp; myself went down to the<lb/>cottage to see Bill &amp; returned rather late &amp;<lb/>remained talking by the fireside until after mid-<lb/>night; when we suggested going to bed, Charlie proposed 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5232_img_0_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline">2</hi><lb/>the Rosary and gave it out himself. If I said all<lb/>my Rosaries as well as that one I'd be alright<lb/>Our Lady of The Rosary won't forget him now<lb/>who was so faithful to her while on earth  Wasn't it an awful shock for you to get<lb/>the sad news in such a way, it reminded<lb/>me of the way in which Mrs. Dunne received<lb/>the news of her son after the shooting of Sir<lb/>Henry Wilson. I thought the least they might<lb/>do was to give the realtives a few days<lb/>notice.  I'll be overjoyed to get a copy of the<lb/>letters - the last he wrote on earth. Wasn't he<lb/>good to think of leaving you all a souvenir &amp;<lb/>to include me in the familly circle. May<lb/>darling don't send on the beads to me at<lb/>present as they may get lost, mother<lb/>will be coming to see me in May or<lb/>June &amp; perhaps you'll be able to give them<lb/>to her &amp; she'll bring them along. Every day<lb/>since I heard of his death I have offered<lb/>up my Mass &amp; Communion &amp; prayers for him       
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5232_img_0_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">3</hi>  al<hi rend="underline"></hi>though I'm sure May he does not require<lb/>them.  I didn't tell you how I heard the sad<lb/>news. Ellis O'Shea Listry was here to see<lb/>her brother &amp; came up to see me on the 16<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi><lb/>March, in the course of a conversation<lb/>she said; wasn't it sad about C. Daly.<lb/>Well May I couldn't say a word I<lb/>was simply stunned and I could not<lb/>believe it as only a few days<lb/>before that Michael was here &amp;<lb/>assured me that Ch. would be quite<lb/>safe.  MIss Crowe was here to see me but<lb/>as I was on distant Retreat I was only<lb/>able to stay with her a little time<lb/>She is a very nice girl &amp; like her father.  Now May you &amp; all the family<lb/>will be delighted to hear that I'll<lb/>be received on the 24<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi></hi> inst. We<lb/>are going on Retreat to-night.  &amp; I wont 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5232_img_0_4"/>
             <hi rend="underline">4</hi><lb/>forget you all in my prayers &amp; an<lb/>extra share will be said for him who<lb/>has gone to his reward. <seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign">Beannacht día<lb/>ar a anam</seg></seg>  How did your poor grand-mother<lb/>take the sad news. May God comfort<lb/>you all. Give my love to your mother<lb/>father &amp; all the others &amp; I hope some<lb/>day to see your mother. How is Susie<lb/>have you heard from the poor child.<lb/>Pray for me May dear I'll require<lb/>a lot of them now.  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">Abair le T. go mbeidh athas mór orm litir </seg></seg>  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">a bfuigidh uaidh; nuair a mbeidh sé saor abair </seg></seg>  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">leis teact anso má is feidir leis. Tá </seg></seg>  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">fios agat féin go mbeidh athas orm cainnt ubre </seg></seg>  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">aris mar do déan me fad ó acht ní orm </seg></seg>  <seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">atá an locth a Máire.</seg></seg>  <seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign"> Grádh diobh go léir </seg></seg>  <seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign">Cáit</seg></seg>       
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>