<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2647">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maria Duffin to Celia Duffin, 27 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maria Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

Maria Duffin writes her daughter Celia a chatty letter about the weather at home (dry and cold), about friends and family, as well as the Johnsons who have decorated their house which overlooks Hollywood hills. She also makes a reference to the fact that they are Unitarians.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2647</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2647_img_2072_1"  type="Letter"  url="ef6be508e3db085716b253c94570d6d0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2647_img_2072_2"  type="Letter"  url="d9556469869cbd2845a8182ff4a00e9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2647_img_2072_3"  type="Letter"  url="a9445d68b2c62bcf1cbba8cadbf10414.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2647_img_2072_4"  type="Letter"  url="2122b2a7f5bebafc8138a1f05bf2ee51.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2647_img_2072_5"  type="Letter"  url="8cf3a5f8e8a7ab15cb30769e1a4a7165.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2647_img_2072_1"/>
             D2109/10/1/B.   Dunowen,<lb/>Belfast.    Feb. 27, 1916.    Dearest Celia   I hear you have<lb/>had snow and now it has<lb/>come to us and is sleeting<lb/>at present. The dry cold of<lb/>the last few days is worse<lb/>than snow.  Sam and Ivan are over again.<lb/>Aunt Margaret is not well.<lb/>She was to have come for<lb/>tea yesterday with M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Finlay<lb/>but sent a message to say<lb/>she was in bed. I only<lb/>thought of her usual indigestion<lb/>but it appears this morning<lb/>there is something wrong<lb/>and D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Malcolm called in<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> <seg type="unclear">Kushi</seg>, who advises an 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2647_img_2072_2"/>
             operation towards the end of<lb/>the week. I do not know what<lb/>they think is wrong. Not<lb/>appendicitis; perhaps some tumour<lb/>I hope it will be all right.<lb/>but it makes one feel anxious<lb/>I suppose Marjorie will be<lb/>recalled, but have heard<lb/>no details. I will let you<lb/>know if there is anything<lb/>to tell later.  Your father &amp; Dorothy walked<lb/>down to see the Ewing's yester—<lb/>day. It is a great pity of poor<lb/>Minnie. Willie insists they<lb/>are ruined and never ceases<lb/>mourning and she poor<lb/>thing! has no-one to relieve<lb/>guard, or cheer her, in any<lb/>way. After being so ill too!   They finished up at the Days'<lb/>and saw his etchings, which<lb/>are very good. In the meantime<lb/>we had M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Finlay &amp; Kathleen<lb/>here for tea. James is ill<lb/>with rheumatism, so they<lb/>have no car. It must be<lb/>dull for them and, I think,<lb/>they were glad to come.  We tried to have M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Knox<lb/>&amp; Hugh Hamilton, for dinner<lb/>but both were engaged, so<lb/>the only guest was Barry.<lb/>Captain Jackson has been<lb/>sent to Cork and Evi Evans<lb/>son to Newry.  We saw the Johnston's house<lb/>on Monday; really very nice<lb/>prettily done up and quite<lb/>country in its look—out. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2647_img_2072_3"/>
             They got it all very prettily<lb/>done up and ready. Gwen<lb/>has a lovely room over the<lb/>smoking room, looking out over<lb/>the Hollywood hills.  We went to the <seg type="unclear">Red Cross</seg><lb/>works on Thursday, again,<lb/>with much the same results.<lb/>In addition to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> George Andrews<lb/>there was M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Bell of Whitethorne,<lb/>and D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Bell's wife (Miss <seg type="unclear">Hacks</seg>)<lb/>who has now taken the little<lb/>house, the Hut, where the<lb/>other Bells lived. M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Andrews<lb/>told me that poor Mrs Kirkpatrick<lb/>the dressmaker, has been dead<lb/>for some months; some internal<lb/>complaint. I feel quite sorry,<lb/>she was such a good, natural<lb/>creature. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2647_img_2072_4"/>
             D2109/10/1/B.  2   Dunowen,<lb/>Belfast.   I had nice letters from Clive<lb/>&amp; Emma. Both very cheery.<lb/>I have sent them to Standtown<lb/>and will afterwards send<lb/>them to you, via Molly as<lb/>I write to her next. I am<lb/>glad the girls were going<lb/>to the Bruces, MacLeods and<lb/>Garretts for holidays —  I had a nice letter of thanks<lb/>from the sister-in-charge and<lb/>she said you were very<lb/>useful and they were glad<lb/>to have you. I replied as<lb/>politely as possible.  I am glad you have made<lb/>some other acquaintances. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2647_img_2072_5"/>
             I suppose a Unitarian would<lb/>be worse than a<lb/>Roman Catholic to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><lb/>Thorpe! It is funny coming up<lb/>against the <seg type="unclear">Christie Millers.</seg><lb/>Emma shared a sleeping<lb/>compartment with Lady Dufferin<lb/>who was very kind.  The Aunts were in very good<lb/>form and pleased with<lb/>their tub and stand.<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi> Cormick brought the<lb/>manured pots of pink begonias<lb/>and we looked quite gay<lb/>but Peter was frightened<lb/>by the crackers and retired<lb/>to <seg type="unclear">'barlnet'</seg> trembling. I never<lb/>saw him daunted before.<lb/>I took him a walk yesterday<lb/>when Ruth and Helen  were at the canteen and he<lb/>was very good.  We are as dull as usual,<lb/>with no news. It is freezing<lb/>and the birds very glad of<lb/>crumbs.  Many thanks and<lb/>Much love from  Your own   Mammy  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>