<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5657">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Timothy Hegarty to Major J. Black, 9 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Timothy Hegarty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Timothy Hegarty, secretary of the Federation of Trade Unions of Cork and District Health Insurance Society to Major J Black. The letter concerns the injury of Patrick Sheehan (1879-?), a labourer who dislocated his ankle while carrying sacks at the Lee Mills. The letter goes on to state that Mr Sheehan has yet to receive compensation, stating that the society will take up a case on behalf of Patrick Sheehan if he is not paid compensation. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3785</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5657</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0997">Timothy Hegarty</persName>
              <date>1916-03-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1452">Grattan Street, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0216">J. Black</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0808">6 Lapp's Quay, Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5657_img_751_1"  type="Letter"  url="66d91697fdfcaddc1985165894918465.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5657_img_751_1"/>
            <lb/>The Federation <lb/>of Trade Unions of Cork and District <lb/>Health Insurance Society.  Grattan Street,   March, 9th, 1916.   <lb/><hi rend="underline">Copy</hi> <lb/>Major Black, <lb/>D. P. O. S.  6, Lapp's Quay.   Sir,   I am instructed by the Committee of above to write you <lb/>that the member of this Society by the name of Patrick Sheehan <lb/>of 14, Desmond's Square met with an accident while in the em- <lb/>ployment of the Government on Jan. 28th 1916 at the Lee Mills. <lb/>He has informed us that he has received no compensation from <lb/>you up to date. Please let me know what you intend doing with <lb/>this man. The Society will be reluctantly compelled to take <lb/>proceedings on this man's behalf if you cannot see your way <lb/>to pay him compensation while he is laid up through the accident.  <lb/>An early reply will oblige.  I remain, Sir, <lb/>Yours faithfully,   (SD.) Timothy Hegarty <lb/>Sec. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>