<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3168">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3168</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0342">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3168_img_2589_1"  type="Letter"  url="9b42134308b871fdcffdc1489a56510a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3168_img_2589_2"  type="Letter"  url="c9a62bc7b44cfcfdf72f3300027601b1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3168_img_2589_3"  type="Envelope"  url="ef7db288b702677b74bc8beb819d8834.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3168_img_2589_1"/>
              May 29th 1916 <lb/><lb/> Dear Katie, <lb/><lb/>I am sure you were expecting a letter from<lb/>me this long time. I had not the time for writing<lb/>as we were three days on the march + a weary time<lb/>it was too. I hope you did not send me any parcels<lb/>lately if you did they will get lost. At present I<lb/>am attached to no Divisions so do not write until you<lb/>hear from me again. We are having a rest first now<lb/>but I would rather be attached to some Division as time<lb/>hangs very heavy on me &amp; I have no money I hope we<lb/>will not be here long. I keep in the very best of health<lb/>&amp; we ate getting plenty to eat &amp; the weather is lovely<lb/>&amp; fine. I wrote to Paddy first before we started on<lb/>the march I hope he recieved it alright. I hope that<lb/>Sinn Fein Crowd are entirely wiped out of Ireland<lb/>now. They know by this time the strength of England &amp;<lb/>so will the huns when we start. I hope all<lb/>are well in the Paddock remember me to them all.<lb/>I think I could sleep out in the garden at home now<lb/>I have slept in a lot worse places out here. I have<lb/>no more to say at present I will write soon again.<lb/>I now say Good Bye &amp; May God Bless &amp; keep you all.<lb/> Good Bye. Peter Mooney  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3168_img_2589_2"/>
             You might send me a Postal Order<lb/>for 6 ./- as I might be here for some<lb/>time register it I may get it<lb/>sometime. My address<lb/>Pr. P. Mooney 101267: R.F.A.<lb/>No 6 Large Rest Camp<lb/>B. E. Fi France. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3168_img_2589_3"/>
            <lb/> Miss. K Mooney <lb/><seg type="unclear">Caulstown</seg> <lb/>Dunboyne <lb/>Co. Meath <lb/>Ireland. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>