<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5259">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 30, June, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell acknowledges receipt of a &#34;splendid&#34; parcel and reassures his mother that he has plenty of socks.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5259</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-06-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5259_img_None_1"  url="217a888f9736e1f6a58607f71d55f029.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5259_img_None_2"  url="01ed5723d1d3edddcc85fc7a121721a5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5259_img_0_1"/>
              30 June 1917    My dearest Mamy.   I did not think there would be<lb/>anything for me to write about<lb/>today but yesterday evening that<lb/>splendid parcel arrived. Really<lb/>you are absolutely the best that<lb/>ever ever lived and I do not know<lb/>how to thank you enough.  Everything was in perfect order.<lb/>bottle and all. You ask<lb/>me about socks. Well I have<lb/>more than enough of everything.<lb/>I have 6 pairs of heavy ones and<lb/>several of the light ones so I have<lb/>tons. There is not a sign of a<lb/>hole in any of them yet.  They are lasting wonderfully<lb/>I was also delighted to get<lb/>long letters from both you<lb/>and Daddy and Minnie<lb/>yesterday. We are living here 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5259_img_0_2"/>
             in absolute luxury. We carry<lb/>on with just the ordinary training.  There is a sort of heavy mist<lb/>today. There seems to be a change<lb/>in the weather.  Minnie had not much news but<lb/>seems to be eagerly looking<lb/>forward to her holidays.  You need not be<seg type="del">en</seg> thinking<lb/>about leave as there is no<lb/>possibility of it until well into<lb/>autumn. Fellows who came<lb/>out in January + earlier are only<lb/>now getting leave and even then<lb/>very few of them. Things are much<lb/>too busy for leave.  Now do not be expecting another<lb/>letter tomorrow as you know that I<lb/>am quite well and there is no<lb/>other news. With very best love from  Your most affec Son<hi rend="underline"></hi><hi rend="underline"><lb/>Willie</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>