<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2254">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to William Hovenden Ffolliott, 2  August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to William Hovenden Ffolliott (b. 1873). Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
This letter discusses Ffolliott&#39;s anticipated trip to England, stating that he should avoid speaking about Irish politics due to the difficulty of knowing what to say due to the political situation. The letter goes on to discuss Home Rule and a chance that it will be repealed stating that the Unionists should be heard if that is the case. The letter also discusses the down sides of the &#39;H. Plunkett Scheme&#39; (Horace Plunkett&#39;s aim of negotiating a settlement). Montgomery states that a council with a chief secretary would not work as there is a possibility the position may not be filled following the resignation of Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) while John Redmond (1856-1918), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, and Edward Carson (1854-1935), Unionist leader, cannot agree.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/51</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2254</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Hovenden Ffolliott</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2254_img_1698_1"  type="Letter"  url="652c787ca47ae64cbca4d58958832a3a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2254_img_1698_2"  type="Letter"  url="f76afe4c8f8ea27b36e9889bdb3764b2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2254_img_1698_1"/>
            Copy  2nd August, 1916.   Dear Miss ffolliott,   Thanks very much, I should like to see the article about <lb/> German sermons, and will send it on to Miss Strong promptly.   I am sorry you did not get the little change of air and <lb/> scene the trip to England would have given you; but in view of <lb/> the fact that when you go there, you are expected to hold forth <lb/> on Irish politics, and of the great difficulty of knowing what to say <lb/> at the present moment, perhaps it is as well that you did not <lb/> go. Does anybody know the true inwardness of the mind of the <lb/> British Elector? If there is any possibility of the Home Rule Act <lb/> being repealed, that is what we should go for as matters stand. <lb/> If there is any such possibility then I suppose it is unwise to <lb/> forfeit the chance of being heard with regard to the terms of an <lb/> Amended Act by absolutely refusing to consider the matter. Sir <lb/> H. Plunkett's scheme does not appear to me to have any points. <lb/> If a man can be found to govern Ireland as Chief Secretary, he <lb/> does not want a Council such as is suggested, and if a man cannot <lb/> be found the Council would be no use as Carson and Redmond cannot <lb/> possibly agree.    By dint of making the most of all the meetings I have to attend <lb/>on public business, I am promised rather more petrol than the <lb/> <sic>rediculous</sic> allowance they are giving you, but what they are giving <lb/> me is totally inadequate, and I am trying to get my case reconsidered. <lb/> I do, not, however, expect that it will be. One would not mind going
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2254_img_1698_2"/>
            without petrol if one did not see other people who deserve <lb/> less getting more.   We still have good news for our five soldiers.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>