<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0423">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Adams to Mary Adams, 13 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Adams</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John Adams (1890-1971) to his mother, Mary, explaining how he came to be injured at the front. John explains that due to an accidental discharge he was shot through the hand, however, he reassures his mother that he is recovering well. John enquires after the family and explains that he has not received any post and is anxious to hear of them. Before signing off John talks about the &#39;riots&#39; in Dublin during Easter Week, he notes that there is plenty of fighting to be done on the front rather than starting it at home.John Adams served with the 9th (Service) Battalion, Royal Irish Fusiliers in the Great War. He was wounded in France in May 1916, and was treated at the Royal Alexandra Hospital in Paisley.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Adams Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/423</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0271">John Adams</persName>
              <date>1916-05-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Adams</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0423_img_1791_1"  type="Letter"  url="62918d19d50f63ea40a325c2dd351d35.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0423_img_1791_2"  type="Letter"  url="10bcc55659bf17ae7aae535aba5e12e4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0423_img_1791_1"/>
                13.5.16    Somewhere in France   My Dear Mother,   Just a few lines, now that I am able to write <lb/> once more to let you know that I am getting on alright. Hoping <lb/> yourself and all at home are still keeping in your normal good <lb/> health. I suppose by this time you will think me dead. <lb/>but thank goodness I am still on the land of the living. After <lb/>I got wounded the Chaplin promised to write to you and tell you <lb/> and so did Jack. Did they do so. You see I have not got a letter since <lb/>then. And I may tell you many a time I wondered how youse <lb/>were getting on at Home. And many a time I was very sorry that <lb/> I could not write to let you know how I was doing. But as my <lb/>hand is getting alright, I will try and explain to you how it <lb/> happened. It was on Monday night the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> of May, and we were out <lb/>of the trenches at the time. But the Batt that we were doing <lb/> reserves to was supposed to be attacked, and we got orders to <lb/> go up to support them. It was about 10 oclock at night and very <lb/>dark. And when outside our quarters the order was given to <lb/> load up our rifles. So I happened to be rather late getting out, <lb/>and when I got out I was standing sideways to where the men were, <lb/>when one of them by accident let off a round. The bullet passing through <lb/>my rifle and exploding it in my left hand. The splinters tearing <lb/> the whole heart out of my hand. I had to go through two operations <lb/> for to get them out. It did feel sore I may tell you, but you  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0423_img_1791_2"/>
              not be uneasy as I am getting alright now. As I have the <lb/>worst of it over me. And it might have been far worse if I <lb/>had lost my hand. The weather is still keeping very wet now <lb/>it is simply pouring today. I suppose it is much the same at <lb/>home. How is Annie and Jimmy getting on, I am sorry I cannot <lb/>write to them as all my writing paper is in my rucksack and <lb/>this is all I have got with me. But I may tell you many a time <lb/>when lying here I thought often about youse all. And I did not <lb/>know how youse were doing as I did not get a letter from anyone <lb/>since I got wounded. That is nearly a fortnight today. I wish <lb/> my hand was better until I would get out again as I am fed up <lb/>knocking about, and not getting any letters to know how all <lb/>is getting on. I believe all the riots in Dublin is settled and <lb/> near time too. If they would come out here they would get <lb/>plenty of fighting to do, without starting at home. If the <lb/>poor fellows had the <seg type="unclear">Hour</seg> and stuff that they destroyed <lb/>out here they would be glad of it, but its as well that <lb/>they put an end to it. I think I must draw to a close as <lb/>my hand pains me still when I use it too much. Excuse the <lb/>horrible scribble. I now close hoping soon to hear from you <seg type="closer"> I remain, <lb/>Your Loving Son,  John Adams </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>