<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2250">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Hugo, 27 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to &#39;Hugo&#39;. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
In the letter Montgomery discusses Hugo&#39;s health. He goes on to discuss Irish politics and the loyalty of John Redmond (1856-1916), Irish Parliamentary Party leader, stating that while he acts loyal to the British government he winks to his followers in Ireland. Montgomery notes the loyalty of the followers of Edward Carson (1854-1935), Unionist leader, comparing the recruitment of Unionists and Nationalists into the British army. The state of the army and police force in Ireland is also reviewed in the letter, with Montgomery noting the loss of power by John Maxwell (1859-1929), commander-in-chief of Ireland, and the disillusionment of the army and the police due to the fact Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928), prime minster, visited the barracks in which injured Irish rebels were treated yet did not visit injured soldiers.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/48</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2250</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Stuart Hugo</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2250_img_1693_1"  type="Letter"  url="fcb0896cd076836dd2bb4a8534ad0b3b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2250_img_1693_2"  type="Letter"  url="c41292a928557113251c996f0569501c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2250_img_1693_3"  type="Letter"  url="a0a0a5c01a1ad2349fb9786c8836cc73.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2250_img_1693_4"  type="Letter"  url="901221522060070129f00127dd8e294c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2250_img_1693_1"/>
             27th June, 1916.   My dear Hugo,   I am very glad indeed to hear that you have started<lb/>going upstairs again. I did not worry about you to the extent<lb/>that your mother &amp; your wife did, as I was quite sure that you<lb/>would get due promotion in time; but I am glad that it has not<lb/>been longer delayed. I am inclined to think you had better<lb/>stick to your job &amp; leave Irish politics alone till the war<lb/>is over. If you had been in this country trying to do what<lb/>you could to make our rotten system of recruiting work, you<lb/>would not be so impressed with the loyalty of the official<lb/>Irish party. Of course one does not like to say publicly<lb/>what one thinks. It is no time to indulge in party polemics<lb/>however severely ones temper is tried. To us here it appears<lb/>that John Redmond made just as many speeches &amp; statements<lb/>as he though necessary in order to provide sufficient eye-wash<lb/>for the British elector, so that the repeal of the Home Rule<lb/>Act should not be his first demand after the war; but hardly<lb/>any of his followers did a hand's turn to help recruiting, &amp;<lb/>the results of such recruiting meetings as have been held drive<lb/>one to the conclusion that while he posed before the British<lb/>public as very loyal, he winked the other eye at his followers here.  Carson's followers provided a while division of very<lb/>good material, though they did not get very much encouragement<lb/>and were left with arms &amp; equipments for a long time after they 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2250_img_1693_2"/>
             -2-  <lb/>would have been otherwise ready to go. They have also provided<lb/>reserve battalions while the so-called Irish Divisions are<lb/>notoriously very short of Irish recruits, and unfortunate fellows<lb/>have been sent over from Wiltshire and other places in England<lb/>to fill the ranks. Of the Irishmen who are serving in the so-<lb/>called Irish Divisions (the 10th &amp; the 16th) a very substantial l<lb/>proportion are protestants and unionists; but Redmond &amp; Co<lb/>have braged of the doings of these divisions as if they were all<lb/>Nationalists. I got from one of the Chaplains the official<lb/>census of religions of the 10th Division which gives one a good<lb/>rough idea of the political constitution of it. I do not know<lb/>actually how matters stand in the 16th Division; but I believe<lb/>not far otherwise. At the last recruiting boom it was ascertained<lb/>that of the recruits obtained in Ulster just 3% were Nationalists<lb/>If we spoke publicly about this we should be help as incorrigible<lb/>bigots, &amp; accused of making little of the undoubted and con<lb/>spicuous gallantry of Irish Roman Catholic troops; but the other<lb/>side are allowed to claim credit for the distinguished conduct<lb/>of all Irishmen, as if all Irishmen were Home Rulers, &amp; we<lb/>must show no resentment.  Over and above all this Redmond's loyalty whatever it is<lb/>worth was strictly conditional at the beginning of the war. It<lb/>was conditional on the King being made to assent to agree to the<lb/>Home Rule Act being put on the Statute Book by a gross breach of<lb/>the party truce, and a Ulster Unionists, who, not<lb/>withstanding flocked to the colours. Redmond also expected his<lb/>advice 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2250_img_1693_3"/>
             -3-  <lb/>advice to be taken in the Government of Ireland. His advice<lb/>was taken, &amp; the taking of his advice was the direct cause of<lb/>the success such as it was that the Rebellion had. Now having<lb/>had a large share in bringing about the Rebellion he says that<lb/>result is that he cannot maintain his loyal attitude, or keep<lb/>up among his followers a loyal attitude during the rest of the<lb/>war unless Home Rule is brought into operation for at least<lb/>three-quarters of Ireland at once. The responsible &amp;<lb/>irreplaceable Government having said this was necessary the Ulster<lb/>Unionist Organization has agreed; but what the result to the<lb/>country of this direct encouragement to pro-German Rebellion<lb/>will be I do not know.  If appears that Sir John Maxwell's powers have already been<lb/>greatly curtailed, &amp; that whoever is carrying on the Government<lb/>has resorted to the old principle to snub loyalty &amp; vigorous<lb/>performance of duty, and reward the opposite. I hear the police<lb/>who on the whole behaved very well during the Rebellion are<lb/>rapidly becoming disaffected under the effects of this treatment,<lb/>&amp; the English soldiers in Dublin are in the worst possible temper<lb/>at various things that have happened, beginning with Anquith's visit<lb/>to the Barracks where there were wounded rebels &amp; wounded soldiers<lb/>and where he ostentatiously made much of the wounded rebels &amp;<lb/>did not as much as look at the wounded soldiers. I hope the next<lb/>Rebellion, which is not likely to be long delayed will not prove<lb/>a serious hindrance to winning the war; otherwise it might not be a 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2250_img_1693_4"/>
             -4-  <lb/>good thing for it to come soon as if the country had to be<lb/>reconquered it might lead to the establishment of a  <lb/>form of Government.   Is the 28th Battalion London Regiment, Artists and Rifles<lb/>in your army corps? as a supporter of mine at Aughnacloy named<lb/>Wright has a son in it - Private 5564 R. A. Wright, for whom he<lb/>wants a commission. He is a clerk in the India Office, London<lb/>and has been in the Officers Training Corps for some years.  I hope Hughie is in a moderately healthy place.  Yours Affectionately.    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>