<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2248">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Mr Glasgow, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to a Mr Glasgow. Montgomery was a lawyer and politician. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
This letter refers to advice given by Ulster Unionist leader Edward Carson (1854-1935). In the letter Montgomery comments that he does not believe the Unionists would have been able to get another leader if they rejected Carson. Montgomery then goes on to discuss getting in touch with the German agriculture co-operators to learn about co-operative agricultural credit. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/41</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2248</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mr Glasgow</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2248_img_1691_1"  type="Letter"  url="16a08d8af88eec70b7c9ed4faf202b12.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2248_img_1691_1"/>
            Copy  18th June, 1916.   Dear Mr. Glasgow,    Thanks for yours of the 17th.   Your points were very good ones, but could hardly have <lb/> been embodied in the resolutions without making them too long <lb/> and confused. I think we were well advised to follow <lb/> Sir E. Carson's advice. I don't see where we could get another <lb/> leader if we rejected him.    My chief object in getting in touch with the German <lb/> Agricultural Co-operators was to learn something about co- <lb/>operative Agricultural credit; but incidentally I picked <lb/> up information about other branches of Agricultural Co-operation. <lb/> I am sorry I have not time to go through my notes and indicate <lb/> where you will find what will interest you. As fas as I <lb/> recollect the question of whether there should be separate <lb/> Societies for each separate enterprise or not was an open <lb/> one in Germany; there being a good deal to be said on both <lb/> sides. The rules supplied to the Co-operative Dairy Societies <lb/> in this country by the I.A.O.S. were worded very widely as <lb/> regards objects and powers. I am sorry I have not time to go <lb/> into this question at present.   I am obliged to you for sending me your notes on <lb/>Bawn branch taxation. I hope I may find time to study <lb/> them.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>