<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3514">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peg O'Sullivan, Birmingham, to James Ryan, 2 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peg O&#39;Sullivan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.
The letter was written after Ryan&#39;s release from Frongach and refers to the prisoners who remained there. The writer sympathises with them as winter is coming and hopes they will be released when the British parliament resumes. The letter refers to others involved in the republican movement and mentions trips to Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/49(1)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3514</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0839">Peg O&#39;Sullivan</persName>
              <date>1916-10-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1191">99 Ashted Row, Birmingham, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3514_img_292_1"  type="Letter"  url="2da7b1635dceb7cc8b8a2d883d67cc2c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3514_img_292_2"  type="Letter"  url="b8bc31a89008bdc5aab9eec083019dcf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3514_img_292_3"  type="Letter"  url="dac7d01d3309e343eaa3d3150562c9ff.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3514_img_292_1"/>
             P88149(1)   99 Ashted Road,<lb/>Birmingham    October 2. 1916    My dear Jim,   Very many thanks<lb/>for letter received this morning<lb/>and so hasten to let you know<lb/>that I am still in the old spot.<lb/>It is indeed very good of you<lb/>to remember me for I am<lb/>sure you are very busy &amp;<lb/>have lots of correspondence.  We have been back<lb/>here since first week in<lb/>Sept and as you may guess<lb/>don't like it a bit. However<lb/>there is Xmas in the future<lb/>to keep our hearts up. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3514_img_292_2"/>
             We crossed over to Ireland on<lb/>the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> August &amp; spent the<lb/>29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> roaming about Dublin.<lb/>I left Kingsbridge on the 3 o'clock.<lb/>The others remained till later.<lb/>Peg &amp; Tess Williams saw you<lb/>in O'Connell St and were<lb/>overcome by a sudden fit of<lb/>shyness. I don't know what<lb/>came over them as they are not<lb/>usually given to that complaint.<lb/>My sister &amp; I were in Dublin<lb/>about the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> on our way<lb/>to Warrenpoint. We saw<lb/>all the sights of course.  You are very lucky to<lb/>be out of Frongoch. I think<lb/>they have not a very pleasant<lb/>
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3514_img_292_3"/>
            <!-- There seems to be a page missing --> Parliament opens, something<lb/>will happen. Do you hear from<lb/>B.Doheny? She had a<lb/>rather exciting time in 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/>last air raid. She was staying<lb/>a week-end in Woolwich &amp;<lb/>was thrown out   bed<lb/>violently. She   the Zepp<lb/>being brought   in flames.<lb/>We are expecting them here<lb/>in B'ham; at any rate the<lb/>streets are darkened enough.<lb/>It is horrible at night trying<lb/>to pick one's steps along &amp;<lb/>bumping &amp; (nearly) swearing.     Well, this is longer than<lb/>I intended but its an old<lb/>failing of mine; so please<lb/>excuse it. Hoping that you<lb/>are well.   Yours V. sincerely<lb/>Peg O'Sullivan 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>