<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1986">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to the Chief Secretary, 9 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to the chief cecretary of Ireland from an unspecified sender. While the letter is address to the Chief Secretary, there was in fact no active Chief secretary at the date the letter was written. This is due to the fact that Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) resigned on 3 May 1916 following his administrational failure during the 1916 Rising, While Henry Duke (1855-1939) did not assume the position until 30 June 1916. The author of the letter discusses his own nationalistic views, however warns of the Ancient Order of Hibernians, stating that they are just as bad as Sinn Féin. He goes on to claim that Joe Devil (1871-1934) started up the society in Belfast, going on to say that there are more Eenians in the AOH than in Sinn Fein. The author then describes how he believes the society governs Ireland, accounting the process for election within the society. He then goes on to warn that they will take charge when and if Home Rule is granted. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5611/7861/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1986</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-05-09</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Chief Secretary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0890">Dublin Castle</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1986_img_1433_1"  type="Letter"  url="65633758bd31ad47395ea2c181452d4a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1986_img_1433_2"  type="Letter"  url="c65de272ced956b1f1f24af352336fa1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1986_img_1433_3"  type="Letter"  url="32a319fd89eb5b778139f26932ca12c1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1986_img_1433_1"/>
            <!-- the first part of marginal note is obscured by treasury tag used to keep pages together --> law of Ireland<lb/>&amp; who made by &amp;<lb/>none other recognized<lb/>The<lb/>Hibernian Law   May 9<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>1916 <lb/><!-- receipt stamp --><lb/>CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>7861 - 10 MAY 1916<lb/>OFFICE<lb/><lb/>Sir as you now have taken charge of Ireland after<lb/>the lamentable occurrence of murder which the Shin Fein has being<lb/>guilty of (well) respectable wise men knew it would come to<lb/>that with virtually no Government in Ireland I am an Nationalist<lb/>&amp; Roman Catholic now a conservative how many more like me now<lb/>in Ireland hundreds of thousands has got enough of home rule<lb/>(there is another body of men or a so called society known as<lb/>the Hibernians just as bad as the <sic>Shin Fainers</sic> &amp; more of the old<lb/>school of Fenians among them in fact they started under Joe Devlin<lb/>in Belfast as Fenian organization or what was left of the old<lb/>Fenian organization <hi rend="underline">but </hi>they wanted to give themselves a decent<lb/>name &amp; they changed it to be called <seg type="unclear">Hibernianisms</seg>and there is not<lb/>an old Fenian in Ireland is not in that organization who works<lb/>on the Fenian lines &amp;principals behind the curtain it is helping<lb/>the Government now by the way because it knows it was the<lb/>Government in Ireland for the past 10 years as there was no real<lb/>Government except in name &amp;what astonished every decent man<lb/>was under the assurance act they got a society to help<lb/>them in their game  How does the Hibernians<lb/>govern they have a Hall in every Town &amp;village in Ireland<lb/>&amp;they makes the laws for their district there<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1986_img_1433_2"/>
             <seg type="del">the   </seg> a man first has to be sworn in by a  <lb/>oath then pay his subscription he must not have previously<lb/><sic>being</sic> in any government employment for fear of being tricked<lb/>an letting the cat out of the bag as the term it. Then the new<lb/>member is told all he will have to do and how he will be<lb/>paid if he is in business all members of the society will have<lb/>to deal with him &amp;any member of the society dealing or leaving<lb/>money with an <sic>un</sic> member is to be boycotted quietly but<lb/>firmly all public situations is to go to Hibernian members<lb/>county and district Councillors to be notified to the results<lb/>of what will follow if they vote against the Hibernian candidates<lb/>and I may tell you God help the county or district<lb/>Councillor would do so at present in most districts<lb/>in Ireland. Again when large meetings attends towns<lb/>notices are to be put in windows that they will know<lb/>the houses to call in and all members will have a pass<lb/>word that they will know each other. <seg type="unclear">Limerick</seg> was their<lb/>password three years ago. <seg type="unclear">To pull</seg>along with the government<lb/>to see will Redmond succeed to get the Irish parliament<lb/>then they the Hibernians will take charge of it in the same<lb/>manner as we have charge of most district &amp; county<lb/>councils now. If Redmond does not get the Irish Parliament<lb/>or the imperial government interferes with us we will<lb/>have a strong army to fight our corner. This is the<lb/>Hibernian programme. I know a certain district council<lb/>in Ireland within those two  bought a plot of town<lb/>parks from a landlord at £300 for cottages but one time<lb/>an Hibernian officer had the use of the ground &amp; always<lb/>grazed it for 10 years without rent or taxes so now this<lb/>Hibernian officer that grazed the land sent for the district<lb/>council &amp;they went down on their knees to him to not have<lb/>a them boycotted so the ratepayers lost the £300<lb/>   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1986_img_1433_3"/>
            <!-- addressed envelope--> The Chief Secretary  <lb/> Dublin Castle <lb/> Ireland <lb/>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>