<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5310">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Earls to the staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, 11 March 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Earls</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Forwards a letter of thanks written by Mr Vincent G. Forth. Forth expresses gratitude on the part of his mother, himself, and his siblings for a motion passed by the staff in memory of Francis C. Forth. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5310</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0494">John Earls</persName>
              <date>1919-03-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1851">Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1851">Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5310_img_None_1"  url="91bc6455c412310160802169942942c1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5310_img_0_1"/>
              Municipal Technical Institute,<lb/>BELFAST :  11th March 1919,   MEMO from Vice-Principal<lb/>To<lb/>Members of Staff.  With reference to the Asselution of sympathy with<lb/>Mrs. Forthand family in their recent sad bereavement which was<lb/>passed at the Meeting of the Institute Staff on Monday, 3rd<lb/>March, 1919, I beg to forward the following letter of thanks<lb/>which has been received in reply fromMr. Vincent G. Forth.   Ravenwood,<lb/>Knockbreda Park, BELFAST.<lb/>5th March 1919.    Dear Professor Earls, <lb/>On behalf of my Mother I wish to thank you for<lb/>your letter of 3rd inst., enclosing copy of the Resolution<lb/>passed at the Meeting of the Permanent Staff and the Occasional<lb/>Teachers of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast.  My Mother is deeply touched by the expression of<lb/>sympathy extended to her, in her great sorrow and bereavement,<lb/>by the Institute Staff and will be most grateful if you will be<lb/>good enough to convey to them her heartfelt thanks: at the same<lb/>time expressing my own thanks and those of my sisters and brother.  My Mother takes this opportunity of expressing her<lb/>deep appreciation of the most beautiful floral tribute sent by<lb/>the Institute Staff.   Yours sincerely,<lb/>(Sd). VINCENT G. FORTH.    Professor Earls,<lb/>Municipal Technical Institute,<lb/>BELFAST <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>