<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2702">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to Maria Duffin, 28 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Olive Duffn to her mother, Maria (1854 – 1954), informing her about the time she has spent with her sisters and her communication with her father. 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/34</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2702</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2125">7 West Cliff, Eastbourne, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2702_img_2122_1"  type="Letter"  url="5a175db7c55cd62223710ff55e2bba3e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2702_img_2122_2"  type="Letter"  url="046a150261b561e704bfefa767126940.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2702_img_2122_1"/>
              D2109/10/1/C    1.West Cliff.    28<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th </hi></hi>March.1916    My dearest Mamma,   I got Emma's wire on Saturday. I went<lb/>up to her by an early train on Sunday morning I<lb/>arrived at the Strand Palace to find Celia just departing<lb/>back to Hospital. You will probably see Emma before<lb/>you get this as she is crossing to-night: She looks<lb/>very   &amp; flourishing. We had a great chat &amp; spent<lb/>most of the time talking! There was not much else to<lb/>do on Sunday &amp; it was very cold too. Dorothy turned<lb/>up on Sunday evg &amp; we all stayed the night &amp; she was<lb/>staying last night too. I met some of E.s V.A.D.<lb/>friends &amp; we went to a Nurses' Hospital in Vincent<lb/>Square to visit a sick one &amp; there was a nice sister<lb/>there who told me Emma had done splendidly.<lb/>It was nice to see them all &amp; have a little change of<lb/>scene &amp; hear some chat. Dorothy is coming down<lb/>here on Sat. night. Miss Roberts talks of giving<lb/>her household a holiday &amp; herself a change by moving<lb/>into the Grand Hotel for a fortnight. She has<lb/>asked May Darbyshire to stay with her &amp; would not<lb/>want me so I may have that time on my hands<lb/>about the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, &amp; don't know quite what to do  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2702_img_2122_2"/>
             with it, but her plans are always liable to change <lb/>so I don't plan much.   I heard from Papa yesterday, don't let him come <lb/>over till the weather is better it was very cold in <lb/>London &amp; on the way down here yesterday evening more <lb/>guns &amp; an awful storm last night. I am glad <lb/>he is feeling better. You will enjoy having Emma <lb/>back &amp; hearing all her news. I enclose a letter <lb/>from Terry which came yesterday.   Why would not Papa offer himself to the Edges  Sir John Edge  for <lb/>a visit &amp; then he would not be very far from here.   Dorothy is trotting round different addresses etc. <lb/>but not finding much success. I think good jobs <lb/>for pay are as difficult as ever to get, &amp; long <lb/>hours &amp; poor pay the rule. I am glad she has her <lb/>small independence now which makes it unnecessary <lb/>to accept the first one can get.   I am anxious to hear about Marjorie. Is Miss <lb/>Isabella better.   Much love to all, <lb/>Your loving   Olive 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>