<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5308">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Staff of the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, to the family of Captain Francis C. Forth 3 March 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Earls</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Tribute to Francis C. Forth from the members of staff of the Municipal Technical Institute.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5308</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0494">John Earls</persName>
              <date>1919-03-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None"> the family of Captain Francis C. Forth</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5308_img_None_1"  url="ab71cc8814c4fc2b0f73ce5eb0a6c318.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5308_img_None_2"  url="707a8d4c7635db2835f81c4356b34d2a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5308_img_0_1"/>
              3rd March, 1919    MUNICIPAL TECHICAL INSTITUTE, BELFAST   <hi rend="underline">The late Captain Fras. C. FORTH.</hi>  Tribute from the Members of the Staff of the<lb/>Municipal Technical Institute.  A meeting of the Members of the Staff of the Municipal<lb/>Technical Institute was held on Monday evening the 3rd inat., to<lb/>testify to their sorrow at the death of the late Principal,<lb/>Captain Forth, and to express their sympathy with the Members of<lb/>the bereaved family.  The chair was taken by Professor Earls, B.A. Vice-<lb/>Principal of the Institute.  There was a very full attendance of Members of the Staff.<lb/>Letters of apology from Members who were unavoidably unable to be<lb/>present were read by Mr. H. H. Dunlop, Registrar.  Professor Earls in announcing the object of the meeting<lb/>stated that there had been held in the past many meetings of the<lb/>Staff, and on at least one other occasion a meeting of a somewhat<lb/>similar character - on the occasion of the death of the late<lb/>Sir Jas. Henderson, the first Chairman of the Library and Technical<lb/>Inatruction Committee. But no meeeting had ever before been held<lb/>to mark an event which had so intimately and profoundly affected<lb/>the Staff and indeed the whole life of the Institute as had the<lb/>death of its first Principal Captain Fras. C. Forth, whose mind is<lb/>expressed in every room of this immense building and in every<lb/>feature of its complex and afficient organisation.  The following Resolution was submitted to the Meeting -<lb/>RESOLVED  That we the Members of the Permanent Staff and<lb/>the Occasional Teachers of the Municipal Technical Institute,<lb/>Belfast, in meeting assembled, place on record our deep regret and<lb/>sorrow at the death of Captain F. C. Forth, the late Principal of<lb/>this Institute.  Since the inception of the Technical Instruction Scheme<lb/>in Belfast more than eighteen years ago he has unaparingly devoted  -1-    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5308_img_0_2"/>
             his outsanding powers of organisation, his wide knowledge<lb/>of educational affairs and his brilliant mental gifts to the<lb/>planning, erecting, equipping and organising the great<lb/>Institute which will always be his chief and most fitting<lb/>monument.  We also wish to express our admiration for, and<lb/>appreciation of, the impartiality, justice and consideration<lb/>which he always evinced in his dealings with the Staff.  We respectfully extend our most sincere sympathy<lb/>to his widow and family in the great bereavement they have<lb/>sustained.  In proposing the Resolution Mr. Dawson, Headmaster<lb/>of the School of Art, referred to his association with Captain<lb/>Forth from the very beginning of the work of the Institute.<lb/>He spoke of the numerous and manifold difficulties which had<lb/>to be overcome in the early stages of the develpoment of the<lb/>scheme of technical instruction and of the great pleasure it<lb/>had been to Captain Forth to see the work develop and prosper.<lb/>He also referred feelingly to the great loss that had been<lb/>sustained by Captain Forth's family.  Mr. Joe Boyce in seconding the Resolution said<lb/>that he had been on eof the first teachers to be engaged on the<lb/>Occasional Teaching Staff of the Municipal Technical Institute,<lb/>and he testified to the great loss which education in Belfast<lb/>and throughout Ireland had sustained by Captain Forth's death.<lb/>He also referred Captain Forth to those who were privileged to be<lb/>associated with him in the great work of the Technical Institute.  The following also paid tributes of respect to the<lb/>memory of the late Principal - Mesare W. Davidson, J. H. Cox,<lb/>G. Gayton, J. Johnston and R. T. Hewitt.  The Resolution was passed in silence the members<lb/>standing. <seg type="del">After which the meeting concluded. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>