<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0129">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James McFadden Brown to Inspector General, Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain, 5 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James M&#39;Fadyen Brown</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by James McFadden Brown (b.1879), a clerk at the Royal Irish Constabulary office, to the inspector general. The letter is Brown&#39;s reply to the Chief Secretary of Ireland, Augustine Birrell (1850-1933), requiring information about Brown&#39;s whereabouts from 24 April to 1 May 1916. Brown states that he attempted to report to the office after hearing that Dublin Castle had been taken by the rebels.The letter was addressed to Inspector General Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain (1856-1944). Chamberlain held the position from 1900 until his resignation in July 1916, making him the second longest serving inspector general in the force&#39;s history.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/24041916/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/129</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0702">James M&#39;Fadyen Brown</persName>
              <date>1916-05-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0205">Neville Francis Fitzgerald Chamberlain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0129_img_1215_1"  type="Letter"  url="3aa8ef71d50fdae32503bc7558b1aee1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0129_img_1215_1"/>
                R.I. Constabulary Office.   Dublin Castle.   The Inspector General,   In reply to the Chief Secretary's <lb/>communication of 1st inst regarding my <lb/>movements, etc. , from noon on 24.4.16 to <lb/> noon on 1.5.16, I beg to report as follows: -   22.4.16. On duty at R.I.C. Office until 1 p.m. <lb/> Returned to private residence (Seapoint House , <lb/>Monkstown) until 4 p.m. Spent the evening <lb/> in the City.  23.4.16. Spent in Monkstown &amp; immediate <lb/> vicinity  24.4.16. - Do. -   25.4.16. Went to the City to report at the Office <lb/>but heard the Castle was held by the <lb/>rebels. Returned to Monkstown at 3 p.m. <lb/> for remainder of the day.   26.4.16 Went to the City but was informed <lb/>by Mr Cooney of R.I.C. Office that no <lb/> business was being transacted. Returned <lb/>to Monkstown about 3 p.m. for remainder of the day.  27.4.16 Spent in Monkstown and immediate vicinity.  28.4.16. - Do. -   29.4.16.Went to the City but informed by <lb/> Mr <seg type="unclear">Cooney</seg> of R.I.C. Office that no <lb/>business was being transacted. Returned <lb/> to Monkstown about 1 p.m. for remainder of the day.   30.4.16. Spent in Monkstown and immediate <lb/>vicinity.   1.5.16. - Do. -   On each of these nights I slept at <lb/><seg type="del">Blackrock</seg>Seapoint House, Monkstown. <seg type="closer"> Jas. Mc F Brown   5th May '16.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>