<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2598">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O’Farrell to W.D. O’Kelly, 8 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O’Farrell </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Sir. Edward O&#39;Farrell (c.1857-1926), the assistant under-secretary to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1973-1939). The letter is addressed to William Declan O&#39;Kelly (d. 1968), a pathologist at the Department of Pathology and Bacteriology at UCD. After the Irish Civil War O&#39;Kelly carried out the post-mortem examination on the remains of Noel Lemass. He subsequently served for a time as the Irish representative to the World Health Organisation.

The letter of 8 March is a follow-up to an earlier letter from Edward O’Farrell. In this letter, O&#39;Farrell queries some of the detail in O&#39;Kelly&#39;s Return of Experiments for the year 1915. As a person licensed to carry out experiments on animals, O’Kelly was obliged to furnish an annual Return of Experiments. 

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/3500</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2598</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1471">Edward O’Farrell </persName>
              <date>1916-03-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1421">W.D. O’Kelly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0764">Department of Pathology and Bacteriology, School of Medicine, Cecelia Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2598_img_2023_1"  type="Letter"  url="34c2218cc6f6a8ae307f1435e58c289f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2598_img_2023_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="e8a1356ae437389ad6ea92f3a7967e5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2598_img_2023_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="bc5658ab8592b67004905e4bc922e161.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2598_img_2023_1"/>
             Any reply to this communication should<lb/>bee addressed to:—<lb/>THE UNDER SEECRETARY,<lb/>DUBLIN CASTLE,<lb/>and the following number quoted,<lb/>3500.   CHIEF SECRETARY'S OFFICE,<lb/>DUBLIN CASTLE    8th March, 1916.    IMMEDIATE    Sir    <hi rend="underline">To be returned</hi>   With reference to the attached Return, I am directed<lb/>by the Chief Secretary to point out that Table 2 thereof<lb/>shows 124 experiments performed by you during the year 1915<lb/>as against 106 recorded in Tables 1 and 3.   I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,<lb/>E O'Farrell <lb/> W.D.O'Kelly, Esq., M.B.,<lb/>Department of Pathology and Bacteriology,<lb/>School of Medicine,<lb/>Cecilia Street,<lb/>Dublin.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2598_img_2023_2"/>
              2654<lb/>IMMEDIATE.    Dublin Castle, <lb/> 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> February, 1916.    Sir, <lb/>I am directed by the Chief Secretary to request that you will state on<lb/>the enclosed form:—<lb/>(1) The number of experiments on living animals performed by you in<lb/>the year ended 31st December last, under licence granted to you<lb/>under the Act 39 and 40 Vic., cap. 77, or an special certificate<lb/>you may have held during the year;<lb/>(2) The general purpose of the experiments; and<lb/>(3) The number of those experiments in which there was reason to<lb/>believe that any appreciable pain was inflicted, specifying the<lb/>kind of animal used and stating in general terms the nature of<lb/>the experiment that occasioned pain.  All experiments under Certificate C must be performed with anaesthetics,<lb/>and it should be stated in your Return that the animals used were killed before<lb/>recovery from anaesthesia.  I have also to request that you will furnish in Table 4 of the form<lb/>enclosed a complete list of any writing based upon experimental work which<lb/>you may have published during the past year, giving the full title of each<lb/>paper with an exact reference to any periodical in which it may have appeared,<lb/>and the name of any Society to which it may have been communicated, and<lb/>that if you have not already done so, you will forward copies of such papers<lb/>for the information of the Chief Secretary.  As it is desirable that the preparation of the Parliamentary Return<lb/>relating to Experiments on Living Animals should be undertaken at once, your<lb/>Return should be furnished  within on week .  Your licence under the Act will expire on the <seg type="del">28th</seg> 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> instant. If you desire<lb/>its renewal an application to that effect should be made stating the grounds.<lb/>The licence should at the same time be forwarded.   I am,<lb/>Sir,<lb/>Your obedient Servant,<lb/> E O Farrell   <lb/> W.<seg type="unclear">I</seg>. Wilson, Esq, M.D.<lb/>Queen's University,<lb/>Belfast  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2598_img_2023_3"/>
             <lb/>RETURN of Experiments performed in the Year 1915 by the holder of<lb/><hi rend="underline">Licence No. 81</hi> <!-- table not transcribed --><lb/>Signature, W.D. O'Kelly<lb/>Date, 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February '16. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>