<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1526">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Laurence Ginnell to Nancy O'Rahilly, 28 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Laurence Ginnell </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Laurence Ginnell (1852-1923) to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). Ginnell thanks Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly for information supplied and asks for more from her and her friends. He describes his own grief on learning of the death of Mr. O&#39;Rahilly. He goes on to tell Mrs. O&#39;Rahilly about two &#39;schemes&#39; with which he is involved: one to publish an account of the &#39;facts&#39; of the insurrection and another to create a dependent&#39;s fund.Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later. Laurence Ginnell was an Irish Nationalist politician and MP in the House of Commons as a member of the Irish Parliamentary Party.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/36</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1526</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0217">Laurence Ginnell </persName>
              <date>1916-05-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0283">51 Queens Road, Richmond, Surrey, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1526_img_987_1"  type="Letter"  url="334cfc6da99941f490c1fcdf7e6d7d4f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1526_img_987_2"  type="Letter"  url="f0c31ed65ea656810ce04c00aabd3fcc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1526_img_987_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">28 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, 1916 </hi>    51, QUEEN'S ROAD,  RICHMOD,  SURREY.   Dear Madame O'Rahilly,   Your note now received <lb/> will have my immediate attention, as well <lb/> as any further facts that you or any friends <lb/> are good enough to send me.   I feared to write to you during the terrible <lb/> time that has passed, feeling that it would <lb/> be an intrusion amounting to desecration. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Of late</seg> needless to say, my heart bleeds for you. <lb/> I watched the papers closely during the early <lb/> days, looking for a certain name. At length <lb/> it <sic>appeard</sic>, first in the <hi rend="underline">Globe</hi>, and I thought my <lb/> heart would break. The soul of frankness and <lb/> chivalry in the bloom of youth cut off. I was <lb/> alone Mrs G. being in Ireland unable to return here.   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1526_img_987_2"/>
              No on to speak to who could understand. <lb/> When at length she returned, I threw myself <lb/> on her lap and cried bitterly. English servants <lb/> thought I had gone mad. 'My poor dear <lb/> O'Rahilly dead. So manly, so grand looking, <lb/> so grander still in manner and at heart.'   If I suffered so, God alone knows <lb/> how much you must have suffered. <lb/> there is, of course, the vast consolation that <lb/> he laid down his life in the cause and in <lb/> the manner that makes him immortal to <lb/> our race. It would be terrible if no <lb/> photograph remained of one who was so <lb/> dearly loved by countless thousands. <lb/> We must do all we can to avert that.   I wish you to know about two <lb/> schemes we have in hands, so that you <lb/> may give us the benefit of any suggestions <cb/> that occur to you, and may mention <lb/> them to friends willing to co-operate.   1. We want as soon as possible, all <lb/> authentic facts of the insurrection, while they are <lb/> fresh in the minds of witnesses, to have a <lb/> connected narrative codified by a competent <lb/> hand, done in English, French, Spanish, etc. <lb/> and circulated all over the world; to <lb/> counteract the lies of the enemy.   2. We are energetically organising the <lb/> collection of a friend in London and throughout <lb/> Britain for relief of dependants of all sufferers <lb/> but especially of those whose men are dead, <lb/> and  who <seg type="del">what</seg> will neither get nor take from any <lb/> other source.   We are trying to get a committee formed <lb/> in Dublin for each of those great purposes.  <seg type="closer">With deepest sympathy from Mrs. Ginnell <lb/> and myself, I remain, Dear Madam O'Rahilly  Sincerely yours  L. Ginnell </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>