<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1093">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 12 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sir Arthur Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) responding to the issues raised by the Joint Committee regarding registration of Irish Nurses by the College of Nursing.Sir Arthur Stanley was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>TPCK-2-6-1-5, TPCK-2-6-1-5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1093</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0219">Sir Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-05-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1093_img_3244_1"  type="Letter"  url="9d9d10728932fa9a98827f357512f451.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1093_img_3244_1"/>
                The College of Nursing, Limited. 95 Pall Mall, London, S.W.   Dear Sir,   I am glad to learn that the letter and documents I sent you <lb/>are receiving the consideration of the Royal <sic>Coleges</sic> and the Heads of <lb/>the Nursing Profession in Ireland, and I now reply to the points raised <lb/>in your communication of the 26th ultimo.   You are right in supposing that there will be an English, <lb/>Scotch and Irish section of Nurses on the Register 'according to the <lb/>postal addresses of the Nurses, as they stand in the Register.' A Nurse <lb/>will presumably see that the address which stands against her name in <lb/>the Register — which address may, of course, be varied at her request <lb/>from time to time — corresponds to the place in which she is living and <lb/>working. For example, an <seg type="del">d</seg> English—trained Nurse working in Dublin would <lb/>give Dublin as her address, just as an Irish—trained Nurse working in <lb/>England, and with interests in England, might give an English address. <lb/>The privilege of nominating candidates for the Irish representation on <lb/>the Council is reserved to Nurses with Irish addresses in the Register, <lb/>but every Nurse registered has as many votes as there are vacancies for <lb/>the Council, and may divide her votes amongst the English, Scotch and <lb/>Irish candidates, just as she chooses. She may give one vote to one or <lb/>any number of candidates, just as she chooses. She may give one vote to one or <lb/>any number of candidates as she will, but not more votes in all than there <lb/>are vacancies, and not more than one vote to any one candidate.   As regards your second point, I should remind you that the <lb/>Memorandum of Association is drawn <seg type="del">up</seg> so as to include every possible <lb/>alternative, and to allow the fullest liberty of notion. Hence it would <lb/>be possible to admit to the General Register persons qualified by an <lb/>examination test only, but I cannot say that so far as I know the opin— <lb/>ions of the Council, there is the least intention of relying on and exam— <lb/>ination test only, without training in a recognised School. Further the <lb/>government and policy of the College are commited to the Members of it; <lb/>Membership is confined to those on that Register, and a Nurse cannot get <lb/>a footing on the Register unless she has a certificate of <hi rend="underline">general</hi><lb/>training, or being a Nurse already in practice is admitted under <lb/>qualifications which have already been laid down by the Council. <lb/>Training in Special Branches does not in itself carry Membership, though <lb/>it may be allowed to count as some part of the recognised curriculum.   I hope that this explanation clears up the points you raised, <lb/>but I repeat what I have said elsewhere, that the Memorandum and Articles <lb/>of Association have been drafted so as to leave the widest possible <lb/>discretion to the executive, which itself can act only when it has <lb/>sought advice from the local Boards and from the Consultative Board. At <lb/>present the registration of existing Nurses is making great demands upon <lb/>the time of Members of the Council and the Registration Bill is also <lb/>claiming great attention. The very important questions of uniformity in <lb/>curriculum, of the recognition of Training Schools, and of the type and <lb/>standard of the qualifying examination <seg type="del">s</seg> have still to be considered.   We look to the assistance of the Irish Board, as of the <lb/>Scotch Board, in the solution of these and other problems which lie <lb/>before the College.  <seg type="closer"> I am, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully,  (signed) Arthur Stanley.   T. Percy C. Kirkpatrick, Esq., M.D., F.R.C.P.I.    December 5th, 1916.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>