<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0837">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maud Joynt to Dr Kathleen Lynn, 28 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maud Joynt</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Maud Joynt (1868-1940) to Dr Kathleen Lynn (1874-1955). Joynt offers her thoughts and sympathy to Dr Lynn, imprisoned after the Rising, and suggests that Lynn may soon face deportation. Joynt discusses the Easter Rising, stating her support for the aims of the insurrection&#39;s leaders but doubting &#39;that they chose the best means of advancing their cause&#39;. Maud Joynt was a Celtic scholar and linguist, a holder of Bachelor&#39;s and Master&#39;s degrees in modern literature, and an advocate for women&#39;s access to higher education and employment.Dr Kathleen Lynn was a medical practitioner, a suffragist, a nationalist, and a revolutionary. Lynn was Chief Medical Officer of the Irish Citizen Army during Easter 1916, and was a part of the City Hall garrison, of which she took command of the garrison after the death of Seán Connolly on the first day of the Rising. After independence, Lynn played a major role in improving public health, playing a significant role in the eradication of tuberculosis in Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Br. Allen Collection, IE/AL/KL/1/18</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/837</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1221">Maud Joynt</persName>
              <date>1916-05-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0115">21 Annesley Park, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1086">Kathleen Lynn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1681">Kilmainham Gaol, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0837_img_2390_1"  type="Letter"  url="74c8f6908b0eee56862bf6d7bda4b131.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0837_img_2390_2"  type="Letter"  url="f8b1821a30221a0b3f89678bc52a7124.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0837_img_2390_1"/>
                21 Annesley Park,  Rathmines,    May 28 1916   My dear Dr. Lynn,   I was at Mountjoy last Thursday afternoon &amp;<lb/> saw Miss Moloney &amp; from her I learnt that your future<lb/> movements are still undecided, but that there is some pro<lb/> spect of your leaving Dublin or at any rate your present quarters <lb/> before long. As I may not be able to see you, I am going<lb/> to write a few lines just to tell you that I have often thought<lb/> of you during these troubled times &amp; have felt deep sympathy<lb/> with you. I do not want to say anything about recent events, for <lb/> tough I am quite able to sympathise with some of the aims of<lb/> the leaders in the movement. I cannot believe that they chose<lb/> the best means of advancing their cause. But I do not for a <lb/> moment doubt the purity &amp; disinterestedness of their motivesâ<lb/> at least those of them whom I know anything of â &amp; I admire<lb/> their courage; &amp; I can <hi rend="underline">never </hi> forget that they loved Ireland.<lb/> As for you , nothing that has happened has altered my<lb/> opinion of your character or lessened the admiration I<lb/> have always felt for you. Perhaps to be honest, I should<lb/> say that I have changed my opinion in one particular; I <lb/> always believed you to be a woman of strong common sense,<lb/> &amp; I am beginning to doubt that now. But though common<lb/> sense is a valuable quality in everyday life &amp; a substitute  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0837_img_2390_2"/>
              for nearly all the virtues (at least I notice that the people<lb/> who possess it in a high degree get credit for virtues<lb/> whether they have then or not), I really think I like you<lb/> better since finding that you haven't so much of it as I<lb/> once thought. If you have made a mistake (which is not<lb/> for me to decide), you will find it out yourself &amp; be all<lb/> the better for it: for I believe that the mistakes we make<lb/> with honest intentions are often the greatest use to us<lb/> afterwards &amp; the people who never make any are not the<lb/> wisest. <seg type="closer"> Goodbye &amp; love from<lb/> your friend,  Maud Joynt </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>