<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4158">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Terence Duffin to his father Adam Duffin, 10 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Terence Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by Major Terence (Terry) Duffin (1886 - 1936), to his father Adam Duffin (1841 – 1924). 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B//9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4158</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0305">Terence Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0513">Adam Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1936</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_1"  type="Letter"  url="64dcb73063a7c0386f8a0a9958048128.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_2"  type="Letter"  url="3f62ceba8e0e8ccdb3ca2873570fcb5d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_3"  type="Letter"  url="6d023e4376f5d2bd890b56726897c3a1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_4"  type="Letter"  url="e104a0f86616ff96049f9988a4285145.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_5"  type="Letter"  url="90883ceede493abc03a7edbd2748c530.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_6"  type="Letter"  url="e6fa80c94d4b7cf7f0708a6f36f0a69b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4158_img_3531_7"  type="Letter"  url="0f8c101d26b0a6c8e2f62c8a5831dd29.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_1"/>
             Dear <hi rend="underline">Father</hi>   Just had the news through Edmund <lb/>of Dorothy's engagement. I am most <lb/>awfully glad to hear of it and am <lb/>sure he will prove nice—I should <lb/>very much like to meet <hi rend="underline">him</hi> but there <lb/>is no possibility of that. We are up here in the fighting <lb/>line once more and getting on well <lb/>though the heavy rain lately has <lb/>played havoc with our trenches— <lb/>many <seg type="unclear">subsidiaries</seg> and endless <lb/> work keeping them under repair <lb/>and making them habitable — ) <lb/>am sorry for the unfortunates who <lb/>have to spend their time constantly <lb/>standing in water or cold slush <lb/>up to their knees; and yet through <lb/>it all they keep cheerful and <lb/>in good health. Strangely <lb/>enough nearly all the casualties <lb/>we have are caused through <lb/>carelessness or rather callousness
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_2"/>
            men looking over the trenches <lb/>to see how things are going <lb/> on etc. It seems strange <lb/>that they have to be taught <lb/>how to take care of themselves.   Our Hd. On is in a <lb/>small village about a mile <lb/>from the nearest trenches— <lb/>The village has been fairly <lb/>well shattered through shell <lb/>fire at different times. <lb/>We have our office and <lb/>2 rooms in one house and <lb/>the men and other rooms in <lb/>a house next door.   My bed room is a bit <lb/>skew-eyed and most of the <lb/>windows gone and the room <lb/>next door is a complete waster — <lb/>a shell <seg type="del">next door</seg> went clean <lb/>through it about 2 months <lb/>ago, knocking out both <lb/>walls and pretty well <lb/>making a muck of things
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_3"/>
            inside! We are all <lb/>perfectly comfortable nevertheless <lb/>and in a palace compared to <lb/>the poor souls in the trenches.   We have a large cellar <lb/>to which we are able to fly when <lb/>they start shelling — so far <lb/>we have been left in peace!   We come up here for a <lb/>spell and then are relieved by <lb/>another Brigade, when we <lb/>retire to another village farther <lb/>back till our tour of duty <lb/>comes round again—   Everybody is at it hard in <lb/>both cases and there is no <lb/>time to stop and think, which <lb/>is really a blessing.   my work up in their <lb/>part changes a bit.— <lb/>corrospondence still continues
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_4"/>
            but is varied by my having <lb/>to draw and deespatch to <lb/>the trenches each night what <lb/>they require in trench stores — <lb/>barbed wire, stakes, <seg type="unclear">questionable reading</seg> <lb/>for any cuts. Corrugated iron <lb/>etc. The difficulty of <lb/>course is the supply which <lb/>is only a fraction of the demand <lb/>and the trouble is to apportion <lb/>it off equally to all.   Every thing is wonderfully <lb/>systematic — I am in charge <lb/>of a Brigade workshop where <lb/>we keep 40 men employed <lb/>making everything we can deal <lb/>with to help men in the <lb/>trenches, floor boards, <lb/>fire <seg type="unclear">slips</seg>, parts of dug <lb/>outs etc.   The men now get a hot <lb/>bath nd change of clothes <lb/>when they come from the
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_5"/>
            trenches — They work it by seizing <lb/>any old barn or broken down <lb/>factory and make baths out <lb/>of barrels and tubs; hot water <lb/>is raised in many ingenious way <lb/>— in one place they still work <lb/>the stem boiler of a sugar <lb/>factory though to look at <lb/>the place outside you could <lb/>scarcely believe it as it has <lb/>been so much knocked about.  I am getting a few papers <lb/>from Belfast for the men but could <lb/>swallow dozens more — we have <lb/>a small recreation room run <lb/>by a person in the rest  &amp; <lb/>I send most of them round <lb/>there. Tell Ruth her <seg type="unclear">"whig"</seg> <lb/>arrives regularly.   There is what they call a <lb/>Field Force Canteen near here where <lb/>we can buy additional luxuries <lb/>to add to our Government rations
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_6"/>
            so I am in no need of food <lb/>luxuries and find that I can now <lb/>get tobacco and cigarettes there.   Glad to hear all goes well <lb/>at home and that you are still <lb/>getting some business through —   We get a free of papers here but I scarcely even have <lb/>time to read them so know nothing <lb/>of what is going on and are <lb/>always glad of the summ— <lb/>aries in your letters   I have been at work every <lb/>day so far from about 8AM till <lb/>11 P.M at night and just as <lb/>hard at all the time as I can <lb/>lay into it.   Just received mothers letter <lb/>tonight dated the seventh for <lb/>which please thank her.   My pockets are filling <lb/>with letters, mostly all unanswered <lb/>I fear — One of my many
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4158_img_3531_7"/>
            jobs is making out warrants for <lb/>all officers and men of the Brigade <lb/>who go on leave — it is no small <lb/>task in itself as each warrant <lb/>requires two signatures and I <lb/>find it tantalising signing <lb/>warrants to Belfast and the North <lb/>of Ireland — However all who <lb/>go in have earned it 20 <lb/>times over.   Best love to all <lb/>from <lb/>Your own   <hi rend="underline">Terry</hi>   P.S. I should be glad if my winter <lb/>flannels could be sent out.   They are in a drawer in <lb/>my room <lb/>Ter 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>