<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5911">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 13 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (1866-1955). As usual, Marie enquires after family members and describes her work in the tents in France. She describes another bathing incident which has led to a ban on swimming for nursing staff.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>France Letters, B/F/1/56</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5911</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-08-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1543">Hardelot, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1155">Monkstown, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_1"  type="Letter"  url="49657226168189707d52e3d2fd6c3e23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_2"  type="Letter"  url="b3bcb0de72f17443fe2c77c74660674f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_3"  type="Letter"  url="80b2f6458823516da2f8dfdc46086107.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_4"  type="Letter"  url="6881284fcbec560b4269143c1e0d5b3d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_5"  type="Letter"  url="49703541b9e4b75e98994dff4b04bc4a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_6"  type="Letter"  url="09002e6c850daf2276b9dfd6dbfb22cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_7"  type="Letter"  url="5ebfd6726ad260c1bd2e0f3cd78fb5e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_8"  type="Letter"  url="b760744f874bbb769300ba02809684d8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_9"  type="Letter"  url="ab143631d4a25cff350fa6be1b65d45f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5911_img_1775_10"  type="Letter"  url="ecb80333d7b035e7e9dac451977fd1c0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">13-8-16</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   I was just delighted to <lb/> receive your letter to-night, I <lb/> am very sorry to hear about <lb/> Tommy but strange to say this <lb/> last few day I have had <lb/> a feeling, a sort of presentiment <lb/> hanging over me that Tommy was <lb/> not well so have been anxiously <lb/> awaiting some news of him through <lb/> you. I hope you will very soon here <lb/> he is well on the road to recovery <lb/> &amp; if he is not, too bad I think <lb/> it is a great relief to know <lb/> he is out of the fighting that <lb/> has started out there. It is <lb/> nice him having <seg type="unclear">Ebbie</seg> <lb/> with him — I think Tommy is  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_2"/>
              wonderful the way he has stood <lb/> the climate   I am so glad to hear Violet has <lb/> gone for a change. What have <lb/> you decided about poor Jack <lb/> it seems a difficult problem. <lb/> I suppose you would like to <lb/> have some sort of an <sic>explanna-</sic><lb/> tion of my neglect about writing <lb/> lately but it is easily explained. <lb/> You remember I wrote to you on <lb/> the 15 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> telling you about the  <lb/> treat, well on Tuesday 16 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I was <lb/> on duty all the morning as usual <lb/> in Tents S.7. my off duty time being <lb/> from 1 to 5 which of course was spent <lb/> preparing &amp; serving the Teas, at <lb/> 4.30 that afternoon Matron came <lb/> &amp; told me she wished me to <lb/> open two new Tents for 3.6  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_3"/>
              Stretcher Gas. Case &amp; the convoy was <lb/> expected at 5 O' <sic>ck</sic> p.m. I went <lb/> up &amp; found the 1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> lot already <lb/> there &amp; they kept arriving till I <lb/> had about 20 cases— al went <lb/> fairly well that night. Came <lb/> on duty next morning to find <lb/> we had received a convoy <lb/> during the night 'Shell Shocks' <lb/> etc. but when the Medical <lb/> Officer arrived he had them <lb/> all transferred as he wishes <lb/> to keep ours only for Stretcher lb/> Gas Cases. no sooner where <lb/> these beds made up again than <lb/> we started taking in again <lb/> &amp; <seg type="unclear">being</seg> the 2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> day of the <seg type="unclear">Tea</seg> my orderly was off for <lb/> half day &amp; had to do <lb/> absolutely every thing for  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_4"/>
              them my self except carry the Tea <lb/> from the Cook-house. I must say <lb/> it was a bit much but nothing <lb/> matters as far as I am <seg type="unclear">concerned</seg><lb/> so long as I am able to <lb/> get through &amp; do every thing <lb/> necessary. The next day I &amp; the <lb/> orderly were on the whole day <lb/> again by this time we had <lb/><seg type="unclear">over</seg> 30 patients — The next <lb/> day I got <seg type="unclear">Janet</seg> as help <lb/> &amp; I was glad as we filled <lb/> up &amp; had another very heavy day. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Really</seg> I could not sit down &amp; write <lb/> I felt only just able to crawl to <lb/> bed. The next day  Saturday  things went <lb/> better, we had all beds full but <lb/> two so could not take a convoy <lb/> so were able to get things a  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_5"/>
              bit straight &amp; clean. <seg type="del">The next day</seg><lb/> Sunday I got off for the evening <lb/> went to Benediction &amp; came straight <lb/> to bed &amp; had a long rest &amp; <lb/> really recover as I was a little <lb/> done up after the rush. To day <lb/> I am in my element as two <lb/> new stripped Sisters arrived &amp; <lb/> one has been sent to me <lb/> I am so relieved &amp; glad as <lb/> I just hated the responsibility <lb/> &amp; with those Gas Cases one never <lb/> knows when they are going to <lb/> take a bad turn, as one did <lb/> this mornings— I got a half <lb/> day to-day to help in a <lb/><seg type="foreign">Fete</seg> for the wounded French <lb/> just to help to serve the <lb/> Tea— it was really quite  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_6"/>
              fun &amp; I ran in the egg &amp; spoon <lb/> race &amp; won 1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> prize being a very <lb/> useful pencil which I am writing <lb/> with at present. Two quite nice <lb/> young Officers who had tea at <lb/> our table one   in the R.S.R <lb/> we got <sic>talking</sic> &amp; they ended <lb/> up by walking back>with us . <lb/> They are down here quite near <lb/><seg type="unclear">Taking</seg> a course of <seg type="unclear">suits</seg> etc, it is <lb/> really to give them a rest &amp; change <lb/> One Officer from each Reg is <lb/> sent down there &amp; they have <lb/> about 4 weeks of it &amp; then go <lb/> back.   There has been another terrible <lb/> bathing accident here to day <lb/> Really it is most depressing — <lb/><sic>Evendently</sic> two French girls were bathing <lb/> &amp; got rather out of their depth &amp; called <lb/> for help, two of these <seg type="foreign">Chateau</seg>  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_7"/>
              Officers who happened to be bathing <lb/> went up to help them but with <lb/> the very strong current got taken <lb/> out of their depth but were all <lb/> saved except one of the Officers <lb/> who could not be found for <lb/> two hours, when the tide started <lb/> coming in his body came up <lb/> on a sand hill with a wave &amp; <lb/> the men who were in looking for <lb/> him brought him it. The Medical <lb/> Officers think there is very little <lb/> chance but <sic>ofcourse</sic> A <seg type="unclear">Respiration</seg><lb/> will be tried on him for about <lb/> 4 hours &amp; every thing is being <lb/> done for him, I do hope <lb/> he will <seg type="del">fir</seg><seg type="del">f</seg> live, it is too <lb/> sad for word &amp; really it is  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_8"/>
              very hard to settle down for the <lb/> night, he was on brought in at <lb/> 9 O' <sic>ck</sic> &amp; of course we have not been <lb/> able to hear any thing of him lately <lb/> We must only pray all will be well <lb/> The other 3 patients are getting <lb/> on well. Bathing will be stopped <lb/> altogether again for the Nursing <lb/> staff &amp; I am glad it is much <lb/> too dangerous    I am so glad to hear about <lb/> Willie M. I only hope she <lb/> is a very nice Girl — <lb/> Did I tell you Paul is being <lb/> moved, so there will only be <lb/> the Sisters &amp; <seg type="unclear">self</seg> for Tents— but <lb/> I am so relieved the responsibility <lb/> has <sic>accually</sic> gone from me — <lb/> I am as fit as a fiddle again &amp; <lb/> quite ready for the next lot of <lb/> Tents to be opened—  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_9"/>
              Imagine it is the 3 <hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> lot <sic>I have</sic><lb/> already opened, we were all delighted <lb/> to see these new Sisters arrive. Matron <lb/> is leaving me where I am as she <lb/> say later she may have to take <lb/> the Sisters &amp; I shall be still there <lb/> to run them for her.   Poor M <hi rend="superscript">rs</hi><seg type="unclear">Grattan</seg> will have a lonely <lb/> time of it, I think Reggie <lb/> might stay at home with her. <lb/> however every one know there own business — I am very <lb/> sorry to hear about Granny <lb/> &amp; hope by now she is alright <lb/> it will be very hard on her <lb/> being knocked up. I am <lb/> also sorry to hear about  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_5911_img_1775_10"/>
              Uncle Frank, all he suffers, please <lb/> give every one my fondest love <lb/> &amp; tell them all my news, you <lb/> see I really have very little <lb/> time for writing even now it <lb/> is very late.   So must say good night <lb/> hoping you will be able to <lb/> make head or tale of this <lb/> &amp; that it does not <seg type="unclear">bore</seg> you.  <seg type="closer"> My every fondest love &amp; <lb/> a big kiss to every one of the <lb/> family— Your ever loving  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>