<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5558">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn, 25 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.  

May is looking forward to their next visit and recounts events at the farm.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5558</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-02-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2121">Togherstown, Westmeath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5558_img_654_1"  type="Letter"  url="82ddb037343715407219be60fe3ddf6d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5558_img_654_2"  type="Letter"  url="047413ff82cd5ed28315cae2fcc769ce.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5558_img_654_3"  type="Letter"  url="77bef3cdba4c98068d74f587ff52c873.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5558_img_654_1"/>
             Togherstown <lb/>Ballinea <lb/>Mullingar   25 Feb. 1916   My dearest James,   I was very glad to get <lb/>your letter this morn. I was looking <lb/>out for it and happened to be at <lb/>the window up stairs when M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rs</hi></hi> L. <lb/>was coming down the hill &amp; it <lb/>teeming snow I could scarcely 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5558_img_654_2"/>
            believe my eye when I saw she <lb/>got down on her knees &amp; crept <lb/>out on the <hi rend="underline">"creep hole"</hi>, you know <lb/>the hole for the sheep so it is no <lb/>wonder the poor thing looked so <lb/>dilapidated. I hope it will never come <lb/>to that with me but I’d make you <lb/>go around with the letters &amp; I’d keep <lb/>the stirabout hot till you would come <lb/>home.   We had a letter from Jennie <lb/>today Tim is not a bit lonely <lb/>up very early studying <seg type="del">she</seg>she <lb/>said he had a letter from Joe Tyrell <lb/>the boy that was going to Mullingar <lb/>along with a very nice letter she gave us one piece out of it. It was <lb/>this - I was very lonely for you <hi rend="underline">but <lb/>I have you forgotten now</hi> be sure &amp; don’t <lb/>let much of the year go by without <lb/>writing to me I’ll be looking out for <lb/>your letter.   Jack Nolan was here today <lb/>he was killing a pig very much <lb/>inclined to inquire about your <lb/>property etc. You know <lb/>Jack   It will be all right about <lb/>the car I’ll take good care <lb/>not to have to walk I’m very <lb/>lazy as far as walking goes
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5558_img_654_3"/>
            Goodbye now till tomorrow <lb/>when I will have pleasure of <lb/>seeing my poor hard working little <lb/>man  All my best love to my <lb/>dearest James from   May  <lb/>    Excuse this hurried letter I’m <lb/>cold &amp; hurried   May 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>