<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5977">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Copy of a letter from John H. Billinge to M. Albert Maeterlinck, Belgian Red Cross, 26 July 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John H. Billinge</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a three-sided correspondence between the Irish War Hospital Supply Depot in Dublin, the Belgian Funds Committee in Manchester, and the Belgian Red Cross in London. The Belgian Funds Committee, represented by John H. Billinge as Hon. Secretary and Treasurer, arranged for the Irish War Hospital Supply Depot to regularly ship medical items to the Belgian Red Cross in London, where they were used to treat wounded Belgian soldiers. Eleanor Dallas Pratt, Catholic wife of a respected Anglican surgeon based in Dublin, served as Hon. Secretary to the Irish War Hospital Supply Depot. The letters on behalf of the Belgian Red Cross were written by M. Albert Maeterlinck and C. E. R. Abbott. Maeterlinck was a Belgian national and returned home in January 1919. All files are kept at the Manchester Central Library. The bound volume also contains the lists all dispatched supplies and letters of thanks or supplication from soldiers and their families.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Manchester Central Library</repository>
                  <collection>GB127.M138/2435, Belgian Red Cross files, 1916-1919: File No. 5 &#34;Belgian Red Cross Fund&#34; (not paged)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5977</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0093">John H. Billinge</persName>
              <date>1918-07-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0444">Belgian Red Cross, Anglo-Belgian Committee, 48 Grosvenor Gardens, London, S. W. 1, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1310">M. Albert Maeterlinck</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1169">Belgian Funds Committee, 78 King Street, Manchester, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5977_img_None_1"  url="phpN3nFqv.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5977_img_0_1"/>
             B/S   July 26th. 1916.    Dear Mr. Maeterlinck,    <hi rend="underline">Belgian Red Cross</hi>  I am today in receipt of your letter of the 22nd <seg type="unclear">inst</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg>I thank you.  You will, I trust, forgive me commenting upon the <seg type="del">fa</seg><lb/>fact that your last receipt to us bears a penny stamp, as I<lb/>think it possible that the course was followed by you or some<lb/>member of your staff who was not fully aware of the position.<lb/>As a matter of fact in law there are very few exemptions from<lb/>but any receipt for a donation or subscription to an institutio<lb/>tion as the Commissionars do not enfoce a penalty if it is<lb/>given unstamped! This paragraph is extracted by me from the<lb/>13th edition of Alpe's Law on stamp duties. this being the<lb/>recognised work on such a point. I only quote this authority <seg type="unclear">in</seg><lb/>case you or members of your Committee desire to refer to it.  I trust the foregoing will be accepted in the<lb/>spirit it is tendered.  With the best of wishes for yourself and your work<lb/>I am   Yours sincerely   P.S. Will you kindly let me know the amount of the donation<lb/>received by you from Messrs. Cross's &amp; Wirksworth, Bolton. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>