<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0829">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lady Henrietta MacDonnell to Lady Clonbrock, 28 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Lady Henrietta MacDonnell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Lady MacDonnell of the Irish Women&#39;s Association to Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). The letter includes a list of Christmas 1916 parcel items that will be dispatched to the 1st and 2nd Batallions of the Connaught Rangers attached to the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force by the Co. Galway Military and Naval Committee. MacDonnell laments that what she considered the best item, &#39;Soup Rolls,&#39; which the men serving on the Western Front greatly appreciated, were substituted out. She hopes that Lady Clonbrock will approve of her amendments to the package.Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Mss 35,787-97, Mss 35,787-97</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/829</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1353">Lady Henrietta MacDonnell</persName>
              <date>1916-10-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1862">Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_1"  type="Letter"  url="7b28be21c3cee8a620436136157a449b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_2"  type="Letter"  url="fd23bedcb8ca5839f8a22622ebd8c85f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_3"  type="Letter"  url="f386905eb367ab03be6d2ee5f7f7c61e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_4"  type="Letter"  url="14dcd8fba53a93b55dac0f5b34ca0d75.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_5"  type="Letter"  url="809f58dc79fd7bacd6f235986262f9f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_6"  type="Letter"  url="1e7541f7fb647153ccf39c2b453a4080.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="4c2106fc1e853483b10b7cd03907392c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="315d2a599b4e4632d7d18396ad8ca56a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0829_img_238_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="3940895ad61ea0ff4cc1b3473a1212b3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_1"/>
             <seg type="head">THE IRISH WOMEN'S ASOCIATION <lb/>(to aid Irish Regiments and Prisoners of War) </seg> I enclose some <lb/>memos of our <lb/>Xmas parcels <lb/>to P. of W. <lb/>for distribution <lb/>if you will be <lb/>so kind!     Kensington Palace,  London, W.    October 26th 1916.   Dear Lady Clonbrook,   Strangely <lb/>enough, I was yesterday morning <lb/>dictating a letter for you when <lb/>I was interrupted by most <lb/>urgent business connected with <lb/>this next Scheme for the P. of W. <lb/>which the Govt. is starting. <lb/>During my absence, your <lb/>letter came â but I got back <lb/>here so late that I was <lb/>unable to answer your <lb/>letter â &amp; when I got home, <lb/>I was too tired to do any <lb/>thing but go to bed.   I was writing yesterday with <lb/>the intention of sending you  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_2"/>
              the single copy of what had been sent <lb/>to the 1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> C.G. in Mesopotamia.   I didn't wait for the  , as my <lb/>people disappointed me as to the date <lb/>of their arrival &amp; substituted what <lb/>I consider the best thing we have for <lb/>cold &amp; weary men â namely some quite <lb/>delicious 'Soup Rolls'. I know our men <lb/>in Flanders love that. It's called Pea <lb/>Soup &amp; Bacon! &amp; is warm and comforting, <lb/>though not as 'Christmassy' as sweets. <lb/>I hope you will think I did right. <lb/>I was so anxious to get our things off <lb/>by the 16th, that I didn't wait for the <lb/>sweets.   The W.O. told me by Novr. 1st <lb/>but <hi rend="underline">I know</hi> it is better to send off a <lb/>fortnight earlier, &amp; I am thankful to say <lb/>our whole 37 bales or cases went off <lb/>on 16 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.   We had some socks ready to send but your <lb/>Co. Galway contribution was so magnificent  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_3"/>
              that <seg type="unclear">I have</seg> kept ours for <lb/>a little later. Indeed I <lb/>doubt if the P.O. at <lb/>Avonmouth would accept <lb/>any more packages for <lb/>me. <seg type="unclear">Request</seg><hi rend="underline"> over 18 <lb/>Cwt. </hi> went off <seg type="unclear">Dover</seg> transfers <lb/>last Monday!   I wish I could see their joy <lb/>when that consignment <lb/>arrives! â In case you <lb/>would like to <seg type="del">have it</seg> know  &amp; <lb/>not because I want the <lb/>money! I enclose a rough <lb/>memo of the cost the <lb/>freight to Avonmouth (our <lb/>new port for Mesopotamia) <lb/>I cannot yet tell, as the <lb/>weekly Cashier's bill is not <lb/>yet in, so please don't send  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_4"/>
              any money yet.   This new W. O. scheme is going to give <lb/>us a great deal of extra work at first <lb/>â but I have no fear for the future. <lb/>I am confident we shall always get <lb/>the money we require. â The new W.O. <lb/>Committee is very friendly &amp; very <lb/>complimentary to us â &amp; I think the <lb/>extra trouble is well worth <seg type="del">the  <lb/>in </seg> going through, for there was a <lb/>hideous amount of overlapping, &amp; a <lb/>woeful amount of carelessness or <lb/>ignorance on the part of many Committees <lb/>who should have known better. <lb/>Our expenses will be on record â but <lb/>as I have already said, I don't feel <lb/>any doubt as to our being able to <lb/>keep up to it for our friends are <lb/>very good to us.   Forgive this badly written letter <lb/> Dear Lady Clonbrook â my hand is almost <lb/>as tired as I am myself.  <seg type="closer"> I am very sincerely,  Henrietta MacDonnell </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_5"/>
              approximate <lb/>Memo exclusive of freight <lb/>of cost of Xmas cases to <lb/>Ps of W Mesopotamia. <lb/>480 lbs plum pudding @ 1/0 per lb <lb/>500 lbs Cake @ 1/- <lb/>(Discount within reduces <lb/>the bill to Â£23-6-8 <lb/>180 Rolls of Soup @ 4Â½ <hi rend="superscript">d</hi><lb/>per doz. rolls. <lb/>9,500 Woodbines @ 7/8 per 1,000 <lb/>12 lbs Gallaghers Plug @ 1/9 <lb/>12 lbs Navy Cut @ 2/- <lb/>100 Pipes @ 7d each <lb/>4 Footballs @ 12/6 <lb/>8  extra  bladders for same 2/6 - <lb/>(these were sent in all <lb/>by <seg type="unclear">water hose</seg>) <lb/>The Soup Rolls <hi rend="underline">each</hi> should make 12 good <lb/>P.T.O.   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_6"/>
              cups of soup â &amp; they do really make <lb/>10 really splendid cups from each roll. <lb/>so each man will get two good <lb/>cups. Alas! the Battalion has not more, <lb/>I hear, than 700 or 800 men.   I sent 'broken' quantities of some things <lb/>(for instance, of plum pudding) on account <lb/>of the packing â I really didn't have <lb/>to add another package.   That's why I didn't spend the Â£80 I <lb/>originally meant to spend â of course <lb/>we divide &amp; pay for half cost of every <lb/>thing with you. I explained to the <lb/>C.O. in my <seg type="del">accompa</seg> covering letter <lb/>that the first six <seg type="unclear">bales</seg> were entirely <lb/>the gift of the Galway Fund, &amp; <lb/>the remainder a joint gift in equal <lb/>parts <seg type="del">of</seg> from  that Fund and the I.W.A.   
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_7"/>
               Pre-printed text  The irish Women's Association <lb/>(to aid Irish Regiments and Prisoners of War) <lb/>Kensington Palace <lb/>London, W.   Exact copy of licence sent by me to the C.O. <lb/>1st C. Rangers   CHRISTMAS PARCEL <lb/>sent to the 1st. and 2nd. Battalions of the <lb/>CONNAUGHT RANGERS, MESOPOTAMIAN EXPEDITIONARY <lb/>FORCE, <lb/>starting on the 16th October, 1916. <lb/><hi rend="underline">O.C. 1st. Battalion</hi><lb/>E.R. (1). Bale. 150 prs. socks, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp; <lb/>Military Committee. <lb/>E.R. (2). Bale. 150 prs. socks, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp; <lb/>Military Committee. <lb/>E.R. (3). Bale. 120 mufflers, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp; <lb/>Military Committee. <lb/>E.R. (4). Bale. 100 mufflers, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp; <lb/>Military Committee. <lb/>E.R. (5). Bale. 80 mufflers, 132 prs. mittens, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp; <lb/>Military Committee. <lb/>E.R. (6). Bale. 276 prs. mittens, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp; <lb/>Military Committee. <lb/>â <lb/>E.R. (7). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding, &amp; <lb/>12 soup rolls, <lb/>From Co. Galway Naval &amp;   
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_8"/>
              Military Committee, and the Irish <lb/>Women's Association. <lb/>E.R. (8). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (9). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (10). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (11). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (12). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (13). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (14). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (15). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (16). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (17). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (18). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A.   
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0829_img_238_9"/>
              E.R. (19). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (20). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>E.R. (21). Case. 32 lbs. plum pudding and 12 soup rolls, <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>â <lb/>E.R. (22) to (35) <lb/>inclusive. Cases. 500 lbs. cake. <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>â <lb/>B.G. (1). Case. 3500 'Woodbines'. <lb/>6lbs. Gallagher's Plug. <lb/>4 lbs. Navy Cut. <lb/>6 pipes. <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>B.G. (2). Case. 6500 'Woodbines'. <lb/>6lbs. Gallagher's Plug. <lb/>8 lbs. Navy Cut. <lb/>94 pipes. <lb/>4 foorballs. <lb/>8 bladders. <lb/>From the Co. Galway Naval &amp; Military <lb/>Committee, and the I.W.A. <lb/>â   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>