<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6611">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mary McDonagh to her daughter-in-law Annie McDonagh, early 1920</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mary McDonagh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a personal letter belonging to the McDonagh family. It was written by the contributor&#39;s great grandmother, probably born around 1860. Mary McDonagh had 12 children. The eldest was born in 1883 and the contributor&#39;s grandfather was born in 1892. This letter enquires about the baby, the contributor&#39;s father, born in 1919. The envelope has not been preserved.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>McDonagh Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6611</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0117">Mary McDonagh</persName>
              <date>1920</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1998">Roundstone, Co Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Annie McDonagh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0036">Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6611_img_None_1"  url="phpzeUF6e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6611_img_None_2"  url="phpEvcYK4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6611_img_None_3"  url="phpPhfdqU.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6611_img_None_4"  url="phpEVLy6J.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6611_img_0_1"/>
              Roundstone<lb/>Co Galway       Dear Annie <lb/>I now take pleasure in writing<lb/>you these few lines <sic>hoaping</sic><lb/>you &amp; the baby are well. I<lb/>am very sorry to have heard<lb/>a very bad news from<lb/>America. I had a letter last<lb/>week &amp; it said Ellie died<lb/>after two days illness. She<lb/>was the youngest girl I had<lb/>&amp; I miss her very much as 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6611_img_0_2"/>
             2/ we were expecting her<lb/>home in March. I hope Joe<lb/>is well tell him to write<lb/>&amp; let us know how he is getting<lb/>on. The weather is frightful<lb/>stormy &amp; wet here at present<lb/>&amp; the place is ever so dull.<lb/>We are all longing for the<lb/>summer to come as we<lb/>expect to see you &amp; the baby<lb/>for a while. There is a very<lb/>bad cold passing here now<lb/>&amp; nearly every body <sic>are</sic><lb/>effected from it. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_6611_img_0_3"/>
             3. Michael is gone to England<lb/>this past <sic>sixweeks</sic> &amp; is<lb/>doing well. I have not<lb/>heard from James this<lb/>past Month he is in<lb/>Scotland. Mamie is still<lb/>at home &amp; is keeping well.<lb/>I don’t think she has any<lb/>notions for <sic>traveling</sic><lb/>so soon again. Remember<lb/>me to your Parents and friends<lb/>tell them we all send<lb/>our <sic>comploments</sic> to them.<lb/>Mary wishes to be remembered 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_6611_img_0_4"/>
             4) to you and the baby. I hope<lb/>it is getting strong now.<lb/>Dear Annie I have no<lb/>more to say in this letter<lb/><sic>hoaping</sic> its contents<lb/>finds yous all well.<lb/>I will now close  with<lb/>fondest love from your<lb/>loving Mother   Mary McDonagh  X X X X X X X<lb/>                  XXX  To Baby X X X X X X X X X 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>