<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0772">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 22 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this brief letter Spender informs Lillian that his brother Rex has arrived. He also informs her that he is being made a General Staff Officer in the 4th Army, and will not protest the appointment, although he will regret leaving his brother and the Ulstermen.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/356</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/772</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0772_img_2305_1"  type="NULL"  url="6cb4e8c73b224de0f2838b235b2ea338.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0772_img_2305_2"  type="NULL"  url="e1d164b86d8286b2a477984c440d7e4d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0772_img_2305_1"/>
                July 22   My pr   Rex has come &amp; I have <lb/>seen him &amp; we dined <lb/>together. Please heaven to <lb/>look after him till the <lb/>end of the war.   My address is <lb/><seg type="del">capt.</seg> Lt Col WBS <lb/>Gen' Staff <lb/>4 Army <lb/>I got the win that I <lb/>was appointed GSO  4 Army  today <lb/>&amp; with very mixed feelings. <lb/>If I had not had <seg type="unclear">that view</seg><lb/>I might have declined to have the Division but <lb/>that has decided me that  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0772_img_2305_2"/>
              My work is done here, <lb/>but you know that <lb/>it means to leave Rex <lb/>&amp; my own Ulstermen <seg type="closer"> Your  b w WB Spender </seg><seg type="postscript"> I told Rex you would <lb/>undertake commissions <lb/>for him if necessary. <lb/>Please send out his <lb/>fruit cake etc as soon <lb/>as possible </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>