<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1127">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Higgins to sir Matthew Nathan, 10 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Patrick Higgins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Higgins, assistant town clerk at Waterford Town Hall, to Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) , Under-Secretary for Ireland, on 10 January 1916. The letter is written on behalf of the mayor (presumably of Waterford) and is in regard to the mayor&#39;s recommendation to the Lord Lieutenant (Lord Wimborne) that Alderman William J Smith be appointed to the city magistracy.Sir Matthew Nathan as the under secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP 1916/695/2/1, NAI CSO RP 1916/695/2/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1127</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1167">Patrick Higgins</persName>
              <date>1916-01-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2101">Waterford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1127_img_360_1"  type="Letter"  url="6f45e95ac7612ed26e4a2e90177d449f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1127_img_360_1"/>
                Town Clerk's Office,  Town Hall,  Waterford    10th Jany., 1916.    Patrick Higgins,  Asst. Town Clerk.   Sir   With reference to your letter of the 27th <lb/>Nov., I am instructed by His Worship the Mayor to <lb/>ask you to be good enough to say when a reply may <lb/>be expected to his recommendation to His Excellency <lb/>the Lord Lieutenant of Alderman William J. Smith to <lb/>the City Magistracy.   I am to add that many citizens consider that <lb/>Alderman Smith is the class of gentleman who would <lb/>make an intelligent and able Justice.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   Pat Higgins <lb/>Assistant Town Clerk.   The Under-Secretary  The Castle, DUBLIN.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>