<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5786">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 10 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
James has heard from May and knows that she will be coming up to Dublin, he longs to see her, wonders if she has heard from her sister Jenny in Mitchelstown. Arrests are going on all over the country. He tells her about the executions and many have been sent to penal servitude</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5786</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-10</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0557">39 Belgrave Square, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5786_img_885_1"  type="Letter"  url="a72e6f24b5993cfe62a724e88efa99b7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5786_img_885_2"  type="Letter"  url="bf759215b175ad0bd2d0ddef6e30a637.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5786_img_885_3"  type="Letter"  url="515a9bbb71a11b63757587511659f1c7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5786_img_885_1"/>
             39 Belgrave Sq.<lb/>Rathmines<lb/>Dublin   10th May, 1916.    My dearest love,   You are a darling to write to<lb/>me again yesterday. I was not expecting a<lb/>letter of course and was delighted when I got<lb/>home yesterday evening to hear from my mother that<lb/>there was a letter waiting for me. It must<lb/>have arrived yesterday after I left for the<lb/>office. The post is very erratic these times<lb/>for example there is no post for the night<lb/>mail after 3p.m. so I have to write to<lb/>you immediately after I come into the<lb/>office or I shall miss it. However we have 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5786_img_885_2"/>
             been so long without mails that we bless<lb/>the post office for any little convenience at<lb/>all now. I was overjoyed to see that<lb/>we may look forward to the pleasure of<lb/>seeing you on Saturday. I need hardly tell<lb/>you with what anxiety and eagerness I<lb/>am waiting for the moment when I can<lb/>embrace my dearest and best girl again and<lb/>thank God for being thought worthy to live<lb/>to see her again. I hope that the trouble<lb/>through which we have all passed will eventually<lb/>bring good to our poor country and that it<lb/>will with Gods blessing make me a better<lb/>man and a more worthy one for the dear<lb/>good true girl who loves me. I hope you   heard from Johnnie since and that all is<lb/>well with them in Mitchelstown. They are still<lb/>arresting men all over the country and I suppose<lb/>you know that they have shot twelve of the<lb/>leaders in the last week. They are P.H.<lb/>Pearse and his brother <sic>Willy</sic>Pearse, Tom Clarke<lb/>(an old Fenian), Thos. McDonagh, J. <sic>Plunket</sic><lb/>(a son of Count <sic>Plunket</sic>), Major McBride (of<lb/>the South African War), Eamonn Kent, Conn Colbert,<lb/>J.J. Heuston, M. Mallon and one or two others<lb/>whose names I forget at the moment. A<lb/>large number (up to 40 I think) have got<lb/>penal servitude ranging from 3 to 20 years;<lb/>Countess <sic>Markievitz</sic> imprisoned for life and<lb/>2000 or 3000 prisoners taken to England to<lb/>be interned.  I had a letter from Johnnie to-day and 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5786_img_885_3"/>
             of course I'll go round and see them at<lb/>Callaghan's about the job there. I will write<lb/>to him to-morrow but don't mention it to<lb/>him when of course he has already told you that<lb/>he is looking for a job there. We are in the<lb/>middle of tradesmen this week <seg type="unclear">papering or</seg> but<lb/>we hope to be in some sort of order by<lb/>Saturday when we shall have the pleasure<lb/>of welcoming yourself and Mrs Seery to<lb/>Belgrave Square. Tell Mrs S. to bring up my<lb/>bag and belongings if she doesn't mind the<lb/>trouble. Let me know what train you are<lb/>coming on and I will meet you at the<lb/>station or thereabouts. I'm not sure whether I<lb/>can get into the station or not but will<lb/>find out and let you know to-morrow.<lb/>Give my warmest regards to your mother Nano Mrs<lb/>Seery and everyone and with fondest love and kisses   Your ever loving <lb/> James  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>