<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1780">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Andrew Philip Magill to William Howell Davies, 11 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Andrew Philip Magill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Andrew Philip Magill (1871–1941) an Irish civil servant to William Howell Davis (1851-1932), a British politician. Andrew Philip Magill acted as private secretary to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) the chief secretary for Ireland. Magill assumed the role in 1913 and continued after the resignation of Birrell in 1916. Davis held a seat in Westminster for the South Bristol district. The letter is written in the context of the death of the chief crown solicitor, Malachy Kelly (1850-1916). The letter acknowledges a previous letter of recommendation sent by Davis on behalf of William Horner (b. 1878), a solicitor in London-Derry. It goes on to state that Horner&#39;s application will be fully considered.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/6463/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1780</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date>1916-04-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0350">Chief Secretary&#39;s Office, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Howell Davis </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0598">Down House, Stoke Bishop, Bristol, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1780_img_1235_1"  type="Letter"  url="f810f03694b39b91b06ec9d1a951a461.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1780_img_1235_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>   11th April, 1916.   Dear Sir William Howell Davies,   I am desired by Mr. Birrell to acknowledge the receipt <lb/>of your letter of 10th instant, and enclosure, recommend- <lb/>ing Mr. Horner for appointment as Chief Crown Solicitor for <lb/>Ireland, and to say that Mr. Birrell has taken a note of <lb/>your recommendation and will see that Mr. Horner's claims <lb/>are fully considered.   Yours faithfully,  <lb/>(Sd) APM <lb/>Under Secy. <lb/>A.P.M. <lb/>11/4/16 <lb/>Sir William Howell Davies, M.P.,  Down House, <lb/>Stoke Bishop, <lb/>BRISTOL. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>