<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5132">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 30, September, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>When travelling through Folkestone William Upton Tyrrell bought an electric stitch which, &#34;is simply wonderful and will remove any stain from anything&#34;.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5132</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-09-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5132_img_None_1"  url="0501354db56e281293f02807df71ad7d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5132_img_None_2"  url="1504c47ca3e843fbba401cfedfcc3afe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5132_img_None_3"  url="5c870f06265dd78b3b93534fc56ad48d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5132_img_0_1"/>
              30 Sept. 1917    My dearest Daddy   There is really no news of interest.<lb/>We are still in the same place. It is a<lb/>great coal mining district and all the<lb/>men are miners. There are enormous<lb/>heaps of slack all round the place<lb/>which can be seen for miles round.<lb/>Small railways run up the sides of<lb/>these and wagons full of rubbish and<lb/>slack are hauled up and then <seg type="unclear">lifted</seg><lb/>down the other side. It is quite amusing<lb/>to watch them.  At present we are training very hard<lb/>for a musketing competition. The brigadeer<lb/>is giving a shield for the best platoon<lb/>in his brigade with an additional 10<lb/><seg type="unclear">frames</seg> for man for the winning platoon.  There is is no use my going into the<lb/>details of the competition as I could<lb/>not explain it in paper but everyone 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5132_img_0_2"/>
             seems very keen on it. This morning<lb/>we were on parade at 6.15 am and<lb/>went out to the range. A good start for<lb/>a sunday morning. You see even<lb/>when we are resting we do a little<lb/>work.  I did not get any letters from<lb/>you yet since I got back but no<lb/>doubt they will soon begin to<lb/>come again.  There have been no additions<lb/>to the battalion at all lately<lb/>I think I have made a discovery.<lb/>I saw a thing in a slot window at<lb/><seg type="unclear">Tolhestone</seg> called electic <seg type="unclear">slich</seg><lb/>for taking stains out of clothes.  As there were some stains on<lb/>some of my trench clothes I bought<lb/>a few and used it. It is simply<lb/>wonderful and will remove any<lb/>stain from anything. It is a thing 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5132_img_0_3"/>
             well worth knowing of in these days<lb/>when <seg type="unclear"></seg> is scarce.  I wrote to Bobby today. I am also<lb/>going to write to Tammy Mather<lb/>to claim by 6th which is or was down<lb/>her  block.    The weather is perfect here. Just<lb/>like what we have had all<lb/>summer up to August.  You might send out sometime my<lb/>wooly waistcoat but there is not<lb/>the slightest hurry as this is not<lb/>the kind of weather that one would<lb/>need it.  No news so must shut up.   With the very best love from    Your most affect Son    Willie     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>