<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0197">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell to James Hamilton, 2 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926) a butler working in Bournemouth. The letter concerns an application by Hamilton for official documents that would grant him permission to travel to Belfast on holiday. The letter states that at the time no permission was granted for travellers to cross to Ireland. However O&#39;Farrell states that it would be advisable for Hamilton to bring appropriate credentials so that no objection to his landing will be made. Edward O&#39;Farrell served as the assistant undersecretary of Ireland after the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9276/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/197</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Hamilton</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1893">Littleton Lodge, Florence Road, Boscombe, Bournemouth, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0197_img_1339_1"  type="Letter"  url="ac75da97a9e24da5138e9701127c5bfc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0197_img_1339_1"/>
                2nd June, 1916   9267.  Sir,    With reference to your letter of the 30th May <lb/> I am directed by the Lords Justices to state that <lb/> formal Permits are not being issued by the Military <lb/> Authorities to enable travellers to cross to <lb/> Ireland.   It will, however, be advisable for you to <lb/> bring credentials to satisfy the Military Authori- <lb/> ties on your arrival that no objection should be <lb/> made to your landing.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Sir, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,   E. O'Farrell   Mr. James Hamilton,  Littleton Lodge,  16 Florence Road,  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>