<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3326">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to his mother Alice Katherine Wynne, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Donegal thanking his mother in Avova for the vegetables and towels and requesting sheets.  Also expressing a desire to be accepted on machine gun course in Dollymount.  

Charles Wynne served as a captain in the Royal Garrison Artillery during the First World War. His application to the Royal Flying Corps was denied in 1916 due to his poor eyesight. Charles ultimately died of wounds received at Armentieres, June 1917. Alice Katherine Wynne was born to Reverend John George Wynne and Emily Goold. She was married to Albert Augustus Wynne and was the mother of five children, among them Charles Wyndham Wynne. Charles served as a captain in the Royal Garrison Artillery in the First World War. He died of wounds received at Armentieres, June 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/798</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3326</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2045">Lenan Head Fort, Clonmany, Co. Donegal, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2056">Avoca, Co. Wicklow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3326_img_274_1"  type="Letter"  url="d00de28d913982dfe27a6b7659d6c69a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3326_img_274_2"  type="Letter"  url="63d3c67e3777e0ae90bb3627b24bd80b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3326_img_274_3"  type="Letter"  url="c9a817dbef26c54f479827840d5362b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3326_img_274_4"  type="Envelope"  url="471d21207ebbc815f8d4cf2453b016c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3326_img_274_5"  type="Envelope"  url="a12ea093f5c82512592ee9ee2cff5323.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3326_img_274_1"/>
              R. A. MESS <lb/> FORT DUNREE <lb/> BUNCARNA    Dear Mother   I was very glad to get <lb/> yours this morning. Gen. <lb/> Arthur writes quite decently <lb/> though he certainly doesn't <lb/>say much. Captain Blackwood <lb/> O. C Troops here has also sent <lb/> in an application for the R.I.C <lb/> he says there is a stiff colour <lb/> test. But I am determined <lb/> to learn up the colours - I
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3326_img_274_2"/>
            will write to a hosier for <lb/>coloured woods and practice <lb/>with them as I <sic>dont</sic> believe <lb/>I am really at all colour blind.   I think I will wait for this <lb/>and till a few more officers <lb/>come back. Also to see if can <lb/>get a machine gun course <lb/>at Dollymount. It seems <lb/>from the General's letter that <lb/>I should have a good <lb/>chance of the R.I.C - wouldn't <lb/>it be splendid if I got it.   Thanks most awfully for <lb/>the vegetables <seg type="del">there</seg>  they're  a real <lb/>treat. I'm sure they will be <lb/>greatly appreciated - its so <lb/>frightfully hard to get anything <lb/>out in this place.   I was very glad of the towels <lb/>what I want much more  though  are <lb/>sheets if they are going at <lb/>Tigroney. but towels also I <lb/>wanted badly.   Isn't it grand Father being <lb/>so <seg type="del">fine</seg> well. I hope he's having
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3326_img_274_3"/>
            some decent weather. Here <lb/>its simply rotten, nothing but <lb/>wind and hail and driving <lb/>rain. This morning there was <lb/>an inspection by General <seg type="unclear">Friend</seg>. <lb/>I had just coming off night <lb/>duty though so I was excused <lb/>he seemed quite pleased with <lb/>the place. Though it was a <lb/>rotten morning.   I hope soon the Mess here <lb/>will not be quite so empty <lb/>as now. as <seg type="del">a few more</seg> <lb/>Mullins will be back tomorrow <lb/>and Montgomery should soon be <lb/>back from Dublin   <sic>Yr w</sic> love    Charles. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3326_img_274_4"/>
             Mrs Wynne <lb/>Tigroney <lb/>Avoca <lb/><hi rend="underline">Co. Wicklow</hi> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3326_img_274_5"/>
            
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>