<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4414">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from North Circular Laundry Co. to Charles Munro, 2 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from North Circular Laundry Co. to Charles Munro, regarding the damaged wall between Mountjoy Prison and the North Circular Laundry Company. 

Charles Arthur Munro (1869-1952) was the governor of Mountjoy prison in Dublin. He is also the brother of the noted author H.H. Munro, better known through his literary pseudonym, Saki.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection> NAI/CSO/RP/1916/10714/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4414</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0836">North Circular Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0487">Charles Arthur Munro</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1716">Mountjoy Prison, North Circular Road, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4414_img_3766_1"  type="Letter"  url="3d40d3f6efbfc2604932e6704e1f604f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4414_img_3766_1"/>
             N.C. LAUNDRY, Ltd. <lb/>IRELAND'S BEST <lb/>LAUNDERERS, <lb/>CLEANERS, AND DYERS.   NORTH CIRCULAR ROAD, <lb/>(TOP OF BERKLEY STREET), <lb/>DUBLIN,   June 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1916   Munro Esq <lb/>Governor H.M. Prison <lb/>Mountjoy   Dear Sir/  <lb/>Yours 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> ult to hand offering to <lb/>contribute half towards cost of erecting <lb/>a substantial wooden fence in lieu of <lb/>the wall. In reply we have to say that <lb/><hi rend="underline">this would not be at all reasnable or</hi> <lb/>just to us. As we have in contemplation <lb/>the erection of a building on this ground <lb/>using the large walls to support metal <lb/>girders carrying roof. It would therefore <lb/>be necessary for us later on to rebuild <lb/>the wall pulled down by your ivy and <lb/>the cost of so doing will be very consider- <lb/>-able and we think you are entitled to <lb/>make us a reasonable contribution towards <lb/>the cost of doing this work of rebuilding <lb/>which we estimate roughly would be <lb/>about £50. We are anxious to get this <lb/>settled and would be willing to accept <lb/>a reasonable sum say £25, to end the <lb/>matter, and trust Prisons Board will act <lb/>in fair and reasonable way and agree <lb/>to this.   Yours faithfully   <seg type="unclear">N C L Ltd</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>