<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4331">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Ronald McNeill to Edward Carson, 22 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ronald John McNeill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Ronald John McNeill, 1st Baron Cushendun (1861-1934) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. McNeill was a British Conservative politician.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/25</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4331</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0622">Ronald John McNeill</persName>
              <date>1916-06-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2011">10 Cadogan Place, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4331_img_3690_1"  type="Letter"  url="4a583d5433a8052e6d370be7796e90c2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4331_img_3690_2"  type="Letter"  url="cc50f2346652a04fbfe0f597c0c663f8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4331_img_3690_3"  type="Letter"  url="f329753415b1038df0b65a0218488fa1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4331_img_3690_4"  type="Letter"  url="a899eb588d944296dea0107f57e86b44.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4331_img_3690_5"  type="Letter"  url="40222bd986964dd9397d4d7df0db0776.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4331_img_3690_6"  type="Letter"  url="3ed43e0cfd7902f9bbfeb8584def12c8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4331_img_3690_1"/>
             June 22. 1916.  D1507/A/17/25 97   18, CADOGAN PLACE,<lb/>S.W.    My dear Chief   I attended the meeting of Unionist<lb/>members today &amp; send you the<lb/>following notes of it.  Banbury in chair. About 70 present.  Banbury explained reason of meeting.<lb/>No one trusted Carson more than he,<lb/><hi rend="underline">but</hi>, Ulster standpoint - not <hi rend="underline">necessarily</hi><lb/>identical with English. Proposed<lb/>that a deputation be sent to B.L.<lb/>to tell him the strong feeling of the<lb/>party against Home Rule during<lb/>the War. Called on W.Guinness.<lb/>Guinness spoke for 1/2 hour, entirely<lb/>on details showing growing power<lb/>of Sinn Fein &amp; their danger. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4331_img_3690_2"/>
             Proposed deputation,<lb/>I followed for 20 minutes. Agreed<lb/>with Guinness's <hi rend="underline">facts</hi>, but what<lb/>bearing had they on existing situation.<lb/>The fundamental fact — to which G<lb/>never alluded — was <hi rend="underline">Act on Statute<lb/>Book</hi>. What was Asquith's promise<lb/>of Amending Bill worth? and<lb/><hi rend="underline">could</hi><hi rend="underline">any</hi> amending Bill give<lb/>more than the proposed settlement?<lb/>Did G. imagine any fact he had<lb/>given was not familiar to Ulster<lb/>&amp; to Carson? I read the Ulster<lb/>Resolutions. Did anyone present<lb/>think we could ever <hi rend="underline">repeal the<lb/>Act</hi>? If not; what alternative<lb/>to settlement? The Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>, including<lb/>our own men, had called on us to<lb/>settle as a matter of war urgency.  <lb/>Could we take the responsibility of<lb/>refusing? If we appointed a deputation,<lb/>it must become known, and the<lb/>Nationalists would jump at a way<lb/>out of their difficulties, by placing the<lb/>odium on English Unionists.   <hi rend="underline">Finlay</hi>, was strongly against the<lb/>proposed settlement on two grounds.  (1) Whatever might be the alternative<lb/>after the war, we should not give<lb/>the Nationlists control of Ireland<lb/><hi rend="underline">during <sic>theWar</sic></hi>.  (2) The necessary Bill for giving<lb/>effect to settlement would divert<lb/>attention &amp; time of Parliament<lb/>&amp; the Country from <sic>theWar</sic>.<lb/>He thought a party meeting should<lb/>be called.  <hi rend="underline">Ashley</hi>read a letter from Bridgman<lb/>saying on B.L's authority that<lb/>the leaders would not commit  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4331_img_3690_3"/>
             the party without first consulting<lb/>them.  <hi rend="underline">:Hickman</hi>agreed with every word<lb/>of Sir R.Finlay!  <hi rend="underline">Astor</hi>was not prepared to join<lb/>in any step that even indirectly<lb/>might embarrass Carson, whom<lb/>he trusted not merely as the Ulster<lb/>Leader, but as a Unionist leader<lb/>from Imperial point <sic>of View</sic>.  <hi rend="underline">Mackinder </hi>agreed with Astor and<lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Neill. He opposed a deputation<lb/>or any resolution  <hi rend="underline">Joynson Hicks</hi> tried to rush the<lb/>meeting. It was the evident &amp;<lb/>general sense of the meeting<lb/>that we should let B.L. know<lb/>our views, he proposed certain<lb/>names as deputation.  I objected. There was no general  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4331_img_3690_4"/>
             D1507/A/M/25 94    <hi rend="underline">2</hi>     18, CADOGAN PLACE,<lb/>S.W.   Sense of the meeting. A deputation<lb/>would not represent <hi rend="underline">my</hi>views,<lb/>and before we could appoint<lb/>one we must have a vote on<lb/>the general question. I would<lb/>claim a vote even if I was alone,<lb/>which was not the case.  <hi rend="underline">Meux</hi>. Supported the proposed<lb/>Settlement on military<lb/>grounds. Finlay was wrong.<lb/>If Settlement were <hi rend="underline">now </hi>turned<lb/>down <hi rend="underline">by us</hi>, you would require<lb/>An army to hold down Ireland.<lb/>If the Settlement were carried,<lb/>Ireland would not be a danger<lb/>for some months anyhow: the  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4331_img_3690_5"/>
             Nationalists would quarrel<lb/>among themselves, &amp; we should<lb/>get on with <sic>theWar</sic>.  <hi rend="underline">Magnus</hi>, was against taking<lb/>a vote The meeting was clearly<lb/>divided, &amp; there was therefore<lb/>no general sense to report<lb/>to Bonar Law.  <hi rend="underline">Finlay</hi> agreed that a vote<lb/>would be a mistake. We could<lb/>all lay our own views before<lb/>B.L. &amp; we had his letter (read<lb/>by Ashley) &amp; that was good enough.  Meeting adjourned <seg type="foreign">sine die</seg><lb/>without passing anything.  I don't think any harm  <lb/>was done, but I suppose a<lb/>party meeting will be held<lb/>unless the Nationalists mean-<lb/>time reject the proposals.<lb/>If there is a party meeting<lb/>there will be a strong element<lb/>against the Settlement. I<lb/>should think that 50 out<lb/>of the 70 present were<lb/>that way.  Yours ever<lb/><hi rend="underline">Ronald M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Neill</hi>.   P.S I went <sic>tosee</sic> B.L. after<lb/>the meeting, but found Finlay<lb/>there &amp; Austen Chamberlain,   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4331_img_3690_6"/>
             96<lb/><lb/>So I came away.  RM<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>N.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>