<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2334">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Colonel Robert David Perceval Maxwell to Edith Maxwell, 18 June, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Colonel Robert David Perceval Maxwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Colonel Robert David Perceval Maxwell (b.1870) to his wife Edith Grace Perceval Maxwell (1872-1928). Col. Maxwell was wounded twice while serving with  the Ulster Division in the Great War. Two of their children, Richard and John  served in France. Richard was killed in action in July 1918.

Maxwell thanks his wife for her letters and expresses appreciation for her consulting him on various domestic/business matters. He comments on the state of some buildings on the farm, including the ‘big house’, and gives advice on works which should and should not be carried out.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Perceval-Maxwell Papers D/1556/27/1/1/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2334</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0553">Colonel Robert David Perceval Maxwell</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edith Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2334_img_1781_1"  type="Letter"  url="47d76386489bf5d1cbc4ea18e119c545.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2334_img_1781_2"  type="Letter"  url="1a7954a9da72edebea3434f42cc0d013.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2334_img_1781_3"  type="Letter"  url="7967ccdb3c4e6e102307c267152f40d5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2334_img_1781_1"/>
             18/<hi rend="superscript">6/16</hi>   My darling   I got two lovely letters from <lb/> you yesterday - all your letters <lb/> are delightful and I love you <lb/> consulting me about things You <lb/> must not think that it bothers <lb/> me a bit it only makes me <lb/> feel that we are nearer together <lb/> &amp; writing every day <seg type="del">juse</seg> just <lb/> as one talks makes things <lb/> much nicer. Now I must <lb/> try and answer your questions <lb/> in turn. You were quite right <lb/> to get Morrison to make up the <lb/> books for you - It is all the <lb/> better really for him to have <lb/> an idea as it will make it <lb/> easier for him to make up <lb/> income tax returns another
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2334_img_1781_2"/>
            time. I agree with you he <lb/>is quite discreet and as I <lb/>said before it would'nt<sic>unusually-spelled text</sic> <lb/>matter really if he was not <lb/>though of course one would<lb/> rather he was discreet. In the <lb/>future I would still make <lb/>him do the work. It is much better. <lb/> As to the UV7 fund I think <lb/> £20 would do very well. <lb/>We can always give more later <lb/>on if necessary &amp; I have not <lb/>given anything locally. If a <lb/>Regt subscription should be got <lb/>up I would not go beyond a <lb/>fiver anyhow &amp; I don't think <lb/>it is likely at present.  As to the house at the Sheep Shed <lb/>unless you actually have to put <lb/>a man into it I would not spend any money on it anyway <lb/>till I have seen it. Of course <lb/>I would keep the roof good <lb/>otherwise I <sic>wd</sic> not put it in <lb/> living order. It is not a very <lb/>suitable place for anyone <lb/>except perhaps a herd or trapper <lb/>&amp; it can always be done if you <lb/>have a man for it. Once you do <lb/>it, it has to be kept up &amp; it is <lb/>very likely to get out of repair <lb/>unless occupied.   About the   I suppose <lb/>you mean the big house at the <lb/>top of the hill not the cottage <lb/>where Cargo lived.   I would not do anything to the <lb/>cottage but the big house if <lb/>really bad should be put <lb/>in proper repair as to roof <lb/><sic>an</sic> essential parts.   Love
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2334_img_1781_3"/>
            wants a lot of watching &amp; <lb/> unless watched is dear <lb/> though he is a good &amp; fairly <lb/> honest workman. Timber <lb/> I know is exceptionally dear <lb/> now. If you think it should <lb/> be done I should send for <lb/> Whiteside &amp; get him to go <lb/>into the matter make a <lb/> specification &amp; estimate &amp; <lb/> let Love tender &amp; make <lb/> Whiteside pass the work. If <lb/> Whiteside thought it would last <lb/> without material damage for <lb/> another winter I would chance <lb/> timber being cheaper next <lb/> summer but it would not <lb/> pay to let damp in. <lb/> Home grown timber would be<lb/> no use as we have nothing<lb/> sufficiently seasoned 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>