<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5950">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Arthur John Eagleston to the Under-Secretary, Dublin Castle, 4 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Arthur John Eagleston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from A. J. Eagleston (1870-1944) to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), the Under-Secretary, Dublin Castle, confirming that the Petition of Right of John and Agnes Scott, John McCullough and Mary Shearer has been laid before the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, with a copy of a letter from the War Office.Arthur John Eagleston was a civil servant who served as assistant secretary of the British Home Office from 1913-1932. Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7280/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5950</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0023">Arthur John Eagleston</persName>
              <date>1916-04-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0856">Home Office, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Under-Secretary, Dublin Castle</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5950_img_1800_1"  type="Letter"  url="cd2ff7449db612ac5f1f576315b6419e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5950_img_1800_1"/>
                HOME OFFICE,  WHITEHALL    4th April, 1916.   Sir,   I am directed by the Secretary of State to transmit <lb/>to you, to be laid before His Excellency the Lord Lieutenant <lb/>of Ireland, the accompanying Petition of Right of John and <lb/>Agnes Scott, John McCulloch, and Mary Shearer, together with <lb/>a copy of a letter from the War Office with reference thereto; <lb/> and I am to request that the Petition may be referred to His <lb/>Majesty's Attorney-General for Ireland for the favour of his <lb/>report whether there is any objection to the document being <lb/>endorsed in the usual manner 'Let Right be done'. <seg type="closer">  I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  A.G.Eagleston   The Under Secretary,  Dublin Castle.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>