<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4620">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Kirkpatrick to Alfred Miller, 2 July 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Kirkpatrick</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

Alfred Miller served as both the registrar of the Royal College of Surgeons (1910-1938) and as secretary to the Conjoint Board of the College of Physicians and College of Surgeons. At the outbreak of the Rising Miller instructed James Duncan, the college porter, to lock the college doors in order to deter Michael Mallin&#39;s occupying rebel force in St. Stephen&#39;s Green. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-238</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4620</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1453">Thomas Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date>1917-07-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0696">Alfred Miller</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4620_img_3961_1"  type="Letter"  url="05865c0db5399e970d7f34783c17a4ec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4620_img_3961_1"/>
             2nd JULY 17.   A.Miller, Esq., <lb/>Secretary, <lb/>Committee of Management, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   I am requested by the President and Fellows of the <lb/>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, in reply to your <lb/>letter of the 15th June, to forward you a copy of the <lb/>following resolution passed by the College last Friday: <lb/>Resolved: "That the College agrees to the recognition of <lb/>the course of instruction in Chemistry and Physics <lb/>given in the Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, <lb/>provided that, in the accordance with the regulations of the <lb/>General Medical Council, such instruction is given in <lb/>the day time."   I remain, <lb/>Yours faithfully,   <lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>