<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5571">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn,  15 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. 

Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.

James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 

Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters. This letter contains much local gossip.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5571</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1972</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5571_img_667_1"  type="Letter"  url="c76ca79b8b6b33379f6c7df222101789.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5571_img_667_2"  type="Letter"  url="4aef4ba78b727d03e93e2944a9523aec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5571_img_667_1"/>
            <!-- Writing atthe top left-hand side of the page, written sideways --> We got currant cake with<lb/>wine on it &amp; Jenny<lb/>called it <hi rend="underline">tipsy cake</hi><lb/>The hint might suit Nora.<lb/>She goes in for them  <!-- Beginning of letter --> Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar,    15<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> March 1916    My dearest James   I was glad to get your letter this morning I<lb/>would have written but the evening turned out so bad<lb/>I could not get it to post I hope you had not been expecting one<lb/>as I would not like to disappoint my poor hard working man, you<lb/>should not have worked so late as to take the sleep of yourself<lb/>so long as you are working like that you have no need to fast or pray or<lb/>anything- it takes a lot of obligations off you after. I may go to the<lb/>post this evening and do the Stations of the Cross. I have gone every<lb/>evening I could since Lent came in &amp; I always say a little prayer for somebody.-<lb/>You need not be one bit sorry you did not speak to John Duffy I am<lb/>very glad you did not let him think someone feels above him. M<hi rend="underline">rs</hi><lb/><seg type="unclear">Sweey</seg> was in Balrath last night. They were telling her there, all<lb/>John was telling Gertie &amp; Cookie Kiernan the day they paid him<lb/>a visit. He said the reason I am going to marry you, is because “I<lb/><hi rend="underline">am <hi rend="underline">mad</hi> he did not marry me- that I was expecting he would”</hi> I<lb/>would not <hi rend="superscript">be</hi> quite so sore about that as about Jennie- he said she<lb/>married Corbett because Jim Fay would not marry her and that she wrote<lb/>scores of letters to him (J Fay), he saw them himself. He told a lot of other 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5571_img_667_2"/>
             stories about other respectable girls all to the effect that <hi rend="superscript">they</hi> were<lb/><hi rend="underline">mad after</hi> him &amp; asked him to marry them etc. I think he<lb/>must be going off his head to say I was thinking of my blood<lb/>first cousin &amp; a man I always looked on as a mild form of<lb/>the <hi rend="underline">old boy himself</hi> <hi rend="superscript">from</hi> the few things as I told you, you may form<lb/>no opinion of him, there was a little foundation for Jennie<lb/>about the letters, You know J. Fay was really in love<lb/>with Jennie, &amp; wanted to marry her, he wrote constant to her.<lb/>She answered a few of them where she wanted to get him<lb/>to sell tickets &amp; again where he said he’d go on a booze<lb/>the morn he should have a letter if he had not. I saw the<lb/>letters she wrote &amp; partly dictated them; the sarcasm of them I<lb/>remember well left them as far as she was concerned that they could be<lb/>read on the chapel gates- I know all that rests with you. He speaks<lb/>of Mother &amp; Mrs S as Monsheen Fay &amp; Mary Seery the talk of<lb/>him in Kelly’s could not be compared to Dan Kiernan’s before<lb/>his bride- enough to make you happy you did not speak<lb/>to him if you did see him-.  I won’t write anymore it has taken me ages to write this,<lb/>you would not see by it my hand is shaking. I have a bit of<lb/>a headache.  Bye Bye now dearest James  Tons of warm &amp; best<hi rend="underline">est</hi> love<lb/>from your loving   May<lb/><hi rend="underline">  </hi> <seg type="unclear"></seg>  I am getting to be a great walker<lb/>I never feel my <hi rend="underline">ankle at all</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>