<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2251">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Maurice Headlam, 19 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to civil servant and Treasury Remembrancer Maurice Headlam (1873-1956). Montgomery was a lawyer and politician. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
In this letter Montgomery discuss present government policy in relation to Ireland. He believes it is lunacy but that statements made in private to the Ulster Unionist Council persuaded him that it was expedient to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposals under protest. Montgomery also endorses Carson as leader seeing as he has managed to avoid &#34;Asquixiation&#34;, a term derived from the &#39;Morning Post&#39; to describe the influence of the Prime Minister Herbert Henry Asquith (1852-1928).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2251</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Maurice Headlam</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2251_img_1694_1"  type="Letter"  url="6f5215a6c54e423fcb0858465bbede9a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2251_img_1694_1"/>
            Copy  19th June, 1916.   My dear Headlam,    There is a good demand for houses in Fivemiletown, <lb/> but I do not think George Armstrong could find a good <lb/> tenant for the present police barracks who would pay him <lb/> more than £31 a year. It is not a favourite part of the <lb/> town.    On the face of it the present Government Policy about <lb/> this country seems absolute lunacy; but statements were <lb/> made in private to the Ulster Unionist Council which per- <lb/>suaded us that it was expedient to accept Lloyd George's <lb/>proposals under protest. I do not like what we did a <lb/> bit, but is still seems to me the only thing we could do <lb/> under the very exdraodinary circumstances. Bonar Law, <lb/> Walter Long, etc. seem to be 'Asquixiated.' Carson seems to <lb/> have kept his head better than any other of our leaders, <lb/> so all we can do is to take his advice and hope for the best.   I am going to Dublin to-day for a couple of nights, <lb/> and may perhaps see you.   Yours very truly , 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>