<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1042">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Miss Frances Reddy to Matthew Nathan, 26 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frances Reddy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Miss Frances Reddy of Carlow to Matthew Nathan, under-secretary for Ireland. It concerns her application for the grand of administration and license of the public house owned by her late sister Margaret Reddy to be transferred from Margaret to herself.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO RP/1916/3661/1, NAI CSO RP/1916/3661/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1042</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1490">Frances Reddy</persName>
              <date>1916-02-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0460">Carlow, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0152">Sir Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1042_img_312_1"  type="Letter"  url="047688cadaf87682427f782af29d13a4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1042_img_312_1"/>
                67 TULLOW STREET  CARLOW    26th Feb. 1916   No. 3201  Sir   I duly received yours of the 23rd instant for which I am <lb/>much obliged. I note that my application for permission <lb/>to sell exciseable liquors until next Quarter Sessions.has <lb/>been forwarded for the consideration of the Commissioners <lb/>of Customs and Excise, and that the police have been <lb/>instructed not to interfere pending the decision to be come to <lb/>at Quarter Sessions.  Kindly say if you will return me the Grant of Adminis- <lb/>tration to my late sister Margaret Reddy and the original <lb/>License which accompanied my Petition or will they be <lb/>forwarded to me by the Commissioners of Customs and Excise? <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir <lb/>Your Obedient Servant  (Miss) Frances Reddy   The UnderSecretary   for Ireland  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>