<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0113">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 20 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Helena Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin. Marie writes home to Dublin from a field hospital in France to keep up to date with the news. She also writes about the possible second cousin she found, Mr. MacDonnell, an Australian in the army. Marie goes on to give her point of view on the leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party, John Redmond&#39;s (1856-1918), speech about bringing in conscription to Ireland. She gives details on the position of the Irish soldiers in the British army and the negative way she hears people talk about the Irishmen in the army.Marie Martin otherwise known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39; was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF169-1916-10-20, BF169-1916-10-20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/113</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0618">Marie Helena Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-10-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1635">Monkstown, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_1"  type="Letter"  url="acf4a745faa9dc34a48882d3b372b788.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_2"  type="Letter"  url="aeea2bf0e333c9c4cb76fb722824d18e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_3"  type="Letter"  url="2ea7b6a73c89e9ba8703c018990e5bcb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_4"  type="Letter"  url="0ced053dd4ee86febbc5fcbb097d197f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_5"  type="Letter"  url="98d6faafbe243969a10591a1ae1ef582.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_6"  type="Envelope"  url="39b1d97af7cb7b291a5542c2b9a59bdf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0113_img_1196_7"  type="NULL"  url="350a0c006cdc43dfcce3be9f6c0e4e7e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">Church Army Recreation Hut</hi><lb/>ON ACTIVE SERVICE <lb/><hi rend="underline">WITH. THE. BRITISH. EXPEDITIONARY. FORCE</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   A 1000 thanks for <lb/>your daily report of Uncle <lb/>Frank, I hope it is not <lb/>giving you too much trouble but <lb/>you have no idea what a relief <lb/>it is to hear from you I am sorry <lb/>to hear there is no decided change for <lb/>the better but still it looks well if <lb/>he has had no return for so long Oh <lb/>I do hope he will get better it must <lb/>nearly kill poor Granny as I do not <lb/>think she has ever been the same since <lb/>poor Uncle Bernard’s death R.I.P. <lb/>I have been wondering ever since your <lb/>letter, where did Uncle Frank Haemorrhage it <lb/>sounds so <sic>extrordanary</sic> with his complaint  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_2"/>
              as I never heard of his <lb/>lungs or <sic>Stomack</sic> being <lb/>delicate. &amp; how is poor Aunt <lb/>Maysie I wrote to her the other day but <lb/>it is so hard to express <sic>one</sic> feelings <lb/>on paper.  Oh ever so many thanks for the cake it <lb/>was just delicious <sic>infact</sic> every one <lb/>said it was the best cake they have <lb/>eaten since they came to <sic>france</sic> I do <lb/>not mind how many you send out !! <lb/>especially if you want work for the <lb/>cook, I hope every thing is <sic>a</sic> satisfac <lb/>tory with her as the cake &amp; all ought to be well—  A most extraordinary thing has happened <lb/>to me, the other day a new M.O. turned  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_3"/>
              up from 32 General &amp; he had <lb/>been here a week or so I just <lb/>met him a few times he <lb/>seems quite nice &amp; an Austra <lb/>lian, the other day he went back to 32 <lb/>to see a friend of his &amp; his greatest <lb/>pal there is a M<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">r</hi></hi>. Mac Donnell who asked <lb/>him if he knew any of the girls at <lb/>25 General so he said No only just a <lb/>few, then he said do you by any <lb/>chance know a Miss Martin, so he <lb/>said yes she just happens to be one I <lb/>know as she was working in my ward <lb/>because he said <sic>Ihave</sic> just received <lb/>a letter from an Aunt of mine telling <lb/>me she is at 25 &amp; that he is my 2<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">nd</hi></hi><lb/>cousin, he has never seen me &amp; I have  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_4"/>
              never seen him &amp; he is Australian. <lb/>The whole thing sounds so funny I never <lb/>knew I had any Mac Donnell cousins <lb/>however he is coming out to see <lb/>me some day when I suppose I shall <lb/>learn more about him — can you give <lb/>me any light on the subject?­­ Captain <lb/>Pinnock says he is a real good sort &amp; one <lb/>of the boys, most probably he will come <lb/>out on Sunday for Tea — I wonder who <lb/>wrote to him to come &amp; look me up. <lb/>I was wondering was it Minnie Fitzgerald <lb/>I wonder if you would mind sending me <lb/>out those very strong pair of Brown <lb/>boots &amp; there are some brown stockings <lb/>in my white cupboard behind the <lb/><sic>the</sic> door, it is so frightfully wet here <lb/>at times I think they would be  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_5"/>
              good things to have out <lb/>here.  I hope by this you will <lb/>have had good news of <lb/>Tommy — it is really terrible <lb/>to think of all the things that have <lb/>happened in this year and cause so <lb/>much extra worry &amp; sorrow but it is <lb/>Gods Holy Will — so we must face it bravely. <lb/>We have a new Chaplain here a much <lb/>younger man &amp; in a way better for <lb/>a large place like this it is really sad <lb/>to hear the way religion is looked <sic>up</sic><lb/>any one is good enough &amp; some just <lb/>remember their Mothers teaching them <lb/>to make the Sign of the cross &amp; then when <lb/>they left home they <sic>when</sic> to any church <lb/>&amp; now they do not know what they <lb/>are. No indeed I shall not forget to <lb/>pray for Ireland, it nearly breaks my  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_6"/>
              heart sometimes to hear the <lb/>way the men speak of the Irish &amp; <lb/>how they will have to fill up the Irish <lb/>Div: with English men. This morning <lb/>I have spent reading the weekly Irish <lb/>times of the 14 Oct: I do not know that <lb/>I quite approve of Redmond’s <sic>speach</sic><lb/>about conscription it would be a pity <lb/>if we had to have it but at the <lb/>same time if the men do not come <lb/>forward it is the only thing to be <lb/>done. <sic>Ireally</sic> do think that threatening <lb/>Ireland with it has stopped recruiting <lb/>to a certain extent don’t you—  Must close now it is time for duty. <lb/>Fondest love to every one a big kiss <lb/>to Andrew &amp; Desmond &amp; heaps of love <lb/>to you dearest of Mothers.  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0113_img_1196_7"/>
               20 OCT 1916   M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Martin  Greenbank  Monstown  Co. Dublin  <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>