<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4476">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marion Elizabeth Duggan to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 16 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marion Duggan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Marion Elizabeth Duggan (1885 -1943) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946). In the letter Duggan thanks Skeffington for leaflets she sent out and mentions that recently discovered the &#39;emotional educational use&#39; of Emmet. Additionally, Duggan discusses her local news, such as the sorrow of her fellow residents over the death of her son and a &#39;feminist victory&#39; that occurred when schoolboys dressed as girls for the production of a play. Duggan aslso invites both Skeffingtons to a party she is hosting, the main entertainment of which shall be a mock debate entitled &#34;Should Sheehy-Skeffington be hanged?&#34;

Marion Duggan was a committed member of the Irish Women&#39;s Reform League. While disagreeing with direct militancy Duggan believed that constitutional reform had a greater chance of achieving the vote than direct action. She was also a continual contributor to the &#34;Irish Citizen&#34;, a newspaper founded in 1912 to further cause of suffrage and feminism in Ireland. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; MS 33,604/17-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4476</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0248">Marion Duggan</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0229">Middleton College, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1943</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_1"  type="Letter"  url="c6f6531f8ceaeb4ba6c92775b4c0c206.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_2"  type="Letter"  url="09c2996607e519537fe211b72f76e530.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_3"  type="Letter"  url="cf02c41c89f83cc91e2bbae8d29fe6e2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_4"  type="Letter"  url="a854109bc27fc186671b804285d1ce62.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_5"  type="NULL"  url="6b2b6b6b740fdcc302d1c53705dcfd8c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_6"  type="Letter"  url="2430fd63eeff7da47967777343e80797.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4476_img_3822_7"  type="Letter"  url="16e82ea07d0cd026edec4f400e351d35.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_1"/>
             Midleton College,<lb/>Co Cork.   16 — 3 — 16    Dear Mrs Skeffington,   A thousand thanks for<lb/>pamphlets, they are both like sea<lb/>breezes! But never, no <hi rend="underline">never</hi><lb/>will I be happy again until I<lb/>know that man, and talk to<lb/>him about teaching! Funnily<lb/>enough, <hi rend="underline">I</hi> had actually discovered<lb/>the emotional educational use of Emmett<lb/>I mentioned it in a current comment<lb/><sic>wh</sic> I hope reached editor?  I am in the mood for a chat and a  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_2"/>
             chat with both of you! Do you<lb/>remember our old Monday afternoons?  It is terribly sad here. The Parkers<lb/>lost their elder boy (4 1/2) last July,<lb/>and it nearly killed her, while<lb/>he  too  is still grieving a good deal.  One is glad to be able to give a<lb/>little sympathy when they talk<lb/>about the dead child, but living<lb/>in the house where there is a great<lb/>personal sorrow is so different<lb/>from our merry  intercourse &amp;  determination to<lb/>right the Universe.  We produced 'The Jackdaw' with<lb/>great success last week. The editor<lb/>would have been repaid for giving  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_3"/>
             me the ticket if he had seen how<lb/>boys enjoyed themselves. We scored a<lb/>great feminist Victory by being let<lb/>dress boys as women. One or two<lb/>strangers refused to believe that<lb/>'Mrs Broderick' was not a girl !  It emphasises the essential<lb/>likeness of the sexes so well.!  They are working very well too.<lb/>But it is hard to influence them,<lb/>at least it takes tact.! I began by<lb/>telling them tons about PR<lb/>regular Aston stuff, and never<lb/>mentioned W.S: try elaborately to<lb/>avoid subject, with result that<lb/>they shudder at 'PR' &amp; try hard to 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_4"/>
             coax me into talking W.S. all 3 are<lb/>great authorities on Mrs Cousins.<lb/>I saw her in Killarney, 2 knows<lb/>a brother &amp; 3 knows a sister (Mrs<lb/>Dobbs) whose husband, he says, is<lb/>a cousin of Mr Parker.  You may picture me resolutely<lb/>refusing to be told whom her brother<lb/>in Dunmanivay married!  I had a horrid experience tho'<lb/>talking to them seriously about<lb/>drink, they started to tell me about<lb/>a former master who drank!  I shut that up, but one saw the<lb/>evil was done. I am sure however,<lb/>they are as yet alright about sex. 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_5"/>
             I'm trying to beguile one of them <lb/>to enter T.C.D as J.M.H's pupil, <lb/>in the hope that he would <lb/>look after them when they go to <lb/>College. R.M. Gwynn will probably <lb/>help too. You might mention <lb/>this to H if you see him.   How is Maurice? I hope his <lb/>wife is better?   I am really writing to tell <lb/>you that I am giving a tea <lb/>party at Shamrock Lodge <lb/>Rathmines Road, during holidays. <lb/>Mrs F  is lending her house,
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_6"/>
             I do want you both! Wil<lb/>Thursday 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April suit you?  I want to ask about 15 <seg type="unclear">pals</seg><lb/>&amp; have a mock debate on<lb/>Shoudl Sheehy Skeffington be<lb/>hanged! but this depends on his<lb/>positively promising to come.  I am going to ask JC too, but<lb/>it is no good writing to that lot<lb/>they never answer. They have<lb/>never sent me a paper all this<lb/>time !  Nothing doing in Courts, I suppose?<lb/>I <hi rend="underline">am longing to see</hi> Citizen!<lb/>Will pay all my debts when I see you ! 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_4476_img_3822_7"/>
             It is nearly schooltime, so I must<lb/>stop.  yours affectionately<lb/>M E Duggan.  <lb/>Mirabile dictu !  have just got letter from<lb/>Graduates Assoc asking me to speak<lb/>re W.Lawyers on April 7th or<lb/><seg type="del">send</seg> suggest  substitute. They <hi rend="underline">may</hi> delay<lb/>meeting till 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> for me. If not, would<lb/><hi rend="underline">you</hi> do it? I am mentioning you<lb/>to them. I think they ought to tackle<lb/>members of Bar &amp; get their support ! 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>