<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0123">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to Mary Martin, 4 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary. Marie writes of how busy her work has been, writing of some cases she has worked with. She describes the death of a man from gas gangrene, and that she has been assigned to work on scabies and impetigo, of which she knows little. The letter includes news on the health of Marie&#39;s uncle, Frank Martin (1870-?) and her brother Thomas Martin (1891-?). Marie explains that she is ashamed for having never written and that she was waiting for news from her uncle Charles Martin (1871-?) and that her work had become busy. The &#39;Skins&#39; that Marie refers to arriving are the Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers regiment.Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>B-F-166-1916-10-04, B-F-166-1916-10-04</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/123</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-10-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0019">Greenbank, Monkestown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0123_img_1207_1"  type="Letter"  url="b0493d6687e2d595a9659905fcbe56ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0123_img_1207_2"  type="Letter"  url="39cc58bd5dbb9163bf1d9a5a483e5eaf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0123_img_1207_3"  type="Letter"  url="6ddc048f4a2bc3d79be007ac82282972.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0123_img_1207_4"  type="Letter"  url="fc94e8ee639cc4b6cd57ad40f5c4d755.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0123_img_1207_5"  type="Letter"  url="78de7cd392dbd0ce6e4a8c6220d1ec1b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0123_img_1207_6"  type="Letter"  url="ef305b6f221909fc02545247e32e1dbb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0123_img_1207_1"/>
              B/F/1/66    <hi rend="underline">4-10-16</hi>   My very dearest Mother,   I do not know <lb/> what you will think of <lb/> me for not writing for so <lb/> long but we have been <lb/> terrible busy since the <lb/> 25<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> when I was sent <lb/> to Surgical 8 9 &amp; 10 <lb/> when we had some <lb/> very bad cases indeed <lb/> &amp; <sic>Iam</sic> sorry to say <lb/> one man died he <lb/>has gas <sic>gangarine</sic>, it <lb/> was too late when he  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0123_img_1207_2"/>
              got down here to amputate <lb/> he had three big <sic>opera <lb/>tion</sic> hoping to save his <lb/> life but he had his <lb/> whole <sic>septem</sic> poisoned— <lb/>&amp; died. We had several <lb/> of these cases but I am <lb/> glad to say the limbs <lb/> have been saved &amp; they <lb/> are all getting on very <lb/> well. After we had been <lb/> open a few days we <lb/> were turned into the <sic>accute</sic><lb/> surgical tents &amp; got all <lb/> the Bad cases from <lb/> the other <sic>Tent</sic>. Just as  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0123_img_1207_3"/>
              we were coming off the <lb/> other night a man <lb/><sic>Haemoraged</sic>, we did have an <lb/> exciting time, poor man <lb/> he lost pints but we got <lb/> it stopped before it was <lb/> too late—  We were just beginning <lb/> to get straight &amp; our <lb/> cases getting better &amp; I <lb/> was to have this <seg type="unclear">evening</seg><lb/> off when a convoy of <lb/> skins The Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers were known as The Skins arrived &amp; filled <lb/> my old tents M. 8 <lb/> so had to go there  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0123_img_1207_4"/>
              in my off duty time <lb/> &amp; have been sent back <lb/> there for duty, it is really <lb/> hard luck as <sic>Ihave</sic><lb/> had all the worry &amp; <lb/> real hard work of the <lb/> other tents &amp; now I have <lb/> to start alone on Scabies <lb/> &amp; Impetigo which I know <lb/> absolutely nothing about. <lb/> However it is all in a days <lb/> work, I am feeling A1 <lb/> now— <sic>but</sic> if you do not <lb/><sic>here</sic> for a day or two <lb/> you know I am alright <lb/> but very busy— Hoping all <lb/> the Mumps are over—  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0123_img_1207_5"/>
              &amp; that you are keeping <lb/> very well. I am delighted <lb/> to hear about Uncle Frank being a little better. <lb/> &amp; poor Tommy <seg type="unclear">how</seg><lb/> he must worry—  <sic>Iam</sic> ashamed to say <lb/><sic>Ihave</sic> never written <lb/> but really <sic>Ihave</sic> been <lb/> waiting till Charlie <lb/> wrote &amp; told me the <lb/> news himself as I <lb/> was not quite sure <lb/> it was public but <lb/> as <sic>Ihad</sic> not heard <lb/> I intended writing  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0123_img_1207_6"/>
              when this terrible rush <lb/> came on &amp; we have <lb/> had time for nothing <lb/><sic>butwork</sic>—  I shall write as soon <lb/> as I can I never <lb/> received his letters. <lb/> Now <sic>Imust</sic> close <lb/> am dead tired <seg type="closer"> Fondest love to <lb/> everyone at home  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>