<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1457">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Catherine Wheelwright to Fr Thomas Wheelwright, 23 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Catherine Wheelwright</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Catherine Wheelwright (née Coll) (1858-1932) to her son Fr Thomas Wheelwright (1890-1946). She writes from Rochdale, New York concerning the Easter Rising and Éamon&#39;s involvement. She tells of the various influential contacts she has made in America on his behalf. Catherine Wheelwright was the mother of Éamon de Valera (1882-1975), teacher, revolutionary and politician and Fr Wheelwright was her son and de Valera&#39;s half brother. Éamon de Valera had joined the Irish Volunteers in 1913 and was adjutant to Thomas MacDonagh (1878-1916), Dublin Brigade commandant. He went on to command forces at Bolands Mill during the Rising and was the most senior participant to escape execution. De Valera would go on to become one of the most influential figures in Ireland&#39;s 20th century.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>DeValera Papers, P150/201/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1457</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1060">Catherine Wheelwright</persName>
              <date>1916-06-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0525">New York, U.S.A.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Fr.Thomas Wheelwright</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1457_img_905_1"  type="Letter"  url="ef90b657e085bd7be003298ba42b84ae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1457_img_905_2"  type="Letter"  url="f92922644f32aac587ca456310c57207.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1457_img_905_3"  type="Letter"  url="958a0a0294f0d33267e66ee755d76308.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1457_img_905_4"  type="Letter"  url="d3744fbd1f07f1ae1b04015d3b0392e6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1457_img_905_5"  type="Letter"  url="ef90b657e085bd7be003298ba42b84ae.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1457_img_905_1"/>
                18 Brighton St  Rochester N Y    23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> June 19160   My Dear Son   We received your <lb/> letters. I am so pleased you are <lb/> well and happy. I hope Our <lb/> dear Lord will always keep <lb/> you so. I know you will <lb/> if you try to do God's work as <lb/> faithful as you can and <lb/> always remember you are <lb/> a priest of God. We are well <lb/> also thank God. I have filled <lb/> the Blank Certificate today it  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1457_img_905_2"/>
              was too late to see a Notary Public <lb/> I will try tomorrow morning to find <lb/> one if possible. Now please if <lb/> you have Sinead's and Uncle <lb/> Patt's letters send them to me. <lb/> There can't be much in them <lb/>to upset me. I have realized <lb/> all the facts about Eddie <lb/>since I saw in the papers <lb/> about the Sinn Fein uprising <lb/> I knew he couldn't escape <lb/> the authorities over there when <lb/> he was a Professor of Gaelic <lb/>in Dublin University. Innocent <lb/> or guilty they treat every Catholic <lb/> alike 'Perfidious Albion' I have <lb/> being praying for him and I  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1457_img_905_3"/>
              hoped Almighty God in His mercy <lb/> would save him from an unexpected <lb/> or sudden death or from a prison <lb/> cell. However May His Holy Will <lb/> be done. I went to see Chief Quigley <lb/> yesterday. he sent me to a Mr McCarthy <lb/> who has charge here of the Sinn Fein <lb/> movement in U.S. I gave him some <lb/> old letters of Ed's also copy of Birth <lb/> Certificate and all particulars, he <lb/> told  me  a Mr Moore was coming here <lb/> in a few days and he would <lb/> shown them and consult with <lb/> him. Mr Moore is National Secretary <lb/> of the organisation. Mr McCarthy got <lb/> a letter from Post Master Buckley <lb/> saying Senator Wadsworth would  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1457_img_905_4"/>
              attend to the matter or had already <lb/> attended to it he had notified Ambassador <lb/> Page in London. I am not <lb/> so sure is this statement correct. I saw <lb/> Mr Whitney and he said he would <lb/> write to Congressman Danforth <lb/> today and he would tell us what <lb/> to do. I am sorry I didn't know about <lb/> it sooner for I can do more than <lb/> you are aware of. You ought  to  know <lb/> although I am frail now Almighty <lb/> God has given me nerves of <lb/> steel and in His Mercy given <lb/> me a peculiar mind, if I must <lb/> say so. All these things I believe <lb/> come from His Divine Wisdom to prepare <lb/> us for a brighter eternity. I will  This is added upside down at bottom of page  P.S send me Sinead's address  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1457_img_905_5"/>
               This is added vertically at top of page  enclose all the letters documents <lb/> in this letter. Don't worry <lb/> for us. Everything <lb/> will come out all right with <lb/> God's help.  <seg type="closer"> Your loving mother. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>