<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0063">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Gerald Horan to James O'Shea, 18 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Gerald Horan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Gerald Horan (b.1880) a barrister, to James O&#39;Shea (b.1866) a member of the Killarney District Council and Kerry County Council. The letter regards a denial on the part of James O&#39;Shea which stated he did not play a prominent role in the disturbance of a Recruitment Committee Meeting. The letter states that O&#39;Shea&#39;s involvement in such an action cannot be over looked by the Lord Chancellor, Stanley Buckmaster (1861-1934). It then states that O&#39;Shea&#39;s position as magistrate is superseded due to his actions. There are three attachments. The first is a printed account of O&#39;Shea&#39;s denial. The second is an extract from parliamentary questions regarding the evidence against O&#39;Shea. The third is a newspaper clipping regarding Poor Law Relief.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7020/3C/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/63</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0761">Gerald Horan</persName>
              <date>1916-02-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1301">Four Courts, Dublin, County Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0144">James O&#39;Shea</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0668">Killarney, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0063_img_1130_1"  type="Letter"  url="6ba633064d1c17bc8d555de388f676ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0063_img_1130_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="72c25803e016f771d6c012b3783a2553.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0063_img_1130_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="c0bf55962c5d709414fa47e83ba162e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0063_img_1130_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="605feef0ef48b92508916241806e0861.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0063_img_1130_1"/>
                Crown and hanaper Office,  Four Courts, Dublin,    18th February 1916   Sir,   I have placed your letter of the 16th inst. before The Lord<lb/> Chancellor who directs me to state that he notes that your denial<lb/> is merely that you did not take a prominent position in the pro-<lb/> cession which interdered with the Recruiting Meeting at Killarney<lb/> on the 6th inst.  The Lord Chancellor cannot overlook your conduct as magis-<lb/> trate in being present with these persons on the occasion, &amp;<lb/> accordingly desires me to apprise you that he has deemed it his<lb/> duty to supersede you from further acting as a magistrate, &amp;<lb/> I am to enclose you herewith the usual Writ in that behalf.  The Lord Chancellor further directs me to say that the que-<lb/> stion of the prosecution mentioned in your letter is not one at all<lb/> in which he can enter, as he is only concerned with your action<lb/> as a Justice of the Peace. <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir,<lb/> Your obedient Servant,<lb/>  GERALD HORAN   James O'Shea, Esq.  Chairman,  Killarney Rural District Council  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0063_img_1130_2"/>
              Summary of Mr. O'Shea's reply dated 16th February 1916 which has <lb/> been mislaid.  Denied that he had occupied a prominent position in the procession<lb/> and stated that if he had interfered in any way with the Recruiting<lb/> Meeting he could be prosecuted for it.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0063_img_1130_3"/>
              Parliamentary Question.<lb/> Dated, 3rd March, 1916. From Power to Under Secretary.  Star Notice for Wednesday 8th March, No.8.<lb/> Mr Ginnell to ask Mr Attorney General for Ireland, if he will<lb/> specify the alleged illegality or breach of duty as a Magistrate<lb/> for which the Lord Chancellor of Ireland has deprived of his<lb/> statutory commission of the peace Mr James O'Shea, Member of the<lb/> Kerry County Council, Chairman of the Killarney Rural District<lb/> Council &amp; in virtue of this position a Magistrate for the County<lb/> of Kerry. What evidence was given. By whom? What opportunity<lb/> was given to Mr O'Shea for cross-examining the informer &amp; under<lb/> what statute did the Lord Chancellor purports to override the pro-<lb/> vision on this subject in the Local Government (Ireland) Act<lb/> 1898.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0063_img_1130_4"/>
             <seg type="head">Poor Law Relief Act, 1914.</seg> 103. Mr COOTE asked the Chief Secre-<lb/> tary for Ireland, in view of the increased<lb/> taxation which must inevitably arise under<lb/> the coming War Budget, if he will assist<lb/> public bodies in Ireland to get rid of their<lb/> unnecessary expenditure in some of the<lb/> forms of poor relief by amending the Poor<lb/> Relief Act, 1914, passed as a war measure,<lb/> wither by omitting in Section 1, line 8, the<lb/> words, In connection with the present<lb/> War, or by adding after after the word<lb/> war the words, In order to secure greater<lb/> economy in Poor Law administration?  Mr. BIRRELL: The Bill for the Poor<lb/> Relief (Ireland) Act, 1914, when introduced<lb/> contained a provision which would have<lb/> had the effect that the hon. Member de-<lb/> sires, but owing to the opposition to legis-<lb/> lation not confined to war purposes I was<lb/> obliged to accept an Amendment omitting<lb/> this proivision. If the hon. Member puts<lb/> down an Amendment for the reinstate-<lb/> ment of this provision n Committee on the<lb/> Local Government (Emergency Provisions)<lb/> Bill now before the House, I should be<lb/> disposed to accept it with the assent of the<lb/> Committee.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>