<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2983">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr Kathleen Lynn to Dora, 31 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Lynn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Dr. Kathleen Lynn 1874-1955) to a Dora (surname not given. The letter consists of a lengthy attempt to persuade Dora of the rightfulness of the Easter Rising and the Irish Nationalist cause. 

Dr Kathleen Lynn was a medical practitioner, a suffragist, a nationalist, and a revolutionary.  Lynn was Chief Medical Officer of the Irish Citizen Army during Easter 1916, and was a part of the City Hall garrison, of which she took command of the garrison after the death of Seán Connolly. After independence, Lynn played a major role in improving public health including the eradication of tuberculosis in Ireland.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Military Archives of Ireland, Br Allen Collection, 1916 Collection, IE/AL/1916/128</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2983</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1086">Kathleen Lynn</persName>
              <date>1916-10-31</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Dora</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_1"  type="Letter"  url="a54a74e042288acfbfbaeb8cd059cd2a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_2"  type="Letter"  url="dcfde72674840ed89d6e4f46b67ada0c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_3"  type="Letter"  url="9bf00a7d5c3fe1322c64796763c3f50d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_4"  type="Letter"  url="b9f9c9c702d596801818189c05899e0b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_5"  type="Letter"  url="97e5b294479fbdc052ceb429256b1e5e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_6"  type="Letter"  url="c2425a1f741cbffdb840ced07b745192.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_7"  type="Letter"  url="3769a43702c18c70219b26752a665287.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2983_img_2387_8"  type="Letter"  url="3fa82e0dcf97e8ffcbee4f4b42dbdf74.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_1"/>
            <!-- The page numbers are wrong in this letter --> .  31.10.16    My dearest Dora   (?Sigerson)   Surely you misunder-<lb/>stand my letter. Did not I say<lb/>Mc Bride had nothing to say to us<lb/>&amp; only joined one centre after<lb/>the thing had started &amp; that nothing<lb/>in his life became him like<lb/>the leaving of it? Was not this<lb/>the gist of what I said? By what<lb/>mental process do you construe<lb/><hi rend="underline">that</hi> into saying I whitewashed<lb/>him or that I have changed my<lb/>opinion of him as regards his<lb/>former life? I have not changed my<lb/>opinion of him, but I think the<lb/>hidden nobleness in him came<lb/>out at the last. If I ever said<lb/>Countess Markieviecz's house was<lb/>a temptation to anyone it was<lb/>before I <hi rend="underline">knew</hi> her, or, perhaps, when<lb/>her husband was there, his influence<lb/>was not for good, but<lb/>madame's always was, she has 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_2"/>
            saved &amp; succoured many a one<lb/> who would otherwise have gone<lb/> under. I know no one purer or<lb/> kindlier, she would divide her last<lb/> crust with anyone she thought<lb/> wanted it more than she.  As to removing my friends  (from No.9)  Miss<lb/> ff.Mullen is very often out for the<lb/> afternoon &amp; there is no one else<lb/> to remove. You need not write<lb/> to me now about my extreme<lb/> wickedness in daring to think it<lb/> right to oppose unjust rule when<lb/> your own <seg type="unclear">infatible</seg> British Empire<lb/> lauds &amp; extols the Greek premier for<lb/> revolting against the chosen king<lb/> of Greece, not a king whose only<lb/> right in the country was the right<lb/> of might, but the beloved &amp; revered<lb/> king, I quote D - Murray in his recent<lb/> lecture in the Parochial Hall here, where<lb/> he stated that King Constantine was<lb/> greatly beloved by his people for 3 reasons,<lb/> 1, because he had so often led his<lb/> people to victory, 2, because of his
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_3"/>
             (2) <!-- This is wrong. Is page 3. -->  miraculous recovery from mortal<lb/>illness, on a very holy Icon being<lb/>brought to him  from a Greek village.  The 3rd reason my<lb/>informant had forgotten. He also<lb/>then stated that the assassination<lb/>of King — &amp; Queen Draga was justifiable,<lb/>for, tho' he held no brief for<lb/>the officers who did the deed, still,<lb/>undoubtedly <seg type="del">Roumania</seg> Serbia suffered<lb/>much from their tyranny, &amp; that<lb/>something had to be done to end<lb/>it. Therefore he holds that <seg type="del">Roumania</seg>Serbia<lb/>was justified in freeing herself from<lb/>oppression, how could he then say<lb/>Ireland was wrong to do the same.<lb/>I think there are few in Ireland who<lb/>would uphold the assassination<lb/>of the Ard Rig, <!-- A misspelling of the Irish Ard Ri? --> if there were one.<lb/>It does not seem as if D  -  Murray<lb/>were the person to show me the<lb/>error of my ways!  As long as you are persuaded that<lb/>what is, is right, &amp; that England is justified in<lb/>justified in wringing the life blood from 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_4"/>
            Ireland, Egypt &amp; India to fatten herself,<lb/> there is no more to be said. I hold that<lb/> England is not justified, that she has<lb/> transgressed the law of God, to set up<lb/> her own law, calling it His, and that,<lb/> as God always works by human means,<lb/> our people were right in the step they<lb/> took. The Irish in Ireland are a vanishing<lb/> quantity, let things go on as they<lb/> have been &amp; in a few years there<lb/> will be no Irish left — self-preservation<lb/> is the unerring  (God-given)  instinct of individuals<lb/> &amp; nations, therefore the oppressed rise<lb/> to throw of the bonds which are<lb/> strangling them &amp; they are justified<lb/> in the sight of God &amp; all men<lb/> except those imbued with the<lb/> spirit of tyranny in doing so.<lb/> You blame me bitterly for concealing<lb/> my views, instead of blaming<lb/> the tyranny which makes such<lb/> concealment inevitable, there are<lb/> many, whose names I find out<lb/> by degrees, but am not at liberty<lb/> to mention, who do the same,
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_5"/>
             (3)  &amp; for the same reason, people<lb/>that you would never suspect<lb/>of any such thing, whom you<lb/>respect &amp; look up to. <seg type="unclear">Ten</seg> in good<lb/>company. Talking of Madam Markiewiecz,<lb/>you say her husband<lb/>went away &amp; she did not bring<lb/>up her own child. Surely if her<lb/>husband chose to go for a time<lb/>to his own family in Poland he<lb/>had a <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>perfect right to do so<lb/>&amp; this casts no slur on him or<lb/>her, &amp; is it not quite usual<lb/>for grandmothers to take a grandchild<lb/>to bring up? It is done<lb/>again &amp; again &amp; is a purely<lb/>domestic convenience.  My conception of right &amp; wrong,<lb/>if you mean by that my conception<lb/>of law has certainly<lb/>altered since I knew the Brehon<lb/>system &amp; compared it with<lb/>the Anglo-Norman, the former<lb/>upholds the spirit, the latter<lb/>adheres rigidly to the letter &amp;<lb/>you know St Paul's comparison<lb/>of letter &amp; spirit. The purity of<lb/>any person's motives is judged 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_6"/>
             fairly accurately by the amount<lb/>they are prepared to give up for<lb/>their principles. We went out<lb/>with our lives in our hands,<lb/>to every human being the most<lb/>supremely valuable possession.<lb/>Expediency, which means usually<lb/>self-preservation, would have<lb/>kept us at home.  I do not think myself <sic>infalible</sic>,<lb/>but nothing you have told<lb/>me has in the least shown<lb/>me I am wrong. You are narrow<lb/>&amp; onesided to an extent amazing<lb/>in one of your education, you<lb/>seem absolutely impervious<lb/>to reason. You call me ignorant<lb/>because I refuse to see through<lb/>your eyes alone &amp; cut off all<lb/>the <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>big, pitiful other side, I can't<lb/>consent to this. Prove to me that<lb/>Ireland exported no food stuffs<lb/>during the famine years, 45-48<lb/>&amp; I will believe you are right,<lb/>prove to me that England is not<lb/>doing the same thing now &amp; that<lb/>cattle, bacon, eggs, butter, grains 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_7"/>
             (4)  are not leaving the country &amp;<lb/>that adequate provision is<lb/>being made to avert the famine<lb/>&amp; I will believe the disinterestedness<lb/>of England's dealings with<lb/>Ireland. You know perfectly<lb/>well you can't do it, you<lb/>know England's occupation<lb/>of Ireland has been one long<lb/>series of devastations, of which<lb/>the last is by no means the<lb/>most inconsiderable. Is there<lb/>any other country in the world<lb/>which would have contemplated<lb/>shelling of all the coast<lb/>towns in order to put down<lb/>a handful of people who rose<lb/>against them? If any other<lb/>country thought of such a thing<lb/>what a howl of <seg type="unclear">exsacration</seg> it<lb/>would raise in Christian England!<lb/>I think I mentioned the famine<lb/>of the forties to you before &amp;<lb/>that you took no notice of it.<lb/>Please don't do the same now.<lb/>I know you do love me still, don't<lb/>you think you could try to believe 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_2983_img_2387_8"/>
             in me a little? Why are <hi rend="underline">you</hi> so<lb/>sure of your <sic>infalibility?</sic>   My love, dearest.<lb/>K.   The service of one's country is a<lb/>higher duty than the service<lb/>of oneself or one's friends 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>