<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1332">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Pte. Herbert Shekleton to his mother in Kingscourt, Co. Cavan, 5 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert Shekleton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Private Shekleton (1895-1917) served in Dublin during The Easter Rising 1916 and records events in this letter written to his mother on 5th May 1916 from the Royal Barracks Dublin. In it he describes the fighting in and around the city centre and the execution and burial of the ring-leaders Pierce,Connolly and Byrne.Herbert Shekleton was from Kingscourt, County Cavan, and while apprenticed to an outfitting firm in Drogheda, enlisted in the Royal Dublin Fusiliers. Shekleton died aged 22 during the battle of Arras on 15th April 1917 and is commemorated on the Lutyens Memorial in Arras.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1332</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0707">Herbert Shekleton</persName>
              <date>1916-05-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0175">Royal Barracks, Dublin.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sarah Jane Shekelton née Dixon </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0419">Kingscourt, Co. Cavan</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_1"  type="Letter"  url="a38d998ead4f5618bdfc64dd02aebf19.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_2"  type="Letter"  url="269a6a8180fb94a34bb9870e15fe151f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_3"  type="Letter"  url="c2ff2b560377533d3d6fe81ad155b81a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_4"  type="Letter"  url="7f7dd4c6d8f677b380b38eb7ef65e30b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_5"  type="Letter"  url="2c9cd0643230c9c0b7f82ceb19678606.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_6"  type="Letter"  url="9b13f2fcc1d95b56ca2b3764db9ace68.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_7"  type="Letter"  url="c7934a61057079e240e50a9238426c7d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_8"  type="Letter"  url="bcf4b3b43e5aca7dc7e039f81845242c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_9"  type="Letter"  url="0c26209fb8ca31b4b3f0487d654e3dca.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_10"  type="Letter"  url="b63330c000c510c219c00412c3edc8ed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_11"  type="Photograph"  url="e26a126be49c5d41c43a9e0bed109854.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1332_img_653_12"  type="Photograph"  url="53d2bb54b4da83a233ccfaf7a3b29171.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_1"/>
                5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916    C Coy 10th Batt RDF <hi rend="underline">Royal Bks</hi>   Dear Mamma,   It seems as if <lb/> I had a terrible nightmare <lb/> so terrible &amp; strange things <lb/> I have been through since <lb/> I wrote you before Easter. <lb/> The letter you wrote to <lb/> me before Easter arrived <lb/> here last night. I know <lb/> you have been anxious <lb/> to know if I am still <lb/> above the <hi rend="underline">sod.</hi> well thank <lb/> God I am but I am <lb/> sorry to say <sic>theres</sic>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_2"/>
              <lb/>many a one in <sic>there</sic> last <lb/> resting place who were in <lb/> the pink of health hardly <lb/> a week ago &amp; but for sheer <lb/> luck there would be double <lb/> the number. Such slaughter <lb/> &amp; wholesale destruction no <lb/> one in Ireland ever saw. <lb/> Here we were on Easter Monday <lb/> morning all unconscious of <lb/> what was to happen in <lb/> a few hours. <hi rend="underline">Luckily</hi> we <lb/> only got a <hi rend="underline">half</hi><hi rend="underline">holiday.</hi> You <lb/> will see how this saved <lb/> the lot of us. We were <lb/> dismissed from drill at <lb/>12. o.c. &amp; of course we all <lb/> went post-haste to dress <lb/> to go down town for the <lb/> remainder of the day. <lb/> Just as I was having a wash <lb/> I heard a volley of shots <cb/>right outside the Barracks. <lb/> In three minutes we were <lb/> rushed into the streets with <lb/> full equipment, Rifles, &amp; as <lb/> much ammunition as we <lb/> could carry The houses <lb/> on all sides were full of <lb/><sic>Seinâfeiners</sic> &amp; the minute <lb/> we turned the corner <lb/> down goes an officer &amp; <lb/> several of the men in <lb/> our party. We got down <lb/> flat on stomachs on the <lb/> road &amp; here our first <lb/> pitched battle raged. <lb/> I forgot to mention that <lb/> while we were both hard <lb/> at it the men, women, <lb/> &amp; children who hadn't <lb/> time to clear from the <lb/> street were screeching, <lb/>&amp; crying to the solders  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_3"/>
              <lb/>to save them &amp; they too <lb/> were shot down all over <lb/> the place by the <sic>Sein-feiners</sic><lb/> from the windows but I <lb/> suppose the bullets were <lb/> meant for us. It was <lb/> awful to see the unfortunate <lb/> wounded ones lying on <lb/> the street crying for <lb/><hi rend="underline">water</hi><hi rend="underline">water</hi> &amp; every time <lb/> we went to rescue them <lb/> the <sic>Sein-fs</sic> fired on us. <lb/> Red - cross, white Cross, <lb/> priest, or parson all <lb/> were fired on. Dozens of <lb/> people rushed into the <lb/> Barracks for safety.   To continue about the fighting <lb/> we succeeded in driving <lb/> them out of the houses <lb/> on one side of the <lb/> street but only when  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_4"/>
              <lb/>we rushed into the houses <lb/> with the bayon e ts. This <lb/> always seemed to put the <lb/> fear of God in their heart. <lb/> They too had bayonets but <lb/> they never dared to rush <lb/> us. There were a few <lb/> houses we couldnât subdue <lb/> with rifle fire alone &amp; we <lb/> got bombs &amp; blew them <lb/> &amp; the <sic>Sein f's</sic> to some <lb/> where in no - where. <lb/> But this was only childs <lb/> play till we got to the <lb/> centre of the city where <lb/> they were in their <lb/> thousands &amp; armed <lb/> to the teeth. We were <lb/>outnumbered &amp; had to <lb/> keep on the defensive <lb/> till reinforcements  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_5"/>
              <lb/>arrived. They were in the <lb/> chimneys firing through <lb/> loop - holes &amp; on the roofs <lb/> sniping for further orders. <lb/> We worried them for 3 <lb/> days &amp; then the Artillery <lb/> came along. Before a <lb/> dozen shells fell in the <lb/> G. P. O. out comes a <lb/> white sheet. The unfortunate <lb/> devils were like ghosts <lb/> when we took them out. <lb/> Inside there were pieces <lb/> of <sic>Sein - fs</sic> which told <lb/> their <seg type="del">old</seg> own  tale. They had <lb/> sufficient food &amp; ammunition <lb/> to last a 3 monthâs <sic>seige.</sic><lb/> The same thing was happening <lb/> all through the city unti l<lb/> three days when practically <lb/> all surrendered. <cb/> At night time the whole <lb/> city was in darkness. Lights <lb/> of any description were <lb/> fired upon. The reason for <lb/> this was that they were <lb/> signalling from one window <lb/> &amp; housetop to another <lb/> with flash lights.  The fighting at night <lb/> time only took place <lb/> between the snipers &amp; <lb/> our sentries. The last <lb/> night I was on sentry <lb/><sic>didnt</sic> the beggars get <lb/> at the Power Station &amp; <lb/> turn on all the streets <lb/> lights &amp; immediately <lb/> several volleys <lb/> rang out. I happened <lb/> to be right under one <lb/> of the lamps so I  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_6"/>
              <lb/>took point blank aim at <lb/> the lamp itself which was <lb/> too high to reach other <lb/> wise &amp; I fear you never <lb/> see the same one in Dublin <lb/> again. Now I could keep <lb/> on telling you about <lb/> incidents such as these <lb/> for a week &amp; hair â <lb/> breadth escapes which <lb/> we wouldnât notice. <lb/> But <sic>theres</sic> something <lb/> else Iâm sure you would <lb/> like to know. How <lb/> did we get our food <lb/> our sleep etc.   As regards food we <lb/>lived on Bully Beef <lb/> &amp; dog biscuits &amp;  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_7"/>
              <lb/>when we happened to <lb/> meet a stray morsel <lb/> it died a noble death. <lb/> We slept on the streets, <lb/> in the streets, on top <lb/> of houses, in stables, <lb/> outhouses &amp; anything <lb/> we could get. No <lb/>such luxury as a <lb/> doze with clothes <sic>of</sic><lb/> not even equipment. <lb/> Even though we might <lb/> be asleep just one <lb/> shout from the lonely <lb/> sentry who watched <lb/> over us &amp; we stood <lb/> up ready for any <lb/>emergency.  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_8"/>
              <sic>Its</sic> almost a thing of <lb/>the past now &amp; <sic>Im</sic><lb/> sure the majority are <lb/> glad. I had the pleasure <lb/> of helping to bury the <lb/> three Ring-leaders who <lb/> were Pierce, Connolly <lb/> &amp; Byrne. They were <lb/> brought out of their <lb/> cells in <hi rend="underline">âArbour Hillâ</hi><lb/> jail where I &amp; a few <lb/> more solders were <lb/> guarding. They were <lb/> blindfolded &amp; their <lb/> hands tied behind <lb/> their back &amp; six <lb/> volleys fired into  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_9"/>
              each man They were <lb/> buried just as they fell, <lb/> no coffin or any other <lb/> covering. Thrown into <lb/> a hole &amp; covered with <lb/> quick lime &amp; then <lb/> sufficient clay to keep <lb/> their toes from turning <lb/> up. This must suffice <lb/> for the present as duty <lb/> calls me elsewhere &amp; <lb/> I hope this finds you <lb/> all like myself over <lb/> the sod &amp; then <lb/> you <sic>neednt</sic> grumble. <seg type="closer"> Ever your loving <lb/>Son  <hi rend="underline">Herbert</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_10"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> Cissâs cake came in so useful as a <lb/>matter of fact I ate it in view <lb/> of the <hi rend="underline">Rebels</hi>.  <hi rend="underline">PS</hi><lb/>Send this letter to Shercock <lb/>as I will not get a chance of writing <lb/> for a while again. </seg> 
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_11"/>
              Pte. Herbert Shekleton (1895-1917)  
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_1332_img_653_12"/>
              Pte. Herbert Shekleton (1895-1917)  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>