<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3528">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to the Registrar of Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital, 20 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Typescript letter stating that at RCPI has re-elected Dr. WH Thompson as King&#39;s Professor of Institute of Medicine in the School of Physics, and that &#39;the existing arrangements with regard to his deputy at St Patrick&#39;s Dun&#39;s Hospital will stand, and passing on regrets that the notice of Dr. Thompson&#39;s re-election was not sent before.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-152</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3528</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0845">Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0272">Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Registrar of Sir Patrick Dun&#39;s Hospital</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1147">The Registrar of Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3528_img_2932_1"  type="Letter"  url="72b2158a38f9d6cef032a6d6efeddf09.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3528_img_2932_1"/>
             RCPI/2/3/2/13/152   20th MARCH 16   The Registrar,<lb/> Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital, Dublin.    Dear Sir,   I beg to inform you that at a special meeting of the<lb/>President and Fellows of the Royal College of Physicians of<lb/>Ireland held on Monday the 10th January,1916, Dr.W.H.Thompson<lb/>was re-elected King's Professor of Institutes of Medicine in<lb/>the School of Physic and presumably the existing arrangements<lb/>with regard to his deputy at Sir Patrick Dun's Hospital will<lb/>stand. I regret that owing to an oversight this formal notice<lb/>of Dr.Thompson's re-election was not conveyed to you before.   I remain, dear Sir,<lb/>Yours faithfully,     Fellow &amp; Registrar.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>