<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4166">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin, November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Olive Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin (1854-1954).

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4166</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2125">7 West Cliff, Eastbourne, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4166_img_3539_1"  type="Letter"  url="5e584fdb605b9dd76f097a624a5c3270.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4166_img_3539_2"  type="Letter"  url="e3f21525b434db97c8f6f380de37b6af.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4166_img_3539_3"  type="Letter"  url="a1f7b5c93d88f8cc19a798f3c9974a09.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4166_img_3539_1"/>
              D2109/9/4/B    7. West Cliff<lb/>Eastbourne    Nov. 1915    Dearest Mamma,   It is awfully good of you to write so<lb/>regularly every week when you have so many to<lb/>write to now, home letters are such a pleasure to get.  Mr &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. <seg type="unclear">H.</seg>Hollins &amp; Emmi have just left this<lb/>morning. Poor things they are very sad, although<lb/>there are so many other children, this boy was evidently<lb/>of enormous pride &amp; pleasure to them. They are very<lb/>nice people &amp; very good &amp; generous to all their be—<lb/>longings. It was rather upsetting as this was the<lb/>first meeting with Miss Roberts since Humphrey's<lb/>death. Mr Hollins was so good sitting talking to her<lb/>for hours though I am sure it was a torture to him<lb/>as he is a very reserved quiet man &amp; she is all<lb/>inquisitiveness &amp; that kind of curious enjoyment of<lb/>emotion that some people have. Poor M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Hollins is<lb/>just a mass of nerves &amp; jumps, never at peace &amp;<lb/>devoting herself entirely to the children's education &amp;<lb/>health, an awfully good little woman, but very<lb/>trying to live with. I left them alone yesterday<lb/>&amp; went for a long walk on the Downs. It was<lb/>warm enough to sit in the sun for a bit &amp; very 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4166_img_3539_2"/>
              D2109/9/4/B   lovely &amp; peaceful up there, poor Miss R gives one the<lb/>feelings that Cousin Flo used to, that one must get<lb/>away for a rest.  You must feel very funny at home with only Helen<lb/>&amp; she out all morning. I am so glad Ruth is estab—<lb/>lished near. It is a great thing to feel that Terry<lb/>wont just be doing monotonous work in the trenches,<lb/>that must require a great deal of endurance. Let<lb/>me know the news of him as he won't have time to<lb/>write to me. I suppose one address's him Headquarters<lb/>Staff <hi rend="underline">107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> Brigade? You told me <hi rend="underline">107</hi><hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I always put<lb/>307<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> before.  Thank you so much for sending the parcel of clothes.<lb/>I forgot to look what the postage was &amp; I owe you for<lb/>Emma's too. I suppose we wont hear from her for<lb/>some time yet.  There is a Col. Archdale I meet at the Dormets he had<lb/>a nephew called Lome in the Ulster Div. &amp; had been<lb/>to the <seg type="unclear">review</seg> by the King &amp; thought they looked<lb/>fine troops &amp; said they were well provided with<lb/>artillery.  Sam &amp; Charlie are lucky so far, one feels as if something<lb/>were bound to happen to one of them sometimes.<lb/>I've been doing a little making of bandages at the 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4166_img_3539_3"/>
              D2109/9/4/B   Red X. place here where they make all sorts of equip—<lb/>ment for the hospitals. told D. I would try to<lb/>help her to raise money for heating the canteen if she<lb/>thought of attempting it. &amp; send me a letter giving<lb/>an account of the necessity &amp; list of people she was<lb/>asking. I have been reading a wonderful book<lb/>called The Soul of the War by Phillip Gibbs, it is very<lb/>well written &amp; one feels it is all true &amp; not exaggerated<lb/>but just what he has seen personally in France &amp; Belgium<lb/>some of it is awful. It is a wonderful record of<lb/>endurance &amp; cheerfulness.  I hope I may get home for Xmas, but it is no me talking<lb/>of that yet, no me making plans these days!  I've been awfully bothered with a funny kind of hay fever<lb/>the last few weeks, which comes on badly every morning<lb/>&amp; makes my nose &amp; eyes ache but I suppose it will go<lb/>with the cold weather. I am so glad Edmund has<lb/>got company with him. I hope he will really be<lb/>better. Much love to Helen &amp; Papa.  Ever your loving   <hi rend="underline">Olive.</hi>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>