<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0510">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from R. C. Kelly to E. A. Aston, 14 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>R. C. Kelly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Captain R. C. Kelly to E. A. Aston acknowledging receipt of his letter dated 11 March 1916 and advising Aston that the letter has been forwarded to Alexander McDowell, the Director of Munitions for the No. 11 Area.Captain R.C. Kelly set up the Ministry of Munitions’ offices at number 32 Nassau Street in 1915. Kelly previously headed the North Eastern Armaments Committee in Britain and had shown great skill in maximising resources of the various engineering concerns available. By November 1915 he was appointed head of recruitment in Ireland and managed to double the figures before returning to London in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7443/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/510</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1278">R. C. Kelly</persName>
              <date>1916-03-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2046">The Department of Recruiting for Ireland, 32 Nassau Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">E. A. Aston</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1501">Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0510_img_1882_1"  type="Letter"  url="348fb0c6bd89eca85e56223de8f36457.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0510_img_1882_1"/>
              Telegrams:&amp;#x2014; 'Reveille'<lb/> Dublin<lb/> All communications should be addressed <lb/> to The Secretary, and the following<lb/> Number quoted<lb/><hi rend="underline">RCK/AFS.</hi>    THE DEPARTMENT OF RECRUITING FOR IRELAND,  32, Nassau Street,  Dublin    14th March 1916.    E A Aston Esq  Local Government Board  Dublin   My dear Aston   I am in receipt of your letter <lb/> of the 11th inst. for which I am obliged.   I have handed same to Mr. <lb/> Alexander McDowell, the Director of Munitions <lb/> for No. 11 Area.   Upon hearing from him I will <lb/>write you immediately.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Yours sincerely,   R C Kelly </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>