<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0802">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 21 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender discusses matters relating to house-hunting and to Lillian&#39;s maids. He expresses regret at his recent promotion, as his chance of getting leave before Christmas is much lower than if he were still in the Ulster Division. He discusses the army&#39;s failure to build on the successes of July 1, his continuing work on a dispatch, and the experience of his brother Rex in the trenches.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/393</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/802</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0802_img_2343_1"  type="NULL"  url="48cbd6b16601c15e84ad167e651719c9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0802_img_2343_2"  type="NULL"  url="3436b1a576c703a4960d149c4d5cbab4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0802_img_2343_1"/>
                GENERAL HEADQUARTERS,  BRITISH ARMY IN THE FIELD.    21 Aug   My pr   So sorry to hear you are feeling as I<lb/> expected rather dumpy, but perhaps you are the better<lb/> for your week end. What have you settled about the<lb/> maids? Perhaps my pleading may make it easier to<lb/> come to terms. If so, I would suggest you <seg type="del">b</seg> send<lb/> them home on a holiday when you pick up and<lb/> that you leave house hunting etc till you have had<lb/> your change if you can put it off so long which I<lb/> am doubtful about.  Poor old thing the b w feels rather as you do, &amp;<lb/> if <seg type="unclear">leave</seg> is really opened in the <seg type="unclear">Ulster</seg> Div will begin to<lb/><seg type="unclear">regret</seg> his titles etc. I can't open any hopes I'm afraid<lb/> but <seg type="unclear">britain</seg> leave may be opened for GHQ  late  in September<lb/> &amp;then I come last which looks like Xmas, so its no less<lb/> fretting especially as I may be in division by then.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0802_img_2343_2"/>
              I saw General Cameron yesterday who strange to me <lb/>attributed the lack of <hi rend="superscript">any</hi> permanent success on July 1st to <seg type="unclear">line</seg><lb/>things of which 2 were those which I most strongly advocated <lb/>before the attack.  I hope to go to the 13th troop this afternoon to get further <lb/>news for my dispatch. It is most promising but going back, <lb/>but is I think improving except in length. Rex is better <lb/>and really plucky. I am glad he has pleasant companions <lb/>but wish Bull was less yackety now. I heard Leader had <lb/>got into trouble &amp; gone home. I find he is kown <lb/>here and as expelled from Japan (?)  There is an early post today so I will <lb/>close but don't expect to write again later! <seg type="closer"> Your bw <lb/> WB spender </seg><seg type="postscript"> PS. I wish you could let Belfast manage the <lb/>Pot War. Your dream is entirely <seg type="unclear">amiss</seg>. It's just <lb/>what might have happened! </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>