<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2007">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Philip C. P. MacDermot to Sir Henry Arthur Wynne, 11 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Philip C. P. MacDermot</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Philip MacDermot (1863-1929), the crown solicitor for Co. Roscommon to Sir Henry Arthur Wynne. Wynne (1867-1943) was the chief crown solicitor for Ireland from 1916 to 1922.
In the letter MacDermot informs Wynne that he wishes to take a leave of absence for a week in order to escort his son to England for school. He notes that in his absence Dermot MacDermot can act on his behalf as solicitor. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSORP/1916/8063/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2007</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1087">Philip C. P. MacDermot</persName>
              <date>1916-05-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2072">Boyle, County Roscommon, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Henry Arthur Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1929</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2007_img_1453_1"  type="Letter"  url="233b11f4b5edce5b6be50afc6211c95e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2007_img_1453_1"/>
             Office of Crown Solictior for Co Roscommon, <lb/>Boyle.   May 11. 1916   Dear Sir,   I beg to apply for <hi rend="underline">leave wit</hi>h <lb/>week <hi rend="underline">from Saturday next</hi>. There are <lb/>no cases pending or likely to come on <lb/>during my absence, but if any business <lb/>requiring attention from a Solicitor <sic>shd.</sic> <lb/>turn up, <hi rend="underline">W Dermott Mac Dermott</hi> of this <lb/>town <hi rend="underline">will act for me</hi>. I may add <lb/>that I want to leave to go to England <lb/>with my boy who is going to <lb/>school and in these times of trouble <lb/>I don’t like having him go alone. I am <lb/>glad to say that so far as I can know <lb/>or learn everything here is very quiet.   Yours Faithfully   Philip C Mac Dermott   The Chief Crown Solicitor <lb/><hi rend="underline">Dublin Castle</hi>   Attorne<hi rend="underline">y Ge</hi>neral <lb/>Do you approve? <lb/>Amendment <lb/>accepted <lb/>12.5.16   Yes. <lb/>M 13.5.16. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>