<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0702">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr Joseph Wrafter SJ to his Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ, 6 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr Joseph Wrafter </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr Joseph Wrafter SJ (1865-1934) to his Father Provincial Thomas V Nolan SJ (1867-1941) in which he describes the conditions of his work as a chaplain at the Front to the 8th Royal Munster Fusiliers, B.E.F. &#39;I have never been away from these horrible guns except one day&#39; (6 July 1916). He writes about the work of his battalion and the Leinsters.Fr. Joseph Wrafter SJ, M.C. was born 9 August 1865, Rosenallis, Queens County (Laois) and died 5 September 1934, Dublin. He schooled at St. Stanislaus, College, Tullabeg. He entered the Society in 1883 and Fr. Wrafter taught in Clongowes Wood College for a number of years before going to Louvain for philosophy in 1893 and returning in 1896. From 1900-03, he was Minister at University College, St. Stephen’s Green. On returning from the war, he was Minister in Leeson Street, Clongowes Wood College and University Hall. Fr. Wrafter served as chaplain in France and Belgium and to interned prisoners in Holland (1915-1919).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IE IJA/CHP1/63/10, IE IJA/CHP1/63/10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/702</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1030">Fr Joseph Wrafter </persName>
              <date>1916-07-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0098">8th Royal Munster Fusiliers, B.E.F., France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1897">St Francis Xavier's, Upper Gardiner Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0702_img_2194_1"  type="Letter"  url="3852250aad9881e2274d63dddadfa3fd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0702_img_2194_2"  type="Letter"  url="e559d9efc125916668a7ca4b8d952742.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0702_img_2194_3"  type="Letter"  url="0487e57e7fb52349a9dac43885fe9292.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0702_img_2194_4"  type="Letter"  url="43fb28aa54cabdfc1d405d8f4cd48567.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0702_img_2194_1"/>
                8<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">th</hi></hi> R. Munster Fus. <hi rend="underline">B. E. F.</hi>    July <hi rend="underline">6/16</hi>   My dear Fr. Provincial, <hi rend="underline">P.C.</hi>    I am a very bad <lb/> correspondent &amp; the atmosphere <lb/> we live in out here is not <lb/> conducive to letter writing. Since <lb/> I came back on Holy Thursday I <lb/> have never been away from these <lb/> horrible guns except one day for <lb/> a few hours when I took a ride <lb/> a few miles back into the country <lb/> for the sake of feeling I was out of <lb/> range. We are back 'resting' now <lb/> for eight days, but we are not in <lb/> a very restful place. The Huns <lb/> shell it several times every day &amp; <lb/> there are frequent casualties. Before <lb/> we came here on Tuesday I had been <lb/><seg type="unclear">16</seg> days in the front line &amp; during  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0702_img_2194_2"/>
              that time I never had my clothes <lb/> off. The Battalions relieve one another <lb/> every four days, but the Leinsters <lb/> had no chaplains of their own so <lb/> I stayed on with them &amp; so was <lb/> in the whole <seg type="unclear">16</seg> days. I have now <lb/>been appointed officially to the <lb/> two battalions &amp; as they always <lb/> relieve each other I expect I <lb/> shall get as much of the game <lb/> as I want. It is a very terrible <lb/> thing where a show is on &amp; no <lb/> one I know wants any more <lb/> of it than he has seen if he has <lb/> been in it at all. But of course <lb/> all have to see it through &amp; the <lb/> men are really splendid. The <lb/> last sixteen days was the worst <lb/> turn we had. There was a constant <lb/> strain the whole time. Between <lb/> killed &amp; wounded we lost in that  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0702_img_2194_3"/>
              period quite a fourth of our Battalions <lb/> &amp; the Leinsters nearly as many. <lb/> But they did good work &amp; the <lb/>enemy got a good deal more than <lb/> they gave. It is dreadful to see <lb/> the way the poor fellows are <lb/>broken &amp; mangled sometimes out <lb/> of all recognition. When they are <lb/> killed it does not seem so bad, <lb/> but it is terrible to see the horrible <lb/> wounds &amp; the way the poor fellows <lb/> suffer. Their sufferings are added to by <lb/> the inconvenience of the trenches, <lb/> where it is often difficult for two <lb/> men to pass. It often takes hours <lb/> to get them as far as the regimental <lb/> aid post which is by no means a <lb/><seg type="unclear">luxurious</seg> place â often only a very <lb/> small dug-out &amp; the wounded can <lb/> only be sent down to the clearing <lb/> stations by night when it is dark, <lb/> so that they are often 18 or 20 hours  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0702_img_2194_4"/>
              waiting. It can't be helped <lb/> but it causes much suffering to <lb/> the poor men.  Well, there is no use telling <lb/> you about war as you have had <lb/> so much of it in Dublin that <lb/> you know all its phases.  I suppose Visitations are <lb/> all over by this &amp; the villas <lb/> in full swing. I hope you &amp; <lb/> all in the Province are very <lb/> well. You are, I am sure busy <lb/> with retreats just now. I hope <lb/> we shall also soon be engaged <lb/> in that way â the retreat of the <lb/> Huns. <seg type="closer"> With very kind regards to all <lb/> &amp; asking a remembrance in your Holy <lb/> Sacrifices Believe me, my dear Fr. Provincial. <lb/>Yours most sincerely in XT  J Wrafter S.J. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>