<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4703">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to the Clerk of the College, Royal College of Surgeons Edinburgh, 29 May 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-91</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4703</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1919-05-29</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0652">Edinburgh, Scotland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4703_img_4040_1"  type="Letter"  url="1c0df223fdf8788248c8d6c6b9c30a76.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4703_img_4040_1"/>
             29th MAY 19.   The Clerk of the College, <lb/>Royal College of Surgeons, <lb/>Edinburgh.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">A mission of Women to Higher Qualifications.</hi>  Dear Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 26th instant above quoted <lb/>I beg <sic>t</sic> inform you that under the Charter of Queen Victoria <lb/>granted to the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland in 1878 <lb/>Women became eligible for the Membership of the College and that <lb/>eight women have been admitted. The Fellowship was opened to <lb/>Women by an amendment of the Bye_Laws sanctioned by the Privy <lb/>Council in 1915, but no women have as yet been elected to the <lb/>Fellowship. All Fellows of the College enjoy the same privileges <lb/>without distinction of sex.   I enclose herewith a copy of the Regulation relating to <lb/>Membership and Fellowship. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>