<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5799">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. 
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters. Aside from wedding preparations, May also mentions Verdun</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5799</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5799_img_899_1"  type="Letter"  url="a16621ce3d695a241d2f254e365bb746.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5799_img_899_2"  type="Letter"  url="b0e251e463c87fd94558fc5d4e783c2e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5799_img_899_3"  type="Envelope"  url="bd94ef46d7387ebcc054ecbf035a12a2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5799_img_899_1"/>
            <!-- Writing at the top left hand side of the letter written sideways --> I couldn’t get a chance of<lb/>posting this. It’s by old time<lb/>the boys stop work they are<lb/>at a particular &amp; ugly job<lb/>now shearing so I hope<lb/>my poor little man won’t<lb/>be disappointed too much<lb/>I was thinking since your<lb/>present won't seem like<lb/>a present at all still I think<lb/>there is nothing I could get you<lb/>would like or want if you<lb/>could suggest anything I would<lb/>like to get it but if you would<lb/>only like the tie pin it would<lb/>be better get it yourself for<lb/>I am afraid I wouldn’t know<lb/>much about such a thing.  <!-- Beginning of letter --> Togherstown<lb/>Ballinea<lb/>Mullingar<lb/>leo. W Meath <lb/> 29<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> May 1916    My dearest James,   Very many thanks for your letter of yesterday<lb/>and today you are very good to write so often I must<lb/>give you something nice for your goodness in that way<lb/>when I see you.  We had Fr Donellon this morning with Mass he brought<lb/>me “my paper” too he had your name on it- <hi rend="underline">Jacobs</hi><lb/>he called you wasn’t that a shame.  I asked Nano about broch, she only laughed<lb/>but I think she’d like red stones, she said tho’ what<lb/>ever you liked yourself I think I’d prefer a fancy<lb/>bracelet  (chain)  to a solid one, and about the size of the ring I’m<lb/>afraid you will have to send me a card I don’t see any<lb/>other way I suppose it would not do to send a porter<lb/>bottle that was the only suggestion Nano could<lb/>make.  The poor British seem to be getting enough<lb/>of it at present- however it will end will the<lb/>subjects have to pay the piper- of course they<lb/>are doing so already but if the land is taxed it will leave    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5799_img_899_2"/>
             all trade going east.  I was yesterday evening standing outside<lb/>of the door when I saw a lady coming walking up the avenue<lb/>who was it but Jocie Casey she had left Miss &amp; Mrs Moran<lb/>at the gate we were glad to see her, she gave us a particular<lb/>invitation to go over before I’d get married I never saw a girl<lb/>to improve in appearance dress &amp; manner as  much as  Jocie in fact<lb/>I never saw her well-dressed before, she had been to see<lb/>Agnes (Mrs Nicholas Duffy) She didn’t call to see John or<lb/>Mary said they thought themselves too grand for her and Annie<lb/>the nun in Cork didn’t write to her for Christmas, too grand also,<lb/>in that case it’s the grand that are to be pitied more than<lb/>the <hi rend="underline">common.</hi>  I am going to Mullingar tomorrow to see about dress<lb/>I’ll see about car for you how long would you want<lb/>it for would it take the day what time would we<lb/>want to leave this about?  Johnnie heard nothing since. Gerald heard talking<lb/>of the French being beaten at Verdun, he was afterwards<lb/>seen trespassing in the hall with a dirty spade, when<lb/>he was asked where he was bound for he said to bury<lb/>the Allies. A big undertaking.  I don’t think I have any news so I’ll finish with<lb/>warmest love &amp; wishes<lb/> from your loving<lb/>May  <lb/><hi rend="underline">  </hi>     
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5799_img_899_3"/>
             J. E, Finn Esq <lb/>39 Belgrove Sq. <lb/>Rathmines <lb/>Dublin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>