<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2079">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Armstrong to Lady Clonbrock, 26 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Armstrong</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Emma Armstrong to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Lady Clonbrock was a prominent member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association, founded in 1915 to provide aid and comfort to Irish soldiers and prisoners of war. In the letter Armstrong is asking about multiple Irish soldiers and whether or not they are able to walk. Armstrong also seems to be worried about the sobriety of the men and suggests that if they can work they should get a trade to busy themselves.
At the bottom there is a note presumably from Lady Clonbrock mentioning who is in or out of hospital.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/10/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2079</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0896">Emma Armstrong</persName>
              <date>1916-06-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0328">Mount Pleasant Avenue, Ballinasloe, County Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2079_img_1531_1"  type="Letter"  url="f37d1ea0606487debdd4a2684f5dec0d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2079_img_1531_2"  type="Letter"  url="5fed049976e0839876690b5bb4ab9fbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2079_img_1531_3"  type="Letter"  url="e6ec7d21c09e66aff4052e9e5e435498.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2079_img_1531_1"/>
             wrote <lb/>all I gathered <lb/>at Rochampton - <lb/> July 14.1916.   <lb/> MOUNT PLEASANT AVENUE <lb/>BALLINASLOE  <lb/> June 26 16  <lb/> Dear Lady Clonbrock   Thank you for your <lb/> letter — &amp; promise of more, <lb/>if necessary —    The 2 men I want to <lb/>send to London is to Lord <lb/>Roberts <seg type="unclear">Winthrops &amp; Leary</seg> <lb/> a trade — <hi rend="underline">if</hi> they will go <lb/>Major <seg type="unclear">Tuder</seg> Craig says he <lb/> will pay their fares <seg type="unclear">on</seg> <lb/> So I will not have to  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2079_img_1531_2"/>
            to trouble you for that.   If you see any of the <lb/>people at Queen Marys <lb/>Hospital. I would be <lb/>very glad if you could <lb/>find out if the following <lb/>men were able to walk <lb/>well on their legs <seg type="del">when</seg> <lb/>before they left there — <lb/>John Murray 3895 Connaught R <lb/> " Burke Irish Guards <lb/> " Griffin 4301 C Rangers <lb/> both L Thigh — <seg type="del">never</seg> <seg type="unclear">hopped</seg> out of <lb/>hospital till able to walk— <lb/>Griffin very troublesome —seldom sober — <lb/>walked well before leaving - but said he wd: never wear leg — but <seg type="unclear">have</seg> it <lb/>over bed &amp; put his umbrella on it <lb/>Weights <seg type="unclear">if minus</seg> legs <lb/>Wylie 8<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">st</seg></hi> he can walk &amp; is <lb/>working on farm <lb/>Griffin — 9<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">st</seg></hi>1 1/2oz does not wear it <lb/>Burke — 7<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">st</seg></hi> 2 1/2 oz Does not wear it <lb/>These are weights <hi rend="underline">without</hi> the boot on— <lb/><hi rend="underline">Griffin</hi> says that Wylie has <lb/>use of his <seg type="unclear">non</seg> stump than <lb/>he has , which makes him able <lb/>to walk better — <lb/>Griffin does <hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">not</seg></hi> wish to be <lb/>sent back to Queen Marys. <lb/>I wonder if they behaved <lb/>alright while there— <lb/>Griffin has been steady <lb/>lately &amp; if he could only learn
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2079_img_1531_3"/>
            a trade &amp; stay in England he <lb/> might do well — he was a <lb/> Protestant &amp; trusted — his mother <lb/> lives in the widows House &amp; is <lb/> fluid — but is an awful old woman <lb/>&amp; I am sure nags a lots at <lb/> him —   I hope you will all enjoy <lb/> your changes &amp; be the better <lb/>for it -   I am feeling much <lb/> better —   With Kind regards <lb/>Yours very sincerely   Emma Armstrong 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>