<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0408">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hariot Georgina Blackwood to Hermione Blackwood, 27 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hariot Georgina Blackwood</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Lady Hariot Georgine Hamilton-Temple-Blackwood (nee Rowan-Hamilton) (1843-1936) to her daughter Lady Hermione Catherine Helen Hamilton-Temple-Blackwood (1869-1960). The letter concerns the Easter Rising. In the letter Hermoine&#39;s mother tells her that Hermione probably knows as much as she does about the events in Dublin as there are no papers in Dublin but plenty of rumours. Her mother then moves onto everyday events such as the weather and that a friend, Jenny, is going to have a baby.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Dufferine and Ava Papers, D/1231/M/2/69/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/408</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0413">Hariot Georgina Blackwood</persName>
              <date>1916-04-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hermione Blackwood</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1643">Standish House Hospital, Stonehouse, Gloucestershire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0408_img_1672_1"  type="Letter"  url="eb4bd1ac40a5107e7fe1a6687711d4f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0408_img_1672_2"  type="Letter"  url="f7d2dbbbe244d8f01c71790c0571bd7a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0408_img_1672_3"  type="Letter"  url="ddf7836a43cd4f6c4b796114c679aa63.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0408_img_1672_4"  type="Letter"  url="eb4bd1ac40a5107e7fe1a6687711d4f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0408_img_1672_5"  type="Envelope"  url="39f340772af8a9349d4ae72dcf954720.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0408_img_1672_6"  type="Envelope"  url="db98f53901b02c580b5bebd70800b4ba.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0408_img_1672_1"/>
               My darling Hermione,   As few letters are leaving Ireland I do not know <lb/> when you will get this. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Duke</seg> could not cross <lb/> tonight &amp; will now wait <lb/> for Trevor &amp; I shall <lb/> send <hi rend="underline">my 4</hi> off the <lb/> first &amp; better next <lb/> week. Basil motored <lb/> to Dublin from Belfast <lb/> on Tuesday &amp; I have <lb/> had Congratulations  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0408_img_1672_2"/>
              on his safe arrival <lb/> there for Mr Dunville <lb/> had been very seriously <lb/> wounded en route &amp; <lb/> cars were confiscated <lb/> &amp;people turned <lb/> out on the road - <lb/> You know as much <lb/> as we do - for very <lb/> little is in the papers <lb/> about what happens <lb/> (we have <hi rend="underline">no</hi> English letters or papers this <lb/> week) <cb/> in Dublin but there <lb/> are plenty of rumours &amp; <lb/> it would be much better <lb/> if we were told the <lb/> truth . I trust Mr Birrell <lb/> will be got rid of after <lb/> this — a good man, <lb/> &amp; not any old joker <lb/> is wanted here.    We had a lovely <lb/> summer day yesterday <lb/> &amp; today a cold dull  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0408_img_1672_3"/>
              one; it seems as if <lb/> fine weather cannot <lb/> begin this year.   I went to see Jenny <lb/> Moffat (Falls Road) <lb/> yesterday - she is going to <lb/> have a baby &amp; from what <lb/> she tells me I fear there <lb/> is a danger I do <seg type="unclear">worry</seg><lb/> about. &amp; I entreated <lb/> her to see a doctor - told <lb/> her it was absolutely necessary <lb/> Her kidneys are <lb/> evidently all wrong. I <lb/> hope Dr.Mitchell will be <lb/> able to do something - <seg type="unclear">Mrs. M Ceallough</seg>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0408_img_1672_4"/>
              Has a rumination <lb/>In her where <lb/>&amp; <seg type="unclear">Casement</seg><lb/>Knew it. <lb/>Advises her <lb/>Not to write. <lb/>Mar got <lb/>a new <lb/>Place. <lb/>No other <lb/>news <lb/>but to  <seg type="closer"> Take care <lb/>V. Loving <lb/>Mother   HBW </seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0408_img_1672_5"/>
                Hermione Blackwood  Standish House Hospital  Stonehouse  Gloucestershire  England    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0408_img_1672_6"/>
              OPENED BY CENSOR.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>