<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2049">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard Fitzgerald Barry to John Gordon, 5 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard Fitzgerald Barry</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the Crown solicitor for Birr, Richard Fitzgerald Barry (1862-) to the Attorney General for Ireland John Gordon (1849–1922). In this letter Barry is writing about an incident that took place in Tullamore in March 1916. The incident occurred at an anti-Sinn Fein demonstration which took place in Tullamore, County Offaly. Fourteen Irish Volunteers were besieged by a hostile mob in the local Sinn Fein hall. Believing they were inadequately protected by the police they fired revolvers to keep the mob away, and when the police moved in to disarm them they resisted arrest, and shots were fired seriously wounding Sergeant Ahearn. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI; Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/8125/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2049</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0474">Richard Fitzgerald Barry</persName>
              <date>1916-05-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2108">Birr, Co. Offally</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Gordon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2049_img_1496_1"  type="Letter"  url="c36f2798e75a2bb561de3519fa77a9f5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2049_img_1496_1"/>
             John's Place, <lb/>Birr, <lb/>King's County   5th, May, 1916.  <hi rend="underline">TULLAMORE SHOOTING CASE</hi>  Sir:-   Referrng to my letter of 20th ulto, I beg to report <lb/>that on Wednesday last, the Accused in the above Case <lb/>(3 on Bail and 10 in Custody) were further remanded to 10th <lb/>inst, when, if Sergeant Ahern can attend, the evidence <lb/>should I think be gone into.   I had an interview with the County Inspector today, <lb/>and if you so approve, he and I, will wait on you on Monday <lb/>next for your further Directions, and to know whether, the <lb/>ordinary procedure is to be followed in this Case, having <lb/>regard to the circumstances of it, and recent events.   I have the honor to be, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant,   Richd. F. Barry  <lb/>CROWN SOLICITOR.  The Right Honorable, <lb/>The Attorney General, <lb/>K.C. M.P. <lb/>DUBLIN CASTLE.   I Wire to Mr. Barry C.I. <lb/>accdly. <lb/>II Send minute in information <lb/>III Instruct I.G. to direct C.I. <lb/>to atend <lb/>I.II.III. done 6.v.16 <lb/>II III done   Reply that I will be glad to see <lb/>Mr Barry &amp; the co Inspector <lb/>here on Monday at 12 o'clock <lb/>Vtt 5 4-16 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>