<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4592">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Alfred Miller, Royal College of Surgeons, 5 April 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Alfred Miller served as both the registrar of the Royal College of Surgeons (1910-1938) and as secretary to the Conjoint Board of the College of Physicians and College of Surgeons. At the outbreak of the Rising Miller instructed James Duncan, the college porter, to lock the college doors in order to deter Michael Mallin&#39;s occupying rebel force in St. Stephen&#39;s Green.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4592</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1918-04-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0696">Alfred Miller</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1450">Royal College of Surgeons, 123 St Stephen's Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4592_img_3934_1"  type="Letter"  url="c9341b91475b170974314a7193c8ecd8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4592_img_3934_1"/>
             5th APRIL 18.   The Registrar, <lb/>Royal College of Surgeons, <lb/>Dublin.   Dear Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 2nd inst., I am requested <lb/>by the President and Fellows of this College to inform you <lb/>that they have nominated Sir Andrew Horne, Dr. Earl and the <lb/>Registrar to meet the Representatives of your College for the <lb/>purpose of seeking further powers in connection with the <lb/>qualifications granted to the Licentiates of the Colleges.   I remain, <lb/>Yours faithfully, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>