<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3409">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to his mother, Alice Katherine Wynne, 18 April 1916	</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles Wyndham Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Charles Wyndham Wynne to his mother thanking her for a food package.  He declares he now feels ready to take the colour blind test necessary for his RFG application.  Also he remarks in the letter how his friend Blackwood&#39;s brother&#39;s &#34;nerves are gone&#34;.  In addition, his wife had died.  

Alice Katherine Wynne was born to Reverend John George Wynne and Emily Goold. She was married to Albert Augustus Wynne and was the mother of five children, among them Charles Wyndham Wynne. Charles served as a captain in the Royal Garrison Artillery in the First World War. He died of wounds received at Armentieres, June 1917. 

Charles Wynne served as a captain in the Royal Garrison Artillery during the First World War. His application to the Royal Flying Corps was denied in 1916 due to his poor eyesight. Charles ultimately died of wounds received at Armentieres, June 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin	</repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/799</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3409</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1182">Charles Wyndham Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-04-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1215">Lenan Head Fort, Clonmany, Co. Donegal</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Alice Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1818">Avoca, Co. Wicklow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3409_img_282_1"  type="Letter"  url="fffb10905f33a0f76a831768c28e504a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3409_img_282_2"  type="Letter"  url="8b735aca457a7d9e5f49ededf347d43f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3409_img_282_3"  type="Letter"  url="ed2b35c2b265b3a3cb2d23a83cec458b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3409_img_282_1"/>
             10247/1/799  UBIQUE<lb/>QUO FASET GLORIA DUCUNT   R.A MESS<lb/>FORT DUNREE<lb/>BUNCRANA    18.IV.16    Dear Mother.   The order you sent on<lb/>to me was evidently a muddle<lb/>at George V Hospital; who<lb/>apparently took me as still on<lb/>leave. It has been sent on<lb/>to <seg type="unclear">C.O Lendall.</seg>. I am of course<lb/>not going. Now that <seg type="unclear">Mullins</seg><lb/>is <seg type="unclear">O 6</seg> here and Fitzgerald<lb/>at <seg type="unclear">Lenan</seg> I am sending in<lb/>my R.I.C. application through<lb/>them. I must say I think 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3409_img_282_2"/>
            General Arthur might have<lb/>bent a little finger! I am <sic>practicing</sic> up<lb/>colours for the Medical from<lb/>a card of coloured wools !<lb/>I'll soon be quite safe I think.  The weather has been<lb/>awful here. Terrible gales —<lb/>its very hard to imagine<lb/>it is getting on for the end<lb/>of April.  Blackwood's brother <seg type="del">deleted text</seg><lb/>very nice man with his little<lb/>boy were here on a visit <lb/>last week end. Blackwood's<lb/>brother is a very nice man<lb/>very quiet. He had a terrible<lb/>knocking about in France.<lb/>and his nerves are gone.<lb/>Also his wife died a couple<lb/>of month's ago so its rather<lb/>sad for him. The little boy<lb/>was a very smart young<lb/>fellow.  It occurs to me have you<lb/>a press for stamping the<lb/>address on note paper like<lb/>this piece is stamped? Shall<lb/>I get one made for <seg type="unclear">Tyrones</seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3409_img_282_3"/>
            and have it sent? I think<lb/>it is very good value. The vegetables were simply<lb/>top hole and the Mess is clamoring<lb/>for more! We had the <seg type="unclear">Seakale</seg><lb/>served up as a course to itself<lb/>the French method I believe; I<lb/>think it is much the best as<lb/>otherwise you don't get half<lb/>the full value of it. I will<lb/>send P.O for postage  Now I <seg type="del">need</seg> must stop to<lb/>write some more letters!  I don't think I've been <sic>two</sic> bad this<lb/>last week    your love<lb/>Charles.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>