<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1473">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sister M. Cyprian to Éamon de Valera, 30 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sister M. Cyprian</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter from Sister Cyprian to Éamon de Valera (1882-1975) was enclosed in a letter dated 29 May 1916 addressed to Sinéad de Valera (1878-1975), his wife, together with a pair of scapulars and a request that they be forwarded to Mr de Valera in prison. Sr.Cyprian sympathises with his situation and reassures him of her prayers - she invites him to join her in prayer daily at 7.00 a.m., and she asks him to urge his wife to bring his children to her for a visit.Éamonn De Valera had joined the Irish Volunteers in 1913 and was adjutant to Thomas MacDonagh (1878-1916), Dublin Brigade commandant. He went on to command forces at Bolands Mill during the Rising and was the most senior participant to escape execution. De Valera would go on to become one of the most influential figures in Ireland&#39;s 20th century.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/531/002</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1473</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0009">Sister M. Cyprian</persName>
              <date>1916-05-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1606">Cork Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0274">Éamon de Valera</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0587">Dartmoor, England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1473_img_922_1"  type="Letter"  url="090fd66eaa3fc1cb14f2b07e0398a1ee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1473_img_922_2"  type="Letter"  url="4aca7df3dbc709dc38f2f2ba5a5245fd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1473_img_922_1"/>
                Mercy Convent  Cork Street. Dublin    30 - V 1916.   My dear Mr. De Valera,   It is no small draught of consolation that you possess the gift of <lb/>life - a gift which has become more precious than ever to those who sympathize with <lb/>you in your loneliness &amp; who love you.   Most men of great genius have to go through in life <lb/>a period of retirement &amp; solitude, brought about by choice or by Divine Providence through <lb/>the medium of human beings. The <hi rend="underline">Poet</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="underline">Saint</hi> have to pass this way. <sic>Saintship</sic> is <lb/> only a special type of genius. Now your time is come &amp; you will come out of it as <lb/> the sunshine from underneath the cloud. A cheerful <sic>acceptation</sic> of the surroundings &amp; <lb/>the observance of rule, will go far to the shortening of your stay there. The beginning will be <lb/>the hardest -: as those in charge get to know you they will appreciate you.   Since 1 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> May I have prayed every day very specially <lb/> for you that you may get grace to bear this cross &amp; be released soon. I shall begin <lb/>this '9 First Fridays' for you on 2nd June. If our religion be true â and we <hi rend="underline">know</hi><hi rend="underline">it</hi><hi rend="underline">is</hi><hi rend="underline">true</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">God</hi> is <hi rend="underline">with us</hi> &amp; since He is with us, we can be in spirit with one another: now I want <lb/>you to keep a little appointment with me each day at 7 o'clock a.m. when we have Mass <lb/>&amp;Holy Communion &amp;at 6.30 p.m. when I shall say each day The 30 days prayer <lb/> to our Blessed Lady for you. I am only asking you to try &amp;remember that you <lb/>are remembered then. Prayer can obtain all things â hope- &amp; when God acts <lb/>He doeth the work as God.   'This gloom after all <lb/>is but the shade of Gods hand outstretched caressingly'   
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1473_img_922_2"/>
              The students regret you exceedingly. Mother   R.I.P died early in May. <lb/>I hope to have the pleasure of seeing your little children very soon. Won't you suggest <lb/>to your wife to have your promise  to me  in this matter carried out.   You will find enclosed a pair of scapulars <lb/>intended to be a token of good will &amp;do something for you if such were in my <lb/>power.As I do not know your address I count on Mrs DeValera giving <lb/>me a corner in her envelope this time.   I am already looking forward to the day when <lb/>you will be once more with your wife &amp;children in the mean time you <lb/>can live for those you love notwithstanding place or circumstance. <lb/>Goodbye, my <hi rend="underline">dear friend</hi> &amp;believe me that I have paid you the tribute of <lb/> many a tear &amp; sympathize with you more deeply than I can tell. Trust God <lb/>not only for the best but for the <hi rend="underline">very</hi><hi rend="underline">best</hi> - try to see the ' <hi rend="underline">L</hi> beyond the <lb/> seems'  <seg type="closer"> Very sincerely yours in Jesus Christ  Sister M. Cyprian. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>