<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0445">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lieutenant Richard Perceval-Maxwell to Colonel Robert Perceval-Maxwell, 7 October, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard Perceval Maxwell </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Lieutenant Richard Henry Perceval-Maxwell (1897-1918), to his father, Colonel Robert David Perceval-Maxwell, (1870-1932) regarding his experiences of the war. Richard writes that his battalion could be going over the top soon but that he will not be going over with them. He also recounts recent German shelling activity which has caused some casualties in the area. In contrast to this, Richard talks about a new chaplain who has been arranging entertainment for the men. He also refers to certain positive reports and rumours but declines to disclose them as he doesn&#39;t believe them. Lieutenant Richard Henry Perceval-Maxwell served in the Cameronians (Scottish Rifles) during the Great War, along with his father and brother. Richard was killed in action in July 1918. Colonel Robert Maxwell was wounded twice while serving with the 36th (Ulster) Division during the First World War..</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Perceval-Maxwell Papers D/1556/27/3/2/3, Perceval-Maxwell Papers D/1556/27/3/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/445</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0917">Richard Perceval Maxwell </persName>
              <date>1916-10-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2057"> France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0111">Robert David Perceval Maxwell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0445_img_1784_1"  type="Letter"  url="f252c69220aec443ebee72e3b6183f64.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0445_img_1784_2"  type="Letter"  url="96a3057bfee9451fc058c35ce18fc699.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0445_img_1784_3"  type="Letter"  url="5b4f3e35b280568fd7ff6189d217e349.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0445_img_1784_4"  type="Letter"  url="6f6cfcd50cc314270412c85f6259db2b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0445_img_1784_5"  type="Letter"  url="f2e3519080fcf916f26e990f932ebe74.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0445_img_1784_1"/>
                10th Scottish Rifles  B.E.F  <hi rend="underline">France</hi>    <hi rend="underline">October</hi><hi rend="underline">7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916</hi>   Dear Father    Thanks so much <lb/> for your letter, We are moving <lb/> up very soon into the trenches. <lb/> I am going up but in the <lb/> event of the Battalion going <lb/> over the top as it usually <lb/> does, I have to remain behind <lb/> in the trenches with reinforcements. <lb/> They have sent my name <lb/> in for a bombing course, so <lb/> I expect it will come round <lb/> in a week. <seg type="del">If</seg> The Bosche dropped <lb/> a few high explosive in <lb/> here &amp; caused a few casualties <lb/> One landed in Battalion orderly <lb/> room of a H.L.I Battalion  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0445_img_1784_2"/>
              And wounded the C.O. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 1/c <lb/> and adjutant &amp; 3 others. <lb/>It was quite amusing watching <lb/> the houses going west as <lb/> we were on parade most <lb/> of the time about 1/4 mile <lb/> away. Only a few fell <lb/> while we went in it. <lb/> They have almost given up <lb/> shelling this place as they <lb/> only have about 1 battery <lb/> that can reach it. Inhabitants <lb/> are coming in, a few every <lb/> day. There was a great joy <lb/> among the men when they <lb/> saw a 'madamoiselle' go <lb/> along the road past their <lb/> billetd. I wonder if my <lb/> letters take as long <seg type="del">comߞ</seg> going   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0445_img_1784_3"/>
              <seg type="del">ming out</seg> home <seg type="del">here</seg> as ones from <lb/> England do coming out here. <lb/>They take a full week. <lb/> Our C.O. Col <seg type="unclear">Ussher Fergus</seg><lb/> quite decent but he has <lb/> great fads. We are not <lb/> allowed to carry walking <lb/> sticks on parade and we <lb/> all walk about with <lb/> our gas helmets slung over <lb/> our shoulder. There is another <lb/> division fast coming in <lb/> now, I suuppose to take our <lb/> place sooner or later. <lb/> There are great reports <lb/> &amp; rumours going about now <lb/> very good ones but I dont <lb/> believe in them much so <lb/><seg type="del">However</seg> I dont think I had <lb/> better repeat them. We  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0445_img_1784_4"/>
              have a Topping Padré <lb/> here. Any amusements to that <lb/> the men get are arranged <lb/> by him. Cinema concerts, he <lb/> goes round and borrows <lb/> bands from other units for <lb/> us and all that sort of thing <lb/> The Bosche here seems to <lb/> have the wind up pretty <lb/> badly as in the last push <lb/> the Battalion were in they <lb/> only killed one officer <lb/> &amp; a few men but of course <lb/> he managed to hit every <lb/> other officer. The Battalion <lb/> was brought out by a <lb/> Sergeant. The only news <lb/> we get is through the <lb/> papers. But that was <lb/> same with you &amp; Jock  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0445_img_1784_5"/>
              I dont think I have <lb/> any more news to give <lb/> except that the winter <lb/> is setting in now I think <lb/> we have had rain <lb/> every day since I came <lb/> up. I dont think I want <lb/> any kit at present I <lb/> will write if I do. Well <lb/> I must end now. so good <lb/> bye for the present. <seg type="closer"> Y<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> aff.   Dick  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>