<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1851">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William M. Nolan to Lord Wimborne, 13 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William M. Nolan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from the town clerk of Limerick, William M. Nolan (1855-1941), to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Churchill Guest, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939). This letter deals with the issue of retirement, specifically the retirement of a Mr Patrick Reidy from Limerick. Nolan was asked by the Limerick Council to obtain permission from Lord Wimborne to award Mr Reidy the highest superannuation possible, because for his years of loyal service which is explained in the letter.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/4810/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1851</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1399">William M. Nolan</persName>
              <date>1916-03-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0904">Town Clerk&#39;s Office, Town Hall, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1941</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1851_img_1305_1"  type="Letter"  url="923289cff0b32bf26f251f485cdb3025.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1851_img_1305_2"  type="Letter"  url="eddeafbe867468502736358c97c0c59e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1851_img_1305_1"/>
             Town Clerk's Office, <lb/>Town Hall, <lb/>Limerick  13th March '16  <seg type="del">1912</seg>  Your Excellency,   I am directed by the Limerick County Borough Council to <lb/>bring before you the undermentioned particulars with a view to <lb/>the obtaining of Your Excellency's consent to their proposal to <lb/>grant a <sic>superranuation</sic> allowance to Mr. Patrick Reidy, pursuant to <lb/>Section 1 of the Local Officers <sic>Superranuation</sic> (Ireland) Act, <lb/>1869-32 &amp; 33 Vic., cap. 79.   By the Limerick Corporation Gas Act <hi rend="underline">1878</hi>-41 &amp; 42 Vic. cap. <lb/>160-the Council is empowered to manufacture and supply the <lb/>inhabitants of Limerick ,and to light the public Streets with gas. <lb/>The control and management of the Undertaking is vested in a <lb/>Committee, constituted as provided by the Act, and partially <lb/>appointed by the Council, and known as "The Gas Committee".   The power of appointment and removal of officers and servants is <lb/>by section 42 of the Act vested in the Committee, but on the true <lb/>construction of the Act there is no doubt that an officer of the <lb/>committee is an officer of the Council for the purposes of the <lb/><sic>Superranuation</sic> Act of 1869.   It appears by the Minutes of the Gas Committee under date <lb/>1st June <hi rend="underline">1894</hi> that the Manager reported that the Foreman had died <lb/>and that on the joint recommendation of the Manager and Engineer <lb/>Mr. P. Reidy was appointed to fill the vacancy, wages £2 per week, <lb/>and a house, light, and coals free. On the 10th February 1896 Mr <lb/>Reidy's wages were increased to £2:10:0 per week, and on the 30th <lb/>December 1897 to £3 per week and similar perquisites. On the 8th <lb/>April 1913 his duties were restricted to that of yard foreman <lb/>whereas he had previously been foreman over the yard and works <lb/>and consequently his cash wages were reduced to £1:10;0 per week. <lb/> On the 1st July 1913 the cash wages were again increased to £2 per
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1851_img_1305_2"/>
            per week. <hi rend="underline">In July 1915</hi> Mr Reidy finally retired owing to the <lb/>fact that he could no longer discharge the duties of his Office <lb/>by reason of permanent infirmity of body. Mr Reidy's connection <lb/>with the Committee has been a long and faithful one. He was, <lb/>prior to his appointment as Foreman in 1894, employed at the <seg type="del">work</seg> <lb/>works as tinsmith, from the year 1880.   Under these circumstances the Committee and the Council <lb/>unanimously desire to grant Mr Reidy the highest <sic>superranuation</sic> <lb/>allowance which it is in their power to give him, and to <lb/>obtain the consent of Your Excellency in order to give effect <lb/>to their desire.   I shall be glad to supply any further information in <lb/>relation to the matter which may be required and am directed <lb/>to ask that the case be dealt with promptly having regard to <lb/>the age and state of health of Mr Reidy.   I beg to remain, <lb/>Your Excellency's obedient Servant,   <hi rend="underline">W M Nolan</hi>  <lb/>Town Clerk.  To His Excellency, <lb/>Lord Wimborne, K.P. &amp;c. <lb/>Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>