<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0412">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Margaret Annie Jones to her brother-in-law, August 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Margaret Annie Jones</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a handwritten copy of an extract from a letter written by Margaret Annie Jones (née Dampney) (b. 1881). The letter concerns the sinking of the HMS Shark at the Battle of Jutland. Margaret begins by describing the battle as she has heard it from the survivors. Margaret writes about her late husband, Loftus William Jones&#39; (1880-1916), injuries and records that at one stage his leg was &#39;completely blown away above the knee&#39;. She states that all but six of the survivors died from cold and shock. Jones was a commander in the Royal Navy aboard the H. M. S Shark during the First World War. He was 36 years old when he died at the Battle of Jutland on 31 May 1916. He was posthumously awarded the Victoria Cross. The letter is addressed to one of Margaret&#39;s brother-in-laws. William had three brothers, Lewis, Frank and Charles, the first two also served in the Navy, while Charles fought for the Indian Army.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Savage Armstrong Collection, D/618/167</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/412</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0894">Margaret Annie Jones</persName>
              <date>1916-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1600">Strangford House, Strangford, County Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lewis Loftus</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0412_img_1685_1"  type="Letter"  url="abe6f3fa8bc9c53b29f5ecb6592d076d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0412_img_1685_2"  type="Letter"  url="ee69f8f25fcc91431b64edbe2004afbf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0412_img_1685_3"  type="Letter"  url="dcbfd83e90195336ee45fdba5a31b63a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0412_img_1685_4"  type="Letter"  url="1baf460bccc37c7a14d24826d4666ff6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0412_img_1685_5"  type="Envelope"  url="d2f898f3e04bace62e6385a6bac295c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0412_img_1685_6"  type="Envelope"  url="9576bf15716a966ce8d1aee87cb7149e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0412_img_1685_1"/>
              Records    Strangford House,  Strangford, Co.Down.    Copy of Extract of letter from Commander Loftus <lb/> Jones' Wife to her brother-in-law regarding the <lb/> last fight of H.M.S. Shark in the Jutland Battle, <lb/> (Made by permission of Major J. Collas, his brother- <lb/>in law.) â   'I have seen the survivors, and they told me that <lb/> Loftus was wounded in the face at the beginning.â <lb/>They were under the fire of the German battleships <lb/>for more than an hour.â The pipe which connect <lb/>ed the steam up was blown away &amp; then Shark <lb/>had to remain motionless.â As each German battle- <lb/>ship came up then fired into the Shark, but no one  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0412_img_1685_2"/>
               Image contains two pages  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0412_img_1685_3"/>
              and there was no cowardice anywhere. Each man did his duty <lb/> as usual, and only one went mad. â Hope was particularly <lb/> great, he stood at his gun from beginning to end and never waver <lb/>ed. â Loftus said to him 'Well done Hope you are splendid'    When Loftus' leg was blown off Hope got two bits of wood <lb/> and bound it together to try and stop the bleeding. â <lb/> Hope won a V.C. if any man has in this war, so the other men <lb/> told me. I saw each man separately, and each one told me <lb/> the same. â Loftus did not go down with the ship , he was <lb/> put on a raft by <seg type="unclear">Filleul</seg>, he had to be tied on as he was <lb/> helpless, but quite conscious. â About 20 of the men <lb/> and the 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi> Lieutenant were on another raft. â <lb/> When in the water Loftus said 'now let's have a song <lb/> lads' and the 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi> Lieut. started 'Nearer my God to <lb/>Thee'. â Later some ships came near and Loftus asked <lb/> 'if they were ours', and was told they were. He said  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0412_img_1685_4"/>
              'That is splendid.'    He didn't speak any more; the ships altered their <lb/>course and did not come near them. â    Loftus soon died after this. â The 1<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">st</hi></hi> Lieut. was not <lb/> wounded but he, and all, except six, died from cold <lb/>and shock. â    The men assured me that death by drowning is not <lb/> a bit painful, so I hope that Loftus just skipped <lb/> away into unconsciousness. He must have been mortally <lb/> wounded, and very tired and he had done his duty.   Aug 1916.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0412_img_1685_5"/>
              Copy of extract of Letter from Commander <lb/> Loftus Jones'. Wife, ( widow ) to her Brother-in-law <lb/> regarding the last fight of H.M.S. Shark in the Jutland <lb/> Battle. ( Made by permission of Major L. Loftus, his <lb/>Brother-in-law ) Capt. L.Jones was in command of H.M.S. Shark <lb/> &amp; the Destroyer Flotilla. Aug. 1916.   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0412_img_1685_6"/>
               Back of envelope upside down. centre:- Aug. /1916 Public records' office stamp partly covered by flap is on left. Beneath the date handwritten number 0816/167 (upside down ). Stamp on right. Oval stamp RECORD written in the centre. Above this is PUBLIC RECORD OFFICE: and OF NORTHERN IRELAND is written at the bottom of the oval  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>