<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1077">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lucy Ramsden, 22 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Lucy Ramsden</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Lucy Ramsden (1862-1928) to the chairman of the joint committee of the Royal College of Physicians (RCPI) and Royal College of Surgeons (RCSI). Ramsden requests that a deputation from the Irish Nurses&#39; Association be allowed to attend a meeting to discuss the formation of a nursing college, similar to one established in England by Sir Arthur Stanley.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-3-15-4, RCPI-2-3-3-15-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1077</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0584">Lucy Ramsden</persName>
              <date>1916-03-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0225">34 St Stephen&#39;s Green, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1077_img_3220_1"  type="Letter"  url="d88682e8e1e46450f10b1c2a923fb3f9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1077_img_3220_1"/>
                THE IRISH NURSES' ASSOCIATION  34 ST. STEPHEN'S GREEN,  Dublin.    March 22nd, 1916, 191    To the Chairman  Joint Committee of the  Royal College of Physicians  and  The Royal College of Surgeons  Ireland.   Sir,   I have heard that you purpose holding a Meeting to consider <lb/>the Hon. Arthur Stanley's Scheme re 'A College of Nursing.'   On behalf of the Irish Nurses Association I venture to ask <lb/>if you would receive a deputation from the Association and so <lb/>give the Members an opportunity of placing their views on this <lb/>Subject before you?   Trusting you will see your way to granting this request. <seg type="closer"> I am, Sir <lb/>Yours very faithfully,   (Signed) Lucy Ramsden <lb/>(President. Irish Nurses' Association)  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>