<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0665">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Montgomery to his father, Harford Hugh Montgomery, 26 October, 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Alexander Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Montgomery to his father enclosing cheques to settle accounts. William sympathises with his father on the death of an acquaintance, Matt. He writes that Major Horace Haslett (1884- 1953), who had been evacuated previously having lost his eye in a gunshot wound, is returning to duty and will take over William&#39;s duty as second in command. Major Horace Haslett was gazetted on 14 July 1917 having been awarded the Croix de Chevalier, likely for actions taken during the Battle of Messines. The Montgomery family lived in Malone Park, one of the wealthiest suburbs of Belfast city. This letter is part of a large collection that their son, William, a Captain with the 9th Battalion of the Royal Irish Rifles, wrote to his parents, Harford Hugh and Sara Montgomery, throughout the war. His first letter is dated 3 December 1914. Captain Montgomery was a decorated soldier. He was awarded both the Victoria and the 15 Star medals and was promoted to the rank of Major. His father owned a fire assessor business.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Montgomery Family, D2794/1/1/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/665</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1502">William Alexander Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-11-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sara Montgomery</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0158">Monacherra, Malone Park, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_1"  type="Letter"  url="9e0c94933fb25c2fa40b31ce7a378c39.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_2"  type="Letter"  url="6a74935904e3dba9861193c4cc4503f7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_3"  type="Letter"  url="21a7bb6c0edd5748c9b902937136bd87.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_4"  type="Letter"  url="64a700d09c82069f5622470d3bca77d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_5"  type="Letter"  url="b3ff6f06dd6f3e99f959621d20429a13.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_6"  type="Envelope"  url="3a842b78eec5f09297f942e9dd7ec700.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0665_img_2158_7"  type="Letter"  url="7d790f42853bb0dc3e6c1fb14c6a5b58.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_1"/>
                In the Field    26.1.16   Dear Father   Please pass cheques <lb/> herewith in payment of accounts <lb/> enclosed. Receipts may be given <lb/> to Emmie.   I duly received yours of 21 <hi rend="superscript">st</hi> inst. <lb/>yesterday with enclosure. I <lb/>note with much interest the <lb/>dizzy heights to which <seg type="unclear">Bennie</seg><lb/>has attained. I hope he continues <lb/>to do well. I was exceedingly <lb/>sorry to hear of Matt's death. I <lb/>expect your were cut up about <lb/>it. I will try &amp; write a note to <lb/>the Surveyors Institution some time <lb/>&amp; tell them of a matter that would <lb/>no doubt interest them. <seg type="del">which</seg>  About a month ago two fellows <lb/>dropped in to see me 'professionally' <lb/>in my Coy. H.Q. in the Front line. <lb/>One was the <sic>Liason</sic> Gunner for <lb/>the day &amp; the other was the O.C. <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_2"/>
              2. <lb/> the Coy on my left. We both <lb/>belonged to different Brigades. I <lb/>don't recollect that I had ever <lb/>met either of them before. But <lb/>the nature of our business brings <lb/>us in touch with a surprising <lb/>number of people many of whom <lb/>we only know by their Command <lb/>or occupation. (e.g. O.C. Trench <lb/>Mortar Battery. <sic>Liason</sic> Officer. <lb/>F.O.O. O.C. Flank Coy .etc.)   It was in the middle of the <lb/>night &amp; we had tea &amp; other <lb/>refreshment &amp; things were <lb/>quiet, &amp; as usual we got chatting <lb/>after we had transacted our <lb/>business. Sociability as I <lb/>understood it before the war is <lb/>a pale shadow when compared <lb/>with the Comradeship of the front <lb/>line trench. You would love this <lb/>side of it. Best of men. Thought <lb/>quick &amp; clear. Judgment swift  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_3"/>
              3. <lb/>Wit sharp. Expression forcible <lb/>rather than polite, but tact is <lb/>always of a high class in a <lb/>successful officer. No tact. No <lb/> cooperation in a good guiding <lb/>light for any officer. Well - <lb/> In the course of our chat, we <lb/>discovered that all three of us <lb/>were members of the Surveyors <lb/>Institution. Both the other fellows <lb/>were P.A.S.I men. One of them <lb/>is the son of a big London one <lb/>time Auctioneer &amp; Estate Agent - <lb/>Harrington's. (I think that is right) <lb/>The father sold the business &amp; <lb/>then changed his name to Cook. <lb/>Very decent fellow the son.   I have forgotten the other fellows <lb/>names but I meet him occasionally <lb/>when I dine out round the <lb/>Batteries. This of course only <lb/>happens during our tours out.   We are expecting Horace  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_4"/>
              <lb/>4 <lb/>(Major Haslett, I beg his pardon) <lb/>to re-join us today. He will take over my job as Acting 2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi><lb/> in Command. Woods is on a 2 1/2 <lb/>months course in England. The <lb/> 2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>in Command job is a delightful <lb/>one. I have had a most perfect <lb/>rest at it this joyous month past.   Owing to the effect Horace's <lb/>rejoining has on my position <lb/>I couldn't say very much when <lb/>I was asked by the C.O. what I <lb/>thought about it. I am however <lb/>doubtful as to its advisability <lb/> in view of the wet &amp; exposure &amp; <lb/> cold &amp; muck. His lack of proper <lb/>eye focus also is a very serious <lb/>drawback as regards observation <lb/> or in the very rare instances in <lb/>which it could arise in his position, <lb/>self protection. It has been <lb/>entirely the C.O.'s effort which <seg type="del">has</seg><lb/>is bringing him back. He  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_5"/>
              <lb/>5. <lb/>hated to think of him in a Clerk's <lb/> job and I know he will do all he <lb/>can to make things easy for him. <lb/>This he can do all right as long <lb/>as Woods is away, but if he comes <lb/>back Horace will have to take a <lb/>Coy. or leave us. I don't think <lb/>even the C.O. believes he could <lb/>stand Coy. work. Horace I know <lb/>was himself most anxious not <lb/>to take over the job of 2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> in Command <lb/>&amp; wrote to this effect to the C.O. <lb/>putting it quite clearly that he <lb/>hadn't the experience &amp; saying <lb/>he would be delighted to serve <lb/>under me. But the C.O. with his <lb/> cast iron ideas of Justice said <lb/> NO. I saw Horace's letter to this <lb/>effect. I have Mother's letter of <lb/>11 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Oct before me but there does <lb/>not appear to be anything in <lb/>it requiring reply.   
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_6"/>
              6. <lb/>I had a very interesting letter <lb/>from my good friend <seg type="unclear">Maj</seg><lb/>Byers of Knock Church on <lb/>Theological subjects in reply <lb/> to a letter I wrote him.   I am in the best of health <lb/>&amp; form.   Drop me a line when you <lb/>find time.  <seg type="closer"> Your affectionate son   W. Montgomery </seg> 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0665_img_2158_7"/>
              <seg type="postscript">  H.H.Montgomery Esq C/o W <hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Montgomery &amp; Son <lb/>2 Wellington Place <lb/>Belfast.  </seg> Post Stamp marked Field Post 26 Oct 1916  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>