<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6705">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frank P. Walsh to all State Chairmen, 18 December 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frank P. Walsh</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Frank P. Walsh (1864-1939), was an American lawyer and political reformer. He was one of the chief architects of the legislative struggle against industrial exploitation of children and an advocate of Irish and anti-imperialist causes. He also fought for civil liberties and was a labour partisan and staunch New Dealer. Walsh was a member of the Irish-American delegation (along with Michael J. Ryan and Edward F. Dunne) who were appointed to represent Ireland at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919. On 10 April 1919 the delegation arrived in Paris. The men returned to America in July 1919 where Walsh began working with the Dail External Loan (Bond Drive). 
In this letter references are made to Mr. Mason a member of the American Legion, who was opposed to the Irish republic. This is being labelled as English propaganda. Walsh urges the chairmen to engage in more activity to counteract the work of opponents like Mr Mason. Walsh&#39;s aim was to obtain positive publicity by doing so.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection>William Bourke Cockran Papers, Box 13, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6705</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0925">Frank P. Walsh</persName>
              <date>1919-12-18</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">State Chairmen, City Chairmen, Speakers&#39; Bureau</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6705_img_None_1"  url="phpsgK4yx.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6705_img_0_1"/>
             American Commission on Irish Independence<lb/>Frank P. Walsh Chairman   411 Fifth Avenue<lb/>New York    December Eighteenth<lb/>Nineteen Nineteen   To:<lb/>State Chairmen,<lb/>City Chairmen,<lb/>Speakers' Bureau:  Gentlemen:-  Mr. Mason, author of the Mason Bill, is being<lb/>mot on all sides with the statement that the American Legion<lb/>is opposed to recognition of the Republic of Ireland and many<lb/>seem to think he is doing a serious thing in antagonizing this<lb/>body. It appears that some of the Posts are sending out very<lb/>strong protests against the recognition of the Republic of<lb/>Ireland. Of course, this is done by individual Posts which<lb/>do not represent the spirit of the American Legion but are<lb/>being used for English propaganda.  This imposes a duty on all of us, and I would suggest<lb/>that we ought to be as active as our opponents. There must be<lb/>many Posts in which our friends are numerous enough to secure<lb/>the passage of strong resolutions favorable to the Mason Bill,<lb/>and if this were done the influence of hostile action by other<lb/>Posts would be effectively counteracted. Some of our friends<lb/>are very sensitive to attacks like this one, and we must do all<lb/>in our power to reassure them.  Resolutions of support should be passed wherever we<lb/>are holding meetings of our own and proper publicity obtained.   Yours very truly    Frank P. Walsh<lb/>Chairman  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>