<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0803">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 22 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender discusses the report he is working on concerning the events surrounding July 1, and reflects on the odd fact that he is writing dispatches while his brother Rex is fighting in the trenches. He recounts a visit he recently received from a Brigadier-General Staff Officer seeking Spender&#39;s influence in order to secure a promotion. Spender expresses amusement that many officers think him influential over who gets promoted, given that his own career has little hope of progress. He mentions a holiday Lillian&#39;s maids are soon to take, and Lillian&#39;s hunt for a new house.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/394</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/803</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0803_img_2344_1"  type="NULL"  url="ff1cb33b17b8c3b04cdcd7cda6d47ab6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0803_img_2344_2"  type="NULL"  url="bc15761dbec52389d02efbc389d4b6d3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0803_img_2344_3"  type="NULL"  url="3a6a89db98565869ccc7833801285a27.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0803_img_2344_4"  type="NULL"  url="585d0271a148fddc43ddff1123e89297.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0803_img_2344_5"  type="NULL"  url="ff1cb33b17b8c3b04cdcd7cda6d47ab6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0803_img_2344_1"/>
                Aug. 22. 16.   My pr   The dispatch is not moving at all. <lb/>I am now back again at the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> July which <lb/>I have just rewritten having found many <lb/>inaccuracies in my former account tho' based <lb/>on official documents! It really is difficult &amp; <lb/>I was never intended <seg type="del">as</seg> to be  a historian but I hope <lb/>to buckle to it again better tho' I don't see <lb/>how I am ever to get up to date. The first <lb/>12 pages before the attack I am fairly well <lb/>pleased with now but than I was in personal <lb/>touch with the whole thing.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0803_img_2344_2"/>
              However I drew one winner today getting <lb/>my evening report passed as 'Excellent' I <lb/>feel as if I was back at School &amp; had got <lb/>top marks on my essay. It really is curious <lb/>to be doing this kind of work in the middle of <lb/>a war with Rex in the trenches.  You seem to  have  been having a happy time in <lb/>Wilts but I wonder whether you ought to have <lb/>spoken about Sam Hu not that I should mind <lb/>if he was found out, so I think it is as well.  A very curious situation came  about  yesterday. <lb/>Gen' B.G a staff college contemporary had a talk <lb/>about the dispatch, &amp; after I had settled down to <lb/>make notes came in &amp; said What do you think  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0803_img_2344_3"/>
              of my position as a Brigadier Gen' GS, kept on <lb/>the staff because of my qualifications &amp; passed over <lb/>by 20 juniors in consequence. I am told it will <lb/> be all right after the war but you know what <lb/>that means. Can't you do anything? !!!   When I add that he attributes his not having <lb/>gone quicker to the fact that he was anti Ulster <lb/>and therefore not acceptable to H.G you will <lb/>realise the humour of the situation. It never <lb/>struck me that I should be held responsible for <lb/>the promotions and awards in the Gazette, &amp; <lb/>my future would indeed be a warm one if I <lb/>were not able to point to one great factor that <lb/>my name is not among them.  I am so glad about the maids and hope <lb/>everything will go smoothly. The holiday for all  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0803_img_2344_4"/>
              as the move certainly seems indicated now <lb/>&amp; I think you can pay their tickets to Belfast <lb/>as a holiday treat (? from us both). I'm rather <lb/>disturbed at your having to house hunt again <lb/>you will be an experienced little pr when we <lb/>come to settle down in our own, whilst Maggie <lb/>ought to know exactly what is essential in <lb/>her department. I'm afraid St James Palace <lb/>sounds rather an expensive neighbourhood for a <lb/>pr. Was it the pr's face or the pr's furs which <lb/>made the porter chivy her to a first class carriage, or <lb/>the <seg type="foreign">tout assemble</seg> perhaps? Mayne in Egypt <lb/>seems to be sorry he left the Division &amp; finds 3 <lb/>ASC's â 2 besides himself as <seg type="unclear">altern</seg> of troop. Falls <seg type="unclear">seems</seg><lb/>rather low in the 36<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> simply stale I fancy.  Quite enough for a pr even a pampered one. <lb/>when you next order at the store could you send out some <lb/>ANIS chocolate. No hurry about it. Has Rex written Paragraph completed on page 1   
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0803_img_2344_5"/>
               Written at the top of the first page page  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>