<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1796">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cardinal Michael Logue, Archbishop of Armagh, regarding Sir John Robert O'Connell, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Logue</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Cardinal Michael Logue (1840-1924), archbishop of Armagh (1887-1924). Logue was resolutely opposed to republican violence, such as that of Easter Week 1916, but described the British reaction to the violence as &#39;foolish and pernicious&#39;.
In this letter Logue praises Sir John Robert O&#39;Connell (1868-1943), after knowing him for many years and states that no matter what office he is appointed to he will be found to be an intelligent and zealous official.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7153/20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1796</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0265">Michael Logue</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0314">Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1796_img_1250_1"  type="Letter"  url="9a8f90861549f593816134b3936cb608.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1796_img_1250_2"  type="Letter"  url="82bdc9c5112f01e8b1a053c7ff0932ce.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1796_img_1250_1"/>
             ARA <seg type="unclear">COELI</seg> <lb/>ARMAGH   I have great pleasure <lb/>in stating that I have <lb/>known Sir John R O,Connell <lb/>for several years, and have <lb/>always found him a <lb/>gentleman of high charac- <lb/>ter, capable, energetic, and <lb/>always ready to devote him- <lb/>self to help on any good <lb/>work which came in his <lb/>way. I believe that his <lb/>professional eminence, <lb/>his strict integrity and <lb/>his conscientious de- <lb/>votion to duty fit <lb/>him for the successful
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1796_img_1250_2"/>
            discharge of any public <lb/>duty with which he <lb/>may be entrusted; and <lb/> that in any public <lb/>office to which he <lb/>may be appointed <lb/>he will be found an <lb/>intelligent, zealous <lb/>and faithful public <lb/>Official.   +Michael Card. Logue   <lb/>Armagh 29<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> March 1916.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>