<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0469">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George F. Montgomery to the Under-Secretary, 20 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Fleming Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from George Fleming Montgomery (b. 1867), a Longford solicitor, to Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938), Under Secretary for Ireland, applying for the vacant post of Clerk of Crown and Peace for County Westmeath. He outlines his twenty-five year career in the legal profession.Sir Robert Chalmers (1858 - 1938) was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5615/10439</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/469</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0990">George Fleming Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0979">Granard, County Longford, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0469_img_1816_1"  type="Letter"  url="d1417c0f5cb895ede51be5b31ea60b97.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0469_img_1816_1"/>
                GEO F MONTGOMERY  SOLICITOR  Commissioner For Affidavits  Office Every Monday at Granard  Longford,    20th June 1916    The Under Secretary  The Castle  Dublin   <hi rend="underline">Sir</hi>   I beg to apply for the vacant <lb/> office of Clerk of Crown &amp; Peace for <lb/> the County of Westmeath I am <lb/> a practising Solr for the last 25 <lb/> years having been admitted in <lb/> 1891 and am now aged 49 <lb/> years and if appointed I shall <lb/> by strict adherence to my duty to <lb/> merit the approval of those who <lb/> are my superiors  <seg type="closer"> I am Sir <lb/> Yours faithfully   George F Montgomery </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>