<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4115">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Thomas Elliot to Edward Kerr, 21 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Elliot</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Edward Kerr Papers D1593/9</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4115</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0059">Thomas Elliot</persName>
              <date>1916-03-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0599">Drumcore, Enniskillen, Co. Fermanagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Kerr</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4115_img_3491_1"  type="Letter"  url="cc593b15ffe5a1e049548d5df74c4f18.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4115_img_3491_1"/>
             Dairie's <lb/>Drumcore <lb/>Enniskillen    21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> March, 1916.   Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Kerr   The gate you refer to in your letter of the <lb/>17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> was put on without the knowledge or authority <lb/>of the late owners of Ballygonnill, M <hi rend="superscript">r</hi>T Elliot, and as <lb/>there never was a cart road through that field <lb/>I had the gate removed to where it now his <!-- should be 'it now is' --> <lb/>and will raise no objection if you put <lb/>it on where it now is for your own convenience <lb/>or that of your caretaker. I understand there is <lb/>a pass that way into your farm in<seg type="unclear">Rabion</seg>for <lb/>carrying turf and luggage of any kind, But if you <lb/>wish to put on a gate and cart that way, it will <lb/>be alright. I have an objection to the making <lb/>of a cart road through my meadow field where <lb/>I intend to plough as soon as possible.   When we get settled in Ballygonnill if you <lb/>run up we can have a look at the place <lb/>and a chat over it.   In the meantime <lb/>I remain <lb/>Yours Faithfully   Thos. Elliott 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>