<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4183">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Patrick Carey to John Quinnell, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Clerk of Union and Council, Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Patrick Carey to John Quinnell </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library, Tralee</repository>
                  <collection>Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians BG104/B/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4183</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0073">Clerk of Union and Council, Killarney Poor Law Board of Guardians</persName>
              <date>1915-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0668">Killarney, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">J.B. Quinnell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2036">Tralee, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4183_img_3556_1"  type="Letter"  url="483a3d8c6dc40a07c6ff3b5190fa0174.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4183_img_3556_1"/>
             22nd December 1915,   Dear Sir,   At a meeting of the Guardians on the 18th Inst. Mr <lb/>James J Coffey inquired how many insertions of <lb/>advertisements were given to the Newspapers; and in the <lb/>course of the discussion Mr John Murphy stated that I <lb/>forwarded his Paying Orders to Mr Quinnell. As Mr Murphy's <lb/>tender  only  has been accepted for the advertising of the <lb/>business of the Union and Council in certain papers I <lb/>shall send the advertisements to him in future and the <lb/>Paying Orders will be drawn in his favour and sent direct <lb/>to him. The Paying Orders hitherto, so far as advertising <lb/>in the Killarney Echo, were drawn in his favour.   Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Clerk of Union &amp; Council.  JB Quinnell Esq <lb/>E Harrington Esq <lb/>Tralee. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>