<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5377">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letters from Kathleen Durcan to Willie Daly, 19 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kathleen Durcan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/16/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5377</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0456">Kathleen Durcan</persName>
              <date>1923-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1717">Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Willie Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0317">Co Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5377_img_4663_1"  type="Letter"  url="7ab1b4a0633b98f8d470cca881adbdf0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5377_img_4663_2"  type="Letter"  url="5b37455d4d5c471b8f542168d64ef8f4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5377_img_4663_3"  type="Letter"  url="d84f4f239a23062fd4f264f16295805a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5377_img_4663_4"  type="Letter"  url="f46a502f07568c0943b27c702b13314a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5377_img_4663_1"/>
              Tuesday<lb/>The doctor was<lb/>in to-day &amp; was<lb/>very pleased with<lb/>Susan's progress.<lb/>She will soon be<lb/>well D[eo]G[ratias]<lb/>Slán leat <lb/> C. Nic D.   <lb/>  <seg type="unclear">Coláirte/<lb/> 19ad Marta '23     </seg>    <seg type="unclear"> Dear Liam </seg>   I suppose you have heard of<lb/>poor Charlie's execution before this, you<lb/>must have got a terrible shock, I am<lb/>sure you are heartbroken for I<lb/>know that Charlie was the idol of<lb/>the whole family. But he is happy<lb/>now, for he never regretted the course<lb/>he took, and would never ask<lb/>for a more glorious death  Susie knows nothing about<lb/>it yet, probably she told you in<lb/>her letter that she was laid<lb/>up with a cold, she had a<lb/>rather bad cold, but she is<lb/>very much improved now, she    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5377_img_4663_2"/>
             was not allowed   up yet, but<lb/>the Doctor will be coming on his<lb/>usual weekly visit tomorrow and<lb/>she will probably be allowed sit<lb/>up for a few hours on the<lb/>coming days. I am allowed in<lb/>to see her every day and she<lb/>is in real good form, she<lb/>loves talking about the three of<lb/>you especially poor Charlie, she<lb/>had a letter from Tom and<lb/>one from your Mother on<lb/>Thursday last — the day we<lb/>heard the sad news here. Tom<lb/>seems to be in good form, he<lb/>was asking for Irish Books and<lb/>seems to be studying, he is<lb/>allowed receive and write one<lb/>letter a week, he can get<lb/>in Irish Books too — I brought<lb/>the ones he wanted to the gate  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5377_img_4663_3"/>
            <lb/>on Sat. last. I had a letter from<lb/>Florrie Mahony to—day, she is really<lb/>heart—broken, Mrs. Mahony was in<lb/>to see Susie, but of course she<lb/>wouldn't be allowed to the<lb/>Infirmary for fear Susan would<lb/>suspect something   I was in Whelan's on Sat. and<lb/>they said that Susan should<lb/>go out to them as soon as<lb/>she is able to sit up, and<lb/>that they would break the<lb/>sad news by degrees to her, I<lb/>think she would like to go<lb/>there too, and it would be<lb/>more suited to her frame of mind<lb/>too for they are all grown up<lb/><seg type="unclear">would</seg> understand her feelings<lb/>whereas in Leixlip there are<lb/>a crowd of youngsters who<lb/>would not understand   Sheila O'Brien was up here<lb/>twice, but she was not in to
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5377_img_4663_4"/>
             see Susan, the <seg type="unclear">nuns</seg> are very careful<lb/>about her and want her to get<lb/>strong herself before she hears<lb/>anything, for she would never be<lb/>able to bear it now. It is very<lb/>hard to hear her talking so<lb/>happily about the three of you, she<lb/>was delighted to have your's<lb/>and Tom's letters. It is very<lb/>hard to think that Charlie<lb/>is dead, for I knew him as<lb/>well from hearing Susan<lb/>always talking about him &amp;<lb/>from his letters which were<lb/>certainly unusual types. All we<lb/>can do now is pray for him<lb/>&amp; pray that God may help you<lb/>all to bear the cross  I must finish now by offering<lb/>you my sincerest sympathy, &amp;<lb/>hoping you will soon be free   Slán [agus] beannacht dé leat<lb/>Mise - Cara do  <seg type="unclear"> dúrí, </seg>  Kathleen Durcan    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>