<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4655">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr Thomas Kirkpatrick to Dr Charles Burland, 15 March 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.

Dr Charles Burland (1861-1924) served as the Senior Medical Officer and Government Medical Inspector of Emigration at the Liverpool port from 1909. The purpose of his inspection was to prevent contagious disease being spread on both travelling ships and abroad. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-67</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4655</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0168">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick </persName>
              <date>1919-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0504">Charles Burland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0898">Board of Trade, Canning Place, Liverpool, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1954</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4655_img_3997_1"  type="Letter"  url="4c28b772c0f30878783db6fd9cb7b0bd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4655_img_3997_1"/>
             15th MARCH 18.   C.Burland, Esq., M.D., <lb/>Senior Medical Inspector, <lb/>Board of Trade, Liverpool.   Dear Sir,   In reply to your letter of the 18th inst., re Mr. John <lb/>Percival Frizell I regret to inform you no one of this name <lb/>was admitted a Licentiate of this College either in less <lb/>or in any other year. The Diplomas of this College bear <lb/>at foot the <seg type="del">names</seg> signatures  of several Fellows of the College <lb/>including the President, Vice-President and Registrar, <lb/>and, if it is not troubling you too far, I should be glad <lb/>to know whose signature are represented on this Diploma.   I remain, <lb/>Dear Sir, <lb/><sic>Yoursfaithfully</sic>, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>