<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2674">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael O'Riordan to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 27 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael O&#39;Riordan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Note for abstract: Mgr. Michael O&#39;Riordan (1857-1919), rector at the Irish College, Rome</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/I/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2674</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0177">Michael O&#39;Riordan</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0191">Irish College, Rome, Italy</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_1"  type="Letter"  url="5926adb3a2108349732aeb8064275f9e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_2"  type="Letter"  url="464d16b024e0a7bae6b02344468dcb94.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_3"  type="Letter"  url="33558bcf81ac1a354295447038bfd041.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_4"  type="Letter"  url="c73a39c74b499ffd8f3356d2e0119543.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_5"  type="Letter"  url="3aa27a1ae5256321db61bffb4775c416.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_6"  type="Letter"  url="3d4cc0774b88db924de6b810288d9882.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2674_img_2097_7"  type="Letter"  url="15d6482e32c3400196e19f6dbf563745.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_1"/>
             Irish College<lb/>Rome   27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May 1916    My Lord Bishop   I enclose a Rescript; I<lb/>suppose it is for a mixed marriage,<lb/>about which Fr O Driscoll wrote<lb/>to me lately.  Your letter gave me great joy:<lb/>I pray that God spare you to<lb/>celebrate the Golden Jubilee of<lb/>your Episcopate, for the reply you made<lb/>to that military autocrat. I<lb/>hope he has brains enough to learn 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_2"/>
             the lesson. I am glad the<lb/>people are awakening from their<lb/>political hypnotism. But the<lb/>price paid for the lesson is awful.<lb/>Many in Ireland must have searching<lb/>of consciences for their acts and speeches<lb/>during the past two years. But for the<lb/>thoughtless talk of these, that military<lb/>man would not have dared to send you<lb/>such a letter. But they were let feel<lb/>that they might do as they <hi rend="underline">willed.</hi><lb/>Persons have gone mad on both sides<lb/>of the war. I never discuss it: but I<lb/>enjoy intensely others fighting over it<lb/>yet my neutrality has not saved me. A<lb/>few days ago I heard that Bp Dontonville,<lb/>(new General of the Oblates) — a Frenchman<lb/>or French Canadian, said to a lady<!-- right side of devided page --><lb/><lb/>What can you think, when the Rector of the<lb/>Irish College is a Fenian. Directly I<lb/>heard it I wrote to him for an explanation<lb/>&amp; for evidence of my Fenian tendencies,<lb/>and asked for an immediate answer.<lb/>He sent me; very apologetically. I wrote<lb/>back to say it was not satisfactory.<lb/>He came back personally twice to the College<lb/>to see me, &amp; explain. He found me in<lb/>the second visit. He was like a<lb/><hi rend="underline">drowned rat: and his explanation<lb/>was not very intelligent; but offered<lb/>to do whatever I told him about the<lb/>matter. I said I did not want him to<lb/>do anything more than he had done<lb/>already: that should take no more<lb/>notice of it, unless I found that he's<lb/>word was going the round, on which<lb/>happening I <seg type="del">would</seg>will have the matter</hi> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_3"/>
             laid before the Pope. That ends that<lb/>affair: It will make others take care.  I have not seen the Pope since<lb/>the troubles in Dublin. I hope to<lb/>see him in a few days. I suppose he<lb/>will ask me about it. I have in<lb/>mind what I shall say as to the<lb/>cause of it; and curious to say, the<lb/>train of thought I have had about<lb/>it is practically what Mr Birrell<lb/>had (partly at any rate) in the<lb/>statement he read before the<lb/>Commission. I am gathering<lb/>materials from the evidence before the<lb/>Commission, and from speeches by Mr<lb/>Asquith &amp; c; and I will write a<lb/>statement on the whole, which I will 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_4"/>
             distribute in the proper quarters.<lb/>I want others to have time enough<lb/>to exhaust their lying first. Then<lb/>I will come, with cold facts, based<lb/>on official testimony. If it will<lb/>do no good, it will prevent  possible  evil.  I transcribe for you a note<lb/>Cord de Lai sent me for your<lb/>last Pastoral.  [F<seg type="foreign">oreign language text.]</seg> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_5"/>
            <seg type="foreign">bene che esso sia fatto e sia<lb/>pubblicals; giacche verva<lb/>tempo in cui si dira che non tulle<lb/>erano cieche e sordi, ma c'erano<lb/>pasori in Israile che vigilavano<lb/>et ammoniconao et alzavano la<lb/>voce <hi rend="underline">in Salutern.</hi> Le prgeo di<lb/>filicitare in mio home quil Veneraundo<lb/>Trelato.Con particulao respetts<lb/> 19.Maggis 1916    <lb/>         I was asked a few days ago, if it<lb/>is true that Mr Asquith wished to<lb/>see the Pope — amongst other things —<lb/>to get the Bp of Limerick to keep<lb/>silent. The person who asked me<lb/><lb/>is one of the officials at the Vicariate.<lb/>He said he had heard it from me<lb/>at the Vatican. I told him to<lb/>tell his informant that there is no<lb/>truth in it whatever; that Mr<lb/>Asquith did not speak of such a<lb/>thing, nor of any such things to<lb/>the Pope.  It is pretty clear that the wish<lb/>has been further to the thought with<lb/>some persons, who have been trying<lb/>to make persons believe that Mr<lb/>Asquith has spoken to the Pope;<lb/>that the inference should be that<lb/>the Pope is displeased with you, &amp;<lb/>so on etc etc. And those people<lb/>are so distracted that they are<lb/>not left sense enough to see </seg>
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_6"/>
             that to be displeased with your<lb/>Pastorals would be to feel dipleasure<lb/>with himself; since you have<lb/>simply followed the line he  <lb/>for peace.   I am doubly glad now that those<lb/>writings have been translated and<lb/>distributed. For those, whose<lb/>thoughts are of any value, will<lb/>have always been made up, at<lb/>first hand, from the texts themselves,<lb/>in what you have really written.  The fools are forestalled; although<lb/>that was not my primary purpose<lb/>originally. Still the thought occurred<lb/>to me now &amp; then. The same<lb/>tribe and race whisper now as they<lb/>have been whispering always.    
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2674_img_2097_7"/>
             that to be displeased with your<lb/>Pastorals would be to feel dipleasure<lb/>with himself; since you have<lb/>simply followed the line he  <lb/>for peace.   I am doubly glad now that those<lb/>writings have been translated and<lb/>distributed. For those, whose<lb/>thoughts are of any value, will<lb/>have always been made up, at<lb/>first hand, from the texts themselves,<lb/>in what you have really written.  The fools are forestalled; although<lb/>that was not my primary purpose<lb/>originally. Still the thought occurred<lb/>to me now &amp; then. The same<lb/>tribe and race whisper now as they<lb/>have been whispering always.  distribute in the proper quarters.<lb/>I want others to have time enough<lb/>to exhaust their lying first. Then<lb/>I will come, with cold facts, based<lb/>on official testimony. If it will<lb/>do no good, it will prevent possible evil.  I transcribe for you a note<lb/>Cord de Lai sent me for your<lb/>last Pastoral.  <seg type="foreign">[Foreign language text.]</seg>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>