<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0682">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 22 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his Mother, Clara Mary Davidson. James is delighted to have received a letter from Kathleen and to learn that she is improving. They are looking forward to spending Christmas in comfortable quarters, although he notes that the plum pudding ordered from Edinburgh had not yet arrived, but since several others have they were not worried. He writes that he will not going back to England for special training. While it would have been nice to go home for a while, he would be conflicted as it would mean separation from the men with whom he has trained for so many months. He ends by writing that it has rained almost every day.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/682</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1915-12-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">S.C. Davidson </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0682_img_2174_1"  type="Letter"  url="debd0fd3e0c120e06139efe0bd42c31f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0682_img_2174_2"  type="Letter"  url="4b400c3974c583f8d14c866cbb77b363.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0682_img_2174_3"  type="Envelope"  url="6817e62c13d238b6fe7c73b7c7a9c3eb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0682_img_2174_1"/>
                22/12/15   dearest Mother   I nearly always have <lb/>to write my letters at night after <lb/>dinner &amp; tonight I am later than <lb/>usual beginning so must make a <lb/>very short one do. Was so pleased <lb/>to get a letter from Kathleen yest. <lb/>&amp; to know that she is steadily improving <lb/>though slowly. What bad luck that Douglas <lb/>cant get leave home. We are all <lb/>looking forward to spending a very <lb/>cheery Xmas. Aren't we lucky to be <lb/>in comfortable quarters! The Plum <lb/>Pudding you ordered from Edinburgh has <lb/>not arrived so far, but lots of others have, <lb/>so if it is late it wont really matter <lb/>&amp; we will enjoy it some other evening. <lb/>I was informed yest. that I would be <lb/>going back to England almost at once  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0682_img_2174_2"/>
              <lb/>for special training in the organisation <lb/> of the new machine Guns Companies, <lb/>but it now appears the order came <lb/> here by mistake &amp; the Company for this <lb/>Brigade is to be trained &amp; organised in <lb/>France instead. It would of course <lb/>have been rather nice to get home for <lb/>a little but I am really glad the order <lb/>has been cancelled as it is more than <lb/>likely had I gone, that I should have <lb/>been posted to some Company outside the <lb/>Division &amp; I did not want on any <lb/> account to be separated from the officers <lb/> &amp; men whom I have now been training <lb/> for so many months. Weather as bad <lb/>as ever - rains practically every day &amp; <lb/>one is always splashing about in mud. <lb/>The Green Canvas Kit Bag arrived all right a <lb/> few days ago. Goodnight Mother dear &amp; <lb/> my fondest love &amp; best wishes to all. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son   Jim </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0682_img_2174_3"/>
              On Active Service  <lb/>Sunday 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dec/15  Passed Censor No 2515   Mrs S.C. Davidson,  Seacourt,   Bangor,  Co Down,   Ireland    J Davidson  22/12/15   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>