<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2683">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Limerick City Regiment of the Irish Volunteers to Bishop E. T. O'Dwyer, 14 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Limerick City Regiment, Irish Volunteers</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Limerick City Regiment of the Irish Volunteers to Bishop Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer (1842-1917), who served as the Bishop of Limerick from 1888 until his death.

In this letter the Limerick Regiment expresses their admiration and gratitude for the stance taken by Bishop O’Dwyer. This stance refers to the attitude expressed by O’Dwyer in his correspondence with General John Maxwell (1859 – 1929). This includes the most renowned of the letters written to Maxwell on 17 May 1916 in which O’Dwyer  described the General as a &#39;military dictator&#39; and denounced the execution of the Easter Rising&#39;s leaders ‘in cold blood’. The Bishop also criticised the deportation of thousands of suspects without trial and declared Maxwell&#39;s regime ‘one of the worst and blackest chapters in the history of the misgovernment of this country’.

Among those who signed the letter were James Ledden (1865 – 1927), Michael Colivet (1882 – 1955) and George Clancy (1881 – 1921). All three were prominent members of the Republican movement.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Limerick Diocesan Archive</repository>
                  <collection>LDA/BI/ET/M/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2683</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0405">Limerick City Regiment, Irish Volunteers</persName>
              <date>1916-09-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1629">Limerick City Regiment, Irish Volunteers, Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1500">Edward Thomas O&#39;Dwyer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0556">Limerick, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2683_img_2105_1"  type="Letter"  url="ac4d06882301646fdfaccb71b5187902.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2683_img_2105_1"/>
              TO The Most Reverend Dr. O'Dwyer,<lb/>Lord Bishop of Limerick,    <lb/>FROM the Limerick City Regiment,<lb/>of Irish Volunteers.    May it please your Lordship,   We, the officers and men of the Limerick City<lb/>Regiment of Irish Volunteers, take this opportunity of<lb/>expressing to you our grateful appreciation of the stand<lb/>you have made during the recent trying times; a stand so<lb/>much in keeping with the long and glorious record of the<lb/>Irish Priesthood in the chequered history of our Fatherland.  In the face of a powerful political oligarchy,<lb/>and a cruel and unscrupulous military dictatorship, you<lb/>have not flinched from openly and clearly accomplishing<lb/>what you considered your duty towards priests and people;<lb/>and that at a time when those who should be the defenders<lb/>of the people either stood idly by or gave active assistance<lb/>to the oppressors.  You require no guidance from us in correctly<lb/>appraising the value of the vaporous revilings which have<lb/>come from certain quarters. For our part we feel great<lb/>pleasure and honour in tendering you this expression of our<lb/>hearty admiration and <sic>gratitudefor</sic> your patriotic actions,<lb/>but particularly for your sympathetic references to our<lb/>fallen comrades.   We beg to remain, on behalf of the<lb/>Limerick City Regiment , <lb/><lb/>Your Lordship's most obedient servants,<lb/> James Ledden, Hon Colonel.<lb/>M.P.Col o vet,Commandant.<lb/>George Clancy, Vice-Commandant.<lb/>Jas.A. McInerney, Capt. &amp; Adjutant.<lb/>Pk. Walsh, Capt. &amp; Q'r-Master<lb/>R.P.O'Connor, Secretary.   Limerick,<lb/> 14th September 1916.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>