<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0521">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major W.S. Lennon to Madge Daly, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>W.S. Lennon</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Major W.S. Lennon, commandant of the Detention Barracks, Kilmainham to Madge Daly declining to return the bodies of Edward Daly and Tom Clarke for burial. Madge Daly (1877 - 1969) was the sister of Commandent Edward Daly (1891 - 1916). Daly&#39;s battalion was stationed at the Four Courts during the Easter Rising until ordered to surrender by Pearse on 29 April. Daly was sentenced t death by court martial and was executed by firing squad on 4 May 1916.The letter also refers to the case of Tom Clarke (1858 - 1916) who was married to Daly&#39;s sister Kathleen. Clarke served in the GPO during Easter Week and was sentenced to death for his role in the Rising. He was executed on 3 May 1916 and buried at Arbour Hill prison cemetery.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Museum of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>HE, EW.149</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/521</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0710">W.S. Lennon</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1681">Kilmainham Gaol, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Madge Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0521_img_1893_1"  type="Letter"  url="e3f1155832bcfbc9997f6e2230152159.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0521_img_1893_1"/>
               Madam   Referring to your request <lb/> for the body of the late Edward <lb/> Daly, I am directed to inform you <lb/> that it is regretted that your <lb/> request cannot be granted. <seg type="closer"> W J Lennon <lb/>Army<lb/> Comm<hi rend="superscript">dt</hi></seg><seg type="postscript"> Miss Mary Daly <lb/> This applies also in the case of the <lb/> late T. J. Clarke, (request made by Mrs Clarke ) </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>