<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0932">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Roger Casement, 9 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Roger Casement</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A facsimile copy of a letter written by Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). In the first part of the letter, Casement refers to his poor physical and mental state. By this time, he had been marginalized by the planners of the Rising and his relations with the Germans were severely strained. Adding later to what he had written, Casement writes a strong critique of the situation in Europe and concludes at the end that Germany&#39;s only enemy is England and that she needs to realise this. It was shortly after this letter was written that Casement left for Ireland for the last time.Casement spent eighteen months in Germany, arriving first as an envoy of Irish-American leaders, attempting to encourage Germany to support Irish separatist aspirations by providing arms. Casement succeeded in securing limited German support but his attempt to form a brigade of Irish soldiers in German prisoner of war camps to fight against Britain was largely unsuccessful. Believing that German support was insufficient, Casement travelled to Ireland to prevent the planned rebellion but was arrested after landing in Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. He was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Mrs Erskine Childers Collection, CD 6/2/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/932</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1253">Roger Casement</persName>
              <date>1916-04-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0930">Hotel Saxonia, Berlin, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0932_img_455_1"  type="Letter"  url="e7cc8f3a85e07ba1a6d6a569071ad9c4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0932_img_455_2"  type="Letter"  url="157e2b542e8b5a339e37517bec353b92.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0932_img_455_3"  type="Letter"  url="738347017d7c425199bab29db48b4585.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0932_img_455_4"  type="Letter"  url="b96fb4c156dc99c185701f802f5612b0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0932_img_455_5"  type="Letter"  url="12e257fc6be1e030b73e960589c1162c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0932_img_455_6"  type="Letter"  url="a4b780275d78160484d81b82874cecb9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0932_img_455_1"/>
              Delayed at last<lb/><hi rend="underline">moment</hi><lb/>    Hotel Saxonia,  <seg type="unclear">Inkaber</seg>  <seg type="unclear">Neve Berliner Hotel- Goselllschaft m.b.H.</seg>  Berlin W 9, Budapesterstr. 10  <seg type="unclear">Am Putsdamerplatz — aske Tiergerten</seg>  <seg type="unclear">Foresprecer Ast Lutrow 2838 und 2871</seg>     Berlin W,  9 den —    9.4.16    It is so hard to see straight. <lb/>Even when one is well &amp; not <lb/> troubled - &amp;&amp; I am not well in <lb/> body &amp;&amp; have not been for long <lb/> &amp; then greatly troubled too <lb/> in mind — so that my remarks <lb/> are often unjust &amp; hasty <lb/> &amp; ill considered.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0932_img_455_2"/>
              The last days are all a nightmare <lb/>— I have only a confused memory <lb/>of them &amp; some periods are quite <lb/><seg type="unclear">blank</seg> in my mind — only a sense <lb/>of horror and repugnance to <lb/>life. But I daresay clouds will <lb/>break &amp; brighter skies dawn — at <lb/>least for poor old Ireland. <seg type="closer"> Kindest thoughts for you ......... Yours,   RC. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0932_img_455_3"/>
              .......................  She may win a Hundred <lb/>Austerlitzes (as I said <hi rend="underline">four</hi><lb/>years ago in my first song <lb/>on the 'freedom of the Seas') &amp; <lb/>yet be beaten in the end. <lb/>That is the terrible factor <lb/>— the power of the sea — that in the <lb/>hands of one people means the <lb/>dominion of the World.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0932_img_455_4"/>
              The 'crime against Europe' is <lb/>an inadequate title, it is <lb/>the Crime against Humanity, the <lb/>World, Nature — this awful <lb/>power in the hands of one <lb/>irresponsible, arbitrary, <lb/><seg type="unclear">tirading</seg>, greedy people — <lb/>the power to shut all the <lb/>oceans, all the coasts &amp; <lb/>to starve whole Continents into <lb/>submission by holding up <lb/>all the ordinary methods of <lb/>subsistence, intercourse &amp; civilized <lb/>contact  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0932_img_455_5"/>
              England need never send a <lb/>single man on the Continent <lb/>&amp; yet in the end she will <lb/>dictate the terms of peace. <lb/>The only hope I had was that <lb/>the submarines might 'break <lb/>through' — but that hope has <lb/>long since gone &amp; I don't see how <lb/>any victories on land <hi rend="underline">in Europe</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">will</hi> change the situation.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0932_img_455_6"/>
              Germany has only <hi rend="underline">one</hi><lb/>Enemy. England. Until <lb/>they realise that in their souls <lb/>&amp; every fibre of their being they <lb/>can only hit the air.  If I don't hear by <seg type="unclear">Wednesday</seg><lb/>I shall go to Dresden for that <lb/>night, &amp; on to Munich next <lb/>day. Please God I'll spend Xmas <lb/>Eve with you &amp; Christmas Day at <lb/><seg type="unclear">Gauting</seg>. <seg type="closer"> My love to the children and with <lb/>.........................   Roger Casement. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>