<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0182">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Abdur Razzaq to the General Secretary's Office, 19 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Abdur Razzaq</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Abdur Razzaq to the General Secretary&#39;s Office. The letter regards a resolution passed in a meeting of Indian students in Dublin on 17 April 1916 requesting that an enclosure is passed on to Lord Wimborne, Ivor Guest (1873-1939), the lord lieutenant of Ireland. The enclosure itself is a copy of a resolution made at the meeting to extend gratitude to Wimborne for his sympathy with the students, who were targeted in the &#39;Eye Opener&#39; newspaper, which referred to them as the &#39;black peril.&#39;Abdur Razzaq was an Indian student studying Law at the King&#39;s Inns in Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9070</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/182</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1513">Abdur Razzaq</persName>
              <date>1916-04-19</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0182_img_1319_1"  type="Letter"  url="9f4a7ac49d2a440f67f8b595b3066ac3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0182_img_1319_2"  type="Letter"  url="9e8d9d79940ac503450f55a4ec3bda4c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0182_img_1319_1"/>
                KINGS INNS,  DUBLIN    19, April 16   Dear Sir,   I have the honour to <lb/> forward herewith a copy of <lb/>the resolution passed in a <lb/>public meeting of the Indian <lb/> Students, with the request <lb/> that you will very kindly lay <lb/> it before H. E. The Lord <lb/><sic>Leiutenant</sic>.   Thanking you in anticipation <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/> Yours truly   Abdur Razzaq. <lb/>President of the meeting  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0182_img_1319_2"/>
              Received from P.S. Vice Regal Lodge. <lb/> Put with papers MN 21/4   H. W. 3.4.17  <hi rend="underline">'Copy of the Resolution'</hi>  'We the Indian students resident <lb/> in Dublin, assembled in this public <lb/>meeting, held at the College Hotel <lb/> on the 17 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of April 1916, beg to place <lb/>on record our heartfelt gratitude <lb/>to H. E. the Lord <sic>Leiutenant</sic> of <lb/> Ireland for his so kindly expressing <lb/> his sympathy with the Indian <lb/> students and for the action he <lb/> has so graciously taken in warning <lb/> the owners, Publishers &amp; printers <lb/> of the Eye — Opener and thus pro— <lb/>tecting the Indians from the <lb/> scurrilous attacks.'   Proposed by Mr. B. Agusti <lb/> Seconded by Mr. <seg type="unclear">J. N. Mahon</seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>