<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1356">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Anna O'Rahilly to Mabel FitzGerald, 25 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Anna O&#39;Rahilly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Anna O&#39;Rahilly (d. 1958) to Mabel Fitzgerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947). The letter refers to a bicycle borrowed by FitzGerald to get to the GPO on the first day of the Rising. Anna enquires about its possible whereabouts on behalf of O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s wife. A note dated March 1992 explains what happened to the bicycle.Anna O&#39;Rahilly was a sister of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly (&#39;The O&#39;Rahilly&#39;) (1875–1916). Both O&#39;Rahilly and FitzGerald had been supportive of attempts to stop the Rising taking place but joined in once it has started. O&#39;Rahilly was killed in Moore Lane on Thursday of Easter week. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1584/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1356</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0639">Anna O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0765">84 Northumberland Road, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1356_img_707_1"  type="Letter"  url="33df56d611412f92ee8bbf832f03133f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1356_img_707_2"  type="Letter"  url="a4efded4662a2401156a474f5eebc60a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1356_img_707_1"/>
                54 Northumberland Road Dublin.    May 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   Dear Mrs Fitzgerald   My sister in law asked me <lb/> to write to you about the bicycle <lb/> that Mr Fitzgerald took that fatal <lb/> morning to go to the post office <lb/> Perhaps by chance Mr Fitzgerald <lb/> did not bring it to there - you <lb/> said something about meeting <lb/> him &amp; that you walked together <lb/> to the office - Could he possibly <lb/> have left the bicycle in some other <lb/> place where it might be now safe  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1356_img_707_2"/>
              Mac lost his cycle since so <lb/> they are badly off for one <lb/> now. <seg type="closer"> With kind regards I am Yours <sic>vy</sic> sincerely  Anna O'Rahilly. </seg> Added in 1992 <seg type="postscript"> The tyre had burst in Mill Town while <lb/> Desmond was on his way to Rathfarnham <lb/> to tell MacNeill that the Rising was <lb/> on and Desmond had abandoned it there. <lb/>Garrett Fitzgerald <lb/>20/3/92 </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>