<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5512">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mary MacDonagh, Sister Francesca, to her brother Jim MacDonagh upon the death of their brother Thomas MacDonagh, 9 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mary MacDonagh, Sister Francesca</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter discusses family life following the death of Thomas MacDonagh. The letter deals with personal matters and with  issues of finance (pensions, the sale of his Thomas MacDonagh&#39;s books, inheritance for the children, concerns about payments from the USA), new housing arrangements for Muriel MacDonagh (wife), thanks to the Plunketts. The letter expresses concern for her brother, Jim, and his family.  It urges secrecy for the correspondence between them. The letters are enclosed with three poems on Irish independence.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NLI MS 44,322 /5. Collection List 131</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5512</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0637">Mary MacDonagh, Sister Francesca</persName>
              <date>1916-09-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Jim MacDonagh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_1"  type="Letter"  url="2ca1eeb6fa6b366b33cde43d7a2696c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_2"  type="Letter"  url="0803051279043054513f3d6fa8ee85ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_3"  type="Letter"  url="e3e71cf07e0b5fa316d9ad60ef16d86f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_4"  type="Letter"  url="56aa3710ce99fe4732b14badfcaf82fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_5"  type="Letter"  url="c969a86e3e835bd1b994a02d3b953ebc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_6"  type="Letter"  url="0328760acd64d9b02bd2be5e0eff6e09.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_7"  type="Letter"  url="ad00f23cf99363c00885492038c182f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_8"  type="Letter"  url="0893df64350484cfdd9056cc9bd804f1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_9"  type="Letter"  url="ec4dce33e82ecf51b459aeff22bf8648.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_10"  type="Letter"  url="3525082d9ec5c8418ed424d356fdf768.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_11"  type="Letter"  url="7ceb73afe17523cbe9d3840b295004a2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_12"  type="Letter"  url="c5f76ca9cc21e041b9d9bdbd9cb44040.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_13"  type="Letter"  url="7fd2b3a4f55c4d6b7eadfae05beba024.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_14"  type="Letter"  url="5d81d1c8fbab7a9e7927ff26c8e18b3b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5512_img_61_15"  type="Letter"  url="f1d5ee1d1c5267d0ac4cece8864f0c0a.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_1"/>
             Poor Jim kept this<lb/>letter I wrote him<lb/>re Tomas death in<lb/>1916, all the years<lb/>till his own death<lb/>1926. Fintan got it<lb/>among his papers<lb/>&amp; <hi rend="underline">brought it</hi>to me 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_2"/>
             I enclose 3 poems considered masterpieces. Dont let them<lb/> out of <sic>yr</sic><hi rend="underline">keeping </hi> <seg type="unclear">.L.</seg> <hi rend="underline">5.9.16</hi>   Dearest Jim   I have been waiting <lb/>ages to find a person <lb/>to take you enclosed by <lb/>hand to you. viz. poor <lb/>Tom's letter, &amp; this, Treasure <lb/>forever. God knows <lb/>his hearts blood appears <lb/>in it. Poor fellow. I cant <lb/>yet realize the awful <lb/>tragedy that has taken <lb/>him from us for <lb/>ever. His last book is <lb/>nearly ready, &amp; in the
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_3"/>
            preface. It is said, "They all <lb/>died bravely, but MacD died like a prince" <lb/>Well may we be proud <lb/>of him, &amp; his name <lb/>will ring down the centuries <lb/>as a hero. His <lb/>name is revered &amp; <lb/>hallowed in Ireland <lb/>as Emmets. As usual <lb/>he never thought of<lb/> himself. Always of<lb/> others, &amp; even in that <lb/>awful last interview <lb/>he was calm buoyant <lb/>&amp; utterly unselfish.Now Muriel's future will be <lb/>I think secured, &amp; the <sic>ch<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi></sic><lb/>education will be seen <lb/>to. She is still looking <lb/>for a house. &amp; now one <lb/>of the Plunketts will <lb/>get her one on nice road.<lb/>I only hope she will take <lb/>it &amp; settle in at once <lb/>Jack is to get £100 per an <lb/>but I am sure Martyn <lb/>will increase it later. <lb/>It is very rushed just <lb/>now. &amp; I'm certain he<lb/> will always get on.<lb/>Now for more news <lb/>Poor Joe has got his confé
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_4"/>
            thus, orders to go to Pudsey in <lb/>York, minus £57 a year. He <lb/>sent a protest saying he <lb/>c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> not possibly live in <lb/>such a hostile atmosphere <lb/>that such a change was <lb/>never made of a man <lb/>in his position, especially <lb/>one that never was accused <lb/>of a fault during his <lb/>9 1/2 years service, that he <lb/>well knew the real reason <lb/>of the transfer, viz. being <lb/>brother of Toms, that he <lb/>means to get questions <lb/>asked on subject in <lb/>parliament, &amp;c. Of course <lb/>they won't cave in. We <lb/>all know what England
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_5"/>
            <lb/>stands for. You sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> see how <lb/>people are treated here <lb/>murdered, robbed <lb/>chased, persecuted &amp; <lb/>afflicted in every way.<lb/>Was the Skeffington <lb/>Inquiry held in Dublin <lb/>published in English <lb/>papers, it was horrifying <lb/>but only on a par with <lb/>the treatment meted <lb/>out to the unfortunate <lb/>Irish, but its good <lb/>enough for us. &amp; <lb/>sufficient thanks for <lb/>the Irishmen who have
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_6"/>
            to you <seg type="del">I ho</seg>  I have just heard that they have not been able to <lb/>reach you. Perhaps it is better so. Yet Father <lb/>Aloysius is going to make another effort to <lb/>do something. God help and sustain you, <lb/>my love. But for your suffering, this <lb/>would be all joy and glory. Good bye.  Your loving husband <lb/> Thomas MacDonagh   I return the darlings' photographs. <lb/>Good bye, my love. 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_7"/>
            <hi rend="underline">In Memory</hi> <lb/>They were hungry they were thirsty<lb/> as they waited <hi rend="underline">there</hi> to die <lb/>Bare was the bitter prison ground <lb/>where they were forced to lie <lb/>We'll remember, we'll remember <lb/>Thank the God that we adore <lb/>Having drunk the cup of <lb/>Martyrdom, our heroes thirst no more <lb/>No longer, do they hunger, for above <lb/>the Feast is spread <lb/>And the rest is sweet in heaven <lb/>of our holy martyred dead <lb/>Tyrants hate can hurt no longer, <lb/> they are safe with God - &amp; yet, <lb/>We'll keep their sufferings in<lb/>our hearts, &amp; we shall <lb/><hi rend="underline">not forget</hi> <lb/>Uplifted on the winds of heaven <lb/>their souls are free at last <lb/>Though scornfully their noble forms
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_8"/>
            in prison clay were cast. <lb/>We'll remember, we'll remember, <lb/>hate for hate we backward fling <lb/>Building in our faithful hearts <lb/>for them, the Cairus of a King <lb/>We shall lace them with the <lb/>highest in the annals of our land <lb/>Through the thunder of the centuries <lb/>their memory shall stand <lb/>And we know no scorn can <lb/>hurt them, wheresoe'er <lb/>they lie — &amp; yet <lb/>We'll keep their graves within <lb/>our heart, &amp; we shall <lb/><hi rend="underline">not forget.</hi> <lb/>Weep not for them with useless tears <lb/>but think of them with pride <lb/>For gallantly they fought the fight <lb/>&amp; nobly brave they died <lb/>We'll remember, we'll remember<lb/> their wounds, their blood, their <lb/>pain Tho' we know no pang was <lb/>wasted, nor one drop was <lb/>shed in vain <lb/>For our Nation has awakened <lb/>we have heard the <lb/>trumpet blast <lb/>The dreams of slaves are <lb/>shattered &amp; we shall be <lb/>free at last. <lb/> Lo! the Dead arise triumphant <lb/> &amp; the Living's task is set <lb/>The Cause is burning in our <lb/>hearts, &amp; <hi rend="underline">we shall not forget</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Sigerson</hi>  <hi rend="underline">Salutation</hi>by AE. Geo Russell <lb/>Your dreams had left me numb <lb/>&amp; cold <lb/>But yet my spirit rose in Pride <lb/>Refashioning in burnished gold <lb/>The images of those who died <lb/> Or were shut in the Penal cell
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_9"/>
            Here's to you Pearse! your dreams. Not <lb/>mine <lb/>but yet the thought for <hi rend="underline">this</hi>, you fell <lb/>Turns life's <hi rend="underline">water</hi> into wine <lb/>I listened to much talk from you <lb/>Thomas MacDonagh, &amp; it seemed <lb/>The words were idle but they grew <lb/>To nobleness, by death redeemed <lb/>Life cannot utter words more <lb/>great <lb/>Than life can meet with sacrifice <lb/>High words were equalled by high <lb/> fate <lb/><hi rend="underline">You</hi> paid the <hi rend="underline">price</hi>, You paid the <lb/><hi rend="underline">price</hi> <lb/> The hope lives on, age after age <lb/>Earth with its beauty might be won <lb/>For labour as a heritage <lb/>For this, has Ireland lost a son <lb/>This hope into a flame to fan. <lb/>Men have put life by, with a smile <lb/>Here's to you Plunkett, noble man <lb/>Who cast thy torch upon the pile.<lb/>Here's to the <hi rend="underline">women</hi> of <hi rend="underline">our</hi> blood <lb/>Stood by them, in their fiery hour <lb/>Rapt, lest some weakness in their mood <lb/>Rob manhood of a single power <lb/>You, brave as such a hope forlorn <lb/>Who smiled thro' crack of shot &amp; shell<lb/> Tho' the world look on you with scorn <lb/>Here's to you, brave ones, in the Cell
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_10"/>
             Heres to you, men I never met<lb/>But hope to meet, beyond the Veil<lb/>Thronged on some starry parapet<lb/>That looks down upon Innisfail<lb/>And see the confluence of dreams<lb/>That clashed together in our night<lb/>One river, born of many streams<lb/>Roll in one blaze of blinding<lb/>light  <lb/><hi rend="underline">Dublin 1916 By A Newman<lb/><hi rend="underline">Priv. I Volunteer</hi><lb/>You poured your spies upon her street<lb/>You ringed her round with steel<lb/>For four most hideous centuries<lb/>She lay beneath your heel;<lb/>You dug your forces round her gates<lb/>You built your barracks well<lb/>And in your castled heart devised<lb/>Foul deeds — too foul for hell<lb/><hi rend="underline"></hi></hi>  <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">2</hi><lb/>And there you planned the Epitaph<lb/>Of Ireland day by day</hi> 
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_11"/>
            And watched our people fade &amp; die <lb/>our language pass away <lb/>All undisturbed &amp; all secure <lb/>You sat for centuries <lb/>And boasted of our loyalty <lb/> And fed the world with lies <lb/> — <lb/>But Dublin tore from off her face <lb/>The horrid mask she wore <lb/>And all the Nation's saw again <lb/>Her beauty as of yore <lb/> She hurled you from your Tyrant <lb/>seat <lb/>And clothed in flame &amp; lead <lb/>She stood a capital unslaved <lb/>And risen from the Dead.<lb/>— <lb/>And tho' a few sad days shall pass <lb/>Till she is wholly free <lb/>And tho' you chain her once again <lb/>God holds her destiny. <lb/>For he shall smite you to the earth <lb/>And raise Her to a Throne <lb/>And for her ages of despair <lb/>That triumph shall atone
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_12"/>
            England is now trying to <lb/>engineer another famine <lb/> as she did before in <lb/>1847. She can't kill the <lb/>Irish quickly enough <lb/>so she subtly starves <lb/>them, commandeering <lb/>all she has. Get the <lb/><sic>ch<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></sic> to pray for us <lb/> all. I can't yet believe <lb/>G has escaped. They <lb/>meant to do for him too  Love to you all <lb/><hi rend="underline">Adieu</hi> <hi rend="underline"></hi>   Just write saying! <lb/>Your friend gave me <lb/> your message viz these letters <lb/>&amp; I shall understand your <seg type="unclear">with</seg> these letters <lb/> &amp; I shall understand your <lb/><sic>rec<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></sic> them. Do let me know how <lb/>G is getting on. What's he doing and where <lb/>living.  After all. Keep this letter &amp;<lb/>hand it down to <sic>yr</sic> children <lb/> With <lb/>love <lb/><hi rend="underline">Mary</hi>  
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_13"/>
            Goodbye now. Morn noon <lb/> &amp; night I grieve &amp; <lb/>ever shall, for as well <lb/>as being my brother<lb/> he was my dearest <lb/>friend with whom I <lb/>c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> discuss everything <lb/>&amp; who <hi rend="underline">never</hi> failed <lb/>me. I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> God has <lb/>him in Heaven &amp; <lb/>I forgive as he forgave <lb/> those who slew him <lb/>If I c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> only explain <lb/>to you the ins &amp; outs <lb/>of what led up to this <lb/>&amp; what is still taking <lb/>place you c<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> understand
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_14"/>
            Bitter our Chalice yet it <lb/>is sweet — <lb/>If we but to the Saviour <lb/>turn, <lb/>And Sigh submissive <lb/>at his feet —- <lb/> My God Thy Holy Will <lb/> be done, — <lb/>What calmness brings <lb/>this hallowed prayer, <lb/>First breath'd by the Eternal Son <lb/> What strength our heaviest <lb/> Cross to bear, <lb/> "My God, Thy Heavenly <lb/>Will be done".<lb/> — <lb/>But if our necks, we <lb/>humbly bend, <lb/>Though sorrow force the <lb/>anguished groan
            <pb n="15" facs="L1916_5512_img_61_15"/>
            What incense to the <lb/>Throne we send. <lb/>By these sweet words — <lb/>"Thy Will be done" <lb/> — <lb/>Lines written by Arthur <lb/>Lynch who died at the <lb/>age of <hi rend="underline">eighteen.</hi>   Excuse writing written <lb/> for yourself this morning,   This was sent to me <lb/>by a dear old nun <lb/>with letter of sympathy. <lb/> Her brother who died at 18 <lb/>wrote it years ago 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>