<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3315">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sean MacDiarmada to John Daly, 8 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Seán Mac Diarmada</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter written prior to Seán&#39;s own execution, also mentioning that John Daly, too, had been condemned to die and was awaiting his death.

John Daly was an Irish revolutionary and involved in the Irish Republican Brotherhood. He participated in the 1916 Rising and was executed alonside his brother Ned Daly.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Cork Public Museum</repository>
                  <collection>T. Mac Curtain Collection, 1971.15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3315</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1090">Seán Mac Diarmada</persName>
              <date>1916-05-08</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1681">Kilmainham Gaol, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1249">Kilmainham Prison, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">Last Letters before Death</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Last Letters before Death</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3315_img_2729_1"  type="Letter"  url="58e1a645ffda0d2b65793d701fd925a3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3315_img_2729_1"/>
             Facsimile of Last Latter <lb/>written by <lb/>Seán MacDiarmada   Kilmainham Prison <lb/>Dublin  <lb/> May 11th 1916   My Dear Daly   Just a wee note to bid you Goodbye. <lb/>I expect in a few hours to join Tom and the other <lb/>heroes in a better world. I have been sentenced to <lb/>a soldiers death — to be shot tomorrow morning. <lb/>I have nothing to say about this only that I look <lb/>on it as a part of the day's work. We die <lb/>that the Irish nation may live, our blood will <lb/>re baptise and reinvigorate the old land. Knowing <lb/>this it is superfluous to say how happy I feel. I <lb/>know now what I have always felt, that the Irish <lb/>nation can never die. Let present day place hunters <lb/>condemn our action as they will, posterity will judge <lb/>us aright from the effects of our action.   I know I will meet you soon, until then <lb/><sic>Good Bye</sic>. God guard and protect you and all in <lb/>No.15. You have had a sore trial but I know <lb/>quite well that M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Daly and all the girls <lb/>feel proud in spite of a little temporary and <lb/>natural grief that her son &amp; the girls, their brother <lb/>as will  inclusion in the list of honours. <lb/>Kindly remember me specially to M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Clarke and <lb/>tell her I am the same Seán that she always <lb/>knew.   God Bless you all <lb/>As ever <lb/>Sincerely Yours <lb/>Seán MacDiarmada. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>