<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0417">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Edward O'Farrell to Sir Reginald H Brade, War Office, 12 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell (1857-1926), assistant under-secretary for Ireland, to Sir Reginald H Brade (1864-1933), the secretary at the War Office in London. This letter is issued on the instructions of the lords justices of Ireland and includes a copy of a report, to be presented to the Army Council, concerning thr prosecution of Elizabeth Morgan for fraudulently claiming Army Separation Allowance and asks the Secretary, War Office, to ascertain how the Army Council wishes to proceed.Edward O&#39;Farrell served as the assistant undersecretary of Ireland after the Easter Rising. Sir Reginald H Brade was the secretary of the War Office throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/18363</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/417</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1915-11-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Reginald H Brade</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0417_img_1712_1"  type="Letter"  url="639d3de439626f4faedca6e31b569957.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0417_img_1712_1"/>
                12th November, 1915.   No.18367.  Sir,   I am directed by the Lords Justices to <lb/> transmit, to be laid before the Army Council, <lb/>the attached copy of a report which has been <lb/>received from Mr. Moorhead, Crown Solicitor, <lb/>Belfast, in connection with the prosecution <lb/>of one Elizabeth Morgan for fraudulently ob- <lb/>taining Army Separation Allowance, and to re- <lb/>quest that you will move Army Council to <lb/> be good enough to  state what they wish to be done in the matter. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  E O'Farrell   The Secretary,  War Office,  London.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>