<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4250">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 2 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/87</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4250</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4250_img_3617_1"  type="Letter"  url="fbfdbf0d024f0ebc5a78c7b051365db4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4250_img_3617_2"  type="Letter"  url="dd150fd4961e283a9d2152dc225d912a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4250_img_3617_3"  type="Letter"  url="1228f5e4c0ba87cf081df349f5c36bc6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4250_img_3617_4"  type="Letter"  url="440f418faf3258a3e2326ae78ef827f2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4250_img_3617_1"/>
             2 Dec   My P.R.   What with no letters, an unpleasant day &amp; unsatisfactory work, the b w is a distinctly home- <lb/>sick animal. There is again some trouble with the <lb/> mails, it is reported that the steamers did not <lb/>cross yesterday, &amp; there have been rumours of a <lb/> railway accident in France. In any case your <lb/> Sunday letter arrived yesterday Wednesday midday <lb/> whilst Monday's papers arrived Tuesday night.    The mail service seems quite disorganised &amp; <lb/> you had better repeat any very important news.   Many other rumours are in the air. The corps
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4250_img_3617_2"/>
            to which we belong is expected to move shortly <lb/> but it seems likely that we shall then be again <lb/> transferred to a new corps which may be raised <lb/> here so that perhaps we may not have to move.   I get a very growly w when I get no letters <lb/> &amp; am inclined to snap, but when I say <lb/> Goodnight to 2 ladies every night I say to my- <lb/>self a letter has been written &amp; will turn up <lb/> later with luck. Wouldn't you like to know <lb/> the 2 ladies are ?   R has decided not to go in for the course. <lb/> He is I think making a serious mistake &amp; I <lb/> have told him so, but I am not sorry from <lb/>a purely personal point of view of course. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4250_img_3617_3"/>
             I shall get into trouble if I don't write <lb/> a general letter so no more.   I don't know where to send this!    Your &amp; the 2 ladies'     bw.   <sic>Notime </sic> to write other letter have <lb/> to go on long motor trip 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4250_img_3617_4"/>
             2 Dec 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>