<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5214">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cornelius Daly to Liam Daly, 15 June 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cornelius Daly </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/8/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5214</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1388">Cornelius Daly </persName>
              <date>1923-06-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0375">Liam Daly </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1937</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5214_img_None_1"  url="d4fe15ee48b4bd1d705ffd8fbb48351f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5214_img_None_2"  url="f00e0b8877fb262b521e6eab5989db1c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5214_img_0_1"/>
              Knockane    june 15th 1923    Dear Willie   I am writing to you at last<lb/>your letter came yesterday, I was glad to<lb/>see by it that you got over the flue all<lb/>right, there was a letter from Tom yesterday<lb/>he is good too Thank God, There was so<lb/>much peace talk going here for the<lb/>past fortnight that we thought yea would<lb/>be home in no time, Willie It would be<lb/>great consolation to us if yea were safe<lb/>home to us after what happened to<lb/>Poor Dear Charlie. Now Willie I know<lb/>that yea must be in a terrible state<lb/>of mind when yea got the awful news<lb/>when like ourselves yea thought there<lb/>was no fear of Him, if yea were at<lb/>home with us yea would not feel it<lb/>near so much but when you are among<lb/>strangers you have to smother it to<lb/>yourself, Well Willie Poor Charlie is in<lb/>Heaven for he died Holy and a Noble<lb/>and Heroic death a Martyr for Faith<lb/>and Fatherland. Oh what a Noble Title   had a letter today from your uncle Thade, his daughter a nun<lb/>both wish to be remembered to you, sympathise with you a<lb/>letter from Katty yesterday<lb/>she is to write to you<lb/>a lovely letter from Mr Arthur<lb/>today Dan is with him        
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5214_img_0_2"/>
             your Mother is sending you on a half<lb/>pound of tobaca today, Tom said that<lb/>Dan Mulvihill &amp; Con Leary were<lb/>removed to some internment camp<lb/>he dont know where to. himself<lb/>was moved into A wing he is with<lb/>Austin &amp; Cooney &amp; the Tralee lads<lb/>Dave Connors Father was buried this<lb/>week I think he had the largest<lb/>funeral I was ever in of course the sym-<lb/>pathy shown the family on account<lb/>of his sons brought a big crowd<lb/>Now Willie you might like me to say<lb/>a word for myself the health is good<lb/>except this Old trouble in my head<lb/>of course Poor Charlie's death was a terrible<lb/>shock to me - so unexpected too - if he<lb/>was Killed in a fight it would not be<lb/>so bitter  to bear, however he was finely<lb/>prepared to meet his God, Well Willie<lb/>I was very much pleased with your<lb/>affectionate enqiries about me in<lb/>your letters all our Friends  are  well &amp; thank<lb/>God, Good Bye Now I hope you will be soon home<lb/> Your Affectionate Father <lb/>PS your Mother is enclosing cards<lb/>all she has<lb/><lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>