<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0981">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter From Varahagiri Venkata Giri to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 22 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Varahagiri Venkata Giri</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from V. V. Giri (1894 - 1980) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877 - 1946). The writer returns tickets that the sender was not able to sell and encloses a donation to the Irish Citizen fund.V. V. Giri was the fourth president of the Republic of India (1969 - 1974). In 1916 Giri was studying law in University College Dublin and studied English there under Thomas MacDonagh (1878 - 1916). Due to close association with some of the Easter insurgents, and a fear of an Irish born Indian conspiracy, Giri was served with a notice of expulsion form the United Kingdon in June 1916. Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47;, MS 33,604/16-7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/981</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0858">Varahagiri Venkata Giri</persName>
              <date>1916-02-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1804">13 Lower Pembroke St., Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0981_img_2827_1"  type="Letter"  url="6e7c49007a786bfc8dd3e73ae4ed4a1e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0981_img_2827_1"/>
              1916    13 Lr. Pembroke St  Dublin    22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Feb 16   Dear Mrs Skeffington,   I am sorry I was not <lb/>able to dispose of the tickets <lb/>you have so kindly sent me <lb/>as <seg type="del">all</seg> many  the Indian friends have <lb/>gone either to London or some <lb/>other places owing to Vacation.  I am sending herein enclosed <lb/>a postal order for 3&amp;L /2&amp;L <lb/>from myself 1/&amp;L from Mr P.A. <lb/>Gupta as a donation towards <lb/>Irish Citizen fund.  Hoping to be excused for my <lb/>inability to dispose of your tickets <seg type="closer"> Yours <lb/>sincerely   V. V. <hi rend="underline">Giri</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>