<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4336">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Archibald Salvidge to Edward Carson, 30 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Archibald Salvidge</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Archibald Tutton James Salvidge (1863-1928) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Salvidge was an English conservative polician and supporter of the Orange Order.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4336</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1373">Archibald Salvidge</persName>
              <date>1916-06-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1928</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4336_img_3695_1"  type="Letter"  url="21bc9dfbc9d6c5cc0f074afe89c963e0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4336_img_3695_2"  type="Letter"  url="9f443ec1b826ef2953c222e2747a1cf7.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4336_img_3695_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   Conservative Club Liverpool   30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> June '16   My dear Sir Edward   I was in the <lb/>lobby of the House last Tuesday <lb/>and was surprised to hear the views <lb/>expressed by many members of <lb/>Parliament re settlement of Irish <lb/>question. I very plainly indicated <lb/>my disapproval of their attitude. <lb/>Nowhere outside Belfast are the <lb/>people more keen and earnest upon <lb/>this question than in Liverpool.   The line I have taken and will <lb/>continue to take is that if Bonar <lb/>Law and yourself have agreed as to <lb/>the settlement that there is nothing <lb/>more to be said.   I thought I would drop you a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4336_img_3695_2"/>
            line to assure you of my absolute <lb/>faith that you would not be a <lb/>party to any settlement but what <lb/>was in the best interests of the nation.   Yours sincerely   Archibald Salvidge 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>