<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1406">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell to Sir Charles Edward Troup, 4 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Sir Edward O&#39;Farrell (c.1857-1926), the Assistant Under Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Guest Churchill, Lord Wimborne. The letter was addressed to Sir Charles Edward Troup (1857-1941). Troup was a civil servant, becoming permanent under-secretary of state at the Home Office from 1908 until 1922. He took special interest in police and criminal work while employed in the Home office.The letter states the O&#39;Farrell is sending Troup a letter from the Bishop of Meath supporting the application of Gustav Adolf Etter, a prisoner of war, for release from internment.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3906</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1406</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-03-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">(Charles) Edward Troup</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2116">Home Office, Whitehall, London S.W., United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1406_img_804_1"  type="Letter"  url="2cdab4525a85df6665386a5555b5b1f3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1406_img_804_1"/>
                4th March,1916.   No.3906  Sir,   In continuation of my letter of the 8th <lb/>ultimo, No. 2265, I am directed by the Lords <lb/>Justices to transmit, to be laid before the <lb/>Secretary of State, the attached further letter <lb/>from the Bishop of Meath in support of the <lb/>application of Gustav Adolf Etter for release <lb/>from internment.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   E O Farrell   The Under Secretary,Secretary of State,  Home Office,  London. S.W.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>