<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4248">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, circa November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.

Sir Ian Hamilton was the British commander of the ill-fated Gallipoli campaign. During the Easter Rising, Hamilton was originally intended to serve as military governor of Ireland. However, his handling of the Gallipoli campaign, and the large number of Irish losses incurred during the campaign, convinced British command to dispatch Sir John Maxwell in his stead. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/85</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4248</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4248_img_3615_1"  type="Letter"  url="a328722c0c29c56f4d70166a51bb4a7a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4248_img_3615_2"  type="Letter"  url="b65a610222fcffcf607df113685c6377.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4248_img_3615_3"  type="Letter"  url="8f9be9e791f432f40ff6dfa2c31cf785.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4248_img_3615_1"/>
             want to do <lb/> so. <lb/> Ever <hi rend="underline">your</hi> <lb/> loving BW   My dear little PR   a very growly <lb/> animal last night when he <lb/> found Richardson with 2 <lb/> letters  from one address,  <seg type="del">&amp; thomas</seg>whilst poor <lb/> Singleton had none. I said <lb/> that if this happened next day <lb/> I would write to Mrs Single- <lb/>ton for him. He was glad <lb/> of my suggestion &amp; said that
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4248_img_3615_2"/>
            if the occasion ever offered itself <lb/> (but of course I knew it wouldn't) <lb/> He would do the same for <lb/> me.   I have been made a kind <lb/> of consolatory friend by Mey- <lb/> nil &amp; find it a very trying <lb/> position. I am really sorry <lb/> for him but have said all <lb/> <seg type="del">my</seg>I could &amp; now he <lb/> asks me to sit next to him <lb/> at meals, &amp; wishes to sit in <lb/> my office &amp; talk about it, <lb/> &amp; this is a little difficult, es- <lb/>pecially as the Gen' does not <lb/> make any attempt to change his <lb/> attitude to him, &amp; looks fiercely at <lb/> us both in consequence!  However I'll do my <lb/> best for him.     Yesterday he asked me whether <lb/> he would be well to apply for GSO, <lb/> (as apparently he had heard that <lb/> there was a question of my stopping!) <lb/> We manoeuvered about &amp; I played <lb/> the silly rabbit quite successfully, I hope. <lb/> Could I have done so 2 years ago?     The glass fastener is acting <lb/> much better now. It only required a
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4248_img_3615_3"/>
            llitle firm handling to recover <lb/> from its bad habits!    The news is not cheerful <lb/> but I am much more afraid <lb/> of being rushed into another adven- <lb/>ture than of going quietly on.    I hear Ian Hamilton is <lb/> seldom in sight of the Dardanelles <lb/>&amp; is exceedingly unpopular out there <lb/> I suppose this means that he has <lb/> been found out &amp; hope it may <lb/> be the case with other rotters <lb/> in high places, wherever they <lb/> may be. We want men with <lb/> high ideals as John Gough wrote to <lb/> me. I wish one could always <lb/> live up to it, but it is something to
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>