<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0731">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Flossie Briggs to George Hackney, 28 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Flossie Briggs</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Flossie Briggs to George Hackney (1889-1977).In this letter, Flossie gives details of her upcoming trip from Leeds, Yorkshire to Sheffield, Derbyshire, and thence to the town of Hope nearby. She plans to call in to George at the hospital in Sheffield on her way. Her excitement at the prospect of the visit is very clear.This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney , a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6-2-5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/731</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0576">Flossie Briggs</persName>
              <date>1916-09-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0547">105 Brudenell Road, Leeds, Yorkshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1546">31 Ward, 'D' Block, Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0731_img_2237_1"  type="Letter"  url="cf09ff2ef6069c7be5fe4bd779ba9304.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0731_img_2237_2"  type="Letter"  url="36ac786c178e5ffc7e9a29948f46a93e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0731_img_2237_3"  type="Envelope"  url="eecf53c76cc2bd5178609079749841d5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0731_img_2237_4"  type="Envelope"  url="8eee47a273ed6c835a707661829bb375.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0731_img_2237_1"/>
                105 Brudenell Road  <hi rend="underline">Leeds</hi>    Sept 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   Dear Mr. Hackney,   Thanks for your letter and all it <lb/> contained. I was so pleased to receive it and to <lb/>hear that you are going on in the right <lb/>way, (as regards health I mean - of course!!)   I am eagerly anticipating the short time <lb/> on Sat. afternoon and hope you will be well <lb/> enough to be up and out.  I expect (D.V.) to leave Leeds on that day at 1 p.m. <lb/>, arriving Sheffield 1.52 p.m. There I will book my <lb/>luggage at the cloakroom, and with as much <lb/> haste as it is 'proper' to make, board a car &amp; <lb/><seg type="del">w</seg> ride out to the Hospital. I hope there won't <lb/> be much delay through my lack of knowledge <lb/> of the place but I'll do the best I can. <lb/> On arriving there I will look for you (and <lb/> the walking stick!) .. and then ..' Three cheers <lb/> for Newlands!'  Now I trust this is alright for you - but if <lb/> not, well just write me a line &amp; I'll arrange <lb/> to suit you.  There is a train leaves for Hope about 5.15 or so  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0731_img_2237_2"/>
              <lb/>I think that will be a suitable time  After all, I have not been over to Hebden, <lb/> for reasons concerning home. But it couldn't be <lb/>helped and its still 'a pleasure to come'!  But I will reserve all news until 2 days <lb/> hence and will finish up this short note.  With very kind regards and good wishes for <lb/> you 'Gaby' ( and adieu — till Sat.. 2.30 p.m. about?) <seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Flossie Briggs</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0731_img_2237_3"/>
               envelope  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0731_img_2237_4"/>
               envelope   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>