<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1795">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Reginald Brabazon (Earl of Meath) to Lord Clonbrock, 6 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Reginal Brabazon (Earl of Meath)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is to Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock. It refers to the proposed foundation of a fund to recognise the service of the Royal Irish Constabulary and the Dublin Metropolitan Police during the Easter Rising. As the British government were only willing to do the &#39;minimum&#39;, a fund was being established to reward the men who served and compensate the dependants of those killed or seriously injured.
Clonbrock notes on the letter that he would donate £10 but would not be able to sit on the committee as he feared he would be unable to get many to contribute in County Galway. &#39;Sinn Fein&#39; was, he believed, so prevalent in the county that people would be &#39;afraid&#39;.
Some of the letter is missing but a list is enclosed of names of those who had been asked to contribute and amounts received.
The Irish Police &amp; Constabulary Recognition Fund was founded by the Earl of Meath to recognise the work of the police during the Easter Rising. It presented certificates, war bonds and awards to policemen who were in active service in the Royal Irish Constabulary or Dublin Metropolitan Police during the Rising and compensation to the widows and dependants of those killed or injured.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No 54; Ms 35,766 (12) </collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1795</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1012">Reginal Brabazon (Earl of Meath)</persName>
              <date>1916-09-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2089">Kilruddery, Bray, County Wicklow</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lord Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1929</item>
               <item n="tag">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1795_img_125_1"  type="Letter"  url="f897ba239afbacb692b258d170eebbd3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1795_img_125_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="bdcdbc773e5c0d670581ce4f0200136e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1795_img_125_3"  type="Letter"  url="1f726b33a07bf698e53a258019615e4c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1795_img_125_4"  type="Letter"  url="79ad9b37e72828d5229b47eb5874a4b5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1795_img_125_1"/>
             ans. 18. <lb/>Encl. £10 — Unable <lb/>to act on <lb/>Committee — <lb/>Fear cannot hope <lb/>to get many to <lb/>subscribe in this <lb/>Co. Sinn Fein <lb/> so prevalent <lb/>people wd. be <lb/>afraid. <lb/>To let me   <lb/><seg type="unclear">what God</seg> <lb/>     Killruddery, <lb/>Bray, <lb/>Ireland   Sept 16. 1916   My dear Clonbrock,   You who know Ireland so well, will I think agree with me, that <lb/>the Royal Irish Constabulary and the Dublin Metropolitan Police, by their <lb/>loyal and gallant services, during the recent Rising, have saved not only <lb/>loyal Irishmen and women from untold sufferings and terrors, but indirectly <lb/>the whole Empire from very serious trouble and possibly disaster. In view <lb/>of the above, I have urged the Government both publicly in the House, and <lb/>also by private interviews with the members of the Executive in Dublin, to <lb/>adopt a generous and sympathetic attitude towards the Irish Police and <lb/>Constabulary, by rewarding those who distinguished themselves and by giving <lb/>generous compensation to the widows and dependent relatives of those who <lb/>were killed or seriously injured during the Rebellion.   The Government will have to be pressed to do its duty, but <lb/>experience has shown that they are not likely to do more than public opinion <lb/>will demand as a minimum.   Anything beyond that minimum will I fear have to be raised by <lb/>those who believe that the security of life and property in Ireland, in <lb/>view of the stormy days which lie ahead of us, will mainly rest on the <lb/>spirit and content, of the Irish Constabulary.   I have been asked to start such a Fund, and Brigadier <lb/>General Byrne, Commanding the Royal Irish Constabulary, informs me that he <lb/>has received a cheque for £100 — collected voluntarily by the Special <lb/>Constables of London for this purpose.   As
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1795_img_125_2"/>
            Irish Police &amp;Constabulary Recognition Fund<lb/> Letters asking for subscription<lb/> to "Police &amp; Constabulary Recognition Fund"<lb/> and subscriptions received.  <hi rend="underline">Sep. Oct. 1916</hi> <lb/> Ashtown. - cheque promised<lb/> Bellew. - unanswered <lb/> R. Berridge 1/0/0<lb/> J. Chivers 2/2/0<lb/> A Courtenay 2/2/0<lb/> J. Daly 5/0/0<lb/> Robin 1/1/0<lb/> A French 1/0/0<lb/> Gough. (anonymous) 2/2/0<lb/> Killanin. has already subscribed<lb/> N. Mahon 5/5/0<lb/> G G. Mahon 5/5/0<lb/> J. <seg type="unclear">MacDermot</seg> 1/0/0<lb/> A. <seg type="unclear">Pender</seg><lb/> C. O Hara French 1/0/0<lb/> W.G. Walkman 2/2/0<lb/> J.G. Ahearn 2/2/0<lb/> E.L. Athy 1/0/0<lb/> J.C. Basil has already subscribed<lb/> M. <seg type="unclear">H.</seg> Burke 0/10/0<lb/> Edmund Blake - per L. Daly 2/2/0<lb/> A N. Comyn 1/0/0<lb/> Col. J. Comyn 1/0/0<lb/> P.J. Dav 2 /0/0<lb/> D. de Stackpoole has already subscribed<lb/> Denis Daly - has already subscribed £20:0:0<lb/> T. Hazell 1/0/0<lb/> Cecil Henry 3/0/0<lb/> Walter Joyce 9/0/0<lb/> Tom Lewin 5/0/0<lb/> James Johnston 1/0/0<lb/> T.Johnston 0/10/0<lb/> J.M.A. Lewis has already subscribed<lb/> G.W. Mahon (<seg type="unclear">self &amp;</seg> wife) 1/0/0<lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1795_img_125_3"/>
            J. R. Martin 5/0/0<lb/> James McDonnell 5/0/0<lb/> G MacPhail 2/2/0<lb/> J. Meldon 2/2/0<lb/> Winston<seg type="unclear">Pender</seg> 1/0/0<lb/> M. Seymour 1/0/0<lb/> <seg type="unclear"> T Shawe</seg> Taylor 2/2/0<lb/> R R Wade 1/0/0<lb/> <seg type="unclear">Westmeath</seg> 5/5/0<lb/> C. O Farrell 2/0/0<lb/> <seg type="unclear">H.</seg> Lewis (Letter after J.M.A. Lewis) 1/0/0<lb/> J.W. Brady <seg type="unclear">Murray</seg> 1/0/0<lb/> R. R Wade 1/0/0<lb/> T. Hazell 1 0 0<lb/> The <seg type="unclear">Misses</seg> Lewis [Letter to J.M.A. Lewis) 1/0/0<lb/> Sir Gerald Burke -  <lb/> Martin McDonagh unanswered <lb/> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1795_img_125_4"/>
             1916<lb/> Irish Police and<lb/> Constabulary Recognition<lb/> Fund.<lb/>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>