<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0487">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from P. A. Murphy to Sir Matthew Nathan, 5 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>P. A. Murphy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter and a memorial from P. A. Murphy, solicitor for John Anderson, to Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939), the Under-Secretary of Ireland. Murphy writes to request permission for Anderson to take over the licensed business (a public house situated at Lukeswell, Mullinavat, Co. Kilkenny) from his deceased sister, Mary Farrell.Sir Matthew Nathan was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSORP/1916/7372/6/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/487</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0604">P. A. Murphy</persName>
              <date>1916-02-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1295">O&#39;Connell Street, Waterford, Co. Waterford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0350">Chief Secretary's Office, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0487_img_1850_1"  type="Letter"  url="5e5236275bb3740b17a257ee138bc189.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0487_img_1850_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="6a9b341a8074710afe576cfbb22ea406.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0487_img_1850_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="808b60836d47cb7c004e491957a2e981.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0487_img_1850_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="102d5b667612e0ba09060d12b400f919.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0487_img_1850_1"/>
             P.A. Murphy, <lb/> Solicitor,<lb/> TELEPHONE No 114 <lb/>   O'Connell Street,  Waterford.    5th Febry., 1916.   To   The Right Hon. Sir Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G.,  Under Secretary, Dublin Castle, DUBLIN.   re <hi rend="underline">MARY FARRELL DECEASED</hi><lb/> MEMORIAL of JOHN ANDERSON of Lukewell, <lb/> Mullinavat, in the County of Kilkenny, <lb/> Publican. <lb/> Sir,   I enclose herewith Memorial of the above — <lb/> named John Anderson for consideration by his <lb/> Excellency, the Lord Lieutenant, and shall be <lb/> much obliged if you will inform me at the <lb/> earliest opportunity of his Excellency's de— <lb/> cision thereon.  <seg type="closer"> Your obedient Servant  <hi rend="underline">P.A, Murphy</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0487_img_1850_2"/>
             <seg type="head"><hi rend="underline">MARY FARRELL</hi> late of Lukeswell, Mullinavat, <lb/> in the County of Kilkenny, Publican, <hi rend="underline">Deceased</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">THE MEMORIAL</hi> of JOHN ANDERSON of Lukeswell aforesaid <lb/> brother of the Decrased and sole Executor of her Will, <lb/> and General Devisee and Legatee thereunder,:— <lb/></seg> <hi rend="underline">JOHN ANDERSON,</hi> by his Solicitor, P. A. MURPHY, <lb/> of O'Connell Street in the city of Waterford, prays that liberty <lb/> may be given to him to carry on the licensed business of the said <lb/> Mary Farrell, deceased, on the licensed premises situated at <lb/> Lukeswell, Mullinavat in the County of Kilkenny aforesaid under <lb/> the following circumstances:—   The said Mary Farrell died on the 25th. day of August, 1915 <lb/> having duly made her Will, dated the 11th. day of August, 1915, <lb/> whereby she appointed the said John Anderson her sole Executor <lb/> and devised and bequeathed all her property whether real or per— <lb/> sonal unto her brother the said John Anderson absolutely.   At Petty Sessions held at Kilmacow on the 9th day of September <lb/> 1915, the said John Anderson was granted an interim transfer of <lb/> the said Licence.   On the 13th day of October 1915, the said John Anderson <lb/> lodged in the District Registry, Kilkenny, the said original Will <lb/> of the said Mary Farrell deceased, and applied for Probate there <lb/> of. James Murphy of Mullinavat in the County of Kilkenny <lb/> Publican, one of the next of kin of Mary Farrell deceased <lb/> lodged a Caveat in the said District Registry, Kilkenny, against <lb/><hi rend="underline">granting</hi>  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0487_img_1850_3"/>
              against granting Probate of the said Will to the said John <lb/> Anderson on the 4th. day of October, 1915, which Caveat was <lb/> warned on behalf of the said John Anderson on the 13th. day of <lb/> November, 1915, and an Appearance was, on the 22nd day of Nov — <lb/> ember, 1915, entered on behalf of the said James Murphy by his <lb/> Solicitor, Mr H.D. Keane, O'Connell Street Waterford.   On the 23rd. day of December, 1915, the said John Anderson <lb/> caused a Civil Bill to be issued and served on the said James <lb/> Murphy to have the said Will admitted to Probate.   On the 12th. day of January 1916, the said Civil Bill <lb/> was heard by his Honour David Fitzgerald, County Court Judge for <lb/> the said court of Kilkenny, and an order was made admitting the <lb/> said will to probate.   On the 14 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day of January 1916 the said James <lb/> Murphy served Notice of Appeal against the order of the said <lb/> County Court Judge admitting the said Will to Probate, and same <lb/> will be heard and determined by one of the Judges of Assize on <lb/> the 15th day of March. 1916   <hi rend="underline">Owing to the litigation above mentioned the said John <lb/> Anderson was unable to get the usual confirmation of the Magistrates' <lb/> Interim Transfer of the said Licence at the Quarter Sessions <lb/> held in Thomastown on the 12th, January last </hi> and cannot obtain <lb/> said Transfer until the appeal is determined by the Judges of <lb/> Assize on the 15th. day of March next. The Police Authorities <lb/> through the Sergeant of the district, have notified the said John <lb/> Anderson that he must get liberty to trade from his Excellency <lb/> the Lord Lieutenant, as otherwise they would be obliged to take <lb/> proceedings against him under the Licensing Act, 1872.   <hi rend="underline">YOUR</hi>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0487_img_1850_4"/>
              YOUR MEMORIALIST accordingly PRAYS that his Excellency <lb/> will be pleased to grant licence or liberty to the said John <lb/> Anderson to trade as a Publican until the 14th day of April <lb/> 1916, when the Confirmation of the Licence will be heard and <lb/> determined by His Honour the County Court Judge for the said County <lb/> of Kilkenny.   <hi rend="underline">AND</hi> your Memorialist will ever pray.   <hi rend="underline">DATED</hi> this 6th, Day of February, 1916   <hi rend="underline">SIGNED</hi> on behalf of the said John Anderson   A Murphy  Solicitor for the said John Anderson   O' Connell Street,  Waterford.  To/  The Right Honourable  Sir  Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G.   Under Secretary, Dublin Castle,  Dublin.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>