<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1125">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O'Farrell to Jean Louis Loiseleur des Longchamps, 4 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to the French Consul, Jean Louis Loiseleur des Longchamps (1872-1969) requesting information about the result of an application by three men who wished to volunteer for the French Army.Monsieur Jean Louis Amable Loiseleur des Longchamps-Deville served as the French Consul in Ireland from 1913.Sir Edward O&#39;Farrell (c.1857-1926) served as the Assistant Under Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Guest Churchill, Lord Wimborne. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI CSO/RP/1916/442/5/3, NAI CSO/RP/1916/442/5/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1125</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-01-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1075">J. des Longchamps</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1125_img_359_1"  type="Letter"  url="c26685d0f1aa3c270b14853c171ccab2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1125_img_359_1"/>
                4th January, 1916.   No. 29.   Sir,   With reference to the cases of the three Alsatians, <lb/>Louis Herr, Romain Willman  n  and Joseph Cheray, who <lb/>volunteered  for  the French Army, I am directed by the Lord <lb/>Lieutenant to request that you will be so good as to state, <lb/>for His Excellency's information, what has been the <lb/>result of the applications made by these men.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   EOFarrell   Monsieur Loiseleur des Longchamps,  French Consul,  8 Leinster Street,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>