<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1507">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Postcard from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington to John Dillon, 23 October 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington (1877-1946) sends the postcard to John Dillon (1851-1927) to cancel an appointment and suggest an alternative date.Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full detail emerged. John Dillon was an Irish Party MP in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs.Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, Ms. 6837/30/6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1507</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0722">Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington</persName>
              <date>1916-10-23</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1899">2 North Gt. George Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1507_img_965_1"  type="Letter"  url="96db0043b20c31229b664e3caa6e2853.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1507_img_965_2"  type="Letter"  url="d81364f22016013be889ea4c2daa0e7e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1507_img_965_1"/>
                 John Dillon Esq M.P  North Gt. George St.  Dublin     
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1507_img_965_2"/>
                 23.10.16    Regret have appointment at hour <lb/> you name tomorrow. Could call on <hi rend="underline">Thursday at 4.30</hi> if that would <lb/>suit equally well. <seg type="closer"> H. S. Skeffington </seg>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>