<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4137">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 4 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>
Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/45A-45B</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4137</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-04</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4137_img_3512_1"  type="Letter"  url="396745742e7ed596279c5f599c10f78f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4137_img_3512_2"  type="Letter"  url="0f927ce67fd3dd11cbada7c4b72fe205.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4137_img_3512_3"  type="Letter"  url="7cf710cd6ac747522a77ce81a1d0d381.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4137_img_3512_4"  type="Letter"  url="91d80a393b035a7422eda1f6c0edb81a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4137_img_3512_5"  type="Letter"  url="cbd6e844224a00f35ce7300317a03dbc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4137_img_3512_6"  type="Letter"  url="2d7373c6f13f5d21b32423ec999afbf3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4137_img_3512_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/45.A   Nov. 4' 15     My dear little pr   No papers to keep a BW happy, only<lb/>a letter, but.....Any how tho' very sleepy<lb/>the <seg type="unclear">b w </seg>will try to begin an answer as it is<lb/>hardly bet time yet.  I know Bramham garden slightly having<lb/>only lived there for about 2 years ! I don't<lb/>remember any houses which would be called<lb/>Cottages except perhaps on the E side, which surely<lb/>look out both ways on to gardens &amp; must be<lb/>very expensive methinks. I rather think I may<lb/>have seen them built in spite of the old timber. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4137_img_3512_2"/>
             <sic>Its</sic> a pity good marks travel so badly by post<lb/>or I'm sure you would send me a lot, &amp;<lb/>possibly I should return them or others simi-<lb/>lar so perhaps it is hardly worth while. What<lb/>do you think?  So sleepy that I went to bed after getting<lb/>so far!  I have just seen Wednesday's papers. As I expected,<lb/>Squiffy's gas was turned on full tap. I am prepared<lb/>to sacrifice myself &amp; to retain my office &amp; £10000 a<lb/>year <seg type="del">fo</seg> until the King (whom I dare to do it !) &amp; the<lb/>Country, of whose many voices I can always take my<lb/>pick, actually kick me out! As <seg type="del">far as</seg> regards  the Dardanelles<lb/>we had a Cabinet debate which was very interesting, &amp;<lb/>as there was no decision — there never is of course — I<lb/>can confidently state that the Government approved of the <lb/>   action taken by my somewhat headstrong &amp; impetuous<lb/>young friend Winston. As regards the future we could<lb/>have gone on comfortably with our mixed responsibility<lb/>&amp; no decisions but for that sneak Carson, who ought to<lb/>have been grateful fo me  for not having hanged him instead of giving the whole show away;<lb/>we could always have stopped the press from stating that we<lb/><seg type="del">have</seg> are   needlessly throwing away 2000 lives a week in the<lb/>Dardanelles to no end, &amp; other unpleasant facts, &amp; so could<lb/>have lived on happily till the end of the war when if we are<lb/>successful we could get the grateful thanks of the nation, &amp; if<lb/>not successful the support of the Germans which we shall have<lb/>earned, for another long tenancy of our  respective  Cabinets includ-<lb/>ing the perquisites.  Redmond's lies were so blatant in comparison<lb/>that one can almost look upon him as an honest<lb/>man. He resembles Leader.  I do not see how Bonar Law can remain in the<lb/>cabinet after Carson's speech in spite of the pressure evidently 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4137_img_3512_3"/>
              Now 4 1915   exerted by the King and the Balfour wobblers.  I think it cannot be long before there is an upheaval<lb/>&amp; hope that the nation will turn to their one strong man<lb/>Carson. Meanwhile it requires all one's faith &amp; patriotism to<lb/>render service, knowing it is being exploited by the politicians<lb/>for their own purpose. <seg type="del">It requires</seg> We need some member<lb/>in the house to sacrifice his future &amp; tell the straight truth<lb/>about Asquith &amp; his colleagues, descending to personalities<lb/>for the sake of the country, &amp; remembering that personalities<lb/>are never forgiven, any more than a Doctor would be<lb/>forgiven for telling the truth about another's <seg type="del">p</seg>operation.  The only man I know who can do anything<lb/>in regard to an exchange from Canadian to Brit<lb/>Art<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> is Colonel Peake AAG War Office. I hardly<lb/>know him well enough to write, but think<lb/>young Huntly might see him if on leave. I<lb/>imagine from what you hint at that it would be<lb/>difficult for him to put on paper the reasons for  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4137_img_3512_4"/>
             D1633/1/1/45B   Nov. 4' 15.   <lb/>his transfer.  There is trouble in the land. This French<lb/>Cook late of the Carlton Hotel who volunteered<lb/>to come to the A mess as he wanted to<lb/>serve his country &amp; could not be a soldier,<lb/>&amp; who accepted very low wages in consequence,<lb/>found life with Army rations too dull &amp;<lb/>has vanished back to the charms of city<lb/>life in/spite of the inspiration of the Duc<lb/>de Luynes. Consequently the hunt for a<lb/>cook male or female has begun all over again<lb/>&amp; with a particular <seg type="del">per</seg>set the treasure if<lb/>found is likely to be expensive, but that is just  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4137_img_3512_5"/>
             what our chief does not intend to have. Contentment<lb/>(but with The best only) is not a quality which lasts<lb/>very long tho' I am often amazed how often some<lb/>people get it by bluff &amp; strafing.  Unless I hear more news of your plans<lb/>tomorrow's letter will go to 29 if there is<lb/>one tomorrow. Perhaps it is hardly worth<lb/>sending it. I have no hint as to how<lb/>long you propose to stay at Rugby.  I still find a p.r a ... nuisance<lb/>but am still her only<lb/>b W'<lb/>W.BSpender  Please give my love to Elsie &amp; Co.<lb/>The children are hardly likely to remember<lb/>the one who spoilt their fine castle at<lb/>Barmouth &amp; made a bathing place which<lb/>was not appreciated.  I bet you dig out the <seg type="unclear">Ford</seg>whilst<lb/>you are at Rugby. Confess to it<lb/>&amp; that I know the wiles of a p r,<lb/>better than anyone else.  Boylan Smith declares that I have<lb/>been in correspondence with Carson as I<lb/>made just the same statement last week of  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_4137_img_3512_6"/>
              4 Nov 15   <lb/>forcing Greece to see that we were better as<lb/>friends than as enemies &amp; that we were not<lb/>afraid of showing what we thought of treachery.<lb/>But this is not a coincidence. It is the obvious<lb/>course for a strong nation &amp; therefore a<lb/>certainty that Carson would have chosen it. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>