<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0726">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from 'Ernie' to George Hackney, 18 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Ernie</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter to George Hackney (c. 1889-1977) from &#39;Ernie.&#39; In this letter, Ernie expresses relief that George is away from the front and recuperating in a hospital in Sheffield. He wryly suggests that George is &#39;not in the least hurry&#39; to return to the trenches, and refers to the &#39;broken down&#39; men who he has met after their return from the war, their characters changed dramatically by their time there. Ernie refers to photographic plates which George has sent him to develop, and speaks briefly of photography. He also writes briefly about numerous mutual friends, offering and inquiring after information as to their well-being.This letter is from the papers of George Naphthali Hackney, a Lance Corporal from Clifton, Belfast. Before his time in the army, he worked as a book-keeper for a florist. He was the youngest in a Presbyterian family of six, with three older sisters. In 2014, his collection of photographs taken in the trenches were made available to the public in an Ulster Museum exhibition, and his life and photography became the subject of a BBC documentary, &#39;The Man who Shot the Great War&#39;. The author of this letter is &#39;Ernie&#39;, apparently a friend of George.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of George Hackney, Belfast, D3503/5/1-6</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/726</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0322">Ernie</persName>
              <date>1916-09-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0370">234 Spamount Street, Belfast</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">George Hackney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1546">31 Ward, 'D' Block, Wharncliffe War Hospital, Sheffield, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0726_img_2232_1"  type="Letter"  url="a72da0529a69e0020c63cf8545bd57dd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0726_img_2232_2"  type="Letter"  url="7777a461c6862bd27cfa75f4cb13a760.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0726_img_2232_3"  type="Envelope"  url="5c04182597cbd0d5afdb3483385844f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0726_img_2232_4"  type="Letter"  url="5ea6432e587af1db8f4f7c8b8ae7133c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0726_img_2232_1"/>
                234 Spamount St., Belfast    18th Sept. 1916  .  Dear George,   Your very welcome letter received this morning. Although <lb/> Jenny told me that you were going into hospital in France, I did not know <lb/> you would be so soon in England. I am sure you are not in the least <lb/> hurry to get back any more than hundreds of others. I have heard of <lb/> chaps who were very anxious, according to the story, to get back to the front, <lb/> but strange to say I never met one yet. I have seen some of the chaps <lb/> home on leave since the advance &amp; I never saw such changes in some of <lb/> them. Some of them appear to be quite broken down  I note your request re plates. Re no 7 set. I was going to <lb/> write to you to say that these had not turned up, but when I got <lb/> up to the place this morning I found them waiting for me. It is <lb/> strange that they should <seg type="del"> </seg> have arrived at the same time as your <lb/> letter. I understand that the chap forgot to deliver them <lb/> No.6 &amp; 8. I made contact prints of  these  and gave them to Jenny to send <lb/> on so probably they are now in France. However I will do the <lb/>p.c.'s as requested. Also the copy of 42D.  Re files 90. This part of your letter puzzled me a bit as I had not the faintest idea to what it referred, and I had not got the note enclosed with no 7 set, when I read your letter.  You ordered two cards of no 15D the dog which J.E. was holding. I <lb/>tried a card one night I was doing some for W.Ewing-who has got  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0726_img_2232_2"/>
              badly bitten with the photographic habit - but it did not turn out very <lb/>satisfactory, and I did not send on. Does this order still hold good? <lb/>The socks <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>you did not receive for the excellent reason that <lb/> they were not sent on. Mother wrote her letter before she had the <lb/>socks finished &amp;&amp; 'the best laid plans, etc'  I suppose you have heard by this time that the one &amp; only W.Campbell <lb/>has got the D.S.O. I would not be surprised at anything he <lb/> got, as he is quite capable of anything.  By the way, the name of Sheffield reminds me that it was in <lb/>Watson &amp; Co. 84 High St. Sheffield, that your camera was purchased.  I believe I forgot when mentioning Albert Mitchell to put in <lb/> his No. &amp; Batt, re. I think I left the place blank as I did <lb/> not know his address at the time I was writing &amp; then closed the letter without putting it in. I suppose however it does not matter now.  Did you ever see anything of Jack McMullan since he went to <lb/><seg type="del">deleted text</seg> France? No person here seems to know anything about him.  I think I will close with kindest regards from all. <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Ernie</hi> </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S. Re Daily Sketch. I will think it over. <lb/>E. </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0726_img_2232_3"/>
                From    234 Spamount St.  <hi rend="underline">Belfast</hi>      14/14815,  L.-Corpl. George Hackney,  14th R.I. Rifles, Y.C.V.  31 Ward, 'D' Block,  Warncliffe War Hospital,  <hi rend="underline">Sheffield</hi>.    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0726_img_2232_4"/>
                <seg type="del">print 4 No 10 Set 8. PC.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">No hurry back</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">No 7 glad</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Cancel Files 8c.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">15D. not if not worth while.</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">WE. P Crage married</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">WE. DSO</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">Camera Sheffield</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">amichell no number in</seg> <lb/><seg type="del">J mc Mullan</seg>   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>