<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4326">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 17 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4326</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-06-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1531">49 Mount Street, W. </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4326_img_3686_1"  type="Letter"  url="49efe222f222daaa3e86082860956653.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4326_img_3686_2"  type="Letter"  url="b446d77ed167628c21c89731e0c3a968.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4326_img_3686_3"  type="Letter"  url="840795283c9cb58416b22092c97ca547.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4326_img_3686_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Private</hi>   D 1507/A/17/20   Telephone, 'Gerrard 4402.    June 17.16    49,Mount Street,<lb/>W.    My dear Carson   Walter Long has told<lb/>me that Lloyd George has<lb/>told you that the Cabinet<lb/>have agreed that the Gov-<lb/>ernment of Ireland Act<lb/>must, with certain mod-<lb/>ifications, be brought at once<lb/>into operation and that<lb/>he used certain arguments<lb/>to you in enforcing this view  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4326_img_3686_2"/>
             I have never been more<lb/>astonished in all my life.<lb/>I repudiate the alleged<lb/>arguments; and as to<lb/>Lloyd Georges' scheme as<lb/>explained to me by Long<lb/>not only have I never<lb/>agreed to it but I have never<lb/>been asked to agree to it.  Lloyd George has made<lb/>No proposals whatever to the<lb/>Cabinet. He was asked to<lb/>try and effect a settlement<lb/>between the Irish Unionists  <lb/>and Nationalists, subject of<lb/>course to the approval <sic>ofthe</sic><lb/>Cabinet; but what did I<lb/>understand by a settlement?<lb/>one for the exclusion from the<lb/>operation <sic>ofthe</sic> Government of<lb/>Ireland Act <sic>ofUlster</sic>or of<lb/>part <sic>ofUlster</sic>. If an agree-<lb/>ment was reached an<lb/>amending act was to be<lb/>passed during <sic>theWar</sic>,<lb/>but non <sic>ofus</sic>Unionists<lb/>in <sic>theCabinet</sic>contemplated<lb/>for a moment that either  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4326_img_3686_3"/>
             the principal act or the<lb/>amending act would<lb/>come into operation until<lb/>after the conclusion <sic>ofthe</sic><lb/>war. I could not possibly<lb/>warn you because I did<lb/>not even know that<lb/>Lloyd George had formul-<lb/>ated such a scheme in his<lb/>own mind  <sic>Yoursever<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg></sic><lb/>   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>