<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4257">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 8 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/93</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4257</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4257_img_3623_1"  type="Letter"  url="5aa78515eb9d0c435300c3dee51b40ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4257_img_3623_2"  type="Letter"  url="966e1012bc99e3bd4d6e7381c736060d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4257_img_3623_1"/>
             Dec.8'   I should be in bed but it is my night on duty &amp; Russell engrossed <lb/> in the National review is "sitting on" my bed. Hence a rather sleepy <lb/> scrawl.   Unless I hear tomorrow I shan't know where to send this to <lb/> but hope you are now "safely" in London somewhere as we are having <lb/> gales which will probably delay the mails.   The new 108 Brigadier is from the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>Bedfords &amp; says <lb/> he "knows" Leader. We look forward to hearing what he knows. I <lb/> have offered to bet Singleton that given 10 mins favourable oppor- <lb/>tunity I will be able to remind Leader of "his tea with the Mikado", <lb/> but Singleton won't accept.   General said something to me about our not having much <lb/> to do in G. I rounded on him squarely, &amp; have made even <lb/> the peaceful Russell really roused when I told him that the <lb/> General thought he read novels in the office, because once <lb/> he had mentioned he would fetch one from there.   I never thanked you for your novels the 4.7<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">ds</seg></hi> I <lb/> have read 2 including Baring Gould's exceedingly gloom Essex <lb/> picture. Very many thanks but dont' send me tragedies in <lb/> future please however engrossing ! However I am spoilt for <lb/> the writing I like best is the p r's footprints &amp; no day is <lb/> complete without them.    Richardson has caught the hump which I had so badly 3
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4257_img_3623_2"/>
            days ago; there is still a <lb/> slight swelling left, which will grow bigger if R is not in bed <lb/> soon.   The papers make ill reading, the victory &amp; capture of Baghdad <lb/> was a poor lie. The Greeks I absolutely mistrust. Our home Govern- <lb/>ment ought to be paid by results when I fancy some of their wives <lb/> would be begging in the streets.   The Times Tuesday has an account of the Irish Volunteer &amp; treason <lb/> in Ireland. I need no other justification for my part.    Had a morning out with Russell &amp; the bombers quite interesting.    Am probably taking some of the Corps round tomorrow.   Richardson a little restive with R for not taking a stronger line <lb/> with the General &amp; the A branch. I rather concur !   3 letters from the p r ! ! I am so grateful to hear of your safe <lb/> &amp; happy return &amp; the success of your mission. I do hope your London <lb/> Committee will be pleased. They ought to be. I suppose you did not put forward <lb/> any of my other suggestions for the agency etc ?   A letter from Ed rather upsets me. He has found a  lost letter I sent <lb/> 6 weeks ago &amp; proposes to publish it now. It is not all correct  now  &amp; I fear <lb/> I shall be too late. I wish to stop it but could have made it so much <lb/>stronger now.   <hi rend="underline">IF</hi> I got home about Feb<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>what should we do <lb/> Stop in town or go to country of what ? ? There's something to <lb/> keep a p r pretty busy thinking. Rather a brave little p r tho' how <lb/> she avoided the tempests I don't know. Mater does seem sorry to lose <lb/> you &amp; you could make any terms for your return there I feel sure.    Your letters always make me want more. Your extra 1/2 stamp <lb/> got your Sunday letter here on Wednesday ! !   Your b w   /WBSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>