<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3987">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Art Ó Briain to John J Neeson, 4 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Art Ó Briain</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a four page letter acknowledging receipt of a letter of August 28th, predominantly referring to arrangements for the provision of supplies of tobacco, money, food, literature/ books as well as a duplicator for prisoners of war at Frongoch. It also refers to the camp leadership arrangements and to classes for the prisoners.  It refers to several men in the camp: Mr Dixon, N. T. Murray, Prisoner 1091, O’ Sullivan and to a Mr MacDonagh (who was not a prisoner).

This letter is part of a period of correspondence between Ó Briain and Neeson (see MS 8434 / 21 – 10).  MS 8434 / 23.8 appears to be a response to this letter. 

From the Art Ó Briain Papers held in the National Library of Ireland.   NLI records indicate that MS 8434 /23 is a collection (13 items) of letters from prisoners in Frongoch and Reading jails.

Art Ó Briain (1872-1949) was Honorary Secretary of The Irish National Relief Fund which was set up to provide assistance to the dependents of those executed in 1916, those sentenced to prison and to the prisoners themselves.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Art Ó Briain papers, c. 1900-c.1945, Ó Briain’s work for Irish political prisoners (1916-21), MS 8434 / 23-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3987</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1063">Art Ó Briain</persName>
              <date>1916-09-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0554">London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John J. Neeson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1189">Frongoch, North Wales, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1949</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3987_img_3374_1"  type="Letter"  url="fef5f00dd24706620a5b39ffec1bd5f9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3987_img_3374_2"  type="Letter"  url="392d0ef3bdaccde312243a5d32c583c5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3987_img_3374_3"  type="Letter"  url="db31ed0f89623d61a22a51012cb1e3d9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3987_img_3374_4"  type="Letter"  url="bbf82e0ca1da855e45586abf2f8045e3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3987_img_3374_1"/>
             4 September 1916   Dear Mr Neeson,   I duly received you letter of August<lb/>28th. I note that Mr Dixon has been removed from<lb/>Frongoch.<lb/><lb/><hi rend="underline">TOBACCO SUPPLIES.</hi>  I am glad to hear that this matter<lb/>is now definitely and satisfac-<lb/>torily settled and that the first<lb/>consignment has arrived.  <lb/><hi rend="underline">MONEY SUPPLIES.</hi>  Your suggestion to draw upon the<lb/>full amount you have in hand now<lb/>and then draw on us for the full<lb/>amount of £68. 10. 0., would be<lb/>very <hi rend="superscript">in</hi>convenient for us, as it<lb/>would mean that we should have to<lb/>keep this amount in reserve in<lb/>case of a sudden call from you.<lb/>Our present arrangements provide<lb/>for collections coming in to us<lb/>every Wednesday, (the Committee<lb/>meets on the same night) when we<lb/>dispose of all demands including<lb/>remittances to the Dublin Com-<lb/>mittee; we only leave a very<lb/>small balance in the bank each<lb/>week for any emergency. It would<lb/>therefore suit us better if you<lb/>could fall in with our previous<lb/>suggestion that you should draw<lb/>on us every week, or every fort-<lb/>night, so as to keep your camp<lb/>fund up to some predetermined<lb/>amount which you would fix upon as<lb/>a safe working margin for all pur-<lb/>poses. I should, perhaps, explain<lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3987_img_3374_2"/>
             2.<lb/>that we do not limit ourselves to sup—<lb/>plying cash for advances to released pri—<lb/>soners, but for any purpose which your<lb/>Committee may decide upon as necessary.  <hi rend="underline">CAMP OFFICERS.</hi> I thank you for giving the names of the<lb/>Head Leader, Secretary and Treasurer of<lb/>the Camp, and we shall be pleased to act<lb/>on any demand received from any one of<lb/>these three.  I note that you will keep us informed of<lb/>any changes in the officers. We should<lb/>also be glad if you could keep us informed<lb/>of --- the total number in the Camp from<lb/>time to time.  <hi rend="underline">FOOD SUPPLIES.</hi> I note your requirements with regard to<lb/>currents. I do not know exactly what<lb/>quantity would be required for 548 men,<lb/>but having consulted some of my lady<lb/>friends, I have calculated the quantity<lb/>to be between 20 and 30 lbs per week. I<lb/>am arranging for a supply to be sent from<lb/>here now, and we will probably arrange<lb/>for subsequent consignments to be sent<lb/>from one of the other Committees.  I also note that fruit would be appre—<lb/>ciated, and I will let you know later what<lb/>can be arranged.  By the bye you mention men in hospital.<lb/>Are there many? Do you want any parti—<lb/>cular food or delicacies for them?  <hi rend="underline">LITERATURE.</hi> (a)<hi rend="underline">PERIODICALS.</hi> I note the list of maga—<lb/>zines you mention, and will arrange for<lb/>them to be sent. With regard to STUDIES<lb/>will it be allowed? I have written to<lb/>the Censor, asking him what Irish publi—<lb/>cations are allowed and hope to hear from<lb/>him soon. It would probably help if you<lb/>could see the Censor with a list of Irish<lb/>periodicals and books, which you would<lb/>like, and give him a rough idea of the<lb/>contents, and then sent the list to us 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3987_img_3374_3"/>
             3.<lb/>and we would attend to it. Are there<lb/>any trade or scientific periodicies<lb/>which any of the prisioners would like,<lb/>to keep abreast of their own particular<lb/>callings?  (b) <hi rend="underline">LIBRARY.</hi> We are glad to hear you<lb/>have the nubleus of a library, and we<lb/>shall be glad to help in buildings this<lb/>up. If you have to remain at Frongoch<lb/>during the winter you will want a good<lb/>library to draw on for the long evenings.<lb/>Let us know what books you have and what<lb/>you would like.  <hi rend="underline">DUPLICATOR</hi> We were glad to hear that you purpose<lb/>starting a Camp Journal, and if you can<lb/>send us a copy, we shall be very glad.<lb/>I suppose any form of duplicator or copier<lb/>would suit your purpose. We shall en-<lb/>deavour to get you one, and I have sent<lb/>out enquiries to three sources to see<lb/>what can be done, and will let you know<lb/>as soon as possible.  <hi rend="underline">CLASSES</hi> We were very interested yo hear about<lb/>the mathematical classes of which you are<lb/>in charge, and it is with very much plea-<lb/>sure that we are sending you on the books<lb/>which you name.  I presume you also have classes formed<lb/>for other subjects. If so, and you re-<lb/>quire any books for these, we will be very<lb/>glad to send them on to you. Have you<lb/>all you want in the way of writing ma-<lb/>terials for the classes? What about<lb/>Irish language classes? I know you are<lb/>not allowed the necesary text books for<lb/>these, but I suppose you conduct oral classes.  Now that we have got definitely into touch<lb/>with your Committee I hope we shall hear from you frequent-<lb/>ly, so that we may be kept informed of your requirements.<lb/>We are constantly receiving enquiries from relatives and 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3987_img_3374_4"/>
             4.<lb/>and friends of the prisoners.  With best wishes to you and your companions<lb/>from our committee.   Yours sincerely,     Hon. Secretary.   P.S. Re your request for Mr MacDonagh's address, he has<lb/>recently moved and I cannot give the address offhand. I<lb/>am sending it to a mutual friend, asking him to forward it,  (2) Can you give me any news of N.T. Murray 1091?<lb/>His brother has written enquiring about him,<lb/>saying he has not heard from him for several<lb/>weeks.  (3) Has O'Sullivan, who was in hospital in Staffs,<lb/>come on to Frongoch yet?  I. John<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>Irish Prison of wAR 200<lb/>Frongoch. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>