<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0776">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Lillian Spender, 27 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender gives an account of his settling into his new position and his workload. He discusses the local surroundings, the character of the Corps Commander, and his own recent promotion, which he believes will be only temporary.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/362</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/776</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0776_img_2309_1"  type="NULL"  url="3ab8aa500bdb3f1b5823fd014ddab1ae.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0776_img_2309_2"  type="NULL"  url="76b510c613450f2f7a5c9fb3b09463ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0776_img_2309_3"  type="NULL"  url="a7c3290e2408117cfa3dfdb6e2b3ae5b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0776_img_2309_4"  type="NULL"  url="3c2b50ddb9f57dbfe9b10f8879533db9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0776_img_2309_1"/>
                July 27   My Pr,   For some reason I did not <lb/> sleep very well last night &amp; had <lb/> to make an <seg type="del">very</seg> early rise to drive <lb/> up to the German lines so am not <lb/>in a <seg type="del">pos</seg> con dition to write much.  Gradually I am picking up my <lb/> work but it is still indefinite <lb/>&amp; of course in a new area am <lb/> feels strange tho' it is not quite <lb/>as new country as the North <lb/> was. No letter for 3 days <lb/>a very hungry b w.   Last night &amp; this morning <lb/> I was up at a Captured German <lb/>village which has been very <lb/>much in evidence lately, A more <lb/> mournful sight one has never <lb/>seen debris dust debris dust <lb/>Pompeii was not in it with <lb/>this. <seg type="unclear">The</seg> are relieving <seg type="unclear">function</seg> was  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0776_img_2309_2"/>
              <lb/>no man's land where many young <lb/> rather uncommon wildflowers <lb/> had taken the chance of man's <lb/> absence to start a home. Rather <lb/> a mistake I'm afraid as it <lb/> will soon be as dusty &amp; <lb/> full as the rest of the country.   My Corps Commander is Gen <lb/> Horn, who has a big reputation <lb/> as a strong man, probably <lb/> rather silent. I have seen <lb/> little of him but have been <lb/> moved to the A mess today <lb/> so shall see more presumably.  I fancy I am more or <lb/>less under trial &amp; may find <lb/>myself being transferred to <lb/> a Division if not found wanting.   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0776_img_2309_3"/>
              I am most anxious not to <lb/>supersede the proper GSO 2 who <lb/>is an excellent chap - a senior <lb/>major - . I may not give <lb/>satisfaction here in which case <lb/>I shall drop back to Capt. <lb/>again, like many others- to <lb/>major - <seg type="unclear">Nonewhich</seg> I do <lb/>my best when people <lb/>call out. Colonel not to <lb/> show that I think <lb/> they are addressing  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0776_img_2309_4"/>
              someone else, &amp; not to jump when <lb/> Sentries present arms.   Must fly back to <lb/>the office. <seg type="closer"> Your  b w <lb/> WB Spender  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>