<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5496">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty to Sir Roger Casement, 6 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from the Dominican priest Fr. Thomas Crotty (d. 1930, born James but took the name Thomas after he joined the order) to Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916). The letter was written during Casement&#39;s eighteen month stay in Germany, where he was attempting to gain German support for an Irish rebellion against British rule. The letter refers to Casement&#39;s attempts to create an Irish Brigade of Irish-born British army soldiers who were then held as prisoners of war in German camps. It was the camp at Linberg, in the Lahn valley, that was designated for the project. Fr.

 Crotty was one of the priests who administered to the men in the camp at Limberg. The project was, however, largely unsuccessful and only fifty-six men signed up. Crotty mentions in the letter that Robert Monteith, the officer in charge of the Irish Brigade, &#39;hasn&#39;t much hope of succeeding&#39; in Limberg but would do what he could to convince people of his views.

Casement was later arrested in County Kerry having returned to Ireland in a submarine to try and prevent the Easter Rising from taking place as he felt German support was insufficient. He was hanged in London in August 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,085 /20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5496</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0444">Fr. Thomas (James) Crotty</persName>
              <date>1915-11-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0529">Limberg, Lahn, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Roger Casement</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0840">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1930</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5496_img_529_1"  type="Letter"  url="3687f9576c031edf0b34bf6f5e75db4c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5496_img_529_1"/>
             Limburg a/ Lahn   6.Nov.15   <hi rend="underline">Monteith</hi>   Dear Sir Roger    Just in my way to camp I received your <lb/> kind letter. Had a visit Thursday last from <lb/>a friend who was but a short time ago with you. <lb/> He hasn't much hopes of succeeding here, although <lb/> he shall do what he can to convince them of <lb/> his views of things.    Wrote last Wednesday to M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Meyer, and <lb/>asked to get the permission to visit all the <lb/> camps or some of them. No reply yet. If you <lb/> should meet him. please remind him of my <lb/> letter, lest he should forget to acknowledge it.    The 14 men who came from Labau were sent <lb/>away again, I believe to Giersen. No more of the <lb/> early departures are come back as I expected. <lb/> Many of those who want to work in the farms <lb/> are now here, and soon I hope the rest shall <lb/>return.    The "Continental Times" still comes, and from time <lb/> to time the American Journals which <lb/> come directly from you.   Excuse haste   With kind regards <lb/>Yours v. sincerely   Fr T.Crotty O.B.   R. in Berlin <lb/> 8 Nov./15. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>