<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4322">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frederick Stringer Wrench to Edward Carson, 15 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frederick Stringer Wrench</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Frederick Stringer Wrench (1849-1926) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Wrench was an Irish Land Comissioner, deputy lieutenant and privy councillor. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/16</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4322</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0793">Frederick Stringer Wrench</persName>
              <date>1916-06-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0083">Irish Land Commission, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1926</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4322_img_3682_1"  type="Letter"  url="5d72a35eb7f87e896ec867bd59a1a91d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4322_img_3682_2"  type="Letter"  url="b5fd045dd81eda83774dd52187ffb47b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4322_img_3682_3"  type="Letter"  url="83c11ca780e758adbac911f62963fa01.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4322_img_3682_1"/>
             IRISH LAND COMMISSION <lb/>DUBLIN   15 June 1916.   My dear Carson,   I congratulate you <lb/>on the result of the Ulster <lb/>Convention - it was <lb/>admirably managed from <lb/>Start to finish. puts <lb/>the Ulstermen in an <lb/>excellent position before <lb/>the Empire, &amp; puts <lb/>the Nationalists in <lb/>a hole. Asquith as <lb/>usual is confusing the
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4322_img_3682_2"/>
            issue, as when I saw <lb/>him the word "provisional" <lb/>was not in Lloyd George's <lb/>mind, &amp; he said more <lb/>than once that there <lb/>was to be no time limit <lb/>whatever to the exclusion <lb/>of the Ulster Counties.   No one can say now <lb/>what will happen, but <lb/>in case it is found impossible <lb/>to bring off a permanent <lb/>Settlement, I enclose <lb/>a copy of a short memo: <lb/>that I wrote before it was <lb/>announced that Lloyd George <lb/>(in whom I have great <lb/>faith) was to be the <lb/>mediator.   To say that the machinery <lb/>of Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> in Ireland has <lb/>broken down is nonsense, <lb/>it was the absolute incapacity <lb/>of the individuals who <lb/>filled the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> posts that <lb/>caused all the trouble, <lb/>&amp; I am still of
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4322_img_3682_3"/>
            <lb/>opinion that there w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> <lb/>be no more than the ordinary <lb/>difficulty of governing the <lb/>Country, if a good Chief <lb/>Sec<hi rend="superscript">ty</hi>or Secretary of State <lb/>was appointed, with a Council <lb/>of sensible men to advise <lb/>him. However there is <lb/>nothing to be done now <lb/>until the Nationalists <lb/>reveal their intention.    Very sincerely   <hi rend="underline">Fred<hi rend="superscript">k</hi> Wrench.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>