<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3996">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward Carson to Thomas McGregor Greer, 12 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Carson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Edward Carson (1854–1935) to Thomas McGregor Greer (1875–1949) chiefly about army recruitment in  County Tyrone, but also lamenting the  &#39;late deplorable rebellion in Ireland&#39;. 

Carson was a lawyer and a politician. In 1916 he was at the peak of his parliamentary influence. It was in 1916 that he accepted the first lordship of the admiralty. Carson was also a leading unionist figure in Irish politics. He sanctioned the formation of the paramilitary Ulster Volunteer Force in January 1913; and he helped to found the Ulster provisional government of September 1913. 

Thomas Greer was an entomologist and pioneer motorcyclist. His family was connected to many of the gentry families in the area of Tullylaggan, Co. Tyrone. He was educated at Bath, and worked as a land surveyor (1890–94) and an electrical engineer (1899–1900). The letter comments on the &#39;late deplorable rebellion in Ireland&#39; and discusses the army recruitment in County Tyrone.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Papers of the Alexander, Greer, and Lowry families D4121/C/1/1/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3996</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date>1916-07-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0880">5 Eaton Place, S.W.,  London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas McGregor Greer</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1847">Tullyhogue, Tullylagan, Co. Tyrone, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1935</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3996_img_3383_1"  type="Letter"  url="6ec290fa3bedb83f2aa29916d32b8eea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3996_img_3383_2"  type="Letter"  url="0027ef19c0e8a529d1f4a07c19e560c2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3996_img_3383_1"/>
             5 Eaton Place <lb/>S.W.   12th July, 1916   Dear Mr. Greer,   I am very pleased to hear that at the request of the <lb/>officers commanding the 9th and 10th Inniskillings you are <lb/>taking up the question of recruiting for these battalions <lb/>in the County of Tyrone. Our old friends and comrades of <lb/>the 36th (Ulster) Division have brought undying fame to <lb/>Ulster and the Empire, and it is the plain duty of those <lb/>of their fellow countrymen who can do so to help to carry <lb/>on the War, and to follow the example that they so nobly <lb/>Inaugurated. We must take care that that work has not <lb/>been in vain, by sending men out to fill the place of our <lb/>fallen heroes, and it would indeed be a lamentable chapter <lb/>in the history of this great Division if, by reason  of the <lb/>sacrifices so willingly made, we were unable to take part <lb/>in the final triumph and victory which assuredly waits us <lb/>if every man will do his duty. I know that many of our <lb/>friends are naturally anxious for the safety and welfare <lb/>of their families by reason of the late deplorable rebellion <lb/>in Ireland, and the inadequate protection that was afforde
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3996_img_3383_2"/>
            through the laxity of the Government, but I think they may <lb/>be assured that the Government is now fully alive to the <lb/>elementary duty of protecting all those who are loyal in <lb/>Ireland, and I have been assured that every step will be <lb/>taken that is necessary to prevent such outrages in the <lb/>future.  The promise of the exclusion of the six counties, in— <lb/>cluding County Tyrone, from the operation of the Home Rule <lb/>Act is an additional reason why we should wholeheartedly <lb/>throw in our lot with all those who place country before <lb/>party, and have firmly set themselves to see this War through <lb/>to a successful conclusion.   I remain <lb/>Yours sincerely,   Edward Carson   T. Macgregor Greer, Esq.  <lb/>Tullyhogue <lb/>Tullylagan, <lb/>Co. Tyrone 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>