<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4618">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Chrystal to Andrew Philip Magill, 14 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Chrystal</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from George Chrystal of the Home Office in London to Andrew Philip Magill (1871-1941), private secretary to the Chief Secretary for Ireland (Augustine Birrell). The letter encloses an amended order of a regulation under the Defence of the Realm Act regarding a weekly half-holiday for employees in the liquor industry.
The Defence of the Realm Act was passed in 1914 for the United Kingdom to give the government extensive powers during the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>CSO RP/1916/6821/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4618</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0361">George Chrystal</persName>
              <date>1916-04-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0856">Home Office, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0014">Andrew Philip Magill</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4618_img_396_1"  type="Letter"  url="0dd715c3add149459dec26c1cd7ed4b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4618_img_396_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="1b9ae9886dae0cb1a3750de57241d5cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4618_img_396_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="cd73d233432e69f66921feb945119c13.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4618_img_396_1"/>
             14th April, 1916.   Dear Magill,   With reference to my note of 25th February<lb/>forwarding a copy of a Regulation under the Defence of the<lb/>Realm Act about weekly half-holidays for liquor trade<lb/>employees, I now send you a copy of an amended Order on<lb/>the same subject, together with the  accompanying  Home Office Circular<lb/>to the Local Authorities, which explain themselves.   Yours sincerely,    George Chrystal <lb/>A.P. Magill Esq. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4618_img_396_2"/>
            <lb/>AT THE COURT AT BUCKINGHAM PALACE, <lb/>The  30th day of March, 1916.  <lb/>PRESENT: <lb/>THE KING'S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY IN <lb/>COUNCIL.  WHEREAS by an Order in Council dated the tenth day of <lb/>June, nineteen hundred and fifteen, His Majesty was <lb/>pleased to make Regulations (called the Defence of the Realm <lb/>(Liquor Control) Regulations, 1915) under the Defence of the <lb/>Realm Consolidation Act, 1914, and to issue the same in <lb/>pursuance of the Defence of the Realm Amendment (No. 3) <lb/>Act, 1915, to take effect in any area to which they should be <lb/>applied under the said Amendment Act.   And whereas His Majesty have been pleased to apply the <lb/>said Regulations and any Regulations amending the same to <lb/>divers areas by Orders in Council made under the said Amend- <lb/>ment Act:   And whereas the said Regulations have been amended by <lb/>Orders in Council dated the fourteenth day of October, nineteen <lb/>hundred and fifteen, and the fifteenth day of February, nineteen <lb/>hundred and sixteen:   And whereas it is expedient further to amend the said <lb/>Regulations in manner hereinafter appearing:   NOW, THEREFORE, His Majesty is pleased, by and with the <lb/>advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered <lb/>as follows:—   The said Order in Council of the fifteenth day of February, <lb/>nineteen hundred and sixteen, is hereby revoked, and for the <lb/>paragraph which by that Order was directed to be inserted at <lb/>the end of Regulation 2 the following paragraph shall be <lb/>substituted:   "Where by an Order of the Board the sale of <lb/>intoxicating liquor in licensed premises in any area is <lb/>42—2 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4618_img_396_3"/>
             (2)<lb/>restricted to a total of five and a half hours a day, or<lb/>less, the weekly half-holiday required to be given to the<lb/>assistants employed in such premises under section 1 of<lb/>the Shops Act, 1912, may in the case of assistants whose<lb/>employment is wholly or mainly in connection with the<lb/>sale of intoxication liquor, begin not later than three<lb/>instead of half-past one o'clock in the afternoon, but this<lb/>provision shall not apply to any licensed premises in<lb/>which any such assistant is employed for more then<lb/>sixty-five hours in any week exclusive of meal times.  <lb/>ALMERIC FITZROY.  <lb/>Printed by EYRE and SPOTTISWOODE, Ltd.,<lb/>Printers to the KIng's most Excellent Majesty. 1916.<lb/>For His Majesty's Stationery Office. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>