<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4373">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from David Lloyd George to Edward Carson, 14 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>David Lloyd George</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from David Lloyd George (1863-1945) to  Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.. Lloyd George served as Minister of Munitions during the Shell Crisis of 1915. His role as Minister won him wide-spread support across Britain. He took over the role of Secretary of State for War on 6 June 1916, after the death of Horatio Herbert Kitchener, (1850–1916) who died on board the cruiser HMS Hampshire when it was sunk by a German mine on 5 June 1916, while on course to Russia. Following the collapse of Asquith&#39;s government, Lloyd George became Prime Minister of the coalition government in December 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/19/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4373</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0876">David Lloyd George</persName>
              <date>1916-10-14</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1945</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4373_img_3728_1"  type="Letter"  url="40981b97d6c4e6a6364a844f89059870.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4373_img_3728_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="3538670bf886b1c937ff56c71ad656a1.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4373_img_3728_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="39b5d254494a56e0c059a491ed4523c9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4373_img_3728_1"/>
             October 14th., 1916   My dear Carson,   I enclose copy of a letter which the Adjutant <lb/>General has just received from the General in Command of <lb/>the Ulster Division. You can if you like communicate it <lb/>privately to the Ulster representatives.   Ever sincerely,    <hi rend="underline">D Lloyd George</hi>    The Rt. Hon. Sir Edward Carson., K.C., M.P. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4373_img_3728_2"/>
              H. Q. <lb/>36th. Division <lb/>B.E.F.   October 6th., 19   My dear General,    You may remember telling me that Carson had said he <lb/> would prefer to see the Ulster Division absorbed in a Highland <lb/>Division instead of seeing them amalgamated with the 16th.   I have thought this over, and I am sure it would <lb/>be disastrous from the point of view of Ireland.   It would mean the complete disappearance of 2 <lb/>Irish Divisions and it would be read as an admission that <lb/>the two Irish Divisions could not combine, that Irish creeds <lb/> <sic>andpolitics</sic> were carried into the fighting line.   It would be a libel on both Divisions. There are <lb/>no politics whatever and I am sure there could be no better <lb/>cure for Irish home troubles than that Protestants and <lb/>Catholics should fight together in the same unit.   If we do get compulsory Service in Ireland, I <lb/>sincerely hope the Ulster Division will not be exclusively <lb/>supplied from one creed. I hope that all creeds and politics <lb/>will be drafted into it. It will then be really representative
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4373_img_3728_3"/>
            and not as at present with too much flavour of t which <lb/>is I hope dead and buried.   If however the question of amalgamation becomes <lb/>imperative, I hope the 16th. and 36th. will be amalgamated so <lb/>that there may be at least one Irish Division.   I am sure that this will be the view of Officers and <lb/>men of both Divisions and I have written to Carson to tell <lb/>him so.   Believe me, <lb/>Your sincerely, <lb/>(ad) O.S. Nugent. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>