<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0710">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Rev Robert Kelso to Mrs.Rankin, 10 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Kelso</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Next of kin letter to Mrs Rankin whose son Ian died of wounds in a Canadian Hospital from the Rev Robert Kelso, Principal Chaplain&#39;s Dept,Bologne Base, B.E.F. France. Rev Kelso advises that Ian had initially showed signs of recovery but then relapsed and died without much pain or suffering. He offered his sympathy and stated that the doctors and nurses had done everything possible for her son but she was one of many mothers called upon to make the great sacrifice. He hoped and prayed that she would find the strength to bear the strain. He gave details of the burial in France on 6/10/16 grave# 4026.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Kelso Papers, D3019/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/710</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0887">Robert Kelso</persName>
              <date>1916-10-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0024">Principal Chaplain Department, Boulogne Base, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs Rankin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2053">226 Poulton Rd, Seacombe, Cheshire, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0710_img_2209_1"  type="Letter"  url="89c707a1e5dc163bc56b6f2bd80dfd1b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0710_img_2209_1"/>
             <seg type="head"> Centred at top of page Serg. Geo Burns (8641) <lb/>2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Canadians </seg>   Mrs Burns, 74 Paisley Rd.  Renfrew  <hi rend="underline">Scotland</hi>    Principal Chaplains Dept  Boulogne Base  B.E.F.France    9 10 '16.   Dear Mrs Burns   I am sure you will have heard the <lb/>sad news of your son's death &amp; I feel I must write to say <lb/> how much I feel for you in your loss. After my last <lb/> letter <seg type="del">you</seg> to  you he was so much better that he said he <lb/> had written you himself so I did not do so. I thought <lb/>he was on the sure road to recovery &amp; I was terribly <lb/>disappointed when he suddenly became worse &amp; passed <lb/>away. He was in such good spirits &amp; so confident <lb/>of recovery that the relapse was — to me — as unexpected <lb/> as it was sudden. He was buried in the Military <lb/>Cemetery here — on 8 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi><seg type="del">Sept</seg> Oct. with full Military Honours <lb/>&amp; the number of the grave is 4039. The <sic>Authoritie</sic><lb/>will send you a photo of the grave on application to <lb/> 'Director of Graves Registration &amp; Enquiries, War Office, <lb/> Winchester House, St James' Sq. London S.W.' but <lb/> it may be a little time before they can reply to you. <lb/>Will you please accept my sincerest sympathy &amp; believe <lb/> me when I say that everything possible was done for your <lb/> son's comfort and welfare while in Hospital. He has <lb/> made the Great Sacrifice &amp; such a life and death as his must <lb/> surely be well-pleasing in the sight of Him who said <lb/> 'Greater Love Hath no man than this that a man lay down <lb/> his life for his friends.'   A line is missing here. <seg type="closer"> Sincerely Yours  R Kelso </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>