<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1996">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Robert Anderson to Sir Matthew Nathan, 15 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Robert Anderson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Robert Anderson (b. 1860), the honorary secretary of the Irish Association of Volunteer Training Corps, to Sir Matthew Nathan. Nathan (1862-1939) was the under-secretary for Ireland from 1914 to 1916. In 1916 Nathan offered his resignation following the outbreak of the Easter Rising.
The IAVTC were a corps consisting of men who were over age or engaged in important occupations and therefore could not enlist for wartime service when war broke out in 1914. This was a volunteering training militia that came to be known by the nickname &#39;Gorgeous Wrecks&#39; due to the G.R. armbands they wore symbolizing Georgius Rex.
This letter and its enclosures concerns the passing of five resolutions adopted by various volunteer training corps around the country.  The resolutions arise out of the committee&#39;s concern that corps will be forced to shut down due to a lack of duties to perform and therefore to hold their members together. Its states that Every member is willing to take the oath of allegiance and to conform to military law and discipline and details activities that the corps have already partaken in, such as assisting at railway stations. The author also suggests forms of employments for the volunteers to undertake such as the guarding of munitions factories. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7964/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1996</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0902">Robert Anderson</persName>
              <date>1916-04-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0481">18 South Frederick Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1306">Matthew Nathan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_1"  type="Letter"  url="5497a798853d4278d822798f0c5a03ab.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_2"  type="Letter"  url="b0c51e21037b59924ffb207c47ce4fed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_3"  type="Letter"  url="2cf151725ff2c23e7bcedfb999002ed9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_4"  type="Letter"  url="e525ba82b1c41d72ffce83b0dfa0460d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_5"  type="Letter"  url="3941f6c2369967950b523d6d83a406a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="da74728051ea8642f5a6dd6b99d960b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_7"  type="Enclosure"  url="c7936a040a13508a613721f9fcaaed04.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1996_img_1443_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="c0214a1da11e882f2e568453fea0a86e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_1"/>
            IRISH ASSOCIATION OF VOLUNTEER TRAINING CORPS. <lb/>(Authorised by the Government as the recognised Central Body of all affiliated <lb/>Volunteer Training Corps in Ireland.) <hi rend="underline">Telephone -Dublin 4772</hi>  18 South Frederick Street,<lb/>Dublin.   15th April, 1916. Sir,   I am directed by the Executive Committee of this <lb/> Association to transmit herewith for the information of His <lb/> Majesty's Government in Ireland copies of five resolutions <lb/> which have been unanimously adopted by the undermentioned <lb/> affiliated Volunteer Training Corps and forwarded to the <lb/> Association, accompanied, in each case, by an urgent letter <lb/> requesting that prompt action in the direction indicated <lb/> should be taken. The Corps referred to are: -  (1) Belfast Volunteer Defence Corps. <lb/>(2) City of Cork Volunteer Training Corps. <lb/>(3) Irish Rugby Football Union Volunteer Corps. <lb/>(4) Queen's University (Belfast) 'Veterans' Volunteer Corps. <lb/>(5) Rathmines Volunteer Training Corps.    2. While the resolutions of a similar character have not, <lb/> so far, been received from the other affiliated Corps the <lb/>Committee are aware that the accompanying resolutions <lb/>reflect accurately and without exception the views of the <lb/>entire body of affiliated Corps. As a matter of fact one Corps - The Howth &amp; Sutton Volunteer Training Corps, quite <lb/>an excellent and efficient unit raised shortly after the <lb/>outbreak of the War — has actually disbanded in consequence <lb/> of the failure to obtain any duty for its members. The <lb/>Committee are apprehensive that other Corps, finding themselves <lb/>in a similar position and being unable to hold their members <lb/>together, may also disband. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_2"/>
             3. The Committee are fully aware that, under the existing <lb/><lb/> law, it is impossible, at the present time, to hope for or expect <lb/> the same full measure of recognition for Irish Volunteer Training <lb/> Corps as has been accorded to kindred bodies in Great Britain. <lb/>Their earnest desire is to help and not hinder the Authorities, <lb/> and their sole plea is for such a measure of recognition as would <lb/> entitle the affiliated Corps to discharge such functions and duties <lb/> as may be preformed by such bodies of men and to do so not merely on <lb/> sufferance but with the express sanction and authority of the Military <lb/> Authorities. the Committee desire me to state that, where these <lb/> duties require the members of the affiliated Corps to act under <lb/> military discipline, every member so employed is prepared not only <lb/> to take the Oath of Allegiance but also to conform in every respect <lb/> to military law and discipline which it has been one of the principal <lb/> aims of the Affiliated Corps to inculcate.   4. It may be of interest to state that all the affiliated <lb/> Corps in and around Dublin have, for some time back, been under <lb/>taking a duty which has earned the approval of the General Officer <lb/> Commanding the Troops in Ireland. This duty consists in detailing <lb/> parties of picked men to attend at the North Wall and other Railway <lb/> termini in Dublin, there to assist the various civilian organisations <lb/> which have been created to deal with the needs of, and lend assistance <lb/> to, wounded soldiers and sailors and those going on, or returning <lb/> from furlough. Parties are furnished daily to meet boats and <lb/> trains and the reports received encourage the Committee to believe <lb/> that the services rendered by the Corps in this connection are much <lb/> appreciated alike by the organisations referred to and the men <lb/> whom it is designed to help. This duty, which involves the <lb/> meeting of long distance boats and trains at early hours in the <lb/> morning and also late at night and, in some instances, providing
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_3"/>
            means of transport by motor car, are most cheerfully <lb/> and enthusiastically carried out by our men. In no case <lb/> does their work conflict in any way with that of the <lb/> Transport Officers and their men.   5. So far, this is the only employment which has been <lb/> entrusted to the affiliated Corps, and it has been undertaken <lb/> at the request of civilian organisations and not of the <lb/> Military Authorities, although it has earned the approval of <lb/> the latter. It is obvious that this duty can only engage <lb/> the services of a very limited number of men, preferably, those <lb/> who have by experience familiarised themselves with all its <lb/> details and are specially qualified for it as it demands more <lb/> than ordinary tact, discretion and good temper.   6. The Committee feel sure that, in a city like Dublin, <lb/> there must be other duties in which the Volunteer Training Corps <lb/> could take a useful part. Their members are only too anxious <lb/> to be employed by the Authorities. The guarding of munition <lb/> factories, for example, might be delegated to them. The <lb/> Committee are also assured that the members of the affiliated <lb/> Corps would, almost to a man, be prepared to act as Special <lb/> Constables if so required, and they submit that a force of <lb/> several hundred experienced and disciplined citizens might <lb/> be of the greatest utility in case of emergency.   7. It will be seen, however, that, in order to keep <lb/> such a force in readiness, it is absolutely necessary to maintain <lb/> in the various Corps a certain degree of cohesion, efficiency <lb/> and discipline and, if no hopes that such employment under the <lb/> properly controlled Authority can be held out there is a <lb/> serious danger that the Corps <lb/> may grow weary and disperse by degrees.   8. There is, further, a reason which the Committee think <lb/> in itself justifies the existence and maintenance of these Corps <lb/> in a state of effectiveness. They have partially trained and have <lb/> sent to the Army and Navy almost every eligible member who was on
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_4"/>
            their <sic>rolls</sic> at their inception  and  they have stimulated, both <lb/> actively and by example, recruiting in Dublin.   9. The Corps affiliated to the Association have, through <lb/> it, bee recognised by the Irish Government as bodies entitled <lb/> to wear the uniform prescribed for Volunteer Training Corps <lb/> in Great Britain, and are authorised to wear the "G.R." brassard <lb/> which is issued by the War Office. They have been given <lb/> authority to bear arms. They have been afforded the use of <lb/> military barracks as headquarters and as drill and parade grounds. <lb/> They enjoy the services of a Military Advisor appointed by the <lb/> Lord Lieutenant. They have been inspected and highly complimented <lb/> by the G.O. Commanding Troops in Ireland. They have been <lb/> reviewed by His Excellency Lord Wimborne who has also done the <lb/> Association the honour to become its President.    10. Neither the Association nor any of its constituent <lb/> bodies have any political affiliations or aims. The Corps <lb/> are open to member ship to any man who is prepared to comply <lb/> with the nine conditions laid down by the Irish Government. <lb/> The sole aim of every member is to serve the State according <lb/> to his ability and in any capacity that may be assigned to <lb/> him and, in order to do so efficiently, every man has made <lb/> considerable sacrifices in time, in work and in money. The <lb/> Committee, therefore venture to express the hope that the <lb/> Irish Government may speedily find some way of utilising <lb/> the services of the Volunteer Training Corps in such a manner <lb/> as will not only encourage the present members to persevere <lb/> but also to increase their numbers and improve their present <lb/> high standard of efficiency. Even if it be not possible <lb/> at present to use the Corps in any of the ways indicated, <lb/> the Committee would respectfully suggest to the Irish
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_5"/>
            Government that a statement might be made that, in the <lb/> event of any emergency arising, the claims of the Corps <lb/> to be actively employed would be considered.   I have the honour to be <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant,   R. Anderson  <lb/>Hon. Secretary.  Lt. Colonel, <lb/>The Right Honourable Sir Matthew Nathan, G.C.M.G., <lb/>Under Secretary for Ireland, <lb/>Dublin Castle. 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_6"/>
            <hi rend="underline">IRISH ASSOCIATION OF VOLUNTEER TRAINING CORPS.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Resolutions adopted by affiliated Corp <lb/>s with regard to recognition.</hi>  1. Belfast Volunteer Defence Corps: - <lb/>"That this Council approach the Central Association <lb/> and other affiliated Corps, to ask them to join us in a deputation <lb/> to the Victory of Irelaand to ask for recognition by the <lb/> Government."   2. City of Cork Volunteer Training Corps: - <lb/>"That the City of Cork Volunteer Training Corps, <lb/> as an affiliated unit of the Irish Association of Volunteer Training <lb/> Corps, most earnestly requests the central organisation to use <lb/> every possible means to impress upon the Government our claim to <lb/> receive the same recognition and status as has been accorded to <lb/> similar bodies in England and Scotland.   We feel that our Corps is capable of doing good and <lb/> useful work in the service of our Country.   We have striven patiently and loyally to fit ourselves <lb/> for the discharge of such duties as may be entrusted to us, in <lb/> full confidence of receiving such recognition and encouragement <lb/> as would justify the expenditure of valuable time and money in <lb/> training our members.   We feel that the matter is now urgent and that the <lb/> efforts which we have made deserve the encouragement or some <lb/> assurance that our services will be practically utilised should <lb/> occasion arise. We feel deeply the importance at the present <lb/> moment of fostering, particularly in this country, the spirit <lb/> which has animated the members of our Corps, and we respectfully
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_7"/>
            suggest that some means be found to grant us a status similar <lb/> to that accorded to cognate bodies in other parts of the United <lb/> Kingdom."   3. Irish Rugby Football Union Volunteer Corps; - <lb/>"That the Committee of the Irish Rugby Football <lb/> Union Volunteer Corps desire to call the attention of the <lb/> Executive Committee of the Irish Association Volunteer Training <lb/> Corps to the fact that this Corps has now been in existence since <lb/> August 1914 and has attained an admitted efficiency for military <lb/> duties in the nature of home defence; That they desire to <lb/> urge upon the Executive Committee of the Irish Association <lb/> Volunteer Training Corps the necessity of pressing upon the <lb/> Government that a definite statement should be made as <lb/>to whether there is any likelihood of any such duties being <lb/> assigned to them, otherwise the Committee fears that the <lb/> existence of the Corps will be endangered."    4. Queen's University (Belfast) Veteran's Volunteer <lb/> Training Corps; - <lb/> " That the I.A.V.T.C., be requested to ascertain from <lb/> the Government whether there is any prospect of this Corps being <lb/> recognised in the same way as the Central Association in England, <lb/> and of its being utilised on the lines originally suggested, <sic>vix; -</sic> <lb/> For the performance of such military duties in Ireland as would <lb/> set free for Active Service as equivalent force of regular <lb/> soldiers."   5. Rathmines Volunteer Training Corps; - <lb/>"That the Irish Association of Volunteer Training Corps
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1996_img_1443_8"/>
            be asked to ascertain from the Irish Government whether there <lb/> is any prospect of this Corps being utilised on the lines <lb/> originally suggested, viz: - For the performance of such <lb/> military duties in Ireland as would set free for active <lb/> service an equivalent force of regular soldiers." 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>