<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4141">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 5 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/46</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4141</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-05</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4141_img_3516_1"  type="Letter"  url="7ac81aa40eb060f029f90575d6261c64.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4141_img_3516_2"  type="Letter"  url="56cae901bcf5695098eb252da1974126.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4141_img_3516_3"  type="Letter"  url="d0df08e9b87996de73c6af65cd2b2062.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4141_img_3516_4"  type="Letter"  url="845fa22e653c9d5784c6cd62b6bca3b3.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4141_img_3516_1"/>
             A letter from <lb/>Hugh Spender <lb/>will be forwarded <lb/>tomorrow.   I believe that <lb/>I am responsible for <lb/>the rule about <lb/>the promotion of staff <lb/>officers. This is <lb/>bad luck on the <lb/>others!   Nov 5 . 1915   If the p were here she would pretend to <lb/>tremble, for the b w is still growling fiercely at his mail of yesterday. Luckily there were other <lb/>letters, &amp; as these have to be answered—which is hardly the case with the scrap ! — I shall cut <lb/>this down.   I have had a certain amount of intercourse with Gen Nugent lately. We are both pretty grim <lb/>&amp; kind of walk round each other, but there has been no outburst <hi rend="underline">yet</hi>. It will come, &amp; may <lb/>clear the air. Everyone else  nearly has had one. He is <lb/>not in the best of tempers as he &amp; the new Gen'
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4141_img_3516_2"/>
            Allenby are not much in the way of friends, <lb/>quite au contraire I believe! A characteristic <lb/>outburst occurred yesterday at teatime when there <lb/>was only Indian tea. We all very busily <lb/>made conversation but the China tea could <lb/>not be suppressed &amp; came up like a volcano <lb/>every now &amp; then.   I saw H P yesterday &amp; and begin to think he <lb/>may not be sorry to go. If it is that he <lb/>realizes that he is <seg type="unclear">unfitted</seg> as I hope, it is <lb/>all right, but if it is simply that the trench <lb/>life does not appeal to the inner man as <lb/>those with him think, well...!    It is almost time for Chichester to come back
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4141_img_3516_3"/>
            but really I do not expect him, tho' I think it <lb/>would be a good thing for him to come &amp; be found <lb/>out. Otherwise he will have some well thought <lb/>out excuse to veneer his position in Ulster later.   I have written to Col Wallace saying I <lb/>hoped Rex would go to his new battalion as I <lb/>did not want him out here till the spring. <lb/>Rex I know would not stand the winter in <lb/>the trenches but when next spring comes he <lb/>must of course take his chance.   The service I think is excellent &amp; <lb/>Col Russell ought to be pleased at this <lb/>form of flattery which Richardson has also <lb/>adopted. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4141_img_3516_4"/>
             Russel is not quite well &amp; it says <lb/>much for his manners that he is just as <lb/>nice as ever.   As you give me no length of visit to <lb/>Rugby this letter will go to 29 to a very <lb/>very spoilt p r.   I am longing to hear the result of your <lb/>visit to Reading &amp; to know whether you have been to <lb/>Lady Carson's or not yet, &amp; what you are <lb/>going to do , but I am <hi rend="underline">not</hi>impatient for <lb/>a decision only to know the decision when made <lb/>which need not be for another month.   Still a little love left for a very very spoilt <lb/>p r from the  B W. W.BSpender    P.S.Note that Walter M's letter>is for <seg type="unclear">certain</seg>. I think I should have <lb/>liked the spectator but it's not quite fair on your  perhaps.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>