<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2814">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Henry Charles Fitzmaurice to Lady Londonderry, 9 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Henry Charles Fitzmaurice</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence belonging to Lady Londonderry, a large proportion of which concerns Sir Edward Carson and opposition to the Third Home Rule Bill. Lady Londonderry was a prominent figure in politics and high-society from 1890 until 1919. Her correspondence includes many important figures in literature, the arts, the military, law and the church. 

This letter was written by Henry Charles Keith Petty Fitzmaurice, fifth marquess of Lansdowne (1845-1927). Lansdowne was a prominent British politician who served in the wartime coalition ministry of H.H. Asquith. Lansdowne came to believe that victory in the war was impossible and his views of the matter led to the collapse of the government in December 1916. On 29 November 1917 he published his views in the &#39;Lansdowne Letter&#39;. 

The letter is addressed to Lady Londonderry (1856 - 1919), the wife of Charles Stewart Vane-Tempest-Stewart (1852 - 1915), sixth marquess of Londonderry. Lady Londonderry was also an active figure in British politics.

This letter concerns appointments and arrangements to have lunch when Lady Londonderry next visits London.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Londonderry Papers, D2846/2/21/64</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2814</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0663">Henry Charles Fitzmaurice</persName>
              <date>1916-02-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2100">Lansdowne House, Berkley Square, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Theresa Vane-Tempest Stewart</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1927</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2814_img_2230_1"  type="Letter"  url="6aee15043cca3b9386f12c31a4ded050.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2814_img_2230_1"/>
             Lansdowne House <lb/>  Berkeley Square, W.  <lb/>  9. Feb 16   Dear Lady Londonderry   Shaftesbury would I fancy<lb/> naturally came in front of <seg type="unclear">Stavy</seg>, and<lb/> his candidature is backed by Portman.<lb/> the county council and others. paragraph   But Shaftesbury is already <seg type="unclear">L⌃L: <!-- Likely is an abbreviation of Lord Lieutenant--></seg> of<lb/> an Irish county, and there is a doubt<lb/> whether he could hold the two, altho' <lb/> Devonshire was L⌃L: for Derbyshire and for<lb/> Waterford - I told the P.M. that I<lb/> thought <seg type="unclear">Stavy</seg> might certainly be appointed<lb/> if the objection to Shaftesbury prevails - I<lb/> shall not be sorry if it does. Until I<lb/> heard from you I did not know that<lb/> <seg type="unclear">Stavy</seg> was in the field.   When are you coming to London?<lb/>You will find us here, and delighted<lb/> to give you luncheon if you should be<lb/> passing through.   Yours ever <lb/> Lansdowne
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>