<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2257">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to John Ross, 27 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924) to John Ross. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
This letter deals with Montgomery&#39;s opinions on the Irish Question and a letter that he had drafted to send to the &#39;Times&#39; newspaper. He also refers to Sir Edward Carson, the Ulster Unionist leader, having said the right thing &#39;for the moment&#39; and the difficulties of Carson&#39;s position.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2257</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1339">John Ross</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2257_img_1700_1"  type="Letter"  url="e5695095d8cef48552ea5c394e72f480.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2257_img_1700_1"/>
            Copy  27th May, 1916.   My dear Ross,    Since I saw you Asquith has joined the category of <lb/>those regarding whom my letter inquired whether they were <lb/> idiots or traitors. This makes the wisdom of publishing <lb/> my letter still more doubtful than it was. I have, however, <lb/> sent it with a paragraph on the lines of your proposed Addendum <lb/>to my son Hubert to do whatever he thinks wise with. A good <lb/> deal of the contents of my letter are embodied in the article <lb/> in yesterday's "Morning Post" and today's "Irish Times."     Edward Carson said quite the right thing on Thursday <lb/> for the moment. I wonder what he will say to Llyod George. <lb/> The situation is extraordinarily difficult. Redmond is <lb/> obviously in a hole, and possibly Carson will be able to take <lb/> advantage of that to get terms tolerably satisfactory to us <lb/> without allowing himself to be manoeuvred by the radicals <lb/> and nationalists into a position in which he can be represented <lb/>as the only obstacle to a friendly settlement.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>