<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2299">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Bishop Thomas Patrick Gilmartin to John Francis Hogan, 26 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Thomas Patrick Gilmartin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Bishop Thomas Patrick Gilmartin (1861-1939) to Rev Dr John Francis Hogan (1858-1918). Thomas Patrick Gilmartin was born in Rhinsinna, Castlebar, County Mayo and was ordained Bishop of Clonfert on 13 February 1910. John Francis Hogan was born in County Clare and was a priest, author and President of St Patrick&#39;s College, Maynooth. Gilmartin is writing to enclose a donation to the Whitehead memorial funds. He complains about his current lack of finances, income tax and the cost of the Ballinasloe Asylum.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>St Patrick&#39;s College, Maynooth</repository>
                  <collection>John F. Hogan Papers, 21/1/9a</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2299</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0016">Thomas Patrick Gilmartin</persName>
              <date>1916-01-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1817">Loughrea, County Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Francis Hogan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1939</item>
               <item n="tag">Faith</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2299_img_1745_1"  type="Letter"  url="4d11941ae776de7665ad515b0c1ffe2e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2299_img_1745_2"  type="Letter"  url="23400babc6888e2daf257dc929d59009.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2299_img_1745_1"/>
             6/24   Loughrea <lb/> Jan 26th, 16    My dear Mgr,   Though I am a very poor man at<lb/>present, I send you a £1   if you will<lb/>want it or I don't <seg type="unclear">mind being</seg> left out.<lb/>They are heaping an uneven tax at an awful<lb/>rate. I am getting such trouble over<lb/>Ballinasloe Asylum finance than I<lb/>could well tell you. I rejoice that  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2299_img_1745_2"/>
             the good  old College is doing so well<lb/>very gloomy weather. Nothing new here<lb/>in the Ecclesiastical order. The<lb/>war has quenched every other interest<lb/>except the usual indoor pleasures<lb/>such as they are.   Yours <seg type="unclear">graciously</seg><lb/>+ T P Gilmartin 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>