<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0599">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Jeannie Adams to her mother Mary Adams, 27 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Jeannie Adams</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Jeannie Adams (d. 1936), to her mother Mary Adams (d. 1942). In the letter Jeannie writes that it is just a short line to say that she is well. She asks if her mother has heard from her brother and remarks that she thinks they are &#39;having a very hard time&#39;. The letter also refers to the fighting that took place in Dublin during the Easter Rising of 1916. Jeannie refers to the soldiers that have been sent from England and Belfast to put down the rebellion. Jeannie Adams, born Jane Adams, later emigrated to Auckland, New Zealand, where she died in 1936. During the Great War, her brother John Adams (1890-1971), served with the 9th (Service) Battalion, Royal Irish Fusiliers. He spent the winter of 1915-16 in the trenches near the Somme valley. John Adams was wounded two months before the Battle of the Somme and spent Christmas 1916 in a camp in Tipperary. After returning to the Western Front in early 1917, he was involved in the Battle of Messines and further fighting in Ypres (Passchendaele). He was seriously wounded in October 1918, a few weeks before the end of the war.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Adams Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>Adams Family Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/599</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0218">Jeannie Adams</persName>
              <date>1916-04-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1084">Holywood, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Adams</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1981">Lisadian, Co. Armagh</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0599_img_2010_1"  type="Letter"  url="4718193725d774ade160678f5756db18.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0599_img_2010_2"  type="Letter"  url="3c1ff63769c0fd284a5216f534521a3d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0599_img_2010_1"/>
                Church Hill  Holywood  Co.Down    27 April 1916   My Dear Mother,   this is just a wee line to say I am well.I hope you got my<lb/> letter and paper on Monday, wasn't the weather very wet for Easter<lb/> this last few days has been nice. I hope you are all well is<lb/> your pains gone yet I hope so, had you any word from Johnnie<lb/> lately I have had none for a long time, I hope he is well<lb/> I think they are having a very hard time. I expect you<lb/> have heard all about the fighting in Dublin,wasnt it dreadful.<lb/> its coming very near us, there was 10,000 soldiers sent from<lb/><sic>england</sic>and a lot from Belfast.I heard there was a Bridge<lb/> blown up so that the train can't reach Dublin I hope they<lb/> won't start in Belfast. I know 3 girls that went to Dublin<lb/> on <sic>Monday</sic> and they have not arrived home yet. I am glad<lb/> there is no one belonging to us in it they say there is a lot<lb/> killed and wounded I think <sic>youse</sic>are fairly safe out there.<lb/> I wish it was all over. what does the <seg type="unclear">Crawlie's</seg>say about<lb/> it are they on for it the volunteers around here have all been<lb/><hi rend="underline">called up.</hi>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0599_img_2010_2"/>
              we have got our new minister settled he seems very nice<lb/> he was preaching on Sunday night himself and the church<lb/> was packed I never saw so many people in it before<lb/> and everyone seemed to like him he has had a wedding<lb/> and a funeral he is only there a week today. he is to<lb/> start visiting soon ; had you any word from Lizzie lately<lb/> how is she getting on, it was very good of you sending me<lb/> the <seg type="unclear">wee</seg>card I thank you all for it, if you get any word from<lb/> Johnnie will you write soon and let me know.  Gordon Copeland was telling me he was up at <seg type="unclear">Tullyhappy</seg><lb/> on Tuesday. He says when he was coming back at night<lb/> he had to wait at Goraghwood from 7.30 till 9 o clock<lb/> before he could get a train maybe it was just as well<lb/> I was not home. If you don't hear from Johnnie don't be <lb/><sic>to</sic> annoyed because there Is very few boats running<lb/> they may not be able to get the<seg type="del">males</seg> mails <seg type="del">accross</seg>across<lb/> I think this is all now.I will send you a paper.<lb/> Write me a good long letter soon give my best love <seg type="closer"> to all I remain<lb/>Your Loving Daughter,  Jeannie Adams <lb/>write soon to me</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>