<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1454">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sinéad de Valera to Margaret Flanagan, 24 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sinéad de Valera</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Sinéad deValera (1878-1975) to her mother Margaret Flanagan (née Byrne). The letter was written while Éamon deValera (1882-1975) was in prison in Dartmoor in England. Sinéad writes to tell her mother that &#39;Ed&#39; (Éamon) has been imprisoned in Dartmoor and not to be troubled by events. She outlines the prison&#39;s correspondence and visitation regime, adding that , even though letters are censored, Ed prefers them, as visits are closely supervised and unsatisfactory. She encloses a letter from him to her mother and assures her again of his good health. Sinéad expresses the opinion that it was American influence (Éamon de Valera had been born in America) that lead to her husband&#39;s sentence being commuted from death to penal servitude for life.Sinéad de Valera (née O&#39;Flanagan), author and teacher, was the wife of Éamon de Valera. After the Rising, Sinéad was pregnant and without an income while her husband was in prison, and was forced to return to the family home in Phibsboro to care for her invalid sister and mother. Throughout much of the ensuing political upheaval she saw little of her husband, who was either imprisoned or on the run.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/172/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1454</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1202">Sinéad de Valera</persName>
              <date>1916-07-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1146">34 Munster Street, Phibsboro, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Margaret Flanagan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1454_img_890_1"  type="Letter"  url="5e2b480fea95abbf969c134401d07353.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1454_img_890_2"  type="Letter"  url="6c1753555f2ab6a0dbfe809c8604a853.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1454_img_890_3"  type="Letter"  url="627b9e22fe3e6b4012fe839d41f8bfb2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1454_img_890_4"  type="Letter"  url="5e2b480fea95abbf969c134401d07353.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1454_img_890_1"/>
                3 Munster St Phibsboro    24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916   My dear Mother   I had a letter from Lizzie on Sat <lb/> morning saying you asked them to tell me to <lb/>write to you. I hope you have got the two <lb/> letters I wrote lately. I fear you are worried <lb/> about us here. Now please do not be in <lb/> the least uneasy. This day week I wrote <lb/> to you I hope my letter has reached you <lb/> alright. When Ed was first sent away <lb/> I did not like to bother you with bad news <lb/>and I told Tom I was keeping it from you. <lb/> But you seem to have heard it from some <lb/> other source. Now don't be troubled about <lb/> us. God is taking great care of us all. <lb/> Ed was sent to Dartmoor prison in <lb/> England on the 18th May. He was allowed <lb/> to write to me on the following day and <lb/>then I got a communication from the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1454_img_890_2"/>
              governor of the prison saying he would not <lb/> have permission to write again till 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> September. <lb/> You can imagine what a pleasant surprise it <lb/> was for me then to receive a letter from him <lb/> this morning. They are entitled to have a <lb/> visitor every four months as well as a <lb/> letter and if they cannot have the visitor then <lb/> they are allowed to write every two months. <lb/> Ed prefers the letter to a visit. The visits are <lb/> very unsatisfactory. Viv, Mairin and I saw <lb/> him for a short time in the prison here <lb/> before he went away but there was a warden <lb/> present all the time. Ed told me to give the <lb/> enclosed letter to you. Of course his letters <lb/> and all he receives are read by the prison <lb/> authorities. I can only write to him once <lb/> in two months. It is a long time to be <lb/> without a word from him, but he is <lb/> in good health from all I can gather <lb/> and I am very hopeful that when God <lb/> has so mercifully spared his life he will <lb/> do much more for us. I know he will  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1454_img_890_3"/>
              keep strong and well by looking forward <lb/> to meeting us all again. Have no anxiety <lb/> about me or the children, we have everything <lb/> we want and I shall be able <lb/> to get along even if Ed is a long time <lb/> away. But he won't be with God's help. <lb/> I form my intention for the masses as you <lb/> told me. What a noble soul dear Tom is! <lb/> He wrote some lovely letters to me. I am <lb/> sure with all your prayers and help <lb/> everything will soon be well. Of course it <lb/> was the American influence here that got <lb/> Ed's sentence commuted. Now please don't <lb/> fret. Uncle Charlie, I am sure, will take the <lb/> same hopeful view of things that I do. <lb/> Perhaps you might be let write to Ed as <lb/> you may have some important news to tell <lb/> him. They get letters containing any special <lb/> information. Or perhaps Tom or Ed's Uncle <lb/> Ed might to allowed to communicate <lb/> with him. Now my dear Mother be of <lb/> good cheer. I am asking the Holy Family for <lb/> a Christmas Gift and wait till you see won't I <lb/> get it. <seg type="closer"> Sinead </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1454_img_890_4"/>
               (At top of page one)  If you can furnish <lb/>Ed with the particulars <lb/> he asks <lb/>will you send <lb/>the same to me <lb/>I hope you will <lb/>be able to read his <lb/>little note Ferdinand <lb/> and Isabella <lb/>are the words I <lb/>I nearly cut away <lb/>the letter was <lb/>very closely written.  (Written up left side of letter)  Please do not be uneasy - all will be well.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>