<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4202">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Shaw to Martha Shaw, 8 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Short letter from Samuel Shaw to his mother, Martha Shaw, reassuring her that he is well and checking in on life at home. 

Samuel Henry Shaw (1896-1967) was a sergeant with the 10th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers. He volunteered for active service in September 1914. Before enlisting Samuel was a member of the Portstewart Company, Coleraine Battalion, North Derry Regiment, Ulster Volunteer Force. Samuel served in France, and was wounded during the Battle of the Somme in July 1916 and again in early 1917 and in 1918. Before the War he was employed as a ironmonger&#39;s assistant. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4202</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0493">Samuel Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-02-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Martha Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1967</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4202_img_3573_1"  type="Letter"  url="f7130da81183d0fe4bf5a0982d53c62f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4202_img_3573_2"  type="Letter"  url="0f1a0f218f441f23105ade1d01b6b75d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4202_img_3573_1"/>
             Same Address   8 — 2 — 16   My Dear <lb/>Mother   Just a few lines to let <lb/>you know I am well. I received your <lb/>2 parcels &amp; letters &amp; paper. I am sorry <lb/>I did not write but we were on the <lb/>move and I did not get the chance.   Have you seen Millar Hutton in <lb/>the Port yet he is home on leave. <lb/>Hedley is back with us again. <lb/>He was telling me he had a good <lb/>time while he was with <seg type="unclear">Headqrs</seg>   I hope the fishing is still <lb/>improving. Scott is back <lb/>again too. They haven't the good
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4202_img_3573_2"/>
            time now that he had. Scott says <lb/>its nicer getting your breakfast in bed <lb/>than rising at 5.30. Tell Mr M Auley <lb/>I was asking for him. All at present. <lb/>With love to all.   I remain <lb/>Your Loving Son   <hi rend="underline">Sammie</hi>. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>