<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4259">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 10 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) ti his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/95</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4259</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-10</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4259_img_3625_1"  type="Letter"  url="87916d947b7e6eaa57d7de35ad0b881a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4259_img_3625_2"  type="Letter"  url="41e2dafe64663951531db4fd639c93be.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4259_img_3625_1"/>
             Dec. 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>   My own pr   a very few hurried lines as I have a big <lb/> job on hand in the way of indexing for the General. Why isn't <lb/> a p r here to help?    Yes I think Douglas &amp; M'Gill would appreciate cakes as <lb/> much as anything but you are hardly likely to be able to <lb/>  Xmas time it exactly. The latter would probably like something <lb/> gaudy.   As regards Mrs KS remember the more she scratches <lb/> &amp; the less notice you take the greater your triumph over her.    I have been thinking things over &amp; have settled that <lb/> as the p r is now manager of our affairs she ought <lb/> to get the manager's fees. Consequently whatever we put <lb/> into the war loan during the war I will put <sic>in to </sic> <lb/> your name &amp; I hope to be able to wash out the extrava- <lb/>gance fund ( &amp; a good deal more if Rubber doesn't bust !)   The PR who I admit needs no other stimulus than <lb/> the B W's approval will now know that she will get <lb/> some little benefit herself as well, not that it now <lb/> makes much difference.    I had a walk today after 2 days without much
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4259_img_3625_2"/>
            exercise owing to Russell wanting me to go with <lb/> him. Tomorrow I am to dine with Indian Corps, &amp; <lb/> I had an invite to dine with the Art<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> VII <lb/> Dir but declined it they are 14 M off &amp; tho' I <lb/> should have liked to have seen <seg type="unclear">Lindsell</seg>again I <lb/> find I cannot gallivant now.   Must end but much love   Your b w    Wilfrid BSpender   I want to hear how all at <seg type="unclear">24</seg> are now that <lb/>they have a p r to play with  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>