<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0215">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Bertram Cubitt to Robert Chalmers, 3 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Bertram Cubitt</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Bertram Cubitt (1862-1942), the secretary of the War Office, to Robert Chalmers (1958-1938), the under-secretary for Ireland. Cubitt began his career in the War Office in 1886, working as a civil servant until his retirement in 1926. Robert Chalmers became under-secretary following the resignation of Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the aftermath of the 1916 Easter Rising due to his administration&#39;s failure during the rebellion. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5612/9542/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/215</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1354">Bertram Cubitt</persName>
              <date>1916-06-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0372">War Office, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0623">Old Queen Street, Westminster, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0215_img_1363_1"  type="Letter"  url="30fb44630f11a58e1c21acd553e04949.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0215_img_1363_1"/>
                War Office,  London, S.W.  <lb/>Contracts. Firms. K/1739. (A.G.3.)   3 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">rd</hi></hi>June 1916.    Sir,   I am commanded by the Army Council to acquaint <lb/>you for the information of the Chief Secretary for Ireland <lb/>that a request has been received in this Department, from <lb/>Messrs George Kenning &amp; Son, of 1,2, &amp; 3 Little Britain, <lb/>London, E.C. asking if there is any objection to Masonic <lb/>Swords being supplied by them to various parts of Ireland.   They are stated to be purely ceremonial articles <lb/>and of no use for any other purpose.   The Council desire me to say that they would be <lb/>glad to be informed whether the Chief Secretary for Ireland <lb/>has any objection to these swords being supplied.  <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,   B B Cubitt   The Under Secretary,   Irish Office,   Old Queen Street   Westminster. S.W.   </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>