<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5267">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 13, July, 1917</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell expresses gratitude for a new penknife. A new draft arrived from &#34;the strawberry jam eaters corps&#34; several days before. Then the previous day strawberry jam came in the rations. 
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5267</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-07-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5267_img_None_1"  url="a2c3e56c5a77ad31f48af9b3e5922262.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5267_img_None_2"  url="7be6655765be455e43b684f655ddec1d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5267_img_0_1"/>
              13 July 1917    My dearest Daddy,   The absolutely top hole parcel came<lb/>today and was most welcome. It<lb/>began with the knife is A1 and just<lb/>exactly what I wanted - not to heavy but<lb/>it contains all the necessary articles.<lb/>Thank you very much indeed for it.<lb/>Nothing could be better. All the<lb/>eatables also are beautiful. They came at<lb/>a very good time too as I am all<lb/>alone here for a <hi rend="underline">couple</hi> of days. All<lb/>the others are out training and my<lb/>job is just to see that <seg type="del">they</seg> rations<lb/>etc go out to them. You see cooks<lb/>and all are out so I am looking<lb/>after myself more or less so the parcel<lb/>is doubly acceptable.  I expect we will very soon be leaving<lb/>here now.  I was also delighted to get long + newsy letters from you all. Friday is always a great letter day 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5267_img_0_2"/>
             for some reason or other.  I am at present lying out under<lb/>a nice big tree in the shade<lb/>and enjoying the fine weather.  The book in the parcel also<lb/>arrived at an excellent time as<lb/>I finished one I had, last night and<lb/>was just hoping for another to<lb/>carry on with.  We got a draft a few days ago<lb/>transferred fron the strawberry jam<lb/>eaters <hi rend="underline">corps</hi> and yesterday up<lb/>came strawberry jam in the rations<lb/>so they must just have hit on the<lb/>ones who used to eat ours. It is<lb/>very good new jam  No news.  Will write again soon.   With very best love to all from<lb/>Your most affec Son<lb/>Willie.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>