<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0369">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John R. Moorhead to Sir Robert Chalmers, 2 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John R. Moorhead</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from John R. Moorhead (1859-1936), the crown solicitor for Belfast, to the under-secretary for Ireland, Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). This letter refers to the case of Mrs Morgan, the wife of the deceased Private Morgan. Mrs Morgan was convicted for obtaining a large over payment of separation allowance and the letter concerns Moorhead&#39;s difficulties in getting Mrs Morgan to repay the amount she &#39;wrongfully obtained&#39;. He believes that it is better to receive the restitution, even if it is delayed, rather than impose a sentence which would put an end to Mrs Morgan&#39;s repayments completely. Enclosed with the letter is a statement detailing the repayments Mrs Moran has already made.Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9392/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/369</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1437">John R. Moorhead</persName>
              <date>1916-07-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1369">30 Rosemary Street, Belfast, Co. Antrim, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0369_img_1616_1"  type="Letter"  url="1c6d864683fcf187add88721b66a1b98.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0369_img_1616_2"  type="Letter"  url="78eb843589d46f62debeaaa03b20cfb8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0369_img_1616_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="c28cd5980401655dc669024593c132a8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0369_img_1616_1"/>
              Counties of Antrim &amp; Belfast Crown Solicitor's Office    30 Rosemary Street.  Belfast.  <lb/>MOORHEAD &amp; WOOD. <hi rend="underline">Solicitors</hi>  2nd June 1916  <lb/>JOHN R. MOORHEAD <hi rend="underline">Crown Solicitor.</hi><hi rend="underline">Telephone No 605</hi> Dear sir,   Relative to the case referred to in the enclosed Memo., you will <lb/>observe that Mrs Morgan, wife of 10692 Private Morgan, late Royal Irish <lb/>Rifles, who was convicted before the Recorder of Belfast, for obtaining <lb/>a large overpayment of Separation Allowance and<hi rend="underline"> who was put under a rule <lb/>of bail for two years from the date of her conviction to come up for <lb/>sentence at any time within that period on getting 10 days' notice from <lb/>the Crown Solicitor and conditional that she repaid the amount wrongfully <lb/>obtained by instalments of 10/- per week</hi>, - you will observe from the <lb/>copy Return attached that Mrs Morgan has not been at all punctually making <lb/>these payments. Sometimes she omitted payment altogether and having made <lb/>the first few payments she began to reduce the amount of her instalments. <lb/>She has constantly made excuses and when reminded of the statement made <lb/>by Counsel on her behalf at the time the order was made that 'about £10 <lb/>per week was coming into her house in the form of wages for munition work <lb/>by members of her family' she replied that that statement was quite <lb/>inaccurate and was a mere fabrication of Counsel. Up to the present I <lb/>have been in great doubt as to what to do with this and the several <lb/>similar cases in which I am collecting instalments under similar orders. <lb/>If I attempt to hold them strictly to the instalment agreed on, and the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0369_img_1616_2"/>
              <lb/>amount is not paid, or not regularly paid, my only remedy is to serve <lb/>the 10-days' notice and have the sentence imposed, but the result of <lb/>that would be no more restitution. It seems to me that the obtaining <lb/>of restitution as far as possible was more important than securing <lb/>the punishment for the offender. I have been temporizing and <lb/>threatening to bring the defaulters up for sentence but have not <lb/>actually done so, but there comes a time when the instalments are <lb/>approaching vanishing point and it begins to appear doubtful whether <lb/>sharper measures should not be adopted.   I should be glad if you will ascertain from the Military Authorities <lb/>what they wish me to do. My own idea, subject to approval of the <lb/>Paymaster's Department, would be, <hi rend="underline">not to bring the parties up on <lb/>notice for sentence so long as there is any hope of obtaining any <lb/>further substantial payments;</hi> in other words, to continue as I have <lb/>been doing, to exercise as much pressure as possible upon them so <lb/>as to obtain the maximum amount of restitution before resorting to <lb/>the notice for sentence. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Your obedt. servant,  John R Moorhead <lb/> Crown Solicitor.   The Under Secretary, The Castle, Dublin.  </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0369_img_1616_3"/>
              <seg type="closer"><hi rend="underline">£11. 19. 6.</hi></seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>