<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3109">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Katie Mooney to her brother Peter Mooney, 4 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Katie Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Peter Mooney was born 5 February 1886 in Folistown, Dunboyne, Co Meath. Orphaned at age 7, he and his sister Katie (b. 1884) were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. 

He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This  letter is from a collection of over ninety surviving letters.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3109</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-02-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1461">Caulstown, Dunboyne, Co. Meath, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3109_img_2516_1"  type="Letter"  url="cdb33e27d1f5c0166a77b93f467280ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3109_img_2516_2"  type="Letter"  url="593de7b54f9fdd68cf1cd6e05e5c875e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3109_img_2516_3"  type="Letter"  url="615962df507f83f0a4061f8484152f49.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3109_img_2516_1"/>
             Caulstown, <lb/>Dunboyne, <lb/>Co. Meath.   4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb '16   My Dear Peter,   <seg type="del">I'm</seg> Delighted to receive <lb/>your ever welcome letter <lb/> today containing the good <lb/> news that we will see you <lb/> next week for certain.   I am writing a few lines <lb/> to the Governor this evening <lb/> telling him that you are <lb/> coming next week. I am <lb/>sure he will be delighted. <lb/> I am going to Dunboyne <lb/> this evening to attend a
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3109_img_2516_2"/>
            committee meeting regarding <lb/> cookery classes which are <lb/> starting next week in the <lb/> old School. Our Nurse's <lb/>meeting is tomorrow evening <lb/>Tom Bracken was married <lb/>on last Wednesday. It was <lb/>a very nice quiet wedding <lb/>no wreaths or veils or bouquets <lb/>nor white silk or satin.   M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Carthy sent the carriage <lb/>with them to the Chapel. <lb/>Miss Walshe gave the wedding <lb/>breakfast. Hugh Mullaly was <lb/>best man and Lillie Murray <lb/>was bridesmaid.   They are living in the <lb/> front lodge. I wonder <lb/> <lb/>what you will say when <lb/>you hear that George Moran <lb/>is listed as a private in <lb/>the Dublin Fusiliers. Himself <lb/>and Little were having a <lb/>good time drinking before <lb/>this. So I hear that the <lb/>old man cleared <seg type="del">th</seg> him. <lb/>Don't say anything about <lb/> this if you write to the <seg type="unclear">Paddins</seg> <lb/>as it wasn't there I heard the <lb/>news.    I didn't get any word <lb/>of how Mrs Farrell was yet. <lb/>I expect a letter in the morning. <lb/>I wont send the Drogheda <lb/>or Sport to morrow, as they <lb/>will be here when you come. <lb/>Bridget says she will give <lb/>you a rare feed <seg type="del">wh</seg> in the <lb/>mornings. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3109_img_2516_3"/>
              I got a new Tyre and Tube <lb/>for my bicycle as the other <lb/>one blew up and left me <lb/>on the road. Before I <lb/>close this letter I must <lb/>wish you every joy from <lb/>all here as to-day is your <lb/>birthday. Many happy <lb/>returns of same to you.   I have Tobacco here for you <lb/>also socks and gloves.   I will now say a fond good <lb/>bye to you. With best love <lb/>from all here. May God <lb/>Bless &amp; Protect you is the <lb/>sincere prayer of your fond <lb/>Aunt &amp; Sister. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>