<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2832">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Robert Bargrave Armstrong to his father, Henry Bruce Armstrong, 22 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Robert Bargrave Armstrong </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is written from the front by &#39;Robin&#39;, James Robert Bargrave Armstrong (1893-1980) to his father, Henry Bruce Armstrong. Robin tells his father his location without actually naming it, instead saying that &#39;Forfo&#39; had been there for some months. He mentions running into former acquaintances from WInchester and Cambridge, and says he had lunch with one of them at HQ, a &#39;very nice old chateau&#39;. He suggests that H.B. may have known the father or grandfather of Robin&#39;s senior captain. He finishes with an account of the weather.

This letter is part of a series of correspondence belonging to  Henry Bruce Armstrong (1844-1943). The correspondence largely concerns Armstrong’s estate and financial affairs with correspondents ranging from family members to high ranking Northern Irish politicians. At the time of this letter he was a County Councillor for Armagh, and he would later become a Westminster MP.

Robin served in the First World War, and later became a barrister.

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Armstrong Papers, D3727/E/18/34/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2832</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0503">James Robert Bargrave Armstrong </persName>
              <date>1916-07-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">H.B. Armstrong</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1980</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2832_img_2247_1"  type="Letter"  url="74c3f30e758a7f363edb9a1433d900c3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2832_img_2247_2"  type="Letter"  url="01c7432a94c868b3dc2a298a14630aa5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2832_img_2247_1"/>
             viiith Hussars <lb/>I.E.F <lb/>France   22/7/16   My dear father   We are still in the same spot — <lb/>the same place where <seg type="unclear">Forfor</seg> was <lb/>some months. We have now <lb/>got a few tents up &amp; are fairly <lb/>comfortable. Of course we may <lb/>be off any time at an hour &amp; <lb/>a half's notice   I have come across <seg type="unclear">3</seg> fellows <lb/>that I knew at Winchester &amp; <lb/>Cambridge. Since I have been <lb/>here — one you remember <lb/><seg type="unclear">Hector Munro</seg> who is A.D.C.
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2832_img_2247_2"/>
            to the infantry corps general. <lb/>I had lunch with him yesterday <lb/>at H.Q. at a very nice old <lb/><seg type="foreign">Chateau!</seg> —   The senior captain in the regiment <lb/>is the Hon. R.N.D. Ryder. I suppose <lb/>it was probably his grandfather <lb/>that was at Trinity with you or <lb/>perhaps his father.   We have had 3 lovely days <lb/>up till now but today it <lb/>is <seg type="unclear">clouding</seg> over again &amp; I'm <lb/>afraid shall have more rain.   Your <seg type="unclear">affectionate</seg> son   <seg type="unclear">Robin</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>