<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4893">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter E. Magennis OCC, National President to Diarmuid Lynch, National Secretary, Friends of Irish Freedom, 1 May, 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter E. Magennis</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Requests pledges and that new branches be opened in light of increased membership.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>American Irish Historical Society</repository>
                  <collection>Friends of Irish Freedom, Office of the National Secretary, 1918-1939, Box 3 Folder 4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4893</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1241">Peter E. Magennis</persName>
              <date>1919-05-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0367">Friends of Irish Freedom Headquarters, Fitzgerald Building, 1482 Broadway, New York City, New York, USA</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1937</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4893_img_None_1"  url="8766a69babfaec46314fac4a863fc3d7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4893_img_None_2"  url="2a460e940ad035284d046e458be0c327.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4893_img_0_1"/>
             Telephone Bryant 5769 Suite 812-813  Frieds of Irish Freedom  National Headquarters   Fitzgerald Building, 1482 Broadway<lb/>New York City    May 1, 1919    A Chara:   The People of Ireland have established a republican form of government.<lb/>America is ringing with the demand that that government shall receive inter-<lb/>national recognition. Americans of Irish blood have formally conveyed this<lb/>demand to Versaills, - its reception and the subsequent action on it by the<lb/>Peace Conference will depend largely upon the extent to which we can inform<lb/>the American People on facts concerning Ireland and organize on behalf of the<lb/>Irish Republic,  Never in modern times have the Irish People in Ireland been so dignified<lb/>in their national position, so cognizant of their international rights, and so<lb/>determined to remain what God made them - a distinct and independent<lb/>Nation. From their many and dignified stand the race in America draws its<lb/>inspiration, its enthusiasm, and its unity of purpose, but, to achieve final victory<lb/>we must ORGANIZE and EDUCATE.  Will YOU, - friend of Liberty and upholder of republican institutions -<lb/>do your share of this work, and do it immediately? The Irish-Americans in<lb/>your community are, we confidently assert, ready for organization, and our<lb/>fellow-citizens generally are anxiously seeking information on the Irish situation.<lb/>Encosed leaflet, No. 4, will instruct you how to co-operate with us in an<lb/>organized manner. Your promt action is solicited.  The F. O. I. F. organization has increased tenford in size, and its activi-<lb/>ties have correspondingly developed during the past six montsl our aim is to<lb/>achieve even greater progress with the next six  WEEKS . In the establishment<lb/>of new Branches we request that instructions be followed in every detail -<lb/>unbusiness-like methods will not fill the bill. The enemies of American ideals<lb/>and of Irish Freedom - in the press, the pulpit, the school, and the social circle<lb/>- are hightly efficient and unceasing in their venomous and pro-British anti-<lb/>American campaign. The justice of our cause and our superiornumbers will<lb/>not avail if we be not at least equally efficient and systematically aggressive.<lb/>We cannot hope to be as well equipped financially, but once organized, our<lb/>thousands of volunteer workers aremed with truth and justice and educational<lb/>literature will more than over-match the hirelings of England supported by all<lb/>her resources.   NATIONAL PRESIENT<lb/>Very Rev P. E. Magennis O. C. C.<lb/>New York<lb/>NATIONAL TREASURER<lb/>Michael B. McGreal<lb/>New Haven, Conn<lb/>NATIONAL SECRETARY<lb/>Diarmuid Lynch<lb/>1482 Broadway, New York<lb/>National Vice-Presidents<lb/>Hon. Frank. F. Walsh<lb/>Kansas City, MO<lb/>Hon. John W. Goff<lb/>New York, N. Y.<lb/>Rt. Rev. Peter J. Muldoon<lb/>Rockford, NS<lb/>Rt. Rev. Thomas J. Shahan<lb/>Washington, D. C.<lb/>Rt. Rev Michael J. Gallagher<lb/>Detroit, Mich<lb/>Rt. Rev Henry A. Brann<lb/>New York, N. Y.<lb/>Rt. Rev. Gerald P. Coghlan<lb/>Philadelphia, Pa<lb/>Rt. Rev. James W. Power<lb/>New York, N. Y.<lb/>Rev. Thomas J. Hurton<lb/>Philadelphia, Pa<lb/>Mrs. Mary F. McWhorter<lb/>Chicago, Ill.<lb/>Mrs O'Neill Ryan<lb/>St. Louis, Mo<lb/>Rev. Peter C. Yorke<lb/>San Francisco, Cal<lb/>Rev John J. Curley<lb/>Boston Mass.<lb/>John J. Splain,<lb/>New Haven, Conn.<lb/>Hon John P. Grance<lb/>Charleston S. C.<lb/>Hon Michael J. Ryan<lb/>Philadelphia, Pa.<lb/>Rev Francis X McCabe<lb/>Chicago, Ill.<lb/>Hon Cornelius F. Collins,<lb/>New York, N. Y.<lb/><lb/>National Trustees<lb/>Josephn McGarrity<lb/>Philadelphia Pa<lb/>Thomas Hughes Kelly<lb/>New York, N. Y.<lb/>Thos. J. Maloney<lb/>New Jersey, N. J.<lb/>Richard W. Wolfe<lb/>Chicago, Ill<lb/>Thomas F. Cooney<lb/>Providence, R. I.<lb/>John A. Murphy<lb/>Buffalo, N. Y.<lb/>Richard F. Dalton<lb/>New York, N. Y.<lb/><lb/>Chairman National Executive<lb/>Robert E. Ford<lb/>New York<lb/><lb/>Vice-Chairman National Executive<lb/>John Carroll<lb/>New York  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4893_img_0_2"/>
             If a Regular Branch of the Friends of Irish Freedom is not established in<lb/>your parish or district, will you not take immediate steps to make good the<lb/>deficiency? Should the name of a person be chosed for your Branch, it must<lb/>be that of one whose republicanism cannot be questioned - thus avoiding any<lb/>semblance of support to the enemies of Irish Independence who are endeavoring<lb/>to befog the issue.  Do you know of any Irish-American Society not yet affiliated with the<lb/>Friends of Irish Freedom as an ASSOCIATE Branch, and consequently not<lb/>in line to receive our educational literature on Ireland?  Has your district yet contributed its share of the $2,000,000 pledged at<lb/>the Irish Race Convention? If not, please call together the friends of Irish<lb/>Independence and uphold the holor of your State. This money is to be used<lb/>to educate public opinion -<lb/>a) To urge that the objects for which American entered the War may be fully<lb/>attained.<lb/>b) To urge and insist upon the recognition of the republican form of  government <lb/>established in Ireland.<lb/>c) To urge that America shall not enter into any League of Nations which does<lb/>not safeguard ALL American Rights.<lb/>d) To maintain and preserve the American ideals of government and to oppose<lb/>and offset the British propaganda, which is falsifying and misrepresenting the facts of<lb/>Americal History as well as facts pertaining to Ireland.<lb/>e) To maintain for the foregoing purposes a widespread and professional publicity<lb/>campaign.<lb/>f)To defray the expenses of the Irish-American Delegation to the Peace<lb/>Conference.  How long shall it be said that the Irish are the only white race in Amer-<lb/>ical whose homeland remains subject to a foreign power? The twenty millions<lb/>of the Gael must themselves give the answer and our fellow-citizens of other<lb/>races who are imbued with the spirit of George Washington and Patrick Henry<lb/>will respect and support our assertion that the freedom and independence of<lb/>the Irish Republic must be recognized.  Act NOW. We will, on request, supply membership application blanks<lb/>so that you may ORGANIZE.   Is sinne bur gcaire i gcuis na saoirseacht    Peter E. Magennis, O.C.C.<lb/>National President<lb/>Diarmuid Lynch<lb/>National Secretary  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>