<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4236">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 26 November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife,  Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/74</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4236</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-11-26</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4236_img_3604_1"  type="Letter"  url="7e7dfb00935b848b7cde2b143edda59d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4236_img_3604_2"  type="Letter"  url="02875daf253ac34c82ed08e617dd07e2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4236_img_3604_1"/>
             Nov. 26.   My p r.   No letter last night from you tho' a nice little scrap from <lb/> Jessie which was of course a good substitute. Please thank her. <lb/> Perhaps it will come midday with the ordinary letters. I think the <lb/> censor must have a special predilection for your letters &amp; don't blame <lb/> him if so.   It hasn't come   the result   Last night I was up till midnight having had a busy day <lb/> with our move. I just glanced at the paper, read Redmond's speech, <lb/> &amp; promptly seized my pen &amp; wrote to Carson. If the tolerance shown <lb/> by our men — to the nationalists is merely to be used as a means <lb/> of exploiting Home Rule, there will be a row, &amp; I shall not stop it, <lb/> I have suggested to Carson that we should write a counterblast.    Reallly we want him as dictator, the Gov<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> seems more weak kneed <lb/> than ever !   The 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Brigade has been doing very well at the front, &amp; <lb/> everyone is finding fault in this Division with <seg type="del">our</seg>  its  substitutes, so <lb/> that the General now seems keen to get them back, I fear more <lb/> so than they are to come !   The 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> got badly strafed yesterday. Major P.Kerr <lb/> Smiley is not a great commander &amp; the Gen'  Hickman now  thinks Col C would <lb/> be better employed elsewhere, having realized that he won't go <lb/> down with the General when he comes, so I think he won't come <lb/> after all.    I think I should write to Mr J Cunningham if you can make <lb/> it quite <hi rend="underline">clear </hi>to him that you want advice not a subscription You <seg type="unclear">have</seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4236_img_3604_2"/>
            the army list. I could have <lb/> thought out such a polite letter for you which would have made them writhe.   I am thrilled about the flat in Sheffield Terrace. Lady K was <lb/>not the C<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Down one I suppose wife of Sir Robert of that ilk?   The Spectator on Thursday will be quite in time. I usually <lb/> see Russell's Times so don't do so badly now.   I went to the bombing of the Brigade Bombers whom I have <lb/> been coaching, &amp; the Gen' was really pleased for once. They did better <lb/> than I expected.   You would have been amused<sic>to day</sic> to see a horse looking <lb/> out over the road from a room upstairs. The horses are many of them <lb/> billeted in  semi ruined houses &amp; in this case this was a house built into <lb/> the side of a hill so that the first floor was level with the ground &amp; the <lb/> horses walked in on to it. The wall was a bit broken &amp; an old horse <lb/> looked out with much complacency.   I am longing for further news of your Com'<hi rend="superscript"><seg type="unclear">mee</seg></hi>meetings &amp; <lb/> plans, but your letters have a way of arriving one day late as far <lb/> as I can make out. Would you put the time of posting on occasionally. It <lb/> is obviously wrong for Tuesday's paper to come before your Monday's letter, &amp; <lb/> I wonder if they get delayed en route. If so the Censor must often <lb/> learn something curious about the natural history of squirrels &amp; a p rabbit.   I think you would do well to encourage Mater to think of going <lb/> to an <seg type="unclear">chemist</seg> later. Had we been at Belfast I would certainly have <lb/>suggested D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>Craig.   Best love to "you all" (how does P.R like this )    Wilfrid BSpender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>