<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2798">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his father Samuel Cleland Davidson, 16 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Samuel Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.

Davidson discusses fighting in the front and reserve trenches, and in particular refers to use of a Hyposcope and several types of guns and pistols.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/28</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2798</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0097">James Samuel Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-02-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1149">Samuel Cleland Davidson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1115">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1916</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_1"  type="Letter"  url="4b815b54a0927118d95fbbd9998dbcbb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_2"  type="Letter"  url="35259ce7813a5b25e97e93f0dbf5102a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_3"  type="Letter"  url="cc5242f5805382058e7b7663c619f0ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_4"  type="Letter"  url="5bbd1a99f8c4d4516f87228b57d104dd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_5"  type="Letter"  url="e9c8d4182e7ed1a0c83cb01fed7247a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_6"  type="Letter"  url="b9cef3cac95baccf3116ef5a19242b77.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2798_img_2215_7"  type="Letter"  url="b022e94b33c7ee4284d741447f4ad77f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_1"/>
            <!-- the first image does not seem to have uploaded properly and is not available to transcribe --> <hi rend="underline">a</hi><lb/>19 February<lb/><seg type="unclear">DEW</seg>  <lb/> 10/2/16    My dear Father  — I have<lb/>just received your letter<lb/>of 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> February &amp; as I have a<lb/>few minutes to spare at<lb/>present am replying at<lb/>once. As regards the<lb/><seg type="unclear">Hyposocpe </seg>I dont think<lb/>you need take any further<lb/>special trouble about these<lb/>for with the introduction of<lb/>the Lewis gun which is employed<lb/>in the front trenches, the<lb/>practice now is to use the<lb/>Vickers guns in the support<lb/>&amp; reserve trenches in which<lb/>positions there is really no<lb/>necessity for using the Hyposcope.<lb/>As you will have heard, we<lb/>are now in the trenches<lb/>&amp; I have 8 guns actually<lb/> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_2"/>
             2<lb/><lb/>in positions the remainder<lb/>being in reserve. By day<lb/>we only fire indirect fire, that<lb/>is from positions concealed<lb/>from the enemy &amp; by night<lb/>when we employ some of the<lb/>others there is no necessity<lb/>for a Hyposcope. We have<lb/>only got <hi rend="underline">4</hi> of the <seg type="unclear">Gardin</seg> Hyposcopes<lb/>in the Coy (there was only 1 per<lb/>Batt) but I dont expect we<lb/>shall ever use them, at any<lb/>rate not in our present<lb/>positions. The Govt.pattern<lb/>issued with the guns is not<lb/>at all satisfactory. The gun<lb/>cannot be fired by one man.<lb/>One man holds the handles<lb/>of the Hyposcope — which is nothing<lb/>more or less than a box<lb/>periscope clapmed to the gun —<lb/>&amp; a second man operates a<lb/> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_3"/>
             3<lb/><lb/>lever to release the safety<lb/>catch &amp; press the firing lever.<lb/>The <seg type="unclear">Gardiner</seg> Hyposcope is<lb/>superior in every way &amp; we<lb/>have done some quite good<lb/>shooting with it on the range<lb/>but mechanically it requires<lb/>improvement. I altered one<lb/>so as to make the top mirror<lb/>adjustable &amp; fitted a new<lb/>bottom mirror of same size<lb/>as top one with much improved<lb/>results. Unless the top mirror<lb/>can be adjusted it is impossible<lb/>to bring the rear sight in<lb/>line with foresight. However<lb/>as already mentioned we are<lb/>not using the Hyposcopes at<lb/>all owing to the different<lb/>method now adopted in using<lb/>the Vickers guns &amp; so as<lb/>the W O seem to have set<lb/> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_4"/>
             4<lb/><lb/>themselves against the <seg type="unclear">Gardiner</seg><lb/>pattern I should let the<lb/>matter drop. As very glad<lb/>to hear the Trench pistol is<lb/>now nearing completion —<lb/>it will be 'great' to get at the<lb/>Germans with something new.<lb/>They have so far alsways been<lb/>the first in this line. I am<lb/>afraid however we wont be<lb/>able to experiment on this<lb/>particular part of the line<lb/>for the trenches are for the<lb/>most part about 400 yds<lb/>apart. There is not much<lb/>rifle fire but plenty of artillery.<lb/>I had a rather narrow escape<lb/>this morning with 2 of my<lb/>officers &amp; a Corp. We were<lb/>inspecting one of the old<lb/>gun emplacements — the<lb/>one nearest the firing line<lb/> 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_5"/>
             5<lb/><lb/>about 200 yds in rear — &amp; I<lb/>was taking some bearings<lb/>with a view to straffing a<lb/>a part of the German support<lb/>trenches when suddenly<lb/><seg type="del">  </seg> 2 guns opened fire on<lb/>us with 15 lb shells. Fortunately<lb/>for us they did not get a<lb/>direct hit on the emplacement<lb/>but the shells hit some of them<lb/>within 10 yds &amp; we were<lb/>well spattered with earth &amp;<lb/>fragments of stones etc<lb/>An adjoining old French<lb/>gun emplacement which<lb/>was very conspicuous &amp;<lb/>which the Germans evidently<lb/>took to be the one we were<lb/>inspecting — for they must<lb/>have observed something —<lb/>was broken up. There<lb/>was no near communication<lb/> 
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_6"/>
             6<lb/><lb/>trench &amp; the trenches were<lb/>very shallow &amp; came to a<lb/>blind end but between<lb/>the shots we scooted along<lb/>as far we could get from<lb/>the gun emplacement &amp;<lb/>lay down in the mud. The<lb/>shelling went on for about<lb/>1/2 hr — about 40 shells in<lb/>all — &amp; as they were all<lb/>dropping about 20 - 25 yds<lb/>away it was certainly far<lb/>from comfortable but<lb/>very exciting. The Corp<lb/>had an almost miraculous<lb/>escape — he ran the other<lb/>way to his dugout &amp; just<lb/>as he got to the entrance<lb/>a shell landed on the<lb/>parapet beside him but<lb/>did not explode &amp;<lb/>rolled down at his feet 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_2798_img_2215_7"/>
             7<lb/><lb/>where I saw it later.<lb/>At present I am having more<lb/>to do than I can well get through.<lb/>It is seldom I am in bed<lb/>till midnight &amp; then up at<lb/>7 am or before. There are<lb/>so many returns to be sent in<lb/>besides all the organisation<lb/>of work etc &amp; the worst of it<lb/>is one feels that the most of<lb/>these returns are never even<lb/>looked at.<lb/><lb/>Have had a note from Kathleen<lb/>but am afraid this will have<lb/>to do for all as I wont have<lb/>time to write again for some<lb/>days. Hoping you are keeping<lb/>well &amp; with kind regards to <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>  &amp; others at office.<lb/><lb/> Your affectionate son<lb/>Jim <lb/>  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>