<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5306">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Francis C. Forth to Members of the Library and Technical Instruction Committee</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis C. Forth</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Expresses goodwill and gratitude for kindnesses.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5306</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0162">Francis C. Forth</persName>
              <date>1919-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1067">Ravenswood, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">The Chairman, Vice Chairman, and Other Members of the Library and Technical Instruction Committee</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1851">Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1919</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5306_img_None_1"  url="32fbe05430781690981abaaf0138b6a9.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5306_img_0_1"/>
              Ravenswood,<lb/>B E L F A S T.    February, 1919.    To<lb/>The Chairman, Vice-Chairman, and<lb/>other members of the Library and<lb/>Technical Instruction Committee.    Gentlemen,   I had looked forward to being present at still<lb/>another of your meetings, but it has been decreed other-<lb/>wise, and one bows to the inevitable.  The opportunity is, however, given me to write,<lb/>and this opportunity I take advantage of, to beg that you<lb/>will allow me to send you, and that you will accept, the<lb/>very sincere expression of my goodwill to every member of<lb/>the Committee. At the same time, I wish to assure you how<lb/>deeply I appreciate all the kindness, the consideration, and<lb/>the thoughtfulness that has been extended to me during my<lb/>whole tenure of office, but particularly during the past<lb/>few months, when I have been unable to render that full and<lb/>complete service to the Institute which it has ever been my<lb/>ambition to give.  It has been a great privilege and a great honour<lb/>to me to have been associated so long (over 18 years) with<lb/>the development of the Technical Instruction Scheme of Belfast.  The Municipal Technical Institute, Belfast, has<lb/>a great future before it, and, in sending the Committee this<lb/>message of farewell I currently trust that all the develop-<lb/>ments that are pending may be fully realised, and that the<lb/>Committoe's work may attain that high pinnacle to which it<lb/>is so justly entitled.   With the renewed expression of my esteem,<lb/>I am, Gentlemen,<lb/>Sincerely yours,    F. C. FORTH.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>