<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1129">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward O' Farrell to J. Holland, 4 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward O&#39;Farrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward O&#39;Farrell (c.1857-1926), on behalf of the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Lord Wimborne (1873-1939), to John Holland. Holland had worked as an overseer for the post office in Limerick but was fined and reduced in rank. Holland complained that his treatment was part of a campaign against him as he was not a supporter of Sinn Fein and asked that the action against him be overturned. The letter informs him that the Lord Lieutenant is unable to do accede to his request.Sir Edward O&#39;Farrell served as the Assistant Under Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, Sir Ivor Guest Churchill, Lord Wimborne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>CSO RP/5596/1916/648/2, CSO RP/5596/1916/648/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1129</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1386">Edward O&#39;Farrell</persName>
              <date>1916-02-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Holland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0193">Rose Cottage, Ballinacurra, County Limerick</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1129_img_362_1"  type="Letter"  url="ec748f3b8abb1ae3bb756ca8017d176f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1129_img_362_1"/>
                4th February, 1916.   No. 648.  Sir,   With reference to your Memorial received in <lb/>this Office on the 10th January, I am directed <lb/>by the Lord Lieutenant to inform you that, after <lb/>consulting the Post Office, His Excellency <lb/>regrets that he is unable to accede to the prayer <lb/>contained therein. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant,  <hi rend="underline">E Farrell</hi>   Mr. J. Holland,  Ross Cottage,  Ballinacurra,  Limerick.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>