<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3147">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">From Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, 9 April 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother Maria (1854-1954) discussing her life in London. Celia also writes about one of her patients taking poison to avoid being discharged from the hospital. 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in  Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland </repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers D2109/9/4/B/27</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3147</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0524">Celia Duffin </persName>
              <date>1915-04-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0733">3rd London General Hospital, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3147_img_2567_1"  type="Letter"  url="70bd4dd06b01feec22f6e26d87d57c77.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3147_img_2567_2"  type="Letter"  url="5f7052f41eacf2cc4f790d4cf19fa037.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3147_img_2567_3"  type="Letter"  url="da0d4830bea4ab4a76ad549dd33dcc83.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3147_img_2567_1"/>
             3<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> <hi rend="underline">London General</hi>   <hi rend="underline">Tuesday</hi>   Dearest Mamma   Here I am busy at work again <lb/>and feeling quite fit after drinking <lb/>a bottle of some awful mixture <lb/>that tasted like strong ammonia. <lb/>It was snowing here this morning and <lb/>very hard to drag myself out<seg type="del">si</seg> of <lb/>bed in the dark. I made an <lb/>expedition into town and ordered my <lb/>winter coat at Harrods yesterday. I had <lb/>to have it made as the ready-mades <lb/>were no use for me and it only <lb/>cost 2/6 more. Don't dream of <lb/>sending me any money for it, I have <lb/>paid for it, and don't want any
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3147_img_2567_2"/>
            more, thanks all the same ever so <lb/>much for offering. I have also <lb/>bought the black winter hat which <lb/>is quite becoming.   It is splendid your having collected <lb/>all that money for Emma, she will <lb/>be delighted when she gets it. It <lb/>must have kept you quite busy <lb/>acknowledging all the letters. Our <lb/>men are quite well-looked after, <lb/>but at present their breakfasts are <lb/>very dull as eggs are too expensive <lb/>and they never get anything but <lb/>porridge and bread and butter <lb/>every morning. We are each <lb/>giving a shilling in our ward to <lb/>get them sausages some morning <lb/>for a break.   I had a kind note from <lb/>the Miss Bruces asking me to stay <lb/>there and get convalescent, but of course <lb/>I got no leave, and the Tillings <lb/>were ever so kind offering to come <lb/>and bring me anything I wanted <lb/>until I was well enough to go to <lb/>them. I couldn't help laughing as <lb/>I got their letters when I was back <lb/>at work again. My sister was <lb/>very kind and looks after me.   One of the patients in our Ward <lb/>took poison this morning; one of the <lb/>men came and told me, and <lb/>we had quite a time trying to <lb/>get him right again. He took <lb/>it on purpose, poor thing, because <lb/>he was leaving hospital to-day. <lb/>It was a mixture we use for <lb/>syringing ears, and was marked 'poison'.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3147_img_2567_3"/>
            The doctor and sisters made him <lb/>very sick and gave him oil and <lb/>whites of eggs, and he seemed all <lb/>right when I left. He seemed quite <lb/>a cheery sort of person, but evidently <lb/>was depressed because he got giddy <lb/>sometimes when he tried to work.   I went to tea with the Halls. <lb/>Bonnie had been seeing Marcia <lb/>at Eastbourne, and says she has <lb/>grown very fat indeed and the <lb/>baby is very pretty. I can't imagine <lb/>her fat. A friend of Lady R's came <lb/>in to tea, rather an amusing person. <lb/>London is so dark, one always has <lb/>to get back early these days.   Thanks so much for the nice par- <lb/>cel from Malcolmson's.   Best love <lb/>from   <hi rend="underline">Celia</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>