<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0008">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Margaret Pearse to Mabel FitzGerald, 16 July, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Margaret Pearse</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Margaret Mary Pearse (1878–1968) to Mabel FitzGerald, (1884-1957), the wife of Desmond FitzGerald, (1888-1947). Miss Pearse acknowledges the kind words Mrs. Fitzgerald sent to her mother (Margaret Pearse (1857-1932)) about her brother, Patrick. The writer goes on to describe her visits to HM Prison in Dartmoor and describes conditions for the Irish prisoners there, which she finds quite reasonable. She thinks it is a good thing that the Irish prisoners are segregated from ordinary criminals. She advises Mrs FitzGerald that it is possible to send books in to the prison but that the books become the property of the prison service.Margaret Pearse was the sister of Patrick Pearse (1879-1916), one of the leaders of the Easter Rising in 1916, who was executed on 3 May 1916. Another brother, Willie Pearse, was also executed. Mabel was a former governess in London. She later vigorously canvassed her former acquaintances in London&#39;s liberal circles for support for Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 -1916) during his hunger strike in 1915. Both Mabel and Desmond would serve in the GPO garrison during Easter Week.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1606/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/8</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1330">Margaret Pearse</persName>
              <date>1916-07-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0113">St. Enda&#39;s College, Rathfarnham, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0008_img_1031_1"  type="Letter"  url="5ee78af1f579e354e0c29adf0a5352cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0008_img_1031_2"  type="Letter"  url="f1a05954fe962f51f6e2c8adaae1ada5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0008_img_1031_3"  type="Letter"  url="a4ebb33d63af1103b47b6efc115a254b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0008_img_1031_4"  type="Letter"  url="ceabeffa99450f77131cf5a89ef8873d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0008_img_1031_5"  type="Letter"  url="611276aa6a2271d81cd455f5c56650ee.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0008_img_1031_6"  type="Letter"  url="5e13e9f7a42d884ef61e2fca5593e858.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0008_img_1031_1"/>
                St. Enda's College  Rathfarnham    16/7/'16   Dear Mrs. Fitzgerald,   In reply to your letter <lb/>this morning to my mother. <lb/>First I must thank you for your kind words about <lb/>my good brother. Life for <lb/>us will never again be the <lb/>same, &amp; yet it is such a <lb/>strange mixture of grief &amp; <lb/>pride. May God bless the <lb/>boys &amp; all who stood by him. <lb/>You have your own great <lb/>trial, but it won't be for very long. Time will bring <lb/>many changes.  About Dartmoor. We saw  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0008_img_1031_2"/>
              <lb/>only our own two personal <lb/>for which we had a special <lb/>permit from the Home Secretary. <lb/>The rule is 4 months must <lb/>lapse before a visit, but <lb/>we got one much sooner. <lb/>I hope to go again in October. <lb/>The conditions were better <lb/>than I had hoped. I heard <lb/>they had 4 months' solitary <lb/>confinement. That is not so. <lb/>It is one month, which <lb/>time in most cases had <lb/>expired before the men <lb/>left Dublin.  There are 69 of ours in <lb/>Dartmoor. They are not <lb/>allowed to mix with the <lb/>ordinary convicts, &amp; that <lb/>in itself is a blessing.  At recreation they walk<cb/><lb/> round in some sort of <lb/>yard quite away from <lb/>the others. At Mass they <lb/>(The Irish Prisoners) are all <lb/>together, &amp; 3 empty <lb/>benches are left between <lb/>them &amp; the criminals. <lb/>They are employed at <lb/>making post bags. <lb/>I think the authorities did <lb/>not think it wise to put <lb/>them at severe work. <lb/>The food, as far as I can <lb/>judge, is good. We had a <lb/>little of the prison bread <lb/>when taking lunch with <lb/>the priest after our visit. <lb/>It was a bit dark, but quite <lb/>all right.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0008_img_1031_3"/>
              Our two friends were well <lb/>&amp; especially the younger, <lb/> in good spirits.   Another good thing, they <lb/>have lots of books &amp; can <lb/>read a good deal. They <lb/>can use nothing that is <lb/>not prison property, but t <lb/>he head warden explained <lb/>a little point about books. <lb/>He told me if I wished <lb/>my young friend to have <lb/>any special book treating <lb/>of his profession I could <lb/>send it, provided the <lb/>book becomes prison <lb/>property. Needless to say <lb/>I have just sent on a  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0008_img_1031_4"/>
              <lb/>valuable book on his <lb/>future profession (Architecture) <lb/>to Conor, or rather to the <lb/>governor as prison property. <lb/>Perhaps you would care <lb/>to do the same for your <lb/>husband.   The priest is an Irish <lb/>man, from the North. <lb/>Not quite 'our way' but <lb/>an Irishman. Our men <lb/>have confession &amp; H. Communion <lb/>every week. The Bishop <lb/>of Plymouth paid each <lb/>one of them a personal <lb/>visit. Rather unusual <lb/>for 'convicts', is it not? <lb/>The head warden who  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0008_img_1031_5"/>
              <lb/>was on duty during our <lb/>visits, &amp; took many notes of <lb/>what we said, seems a <lb/>decent, good man. He <lb/>was quite a formal &amp; <lb/>official person when <lb/>speaking to us, but <lb/>when he spoke to Conor <lb/>he was much nicer &amp; <lb/>more sympathetic. I <lb/>took this as a good sign.  It has been explained to <lb/>our prisoners that if their <lb/>friends cannot visit them <lb/>they can write an extra <lb/>letter in lieu of the visit. <lb/>This would mean an<cb/><lb/>ordinary letter about Oct. <lb/>&amp; another, instead of a visit, <lb/>sometime in Dec! However <lb/>I'll do my best to go see <lb/>my two in October. It is <lb/>expensive, over Â£4-5 return to Princetown.    I have just learned that <lb/>the younger brother of the <lb/>boy I saw in Dartmoor <lb/>arrived home last night <lb/>from Frongoch, also <lb/>another of our past boys. <lb/> I think I have told you <lb/>the chief particulars. If <lb/>you could come see us I <lb/>might remember a little <lb/>more. But you now have  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0008_img_1031_6"/>
              <lb/>as much as any visitor <lb/>could gather. <seg type="closer"> With kind regards from Mother &amp; myself<lb/> Yrs. very sincerely  Margaret Pearse </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>