<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3524">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, to Capt William Francis M. Loughnan, RAMC, 6 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Typescript letter to Captain William Francis M. Loughnan (1881-1956) wishing to &#39;convey to you the congratulations of the College on the award of the Arnott Medal.  It is with a feeling of pride that the President and Fellows follow the records of their Licentiates on the present crisis and they feel all the more proud that this unique distinction should be won by a graduate of the College.&#39; (See related letter RCPI/2/3/1/58/T66)</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-13-149</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3524</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0845">Fellow and Registrar, Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</persName>
              <date>1916-03-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0272">Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William Francis M. Loughnan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3524_img_2929_1"  type="Letter"  url="964346f3727fc1cf28da10bed0b38b64.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3524_img_2929_1"/>
             RCD1/2/3/2/13/199   6th MARCH 16.   Capt.W.P.M.Loughman,R.A.M.C.,   Dear Sir,   I am requested by the President and Fellows of<lb/>the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland to convey to<lb/>you the congratulations of the College on the award of<lb/>the Arnott Medal. It is with a feeling of pride that<lb/>the President &amp; Fellows follow the records of their<lb/>Licentiates in the present crisis and they feel all the<lb/>more proud that this unique distinction should be won by<lb/>a graduate of the College.   I remain,<lb/>Yours faithfully,<lb/>Fellow &amp; Registrar.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>