<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3688">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Francis Hopwood to John Redmond, 2 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Hopwood</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Francis Hopwood (1860 – 1947) to John Redmond (1856-1918) regarding the events of the Easter Rising and Casement&#39;s arrival in Dublin. He expresses his sympathies and offers Redmond any services he might require. 

Francis Hopwood, 1st Baron Southborough, was a British civil servant. In 1917 he was elected secretary to the Irish Convention, and was chosen to find solutions to the Irish Home Rule question.

John Redmond was an MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. He was instrumental in securing the promise of Home Rule from Asquith&#39;s liberal government. Upon the outbreak of war, Redmond addressed a group of Irish Volunteers at Woodenbridge, Co. Wicklow, encouraging them to fight with the British Army to ensure the implementation of Home Rule. Redmond&#39;s words split the Irish Volunteers across the country. The Easter Rising shocked Redmond, who condemned it bitterly. Nonetheless he appealed for leniency towards those who had not been involved in planning the Rising. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>John Redmond Papers, Collection List No. 118; MS 15,197/4/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3688</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1351">Francis Hopwood</persName>
              <date>1916-05-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1486">John Redmond</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3688_img_3080_1"  type="Letter"  url="35fe7698ffd18f0abf59447ed19eb2fb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3688_img_3080_2"  type="Letter"  url="feabc238f6b0ead615bf3ac73cf8e33b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3688_img_3080_3"  type="Letter"  url="821d2a0bbe4f9cf457893cf79e4b52cf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3688_img_3080_4"  type="Letter"  url="2406aedb3ea6ef16176115209ad839b2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3688_img_3080_1"/>
             personal   May 2nd /16    Dear Mr. Redmond,  <lb/><seg type="unclear">Granard</seg><!-- A name -->has been <lb/>writing me letters couched <lb/>in terms if misgiving <lb/>as to whether he did <lb/>the right thing as regards <lb/>yourself &amp; other friends <lb/>in not responding to the <lb/>suggestion that he should <lb/>return to Ireland. I have <lb/>told him that you made <lb/>it plain to me that <lb/><sic>altho'</sic> you would have been
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3688_img_3080_2"/>
            glad to have him 'other <lb/>things being equal you <lb/>recognised at this <lb/>moment his talk of <lb/>duty lay elsewhere. <lb/>If he writes to you in the <lb/>same strain perhaps you will <lb/><seg type="unclear">fire</seg> him like advice. <seg type="unclear">His</seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear">Lordship</seg> feels sure that what <lb/>was done was right. <lb/>Another letter in this same <lb/>sense came from him <seg type="unclear">only</seg> <lb/>yesterday &amp; where Granard <lb/>hears of the terrible happenings <lb/>in Ireland he will become <lb/>more uncertain than ever.
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3688_img_3080_3"/>
             And the happenings have<lb/>been terrible &amp; I sympathise<lb/>deeply with you. Last<lb/>night I pulled out Barnaby<lb/>Rudge again &amp; read it after<lb/>long years. If Casement<lb/>had arrived in Dublin<lb/>he would have   the<lb/>Lord George Gordon to perfection.<lb/>Among his followers there<lb/>must be many. With Barnaby<lb/>Rudge humself. Reminiscenses<lb/>of the gravity of crime &amp;<lb/>without understanding of the<lb/> <seg type="unclear"></seg> involved. Now like<lb/>Barnabys they are all <seg type="unclear">food</seg><lb/>for the   only <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>be bought off by petition.    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3688_img_3080_4"/>
             It is only the other day that<lb/>I hoped &amp; expected to be<lb/>taking a part in this<lb/> <seg type="unclear"></seg> to inaugurate<lb/>the new government of Ireland.<lb/>For the time that has passed<lb/>away. If I can be of<lb/>any service in a <seg type="unclear"></seg> <lb/>to inquire into this wretched<lb/>business. For I think we<lb/>must be appointed. I<lb/>should be glad to be of<lb/>service. But I only<lb/>mention this to you in<lb/>strict confidence in <seg type="del">our</seg> the<lb/>event of its being of <hi rend="underline">use</hi>.<lb/>There is no other <sic>other</sic>  but<lb/>that &amp; a general sympathy.<lb/>Alas! I have quite enough to<lb/>do already.      <seg type="unclear"></seg>      Francis J Hopwood     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>