<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0225">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate English to Patrick English in Stafford Prison, c. June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate English</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Patrick English (1894-1970) in Stafford Prison, from his mother Kate English (b. 1855). She inquires after his health and visiting him when he is sent to Frongoch. She mentions a &#39;May&#39; (probably Patrick&#39;s sister May) who sent Patrick a parcel. She advises Patrick that she is well and is receiving money weekly. Patrick English (1894-1970) was part of F. Company, 4th Battalion, Dublin Brigade who fought in the General Post Office Garrison. After the surrender, he was imprisoned in Stafford, and later transferred to Wormwood Scrubs and then interned in Frongoch.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/225</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0077">Kate English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0478">Dunsink Cottage, Castleknock, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1848">Stafford Prison, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0225_img_1383_1"  type="Letter"  url="c4b86165faa57dfd9c0b3701e96ec8ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0225_img_1383_2"  type="Letter"  url="3967fb4c8dcc0c9c460617c07f7e7bd2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0225_img_1383_3"  type="Letter"  url="ce7f5154f81bbdcabca364675d9bcfc0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0225_img_1383_1"/>
              Don't forget <lb/> and let me <lb/> know if you <lb/> get the Postal <lb/> Order. All at <lb/> home send <lb/> you their <lb/> best. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Love</hi> xxxx     Dunsink Cottage,  Castle Knock.   My Dear Patrick,   I received <lb/> your welcome letter glad to <lb/> hear you are well I was <lb/> uneasy about you when you <lb/> were not writing I thought <lb/> you were sick but thank <lb/> God you are all right <lb/> I am also pleased you <lb/> got my two postal orders <lb/> I sent you. If I had <lb/> known you had no <lb/> stamps I would have <lb/> sent you some. <lb/> Iam sending you <lb/>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0225_img_1383_2"/>
              here enclosed 2/ postal <lb/> order and 3 stamps. <lb/> You were talking about <lb/> going to Wales to the detention <lb/> Camps. When I find <lb/> out where you are <lb/> going to I will go <lb/> over to see you <lb/> find out all particulars <lb/> how I would get over <lb/> to see you. I suppose <lb/> I would not know <lb/> you with your <lb/> whiskers. I had <lb/> a letter from May <lb/> last week and she <lb/> was telling me that <lb/><cb/> she had a letter from <lb/> you several times she <lb/> also told me she <lb/> sent you some <lb/> parcels she is very <lb/> kind to you. I will <lb/> send you on the coffee <lb/><seg type="del">on</seg> later on as I was <lb/> not in town to get <lb/> it. It was a fortnight <lb/> since I had a letter <lb/> from you until I <lb/> got this one. and date <lb/> your letters when <lb/> sending them, I <lb/> hope you are not  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0225_img_1383_3"/>
              fretting about me as <lb/> I am going on splendid <lb/> As I told you I was <lb/> getting some money <lb/> every week from <lb/> A committee so I am <lb/> not too bad keep <lb/> up your poor heart <lb/> and you will be home <lb/> some time. I believe <lb/> you have got fat. <lb/> the rest will do you <lb/> good I have no more to <lb/> say at present hoping <lb/> to hear from you soon <lb/> again.  <seg type="closer"> Good Bye Dear Patrick <lb/> From Your Loving <lb/> Mother.   K. English <lb/> xxxxxxxxx  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>