<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2261">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery to Waldron, 26 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery (1844-1924). Montgomery was a lawyer and politician. Originally a Liberal and a strong supporter of Gladstone, Montgomery was also a firm Unionist, but by 1916 he believed that Ulster Unionists had no choice but to accept Lloyd George&#39;s proposal for a six-county Northern Ireland.
In the letter Montgomery is discussing the leadership of John Redmond (1856-1918). Montgomery believes that a situation has developed which may allow Redmond to maintain his position as leader of the majority of &#39;Irish Nationalists in Ireland, Great Britain and America&#39;. Redmond was a nationalist MP and leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party. On the outbreak of the Great War Redmond had called on Irishmen to support the war effort and enlist in the British army. Montgomery considers this development a considerable gain as Redmond professes loyalty to the Empire for the purposes of the First World War. However, Montgomery foresees difficulties for Redmond when negotiations eventually come to an end and Redmond will have to set up a government. Montgomery believes that this will result in another rebellion. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Montgomery of Blessingborn Papers; D/627/429/45</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2261</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1402">Hugh de Fellenberg Montgomery</persName>
              <date>1916-06-26</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Waldron</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1924</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2261_img_1704_1"  type="Letter"  url="40638bff62ed84a070efe50f6163557d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2261_img_1704_1"/>
            Copy  26th June 1916.   Dear Mr. Waldron,   I am much obliged for your interesting letter, part <lb/>of which I entirely agree with. I do not believe the Lloyd <lb/>Geroge arrangement could possibly come into actual operation; <lb/>but a situation has been created which may enable Redmond to <lb/>maintain his position as leader of the majority of Irish <lb/>Nationalists in Ireland, Great Britain and America for the <lb/>present, and from the point of view of the Cabinet, and in <lb/>view of Redmond's professed loyalty to the Empire for the <lb/>purposes of the present way, this is a considerable gain. <lb/>What the ultimate consequences will be is another matter; <lb/>but our present rulers are not able to rise above a hand- <lb/>to-mouth policy.   Very likely Redmond will not be in any desparate <lb/> hurry to bring the negotiations with Carson to an end, His <lb/>real difficulty will begin when he actually has to set up <lb/>a Government. I should think that as soon as he does he <lb/>will have to deal with a fresh Rebellion.   I am with you in taking a decidedly gloomy view of <lb/>the future of this country.   Yours very truly, 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>