<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0278">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Field to Augustine Birrell, 14 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Field</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Field MP (1843-1935) to the Chief Crown Secretary of Ireland, Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). In the letter, Field writes to Birrell to bring to his attention the issue of a boy named Mulligan who had been fined for throwing stones. He also encloses newspaper clippings of the incident.Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) served as the Chief Secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish educational system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Birrell offered his resignation on May 1.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI, CSO RP/1916/7801/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/278</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0260">William Field</persName>
              <date>1916-04-14</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0141">16 Booterstown Avenue, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0278_img_1478_1"  type="Letter"  url="2555951caa4487fcf71345a7ae3171ed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0278_img_1478_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="1245adf32fcd67f7434c36b0dc56a450.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0278_img_1478_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="0794d5e39644d8b9121cc1b400df4b11.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0278_img_1478_1"/>
                16 Booterstown Ave    14 Apl    My dear Mr Birrell   Excuse giving trouble <lb/> but if convenient Kind friend <lb/> reply to Mulligan &amp; other boys <lb/><sic>held</sic><hi rend="underline">several</hi> enquiries — also <lb/> please look into enclosures <lb/> in <hi rend="underline">'Gaelic Press'</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">'Advertising agent'</hi><lb/> 'Dublin Castle <seg type="unclear"><hi rend="underline">nicting</hi></seg><lb/><hi rend="underline">Industrial School children'</hi><lb/> I have put down a question <seg type="unclear">never</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">avail</seg> (as I dont wish to take up <lb/> the time of the house) please <lb/> let me have reply likewise about <lb/> Mulligan —  <seg type="closer"> with thanks &amp; best <lb/> wishes  <lb/> William Field </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0278_img_1478_2"/>
              We are favoured with the following <lb/> official statement made on behalf of the <lb/> Gaelic Press by the Manager, Mr. J. M. <lb/> Stanley:-   paragraph On Friday last, March 24th, the offices <lb/> and works of The Gaelic Press at 30 <lb/> Upper Liffey Street, and 3 Proby's Lane, <lb/> Dublin, were entered by a large force of <lb/> armed military and civilian police. A <lb/> warrant was read to the manager, Mr <lb/> J.M. Stanely, empowering the military <lb/> and police to seize all copies of a news- <lb/> paper called the Gael, and all type and <lb/> machinery used in the production of this <lb/> publication, the grounds alleged being <lb/> that it contained matter of a seditious <lb/> character, and likely to prejudice recruit- <lb/> ing. No particular article was referred <lb/> to. Mr. Stanley protested formally. The <lb/> military and police then took possession <lb/> of the two buildings and proceeded to <lb/> transfer the contents to a lorry in attend- <lb/> ance, which subsequently conveyed a <lb/> lot of miscellaneous matter to Dublin <lb/> Castle, under escort, two loads being <lb/> removed in this manner.   The Gaelic Press, in additiion to being <lb/> printers of The Gael, were also the <lb/> printers, or the printers and publilshers of <lb/> the following weekly newspapers: The <lb/> Gaelic Athlete, Spark, Honesty.   The firm also acted as wholesale news- <lb/> agents for the distributions of several <lb/> other weeklies, monthlies and periodicals <lb/> of which a large stock was kept on the <lb/> premises. Although the warrant for the <lb/> raid contained no clause that permitted <lb/> the removal of these various publications <lb/> still the office and storeroom stocks were <lb/> almost entirely seized and taken away. <lb/> Among these publications, in addition to <lb/> those named, were —    The Father Mathew Record, a tem- <lb/> perance organ; The Catholic Bulletin, <lb/> a religious monthly; the Irishman, a <lb/> non political literary monthly; The Red <lb/> Guide, a railway guide; Irish Society, a <lb/> Society paper; The shamrock, a maga- <lb/> zine; An Claideamh Solus, the official <lb/> organ of the Gaelic League; The Hiber- <lb/> nian, The Leader, New Ireland, <lb/> Nationality, etc.    In additiion to the foregoing, the fol- <lb/> lowing amongst other articles were seized <lb/> on the premises: All office account <lb/> books, cheque book, cheque, office files <lb/> of several newspapers, office stationery, <lb/> three formes of type, various samples <lb/> printing, 15 halfpenny stamps, postal <lb/> order 2/6, miscellaneous books, pam- <lb/> phlets, press cuttings, blank paper <lb/> essential parts printing presses, dustbin, <lb/> large quantities of private and business <lb/> correspondence, Gaelic Press signboard, <lb/> Jobbing work, the property of the Gaelic <lb/> Athletic Association and others.   The warrant read prior to the raid <lb/> only dealt with the publication entitled <cb/><lb/> The Gael, yet the above articles, in no <lb/> way appertaining (most of them) to the paper <lb/> paper named, were also summarily seized <lb/> and carried away.   No previous warning or intimation <lb/> was given that the Gaelic Press has acted <lb/> illegally, and in consequence of this <lb/> drastic action of the military authorities <lb/> the business has been dislocated and <lb/> much unemployment created in consequence <lb/> of the dismantling <lb/> of the machinery. The <lb/> firm was left without any means of securing <lb/> its outstanding debts, and consequently, <lb/> its revenues by reason of the <lb/> seizure of its account books, and its <lb/> records of business transactions.   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0278_img_1478_3"/>
              <hi rend="underline">THE CASTLE &amp; INDUSTRIAL SCHOOLS</hi>  To the Editor of the Freeman's Journal.  Dear Sir — I have read with much interest <lb/> a letter from Rev. F. Carroll, Rathmines, in <lb/> your issue of Tuesday last, on the discharge <lb/> of our poor children from industrial schools. <lb/> Like Fr. Carroll, I think the action of Dub- <lb/> lin Castle in ordering the discharge of chil- <lb/> dren who have been legally committed under <lb/> a magistraste's order, and without any re- <lb/> ference to the magistrate who has made the <lb/> order, requires explanation.   Fr. Carroll asks: 'Will Dublin Castle give <lb/> any explanation' No. Dublin Castle will <lb/> give no explanation, unless an explanation is <lb/> forced from it. But perhaps some of your <lb/> lawyer readers will tell us:- 1. Under what statute or other legal <lb/> authority does 'Dublin Castle' order any <lb/> such discharge? <lb/> 2. If there be any legal authority, who in <lb/> 'Dublin Castle' is empowered by law to <lb/> exercise it? <lb/> 3. Is it legal to order the discharge, with- <lb/> out any reference too the magistrate who <lb/> publicly ivestigated the case and judicially <lb/> decided it was a proper case for committal? <lb/> 4. If the magistrate need not be consulted, <lb/> is any and, if so, what kind of investigation <lb/> binding on 'Dublin Castle' before it reverses <lb/> the magistrate's decision? <lb/> 5. What is the English procedure in such <lb/> cases?   It may be that 'Dublin Castle' is acting <lb/> within its legal rights, even when it acts most <lb/> harshly, as it seems to have acted in the <lb/> case Father Carroll refers to. But, if so, <lb/> some changes would seem to be needed in the <lb/> in the law itself, as certainly some change seems <lb/> to be neded in the law's administration, <lb/> and I have no doubt some Irish members of <lb/> Parliament can be found to interest them- <lb/> selves in the question.   It is well to remember that it is our <lb/> Catholic children who are chiefly concerned; <lb/> and I am informed that it is almost exclu- <lb/> sively Catholic children who are discharged <lb/> from the inidustrial schools under 'Dublin <lb/> Castle' orders. — Faithfully yours, THOMAS J. O'FARRELL, C.C. <lb/> The Presbytery, Meath street.   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>