<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1219">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Pte B Ward to The Lady Clonbrock, April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Pte. B. Ward</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A note from a prisoner of war, Private B Ward, to Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Ward writes an acknowledgement of parcels received from Lady Clonbrock yet laments that he his parcel of clothing has not arrived yet. Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834 - 1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Collection List No 54, Ms 35796-14</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1219</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1274">Pte. B. Ward</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0049">Lady Clonbrock</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1043">Ahascragh, Galway</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1219_img_40_1"  type="Letter"  url="3e485c5300da03309609918740a15ee6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1219_img_40_2"  type="Letter"  url="fa768bb30456d1065ba57204724a105c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1219_img_40_1"/>
                <seg type="foreign">Kriegsgefangenenalge</seg>    Limburg,   Dear Madam,   I have received your <lb/>parcels in good condition sent <lb/>by your request from the I.W.A. <lb/>and very thankful to you for <lb/> your kindness. There have been <lb/>parcels of Clothing and boots <lb/>sent to my comrades in the <lb/>camp and  I  have not got the clothing <lb/>parcel up to the present. I hope you will see about it.  <seg type="closer"> <seg type="unclear">I remain</seg> your obt servt   B. W. </seg> Containing food  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1219_img_40_2"/>
              <lb/>This is my address: <lb/>Name Pte B Ward <lb/>Name of the Regt. Conn Rangers <lb/>Regt. No. 10685 <lb/>Gef. Batt., II, 6 Gef. Comp., Gef. No.774 <lb/>Prisoner of War Camp <lb/><seg type="foreign"><hi rend="underline">Limburg an der Lahn, Germany</hi></seg> Right side   The Lady Clonbrock,  Clonbrock, Aherscragh  Ireland    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>