<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1650">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 19 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (née Moore). At the outbreak of war in 1914 Marie (1892-1975) joined the Voluntary Aid Detachment, a division of the Red Cross. She returned home briefly in 1916 following the death of her brother in battle until being called to serve again two months later in a field hospital in Heraldo France. Marie later founded the Medical Missionaries of Mary.
In this letter Marie thanks her mother for her letters and the shamrock sent be her brothers and grandmother. She informs her  that there have been some concerts on close to where she works for St. Patrick&#39;s Day and that the men are longing to be in Ireland again. Marie tells her mother about their new matron who is very kind to her. Marie asks for news about her brothers Charlie (1895-1915) and Tommy (b.1891) who are serving on the front.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF135</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1650</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1916-03-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_1"  type="Letter"  url="406c8043dd1316fbf870b2b664a23afb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_2"  type="Letter"  url="b73d16026b454ca48de31c75cf716a78.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_3"  type="Letter"  url="0344238d00924792cdf113164ddb60b2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_4"  type="Letter"  url="c38aefbe99a8fa443a693cff4a075f5b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_5"  type="Letter"  url="3664698e2e57e862c0a23efd515cb47b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_6"  type="Letter"  url="667fbbd60d75fbf4fbb3d4188e7df596.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_7"  type="Letter"  url="c1bcb0b3231dcf88d7f9784a5e2dea24.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1650_img_1110_8"  type="Letter"  url="656832acf4a47e0041ac3ac459f28c83.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_1"/>
             19-3-16  <lb/>3 A.M.  My very dearest mother,    A thousand thanks for <lb/>your letter dated the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of March, <lb/>also one the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi rend="superscript">superscript text</hi> of Feb: which arrived <lb/>the same day. I was delighted to <lb/>get them, also the shamrock <lb/>from the boys &amp; Nana. I gave <lb/>it round to all my men &amp; <lb/>they were delighted with it although <lb/>it was quiet dead. I <lb/>was the only Irish person <lb/>who got some in time. I sent <lb/>  off in <seg type="unclear">Corotsies</seg> to High Mass <lb/>on St Patrick day which they <lb/>were all delighted with. There <lb/>was a concert not very far <lb/>away from here that evening <lb/>&amp; on Saturday another <lb/>concert &amp; Sunday a tea or
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_2"/>
            Bun fight as the men call <lb/> it of course they all longed <lb/> to be in Ireland &amp; the day <lb/> &amp; took great delight in telling <lb/> us that if they had been at <lb/> home they would have got <lb/> drunk, they look on it as <lb/> by far the best way to enjoy <lb/> themselves. One of my orderlies <lb/> who is an Irish Rifle had <lb/> really had a good day of it <lb/> but I had not the heart to <lb/> report him on St Patrick's <lb/> Day but then I had all <lb/> the trouble &amp; worry that he <lb/> was not seen or I should <lb/> have got it hot but I got <lb/> the other orderly to put him
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_3"/>
            to bed in our empty ward <lb/> &amp; when the Ward Master &amp; <lb/> Orderly Officer came round <lb/> he was always doing something <lb/> for a patient in a ward. <lb/> I am glad to say it went <lb/> off alright &amp; I gave him a <lb/> good talking to next night <lb/> &amp; said of course if it occurred <lb/> again I should have to <lb/>report him. He seemed so <lb/> sorry &amp; ashamed of himself <lb/> &amp; is altogether much more <lb/> satisfactory. As I say I <lb/> spend most of my time going <lb/> round seeing all the patients <lb/> are asleep &amp; waking up <lb/> the Orderlies. I have 14 new <lb/> patients since I last wrote,
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_4"/>
            a few Irish but not quite <lb/> so many as last time. I really do <lb/> not know what is going to happen <lb/> about this hospital they all think <lb/> now it will be kept open.  Did I tell you we have a charming <lb/>new Matron it is the greatest <lb/> pleasure to work &amp; try &amp; please <lb/>her. Her one thought is that we should <lb/> all be as happy as we can. She <lb/> is a Territorial./p>  You need not worry about me as <lb/> she will be the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> person to take <lb/> me off night duty if she thinks <lb/> it is not agreeing with me. <lb/> She has been sweet to me &amp; <lb/> <sic>askes</sic> me every morning how <lb/> I feel &amp; like it. I think it <lb/> will suit me alright natural <lb/> I feel very tired in the mornings
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_5"/>
            so far I have been able to get <lb/> quite a good sleep by day. I <lb/> nearly always get about 5 hours <lb/> sleep, so that is not too bad. <lb/> It is ages since I saw A. Lily <lb/> so am ringing her up &amp; asking <lb/> her up to tea at 5 <sic>Ock</sic>. I <lb/> shall be in bed but that does not <lb/> matter. I want to hear her <lb/> latest news.     I am so glad you did not miss <lb/> seeing Gerald. I have not <lb/> heard from him since. I am <lb/> looking forward to his next <lb/> letter very much telling me <lb/> how he found you all. <lb/> I suppose there is no more news <lb/> of Charlie &amp; what about Tommy
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_6"/>
            has he left Alexandria yet then he <lb/> is supposed to be getting a rest. I <lb/> hope this is true. I have a <lb/> Srg. Connaught Ranger &amp; a Pt. <lb/> How are they all at 28 Clyde <lb/> R<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> it is ages since I have heard <lb/> from any of them. I hope <seg type="unclear">tht</seg> <lb/> Charlie is very well &amp; got my last <lb/> letter tell him all about Paul, <lb/> the Captain we met on our way <lb/> back from West Indies. <lb/> I think it will be nearly time <lb/> to go home in May or I shall <lb/> be walking out of all my clothes. <lb/> My uniform dresses are going to <lb/> ribbon &amp; underclothing are <lb/> nearly rags, the washing must <lb/> be very hard on the clothes.
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_7"/>
             &amp; as for shoes, tell Nana the <lb/>Greenbank <seg type="unclear">parcel</seg> is not in it. <lb/> my combination are a delightful <lb/> bit of patrol work, but it all <lb/> only add to the excitement of <lb/> the whole thing - it is not worth <lb/> <sic>buy</sic> any thing we're getting things <lb/> sent out. Did you get my <lb/> coat done? I spend my nights <lb/> mending. Will try &amp; make <lb/> myself some nice camisoles <lb/> when every thing is mended. <lb/> I was just delighted to hear <lb/> you &amp; Ethel went for a few <lb/> days change to Kilkenny <lb/> I hope it did you good &amp; <lb/> must have been a great treat <lb/> for Aunt Eileen — I hope she <lb/> is quite strong now.
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1650_img_1110_8"/>
            The new lot of V A D have not <lb/> gone home yet.  How funny about old W <lb/> Gravely turning up, he has <lb/> not come here yet.    Now I must close with every <lb/> loving thought, good wish &amp; <lb/> luck.  Your most grateful &amp; <lb/> loving daughter,    Marie 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>