<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2874">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 4 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>WIlfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of  the Great War.

In this letter Spender is writing to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served  in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution.

In this letter, Spender descrbes Lillian&#39;s letters as &#39;the greatest help possible&#39;. He expresses satisfaction that she is settling into the new house, and dismay that because there are only two maids, they will not be able to take afternoons off together. He suggests that Lillian employ another girl once a week to give the maids a chance to take an afternoon off together. Spender then criticises the turn of The Times towards support of Home Rule, and also criticises Carson&#39;s position as &#39;anomalous&#39;.  He instructs Lillian to send their joint best wishes t the parents of the captured C Craig, and discourages Lillian from writing &#39;such long letters&#39;. Spender writes that he is finally free from his &#39;gas shell head&#39;, and worries that the men of the Ulster Division will get little credit for their valour, because few people wish to be associated with a &#39;glorious failure&#39;.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/334</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2874</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0708">WIlfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-07-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2874_img_2286_1"  type="NULL"  url="dcd191eafba737346a5d88c121408be8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2874_img_2286_2"  type="NULL"  url="980defe2d814cb06240d1496c99408dc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2874_img_2286_3"  type="NULL"  url="188213328dc5c53b716db459fea9c218.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2874_img_2286_4"  type="NULL"  url="24bd4e85a0a4ed4d14d36a130e2cdb9b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2874_img_2286_1"/>
             D1633/1/1/334   4 July    My p r    We are back resting I have seen something more<lb/>of our heroes as cheerful as possible in spite of everything.<lb/>Your letters are the greatest help possible. I am<lb/>so glad you like the house &amp; its atmosphere,<lb/>but a little sorry for the 2 maids not being<lb/>able to go out together. Cannot you get some<lb/>little girl in once a week so as to let them<lb/>have an afternoon out.  I wil not discuss the military situation<lb/>as the papers will give you the news especially<lb/>if you don't read what they say.  <lb/>The Times on the Irish question is too<lb/>abominable it is completely Home Rule now, but Carson's<lb/>position is also somewhat anomalous. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2874_img_2286_2"/>
             I'm afraid C Craig is wounded &amp; a prisoner. If this<lb/>is confirmed in the papers please write to Mrs in both our<lb/>names if you can spare the time.  Cannot you get a girl typewriter to your office<lb/>now &amp; dictate your letters. This would be my contribution<lb/>to the fund.  You mustn't attempt such long letters to<lb/>the b w now. I quite understand it is unfair on a<lb/>p r &amp; if I get letter slips regularly I shall be<lb/>content.  My gas shell head has quite gone now, but<lb/>yesterday my eyes were still giving me much trouble<lb/>&amp; I began to be anxious today they are quite all<lb/>right.  The men are truly wonderful, &amp; this<lb/>General is about speaking to them, but the Ulster 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2874_img_2286_3"/>
             Division will of course get little credit for what<lb/>it has done, because there <seg type="del">was</seg> is no one <seg type="del">to</seg> who<lb/>likes to be associated with  even a glorious failure.  If you have not sent my yesterday's<lb/>letter to Mr. G &amp; still intend to do so, make it<lb/>clear that I do not wish any publication of<lb/>the letter; tho' the press censor would not object<lb/>I have sent it mainly to let him know how<lb/>our men did. He can make his own comments<lb/>using my letter if he wishes of course.  Richardson is a good chap. He was here<lb/>yesterday, &amp; is staying here at our old H Q.<lb/>I am back in my hut again, &amp; had a splendid<lb/>night.  I must write to Craig<lb/> Always your b w<lb/>W B Spender   P T O    
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2874_img_2286_4"/>
             Of course you were right to get the best carpet<lb/>sweeper. Am delighted to hear that I am to have a<lb/>nice bedroom to myself; so there! - away from all<lb/>vermin.  I'm afraid Major (?Capt) Jenkins of Leitrim is<lb/>killed. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>