<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4197">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Samuel Shaw to Martha Shaw, 21 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Samuel Shaw</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Samuel Shaw to his mother, Martha Shaw, updating her on his well being. Samuel writes that he has heard from his father and is glad that the fishing is improving. He mentions that there are rumours going around the camp about getting leave but that he does not believe they are true.

Samuel Henry Shaw (1896-1967) was a sergeant with the 10th Battalion, Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers. He volunteered for active service in September 1914. Before enlisting Samuel was a member of the Portstewart Company, Coleraine Battalion, North Derry Regiment, Ulster Volunteer Force. Samuel served in France, and was wounded during the Battle of the Somme in July 1916 and again in early 1917 and in 1918. Before the War he was employed as a ironmonger&#39;s assistant. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-20</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4197</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0493">Samuel Shaw</persName>
              <date>1916-01-21</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Martha Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1027">Shorncliffe, Portstewart, Co. Derry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1967</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4197_img_3569_1"  type="Letter"  url="9988d6aa217ebf2ae74442ee2d81fd29.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4197_img_3569_2"  type="Envelope"  url="b12b6d5e72f35a74fb92547fcc9e06cd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4197_img_3569_1"/>
             Same Address   21 — 1 — 16   My Dear <lb/>Mother   Just a few lines to let you know <lb/>I received your letters &amp; parcel all right. There is <lb/>not much to say, things are very quite just <lb/>now. I see by a letter I h#ad from dad to— <lb/>;day that the fishing is improving. I am <lb/>glad to hear it. There is a lot of <sic>roumours</sic> <lb/>going about here about leave, but I don't <lb/>think there is any truth in it. I hope <lb/>this finds you all in the pink of condit- <lb/>ion. I have not seen Hedley for a day <lb/>or two, he is with the Bomb Throwers <lb/>now. All at present. With love to all   I remain <lb/>Your Loving Son   <hi rend="underline">Sammie.</hi> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4197_img_3569_2"/>
             Mrs Jas Shaw <lb/>Shorncliffe <lb/>Portstewart <lb/>Co. Derry <lb/>Ireland 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>