<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0648">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy Duffin to her mother, Maria Duffin, 30 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Dorothy DuffIn (b. 1881) to her mother, Maria (1854–1954). In this letter Dorothy hopes that her sister Emma (1883–1979) has reached home. She writes that unless she gets a raise in pay at the Admiralty she will be in a net loss situation. She has been talking to a secretary in the War Office and has learned that pay and conditions there are much better but there aren&#39;t any vacancies at the moment. Despite the snow Dorothy hopes her mother will be able to visit in May.This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family that lived in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who was a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/648</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0232">Ardeevin, Epsom, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0648_img_2123_1"  type="Letter"  url="6ee860200451775fc576848155f321ea.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0648_img_2123_2"  type="Letter"  url="0622142c57916ee8f79cd1c2301528b3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0648_img_2123_3"  type="Letter"  url="84e182a9a4875da4279491e5b81bbed8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0648_img_2123_4"  type="Letter"  url="65a07edfaf424962080ed60e21e47120.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0648_img_2123_1"/>
                'Ardeevin'    March 30th   Dearest Mamma    I do hope poor Emma<lb/> has returned home! I have been thinking<lb/> &amp; worrying about her being <seg type="unclear">showered</seg><lb/> and she would feel the cold so.  We had a great meeting together<lb/> but she will tell you all that<lb/> &amp; about our visit to the Admiralty.  I hope I've done the right thing.<lb/> I don't know. But any way I am not<lb/> bound to anything. I dread the start.<lb/> I wish I could have had my visit<lb/> to Eastbourne &amp; <seg type="unclear">Winchester</seg> first.  I have found rooms (for a time anyway)<lb/> by a strange chance at <lb/> 152 Vauxhall Bishope Road London  I went to enquire at Alexandria<lb/> Ladies Club, Grosvenor St about rooms,<lb/> quite a smart place. Not II feel<lb/> sure the place I intended. I saw  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0648_img_2123_2"/>
              the Secretary who was pleasant and<lb/> said she had a friend upstairs who<lb/> might keep me. Down came a Mrs<lb/> R ONeill, widow of a Colonel R ONeill,<lb/> who said she was now living &amp; working<lb/> at the Club but she had left<lb/> a friend, Miss Holmes at her<lb/> flat &amp; this friend was anxious<lb/> to find paying guests so as not have<lb/> to give it up. Already a girl<lb/> working at the Admiralty is there<lb/> &amp; one or two other ladies. After<lb/> much chat we came to terms ( I<lb/> think I must have looked pathetically<lb/> tired!) She said I will lodge<lb/> at the flat for a guinea a week<lb/> &amp; have breakfast &amp; dinner there,<lb/> (also lunch on Sundays) bath, light<lb/> and <seg type="unclear">attendance.</seg>  Her friend (Miss Holmes) was coming<lb/> to tea with her at the Club, <seg type="unclear">and</seg><lb/> she gave me a note to the maid<lb/> &amp; I went off &amp; saw the place. It  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0648_img_2123_3"/>
              is near Victoria station &amp; convenient to<lb/> Whitehall - quite a pleasant house,<lb/> with a nice drawing room, flowers<lb/> and bright fire, quite nice bedrooms<lb/> &amp; a cheerful maid.<lb/> Well â I've heard from Miss Holmes,<lb/> &amp; I go there on Saturday. I shall<lb/> lunch with the <seg type="unclear">MacLeods</seg> &amp; probably <lb/> meet Celia in the evening, &amp; start<lb/> work on Monday. It seems a<lb/> promising venture but I doubt if<lb/> she'll keep me long on those terms.<lb/> 26/â was asked even so with<lb/> washing, lunching out etc, I calculate<lb/> I shall be losing at least 10/â a week! If there is<lb/> no rise I can't stay at the Admiralty<lb/> â however they may <seg type="unclear">chuck</seg> me!    I interviewed a Secretary at the new<lb/> War office place â the pay and hours were<lb/> better there but no immediate<lb/> vacancy. The Secretary said I  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0648_img_2123_4"/>
              should do much better   I'm sure you are delighted to<lb/> have Emma. I feel I did not <lb/> half see her - everything was so<lb/>rushed  I've been all over London lately <lb/> between looking for jobs &amp; lodgings.<lb/> Bedford House was quite full<lb/> up.  Annie <seg type="unclear">Hollins</seg> turned up here last<lb/> night 6 hours late because of <lb/> the snow which make me fear for<lb/> Emma. She has been babbling<lb/> ever since!  I trust that now you will come over in <lb/> May &amp; see me &amp; Annie F.  Best love Dear- I won't have<lb/> much time for letters when I start<lb/> work! <seg type="closer"> Your loving   Dussie </seg> Best love to Papa.<lb/> I hope he keeps well.<lb/> I didn't expect to be away so long when<lb/> I left home!  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>