<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0626">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Celia Duffin to Maria Duffin, February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Celia Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Celia Duffin (1888-1979) to her mother Maria (1854-1954) informing her about her latest activities in London. Celia writes about the various visits she has made during the week and looking at Raemaekers ghastly war cartoons. When speaking of her patients, Celia mentions an Italian chef nicknamed &#39;Spaghetti&#39;, who somehow has made it into the British army. This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA. Celia Duffin along with her sister Ruth published a book of poems titled &#39;&#39;Escape Poem&#39;&#39; (illustrated by their sister Emma Duffin) and published by Maunsell #&amp;amp; Co. Ltd in 1929.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/B/6/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/626</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1155">Celia Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0626_img_2067_1"  type="Letter"  url="a748c44c2f59098b062c9aeafe363aaf.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0626_img_2067_2"  type="Letter"  url="d14894df8f385222bfa3172b10892e28.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0626_img_2067_3"  type="Letter"  url="c622e91f64e149da95bfab4ef34e5bd2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0626_img_2067_4"  type="Letter"  url="5094ed54d4efa2816a5ec8b5d4b4fd67.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0626_img_2067_5"  type="Letter"  url="aef8606893e81118c816ac283acd344e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0626_img_2067_1"/>
                <seg type="unclear">11</seg> Feb 1916, <hi rend="underline">Friday</hi>   Dearest Mamma   I have just finished counting <lb/>my washing and will have time <lb/>for a letter home before going back to <lb/>hospital. Yesterday I went home to <lb/>Ealing with Marjorie Monaghan and <lb/>had tea and dinner there. We <lb/>didn't do much except sit and <lb/>talk over the fire. She has<seg type="del">had</seg><lb/>a new hut now at the hospital <lb/>to cook all the orderlies meals <lb/>at. I think it is awfully <lb/>clever of her. She and one other  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0626_img_2067_2"/>
              girl do all the cooking for 60 <lb/>orderlies. The detachment quartermas— <lb/>ter arranges all the meals and <lb/>orders the supplies and she does <lb/>the cooking and sewing, with <lb/>nobody to help, except scrubbing <lb/>women who do the washing <lb/>up. Mrs Monaghan and the <lb/>sister were there; the sister is very <lb/>pretty and is busy working at <lb/>one of those depots for supplying <lb/>hospitals with bandages etc  M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Caldecott is still invalided, <lb/>I went to visit her the other day <lb/>at a nursing home in Henrietta <cb/><lb/>Street. She has strained herself and <lb/>the doctor says will have to lie on <lb/>her back for some time. She is <lb/>very depressed at having to give <lb/>up her nursing.  I went up to town with the <lb/>Lecky girl last Saturday and <lb/>looked in at Raemaekers cartoons <lb/>in old Bond St. They are awfully <lb/>clever but most of them very <lb/>ghastly, and all about the <lb/>war. We had tea together at <lb/>a nice little shop in Oxford <lb/>St. and then I went back <lb/>to Putney for dinner. Mrs  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0626_img_2067_3"/>
              Lecky is most kind and affectionate. <lb/>The girl does visitng connected with <lb/>Board Schools and is kept pretty <lb/>busy. I hadn't met M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lecky before, <lb/>he had great enquiries to make <lb/>about his 'fat old cousin', as <lb/>he calls M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Sinclair. He is <lb/>evidently very well read and <lb/>clever, and interested in monu— <lb/>ments, old castles and things of <lb/>that sort which I know nothing <lb/>about.  The other pro: has been removed <lb/>to another ward, <seg type="del">so</seg> which I <lb/>am rather glad of as I didn't  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0626_img_2067_4"/>
              care much about her, and although <lb/>it gives me more work, it is <lb/>really more satisfactory working <lb/>by yourself, as you know exactly <lb/>what has to be done.  We have a funny old Italian <lb/>chef in the ward, we always <lb/>call him spaghetti as no one <lb/>ever remembers his real name. <lb/>I can't think how he got into the <lb/>English army, and he tells <lb/>the most awful lies about all <lb/>his doings. Then there is a <lb/>very swanky sergeant—major  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0626_img_2067_5"/>
              who reigns supreme in the ward, and <lb/>a funny little mousy boy who <lb/>spends all day smoking cigarettes <lb/>and playing with the gramophone, <lb/>then there is an amusing old <lb/>fellow who talks strong cockney <lb/>that I can hardly understand <lb/>him, and a nice boy whose <lb/>father is on the war office staff. <lb/>So you see we get a funny <lb/>mixed crowd in a hospital ward. <lb/>At the far end sleep two <lb/>jolly boys who have both had <cb/><lb/>operations for appendicitis and do <lb/>nothing but giggle all day long.  I am going to make myself <lb/>a cup of your tea. I hope <lb/>your cook will be a success <lb/>this time and give you no <lb/>bother. <seg type="closer"> Best love <lb/>from your loving  Celia </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>