<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1115">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 27th May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from James Finn (1877-1922) to May Fay (1897-1976) regarding rumours of a second rebellion in Dublin. James writes that perhaps May should pray that the second rebellion won&#39;t disrupt their wedding plans rather than wasting her breath over Roger Casement&#39;s conversion. James then informs May of his progress in relation to the wedding presents he has been arranging for May and her family. James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. While neither James nor May were politically active their letters provide a very unique insight into the affairs of Easter Week and its aftermath. James died in 1922 as a result of the flu epidemic, May was pregnant with their fourth child at the time.May Fay became engaged to James Finn in January 1916. Despite the twenty year age gap their letters show a very personal and private insight into courting in early 20th century Ireland. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. May never remarried and focused her attention instead on her businesses in order to provide for their children.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>, none</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1115</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-05-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2126">National Health Insurance Commission, Pembroke House, Upper Mount Street, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1115_img_348_1"  type="NULL"  url="f3c039ce45181da3b975f06fa2c95772.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1115_img_348_2"  type="NULL"  url="60ef0503aaef6038add75c92b663ec7e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1115_img_348_1"/>
                NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE COMMISSION (IRELAND),   PEMBROKE HOUSE,   UPPER MOUNT STREET,  DUBLIN.    27th May, 1916.   My dearest May,   I wonder what I’m going to write about today. My <lb/>mind seems to be an absolute blank so far as news are concerned <lb/>except perhaps the yarns and rumours of all kinds that are going <lb/>about Dublin at present. I suppose you have heard that we are going <lb/>to have another rebellion on Whit Monday. The rumour has been <lb/>around Dublin for the last fortnight and I believe priests have <lb/>been advising people to be very circumspect during the Whitsuntide <lb/>holidays and to keep near the “shelter” &amp;c. You will observe it is <lb/>to break out just after our marriage and we shall probably be <lb/>right in the middle of it in the County Kerry so you had better <lb/>start saying your prayers for <hi rend="underline">both</hi> of us and don’t be wasting your <lb/>breath over Sir Roger Casement’s conversion. What’s the good of <lb/>my keeping a wife if she is going to pray for all and sundry <lb/>and neglect her poor husband that wants all the prayers she can <lb/>say. I have been enquiring at Hopkin’s about bangles and the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1115_img_348_2"/>
              brooch for Nano. The most of their stuff has gone in the week <lb/>but they will be able to let me see a selection of bangles on Monday. <lb/>As to the brooch, I was thinking of getting Nano something on the <lb/>Tara brooch style but I’m afraid they are not to be obtained hardly <lb/> in Dublin now. Hopkins were practically the only makers and all <lb/>their stocks of such brooches and also the dies for making them <lb/>have I hear been destroyed. I’ll see what I can do however but <lb/>perhaps she would prefer some other design. Let me know on that <lb/>point by Monday if possible. If she likes stones, let me know the <lb/> colour &amp;c. As regards yourself do you prefer a chain <seg type="del">bracelet</seg><lb/> bangle or a solid bracelet? If the former is it a curb chain <lb/>or a fancy chain? I suggest the fancy chain as the curb chain is <lb/> a bit common I think. If you prefer a solid bracelet would you <lb/> like it with stones and if so what colour? Hope the dress is <lb/>getting on well and will turn out  as big  a success as the wearer. I <lb/>fancy I can see my dear dear girl looking a picture in it and I long <lb/> to kiss her sweet face. I hope that God will bless us both. I <lb/> hope you are praying for me because I need it so badly. I have <lb/> no other news at all so will say goodbye with warmest <lb/> and most devoted love <seg type="closer"> Your ever loving   <hi rend="underline">James</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>