<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4297">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Monsieur J. des Longchamps to Sir Neville Chamberlain, 23 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J. des Longchamps</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter concerning the travel arrangements for three men who are returning to France from Londonderry and Roscommon to sign up with the French Army.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI_CSO_RP_1916_442_7_4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4297</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1075">J. des Longchamps</persName>
              <date>1915-12-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sir Neville Chamberlain</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4297_img_366_1"  type="Letter"  url="6243a68dd64865a7dc30646a69ccf40f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4297_img_366_2"  type="Letter"  url="f17d6cdc344669337946d5f14ffadfb0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4297_img_366_3"  type="Letter"  url="1ab61fd0e1e8ec33ad7322e0cd35bb28.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4297_img_366_1"/>
             CONSULAT DE FRANCE <lb/>EN IRLANDE  <lb/> Dublin le  23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> December 1915  92127<hi rend="superscript">C</hi>  Dear Sir,   I beg to <lb/>acknowledge with many thanks <lb/>the receipt of your letter of the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> inst.   I have received from the French <lb/>Embassy warrants for the free <lb/>travelling of the men you refer to, <lb/>from Londonderry &amp; Roscommon <lb/>to London.   I would be very much obliged <lb/>to you if you kindly would give <!-- address on the bottom left of page -->  Sir Neville Chamberlain  Inspector General of <lb/>The Royal Irish <lb/>Constabulary <lb/>The Castle <lb/>Dublin 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4297_img_366_2"/>
            the necessary directions for the <lb/>handing of the enclosed <lb/>warrant (N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 337684) to <lb/>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Louis Herr, Carrowroe <lb/>Park, Roscommon, to travel on the 28<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> December <lb/>next, and for the Police <lb/>giving to Louis Herr all <lb/>facilities for travelling.   M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Louis Herr should <lb/>leave Roscommon by such <lb/>a train on the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> or 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>December as to be able to <lb/>call at this Consulate, 8 <lb/>Leinster Street, on Tuesday <lb/>28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> inst between 11.a.m. <lb/>and 1.P.m. to receive the <lb/>necessary papers to leave <lb/>Ireland. It is indispensable <lb/>that he should bring with <lb/>him a small photograph
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4297_img_366_3"/>
            of himself to be stuck on <lb/>those papers.   Please accept my best <lb/>thanks in anticipation   Believe me <lb/>Yours faithfully  <!-- stamped --> LE CONSUL DE FRANCE P.S. J. <hi rend="underline">des Longchamps</hi>  P.S.We have asked a few days ago, <lb/>(the 19<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> Dec.) M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Joseph Chenay <lb/>45 Rutland Square Dublin <lb/>to present himself at this <lb/>Consulate to be sent also to <lb/>London under the same <lb/>circumstances; he has, however, <lb/>never presented himself. <lb/>J des Long 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>