<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_6641">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from George Gavin Duffy to Joseph Cyrillus Walsh, 6 July 1920 </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>George Gavan Duffy</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library Manuscripts and Archives Division</repository>
                  <collection> Folder: Box 1. f.5 Joseph C. Walsh Papers. Letters Earls - Foy</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/6641</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0467">George Gavan Duffy</persName>
              <date>1920-07-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2027">Grand Hotel, Paris</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0319">Joseph Cyrillus Walsh</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1951</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6641_img_None_1"  url="phpSlT78B.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_6641_img_None_2"  url="phpYJ1as1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_6641_img_0_1"/>
             12. Boulevard des Capucines   Paris, le 6 July 1920   J.C. WALSH Esq.  Confidential.   Dear Walsh,   a certain amount of harm is being done to Irish sym-<lb/>pathies in France by the constant attacks, direct and indirect,<lb/>on France in the Catholic and the Irish press of America. I do<lb/>not think I can do better than go to you in the matter, as you<lb/>are so much in touch with this press and America is alleged<lb/>to be not the least of the offenders. The French Catholics,<lb/>of whom the more wide-awake are by no means ignorant of what is<lb/>said in the American Catholic papers and in fact scan these<lb/>papers closely, put down the attacks on France to German in-<lb/>fluences in the States, with which they say our people are allied.<lb/>I want in the first place, to ask you to let those concerned<lb/>know with what close interest they are watched here and the<lb/>bad effect, from the point of view of Franco-Irish relations,<lb/>of the attitude in question, tho' I fancy it is rather ex-<lb/>aggerated by my French friends; in the second place, to tell<lb/>you that since Clemenceau fell the best Catholic opinion here<lb/>has dropped its aloofness from Ireland and became very friend-<lb/>ly; I refer to the directors of general Catholic opinion who<lb/>for a long time were shy of Ireland, partly because we were in<lb/>the way of French amity with England (which is now happily at<lb/>a discount) and partly because Sinn Féin was regarded as an<lb/>Irish variety of Bolshevism; thirdly, I submit that we are en-<lb/>titled to remember how basely Germany behaved towards the men<lb/>of Easterweek and how consistently the German authorities have<lb/>for many months now been kowtowing to England and seeking to<lb/>curry favour with her; I do not myself think there is at<lb/>present any chance of a rapprochement in Europe between Eire<lb/>and Deutschland, however friendly to two races may be in the<lb/>States; fourthly, France is a traditional ally  of ours  and one whom<lb/>the English are stupidly losing no opportunity of alienating,<lb/>tho' had John Bull behaved himself he could have had these<lb/>people as warm allies, for they were grateful to him and friend-<lb/>ly after the armistice and he has thrown that advantage away;<lb/>France is becoming more and more friendly to us and I think that<lb/>that friendship is capable of considerable development and that<lb/>it may be very useful hereafter, if properly cultivated.<lb/>Lastly, 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_6641_img_0_2"/>
             if you in America take the view so sedulously propagated by the<lb/>Cocoa press in England to the effect that France has shown her-<lb/>self to be out for grab and imperialism, I wd ask for a little<lb/>reconsideration of that matter; the American politician and man<lb/>of letters who came here in his hundreds in the spring of 1919<lb/>saw only the official, Clemencist France, which was sold to<lb/>England, and the sight did not inspire him; but, at that time,<lb/>the press was severely censored and French public men gener-<lb/>ally were floundering in the conflicting eddies of post-war<lb/>international politics; it was difficult for them to orientate<lb/>themselves and those who saw clear were silenced; since then<lb/>there has been a complete change in public opinion and no one<lb/>has a good word for Clemenceau; it is a pity that the two<lb/>great countries which hate England do not love and do not in<lb/>the least understand one another. I do not think it is realised<lb/>in America that the French are now but slowly recovering from<lb/>the stunning effects of a trial which was too great an ordeal<lb/>for them; I do not think it is realised that a country which<lb/>has gone thro' the horrors of German invasion as this land<lb/>has must naturally view the future thro' rather grey spec-<lb/>tacles; France is afraid of another invasion and when that<lb/>invasion comes looks to England to come to the rescue ; being<lb/>under that dread apprehension she cannot do otherwise than<lb/>look to England as things stand now, for Italy does not count,<lb/>Germany cannot yet be conciliated in the teeth of a popular<lb/>opinion (natural after such a war) and America is a long way<lb/>off and wd look coldly a shily on any new European ad-<lb/>venture. Again, it is essential to France to recover what<lb/>she can from Germany by way of indemnities, for she is broken<lb/>without this reparation and no one supposes that Germany is<lb/>going to pay if she can help it; I am not discussing the<lb/>question whether she is being asked for too much, but on<lb/>every principle of justice it is clear that she has some com-<lb/>pensation - and that of a considerable amount - to make;<lb/>here again France is obliged as things stand to look at Eng-<lb/>land; so that, hating England's universal <seg type="unclear">grah,</seg> as she does,<lb/>and her constant encroachments, she feels herself forced to<lb/>put up with the kicks for the sake of the expected halfpence.<lb/>Whether she looks at the matter from the standpoint of<lb/>security or from the standpoint of reparation, she must to a<lb/>great extent lean on England; and America could have pre-<lb/>vented this result.  I write in haste just to suggest a line of thought<lb/>that recognises the terrible plight this country is in and<lb/>involves the making of allowances for her attitude and to<lb/>emphasise the value, as I see it, of amity with France, even<lb/>at the expense of cordial relations with the Germans who<lb/>have no cordiality for Ireland. If these views are well<lb/>founded, it is time our Irish and Catholic press in the U.S.<lb/>and elsewhere adopted at least a more circuspect attitude<lb/>in dealing with this country; if you agree, and if you concur<lb/>in thinking that the evil effects now being produced here are<lb/>to be deplored, perhaps you will forgive this long screed and<lb/>say a word or two in season in the proper quarters.   With kindest regards, I am very sincerely yours,    G. Gavan Duffy     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>