<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0164">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from E. Russell to Anne O'Rahilly, September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>E. Russell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter to Anne O&#39;Rahilly, the sister of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The letter refers to a missed opportunity to meet in Dublin and goes on to discuss a demonstration of flying machines that had a great impression on the writer, an acquaintance doing penal servitude and &#39;Dick&#39;, who is attending college.Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly, was involved in the procurement of arms in the lead-up to the Rising and was involved in the Howth gun-running incident. He fought in the G.P.O. During the Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Sighle Humphreys Papers, P106/182/1/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/164</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1410">E. Russell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0150">Central Hotel, Ballybunion, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Anne O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0164_img_1295_1"  type="Letter"  url="05a7cb220fdb329e4461ecc504c2b6a7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0164_img_1295_2"  type="Letter"  url="3cb3d60353022d06a6bf6f0aa41cfef8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0164_img_1295_3"  type="Letter"  url="a6d3071fb54ac60191a6135d2f2d2412.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0164_img_1295_1"/>
              I have written this letter in the public room under difficulty     Central Hotel,  Ballybunion,  Co. Kerry.    Sunday Sept   My dear Miss Rahilly   I thought I could <lb/> write you a long letter <lb/> but  I find  the thing can't be <lb/> done at pleasure. I was <lb/> in Dublin at the <lb/> Aviation — I had a letter <lb/> from you just in time <lb/> to tell me that you would <lb/> not be in Dublin until  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0164_img_1295_2"/>
              I had left. F<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> O'Dwyer was <lb/> with me. I gave him your <lb/> address. He promised he <lb/> would call &amp; explain <lb/> how I had to come back <lb/> on Wednesday. I was really <lb/> sorry I missed the chance <lb/> of an evening. The first <lb/> day of the flying was <lb/> a complete success.   The papers represented <lb/> pretty accurately what <lb/> took place. The flying <lb/> of the Monoplane in <seg type="unclear">Dingel</seg><lb/> was an unexpected treat  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0164_img_1295_3"/>
              I would not have missed it for the world. <lb/> I changed my mind on the subject at once. <lb/> The flying machine has come to stay.   The number of people, motors, carriages, <hi rend="underline">was</hi><lb/> unique — never such a sight in holy Ireland <lb/> before. The sight has left an impression on <lb/> my mind that will remain. T. O'Dea <lb/> is still, much against his will, in Parteen. <lb/> He expects at all events to be <seg type="unclear">timed</seg> this <lb/> time as a P.P. died &amp; another is in via. <lb/> The poor man is undergoing penal servitude here <lb/> though I should be glad to release him <lb/> if <seg type="del">If</seg> I could — I was not in Lisdoonvarna this <lb/> year &amp; probably shall not. The strike in West <lb/> Clare railway makes the journey to &amp; from <lb/> uncertain &amp; hazardous — you know I don't go<lb/> in for risks - I am glad Dick is going to <lb/> College - <seg type="del">alto</seg>No amount of knowledge could <seg type="del">nd</seg><lb/> finish a man's education without the <lb/> fellowship &amp; association to be found only in <lb/> college life. I am leaving here <sic>tomorro</sic> for the <lb/> western part of this Kingdom very likely Dingle. <lb/> Must be back in Parteen next Sunday.  <seg type="closer"> Hoping you &amp; Mrs. H and all are well. Best wishes  E. Russell </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>