<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3155">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Peter Mooney to his sister Katie Mooney, April 16 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>In this letter Peter (b.1886) is writing to Katie (b.1884) thanking her for the parcel she sent him. Peter mentions seeing Miss Conlan and asks Katie to tell her he said hello. He talks about Father Cooney and how he got a great send off and refers to David Kennedy getting the worst of the law case. He asks about Paddy and hopes he will back all the winning horses. He asks for Joe Gaffney too. He asks Katie to send him a razor the next time she is in Dublin and to send him on some paper too along with a pencil. 

Orphaned at age 7, Peter and his sister Katie were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This letter part of a collection of over ninety surviving letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3155</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1916-04-16</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1038">Katie Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1966">Caulstown, Dunboyne Co.Meath</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3155_img_2577_1"  type="Letter"  url="10b010fac690513c7e67093b11481187.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3155_img_2577_2"  type="Letter"  url="275d808b5fdb91ccd8d8958a9bf9c3c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3155_img_2577_3"  type="Letter"  url="9ee0cbb172eeef3bd2a050eea572d3ba.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3155_img_2577_4"  type="Envelope"  url="2005e2ff5593ea4aed3ec026c68fcadd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3155_img_2577_1"/>
             April 16 1916   Dear Katie,   I received the parcel <lb/>you sent me alright. Every <lb/>thing in was very welcome <lb/>to me especially the Tobacco <lb/>&amp; socks. I saw Miss Conlans <lb/>name on the life boxes, <lb/>tell her I was asking for <lb/>her. I see by the Drogheda <lb/>that they gave Father <lb/>Cooney a great send off <lb/>from Kingstown. I hope <lb/>he came through alright. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3155_img_2577_2"/>
             David Kennedy seems to <lb/>have got the worst of <lb/>the law case. Connolly &amp; <lb/>Moore look very well <lb/>in the Drogheda, they keep <lb/>the public well amused. <lb/>If they were out here for <lb/>a while it would do <lb/>both of them a lot of good. <lb/>I suppose Paddy has a <lb/>busy time with all the <lb/>Ewes yeaning now ask <lb/>him does he remember the <lb/>evening we took the <lb/> <lb/>stag of Peter &amp; caught <lb/>him in the <seg type="unclear">Sixteen Acres</seg>. <lb/>Fairyhouse has good entries <lb/>this year. I hope Paddy <lb/>will back all the winners. <lb/>I suppose Joe Gaffney comes <lb/>down often tell him I <lb/>was asking for him &amp; I <lb/>hope he will have a <lb/>good year with the land. <lb/>The Grey horse should <lb/>be a beauty it would <lb/>be time to put him <lb/>out on the grass now. I hope <lb/>to have a good few
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3155_img_2577_3"/>
            hunts on him must win. <lb/>The next time you are in <lb/>Dublin send me on a good <lb/>Razor as the one I have <lb/>is worn out. I have no <lb/>more to say at present as <lb/>I say Good-Bye and pray for <lb/>me.   Peter Mooney   P.S. you might send on <lb/>a writing pad as it would <lb/>be better than this sort of <lb/>paper also a blue copying <lb/>ink pencil. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3155_img_2577_4"/>
             Miss. K. Mooney <lb/>Caulstown <lb/>Dunboyne <lb/>Co. Meath Ireland   RW Sansom 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>