<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3609">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maurice Wilkins to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 3 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maurice Wilkins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Maurice Wilkins to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) concerning the murder of Hanna&#39;s husband, Francis. Maurice expresses his sadness regarding the event and the rumour that surrounded it, as well as elaborating on the character of Francis&#39; life and the effects his death will have.

Maurice Wilkins was a suffragist who helped to produce the &#34;Irish Citizen&#34;, a suffragette newspaper. Wilkins was also the husband of Eva Wilkins (née Stephenson) who spent time in Holloway prison for suffrage activism in 1910.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy-Skeffington Papers, Collection List No.47; MS 33,605/3-10</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3609</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0888">Maurice Wilkins</persName>
              <date>1916-05-03</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0331">9 Dunville Avenue, Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_1"  type="Letter"  url="ebdb355012f7b6f6d23066e9145c49c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_2"  type="Letter"  url="e4e99203a7fd98acd4e24328f993b05a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_3"  type="Letter"  url="b0d9a5681ba184c91ca979a3669e71d2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_4"  type="Letter"  url="dacc2448e6c058d96e15bfc49244a6a3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_5"  type="Letter"  url="5e9a68ae58ccea44ee62e63bb23a74bb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_6"  type="Letter"  url="79f79519bb551f3a044e5c37500e50e8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_7"  type="Letter"  url="6e46b7eaab8371b0cab34916467bae51.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3609_img_3009_8"  type="Letter"  url="2ae39a25e97b354f5d315816cc37a374.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_1"/>
             9 Dunville Avenue<lb/>Rathmines<lb/>Dublin   3rd May, 1916    My dear Mrs Skeffington   I have been for some<lb/>time dumbly anxious to let you have a<lb/>word from me to tell you, however<lb/>inadequately, what we have been<lb/>feeling about Frank's death, — his<lb/>heroic death, — and about his life too,<lb/>for his life and death were of the same<lb/>pattern. For a number of days we,<lb/>in common with many others, were in a<lb/>state of horrible uncertainty about him,<lb/>— afraid of every rumour, hating to 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_2"/>
             credit the wickedness which made it<lb/>possible to murder wantonly such a<lb/>life as his, and yet forced to a slow<lb/>and reluctant conviction of the dreadful<lb/>reality. One thing that made it<lb/>credible was the agreement of what we<lb/>were told of his last moments with the<lb/>unflinching character and devotion to<lb/>principle which we knew so well;<lb/>another was the conspiracy of official<lb/>silence regarding his fate which revealed<lb/>so truly the nature of the hostile element<lb/>which dared to kill him in violation<lb/>not only of constitutional right and<lb/>of the law of humanity, but <sic>wen</sic> of<lb/>the laws of war, — but did not dare to 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_3"/>
             avow publicly the murder. He has<lb/>been killed for his principles, — killed<lb/>because he was an outspoken and<lb/>fearless opponent of every tyranny<lb/>and lying pretence; because also he<lb/>was in the truest sense an uncomprom—<lb/>ising Nationalist; but more than all<lb/>I believe, because he dared to stand<lb/>for peace and for the international<lb/>friendship of peoples. The last has been,<lb/>doubtless, his crowning offence against<lb/>the ruling powers. He will live not<lb/>only as one of the national martyrs<lb/>of Ireland, but as a martyr of<lb/>international humanity, as a martyr 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_4"/>
             in the cause of oppressed womanhood and<lb/>of the trampled multitudes of every<lb/>clime and age.  I cannot think of him as dead: it<lb/>seems altogether unreal. He was the<lb/>very embodiment of life in its best<lb/>and highest quality. Utterly brave, he<lb/>had yet no trace of bitterness or<lb/>arrogance or contemptuousness. Utterly<lb/>uncompromising in his demands upon<lb/>himself, he was yet tolerant of others'<lb/>weaknesses and kindly and unruffled<lb/><sic>wen</sic> in the most critical of moments.<lb/>To me he has been for years an ideal<lb/>figure. It is truer for me to say that<lb/>of him than any other whom I have 
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_5"/>
             9 Dunville Avenue<lb/>Rathmines<lb/>Dublin  known personally. I have wondered at<lb/>him, looked up to him, and loved him.<lb/>Now I feel not unlike a disciple whose<lb/>master has been taken away, for there<lb/>was no one else like him and for me<lb/>there is a gap left which can never<lb/>be filled. There was a spiritual<lb/>keenness and moral tonic about him,<lb/>a strength and inspiration, and a<lb/>courage and selflessness which was all<lb/>his own. His intellect and energy were<lb/>a marvel to me, but even they were not<lb/>what made his deeper influence.    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_6"/>
             I cannot think of him as dead,<lb/>and I do not believe that he is<lb/>dead. A spirit like his is quenchless.<lb/>Bullets cannot end or destroy it. The<lb/>world of aspiration and thought, of<lb/>energy of mind and heart, in which<lb/>he dwelt must have a reality and<lb/>permanent quality superior to that of<lb/>the leaves which fall and perish.<lb/>Like him, I turn aside from<lb/>religious orthodoxies of every brand,<lb/>but nothing can annihilate my<lb/>faith: somehow, in the immortal<lb/>nature of life and especially of its<lb/>nobler forms of consciousness.  His death and the manner of it may 
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_7"/>
             work as a potent influence  to do more<lb/>for the causes which he had at heart<lb/>than years of plodding work would<lb/>have accomplished. I pray and<lb/>believe that it will be so. Ireland and<lb/>the world, if they are in one sense<lb/>the poorer for his loss, in another way<lb/>will be compensatingly enriched by<lb/>the nobility of the life so barbarously<lb/>cut off. Tyranny, in his case, will<lb/>have overreached itself. As I write<lb/>these words, I feel the uselessness<lb/>of words to appease the <seg type="unclear">source</seg> of<lb/>personal bereavement. I am haunted<lb/>by it: what it must be to you and<lb/>to Owen I can only guess. We must 
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_3609_img_3009_8"/>
             mourn, Dublin must mourn, his loss<lb/>as well as that of many another of<lb/>her bravest and best; — and yet I<lb/>know that Frank himself would wish<lb/>us to have done with sorrow as soon<lb/>as might be.  With deepest sympathy from <seg type="unclear">Eve<lb/>and myself.</seg>  Ever your sincere friend,<lb/>Maurice Wilkins 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>