<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0517">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from a War Employments Inspector to Cecil Pim, 20 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>War Employments Inspector</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from a War Employments Inspector at the Local Government Board (LGB) to Cecil Pim, thanking Pim for the information supplied in a previous letter, dated 15 March, concerning the conditions and prospects for Belfast&#39;s spinning and weaving factories. The writer concludes that &#39;it is wonderful how difficulties can be overcome if they are foreseen,&#39; implying that Pim will have to make do should the worst come pass regarding the coal situation.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>, NAI-CSORP-1916-7443-17</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/517</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0459">War Employments Inspector</persName>
              <date>1916-03-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0536">War Employments Branch, Local Government Board, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1170">Cecil Pim</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1772">Greenmount Factory, Harold's Cross, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0517_img_1889_1"  type="Letter"  url="841bcbb8ca3e9e15bc868c55f16523eb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0517_img_1889_1"/>
              Copy    LOCAL GOVERNMENT BOARD,  ( War Employments Branch )  DUBLIN    20th March, 1916.   Dear Mr Pim,    It is very good of you indeed to have taken <lb/> the trouble to write me so fully as to conditions and <lb/> prospects in Belfast.    I hope the coal difficulty will not prove serious. <lb/> It is wonderful how difficulties can be overcome if <lb/> they are foreseen.  <seg type="closer"> With kind regards and many thanks, <lb/> Yours truly,    War Employments Inspector.    Cecil Pim, Esq  Greenmount Factory  Harold's Cross,  Dublin.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>