<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5588">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Desmond FitzGerald to Mabel FitzGerald, 7 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Desmond FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947) to his wife Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958).
Desmond FitzGerald had served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Mountjoy, Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.
The letter refers to a visit by his family, his sons&#39; birthdays, news about family friends and colleagues and his time in the prison.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Desmond FitzGerald Papers, P80/1543/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5588</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0538">Desmond FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-03-07</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0259">H. M. Prison, Mountjoy, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5588_img_682_1"  type="Letter"  url="6bcc6b748cef7729da5a9969656b6ff2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5588_img_682_2"  type="Letter"  url="814ea6faf1d0a90bd17c35de9f24d8b0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5588_img_682_3"  type="Letter"  url="104609e8bcba41aafb1e30d043d2a4ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5588_img_682_4"  type="Letter"  url="8de341ddb3c36359eda82a32b17d3ca4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5588_img_682_1"/>
             C. 7/3/1916  P80/1543 <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Form 21/AD</hi> <lb/>In Replying to this Letter, please address the Envelope as follows:- <lb/>Number 1817 Name: Desmond Fitzgerald <lb/>H.M. Prison, Mountjoy <lb/>IV Stáge  2988/1902   The following regulations as to communications, by visit or letter, between <lb/>prisoners and their friends, are notified for the information of their correspondents.   The permission to write and receive letters is given to prisoners of the pur- <lb/>pose of enabling them to keep up a connection with their respectable friends and not <lb/> that they may be kept informed of public events.   All letters are read by the Prison Authorities. They must be legibly written <lb/>and not crossed. Any which are of an objectionable tendency, either to or from <lb/>prisoners, or containing slang, or improper expressions, will be suppressed.   Prisoners are permitted to receive and to write a letter at intervals, which <lb/>depend on the rules of the stage they attain by industry and good conduct; but <lb/>matters of special importance to a prisoner may be communicated at any time by <lb/>letter (prepaid) to the Governor who will inform the prisoner thereof, if expedient.   In case of misconduct, the privilege of receiving and writing a letter may be <lb/>forfeited for a time.   Money, books, Postage Stamps, Food, Tobacco, Clothes &amp;c <lb/>should not be sent to prisoners, for their use in prison, as nothing is allowed to be received at the <lb/>Prison for that purpose.   Persons attempting to clandestinely communicate with, or to introduce any <lb/>article to or for prisoners, are liable to fine or imprisonment, and any prisoner <lb/>concerned in such practices is liable to be severely punished.   Prisoners; friends are sometimes applied to by unauthorised persons, to send <lb/>money, &amp;c, to them privately, under pretence that they can supply it for the benefit <lb/>of the prisoners, and under such fraudulent pretence, such persons endeavour to <lb/>obtain money for themselves. Any letter containing such an application, received <lb/>by the friends of a prisoner, should be at once forwarded by them to the Governor.   Prisoners are allow to receive visits from their friends, according to rules, <lb/>at intervals which depend on their stage.   When visits are due to prisoners, notification will be sent to the friends whom <lb/>they desire to visit them.   (6209) Wt.2774—7.10,000.7 / 15.A.T.&amp;Co.,Ltd.(Sch. 139.) 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5588_img_682_2"/>
             <seg type="unclear">CM</seg>   My dear Mabel: -   Those visits of yours are so exciting that I am amazed - and hardly <lb/> know what I say or what you say either. But it is a great comfort to see you and the <lb/>wee son. More especially this last visit which seems to bring my going out so <lb/>near. I should like you to get this for Denis birthday. But I hardly think that <lb/>possible. Still I know you will wish him many returns from Daddy, and, if the <lb/>finances are not too utterly straitened — buy him a present for me. The other wee <lb/>son will also have a birthday before I am with you, but it will only be a few days <lb/>then till I come. As you could see for yourself, I am in excellent form. I know you <lb/>don't care for the beard, but I will get rid of that before I leave here. I don't care to - <lb/>keep having it clipped, as each time I should have to <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>see the scissors <lb/>sterilised - and the once at the end will do for all. I am glad that you have a pretty <lb/>good time. That is the chief thing. It is a pity that the money was so much less this <lb/>month. But of course that was to be expected. No doubt also, we ought to get <lb/>back more income tax rebate. We can only do our best, any way. I hope the <lb/>kindergarten scheme will materialise. It would coordinate the Dublin Gaeltacht <lb/>I suppose that as Eimar is back with his father, Seán is on his own now. He is <lb/>a dear fellow. I suppose he is in Bray most week ends. Who were there the <lb/> weekend Redmond's nephew (Redmond Howard) came? I am sure he is <lb/>of the   type? I think I rather felt his pulse in an article he wrote in <lb/>are Boston Transcript when we were living in France. Now that E. is with <lb/>his father, I suppose he is rather cut off from things. I hope the Bray C  mt. <lb/> will be a success. I don't think much of the 'material'. None of them seems to me <lb/>to be moved by simple enthusiasm for the cause - unless that Miss G.C. whom <lb/>I don't know. Let me know what sort she is. Of course you that when I come <lb/>out of here I shall be very much at loose ends and bewildered. But no doubt <lb/>I shall soon get used to the world again. You remember when we lived in <lb/>France how exciting those dances were after our quiet life. I couldn't sleep <lb/>after them. My life here has naturally been much quieter than it was in <lb/>France. I shall probably have a splitting head before I am an hour out. <lb/>If any of the prisoners here should come to you and ask for clothes or anything <lb/>of course you won't give it. I work in the wood yard, and am daily in <lb/>contact with the <seg type="del">deleted text</seg>. They all know who I am, and I shouldn't like any <lb/>of them to impose on you while I am still here. I have no intention of <lb/>being bothered by them when I get out. Of course there are decent enough <lb/>fellows here too. But I have noticed that some of the really old hands <lb/>take a great interest in my clothes. Apropos of clothes, I think everything <lb/>will just last me my time out here. The boots will manage it all right, <lb/>this old suit - the tie that you took such exception to on Saturday, and <lb/>the hat. I am interested to hear that my friend will be in Dublin on the 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> <lb/>It is a pity that we have no idea what time he will be in Dublin. If I were out <lb/>I should try to meet him. He was a very dear friend to me. One of the most <lb/>lovable fellows I ever knew. Perhaps someone will be able to see <lb/>him. His tastes are almost identical with my own. I suppose he will <lb/>be going to <seg type="unclear">Rathmona</seg>- or at least to within sight of it. Of <lb/>course if no one sees him it won't really matter. If anyone does <lb/>see him they should give him a bundle of all the interesting papers <lb/>It is a pity Eileen <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> <lb/>has no national pride — but still, what can you expect. <lb/>Did you say that Dyar is married, or about to be? I always wonder what <lb/>you are doing on the week ends, and who are with you. I watch the  Letters must be legibly written 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5588_img_682_3"/>
            <lb/>weather to see if it allows any good walks. As we have been <hi rend="underline">out</hi> to exercise <lb/><lb/>every Sunday, I suppose you have managed to get out every Sunday also. <lb/> Did you say on Saturday that P. G Ryan was going down this week end. I hope <lb/> you didn't keep him up all night talking, as I suppose he is still pretty weak <lb/> after his illness. I suppose B. H. <seg type="unclear">Claire</seg> and Sean were down also. Has <lb/>Eimars new arrangement put an end to his visits. I thought GR looked <lb/>in particularly good form on Saturday. I am sorry that you were kept <lb/>waiting outside for so long. But I suppose that that is part of <lb/>the etiquette of prison. I have been on a C. diet since the first of this <lb/>month. I had thought to break my long abstinence from meat on <lb/>Sunday. 4 oz. of beef with ought bone, the dietary says - but apparently <lb/> it means without lean — and I being a Jack Spratt in that <lb/>respect, still abstain. I have grown very used to comparatively <lb/>plain food one gets here. I hope to have things very nice the day <lb/>I leave here, but after that I think I shall be prepared to <lb/>put up with a simple diet, if that is required. I believe the hot water <lb/>pipes just last my time out here, and are turned off the day after I <lb/>leave. <seg type="unclear">Den</seg> was rather good I thought on Sat. He looked well. His <lb/>voice seemed to me very high pitched — I suppose because I hadn't <lb/>heard it for so long. It is <seg type="unclear">inevitable</seg> that he <sic>shd.</sic> have become such an <lb/>English speaker. Miles G.R. has the advantage that his playmates <lb/>are at least partially Irish speakers. Poor <seg type="unclear">Den</seg> would have a long <lb/>hunt in Bray to find anyone to play with in Irish. Is A. Somers <lb/>still with Mrs. M. I suppose the gardens in Bray will be rather lovely <lb/>when I get out. it is rather exciting not to know where I shall <lb/>be living when I get out. I shall be rather disappointed not to <lb/>have you with me on my visit to my mothers. I hope their moving is successfully over. I wish yours was also, poor darling. You <lb/>might let me know the name of the restaurant <sic>wh</sic>. used to supply <lb/>my food when I was awaiting trial. Also the name of a firm in <lb/>Dublin — central part of Dublin — which sells the requisites for <lb/>fretwork — woodcarving. Wood - designs - and knife. There <lb/> seem to have been a fair number of things on in Dublin recently. I am <lb/>glad you enjoyed the Abbey and the Opera. I hope France won't have <lb/>to shut down the factory — that would be a pity. I hope my mother <lb/>and the dear ones are all well and in good form. Has anyone been <lb/> down to Bucks yet, to give a first hand opinion of the twins. <lb/>I hope Miss Trench will really make the picture of you. I wonder <lb/>if Ernest will be in Dublin when I get out. I hope his reports are <lb/>good. I don't suppose Claude <seg type="foreign">Chevasse</seg> will hear any more about his <lb/>appeal. I owe him my apology as I did not answer his last letter <lb/>to me. I forget why. I had some good reason. I believe I had to <lb/>get something from Blythe and B. was away, and before he came <lb/>back came our extradition 'with loss of Eden and with all our <lb/><seg type="unclear">woe.</seg> Tell me abut the anti taxation meeting. I asked you <lb/>about books, but I really have plenty to read. What I wanted <lb/>was something modern in my own line - with landscape, <lb/> atmosphere and romantic realism. You know what I mean. Think <lb/>of those two alone on the tower watching the stars, and the tragedy <lb/>growing up between them. That is what gives me real pleasure. <lb/>I am just about to read Cranford. I have recently read Kingleys  on the ruled lines and not crossed 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5588_img_682_4"/>
            <lb/>Hypolita, a book by no less a person than Mrs <seg type="unclear">Clephant,</seg> and the Lady with the Fan <lb/>by R Hichens. Do you hear from Ms Hegearty in Ballingeary and <lb/>from P.S. Is the camp still at Kimmage — and how many are there? <lb/>I suppose I shall see <seg type="unclear">Stoner</seg> when I am out — Remember me to him if <lb/>you see him in the meantime. Do you ever see the Campbells? I think <lb/>Mrs goes to Bray on Fridays only, and as you are never in <lb/>Bray she is hardly likely to make another journey on <lb/>Sunday — while the weather is bad at any rate. Today is Tuesday <lb/>7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> I am out on Friday 3 weeks. Remember I don't get <lb/> your letter till about eight days after it reaches here, so <lb/>it would be as well to send it as soon as possible, otherwise it <lb/>may only be forwarded to me after I am out, and on the whole I <lb/>think it will give me more pleasure in here than outside. When <lb/>I get it I am pretty sure not to have more than another fort- <lb/>night to do. You will of course remember me to all of my friends. <lb/>I hope Dollie is doing well. The citizen was a good chap. I suppose <lb/> your people are in Nice now. I suppose you don't hear from Lizzie. <lb/>I am glad Miss S. has been so sucessful recently. I am <lb/>sure she was very thankful to Mrs <seg type="unclear">O.R.</seg> of course she is living <lb/>off for this couple of weeks. Remember me to the McDonaghs if <lb/>you see them. I went to the Oireachtas the year before last, you last <lb/>year — I wonder if we shall both go this year. You will of course <lb/>send me all news of my people. I do hope there is no cause to worry <lb/> about France. I hope there will be a continual round of diversions <lb/>for the next three weeks, dear, so that you won't notice the time <lb/>passing — as it draws near one counts the days so that each day <lb/>seems a much lengthier affair than one thought it was. No one <lb/>need worry about me. I quite enjoy my stirabout of a morning. Each <lb/>day I look forward to the night when I can lie in bed in a sort of half <lb/>sleep, and dream, and each week I look forward to the Sunday — <lb/>Mass — exercise on the ring and a quiet read — and so the time <lb/>goes by till I shall be with you once more. I now have your <lb/>letter to expect, and I shall count myself as almost out. I am <lb/>glad my mother enjoyed her birthday. They were due to move <lb/>on March 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> so when you were here I suppose they were busy <lb/>getting settled in the new house. I hope Ciss and the children are well. <lb/>I am sure that when my mother sees the twins her comments upon them <lb/>and Mick will be such as to annoy <seg type="unclear">Dollie</seg>. I am glad that William isn't <lb/>moving. I am sure they would have found it a dreadful business. <lb/>You didn't tell me if you saw Mrs B.S. + <seg type="unclear">Fr Costelloe</seg>. I suppose I <lb/>shall hear in your letter. This isn't much of a letter but I shall soon <lb/>be with you now dear. Kiss my wee sons for me. God bless them. <lb/>How are your neighbours in Bray. I often smile when I think of, say, <lb/>my first encounter with Mrs Hall. If you are moving before I get out <lb/>I am sure that <seg type="unclear">McConatty</seg> will help you. I am sure too Joe K will <lb/>want to help but perhaps he will be most helpful by keeping away. <lb/> When you get this - say 'another three weeks,' And when I get yours I shall <lb/> probably say 'less than 2 weeks!' In all I shall have been here nearly <lb/> 24 weeks. A longish time. Goodbye, my dearest, it is nearly <lb/>all over now. Have good time for the next three weeks and before you <lb/>know where you are, you will be with me outside Mountjoy. I shall <lb/> like to hear the programme of my first morning.    Love  <lb/>Desmond FitzGerald
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>