<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1211">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Frank Quinlan to Fr Provincial Thomas V. Nolan, 29 November 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Frank Quinlan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Frank Quinlan to Fr Provincial Thomas V Nolan (1867- 1922) regarding the delay on solving issues related to the death of Fr Fitzgibbon.Fr. Thomas Nolan became the Provincial of the Irish Province of the Society of Jesus from 1912 to 1922. Besides that, he was a Distribution Committee member responsible for the welfare and distribution of the Belgian refugees who had found refuge in Ireland on account of the World War I.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Irish Jesuit Archives</repository>
                  <collection>IJA/CHPI/21/37, IJA/CHPI/21/37</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1211</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1529">Frank Quinlan</persName>
              <date>1918-11-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Thomas V Nolan </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1211_img_3895_1"  type="Letter"  url="25e00aa68b53149316623f3dd4dbf225.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1211_img_3895_1"/>
                68 Middle Abbey Street,  Dublin    29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Novr 1918.  <lb/>P.F. QUINLAN, LL.B., <lb/>Solicitor. <lb/>Major Rev. J. Fitzgibbon decd.  Dear F<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Nolan   I am sure you are wondering why I am not going to make <lb/>another move with the above Probate. I was hoping I might see you yesterday <lb/>at the Requiem Mass and tell you how matters stand. I have written three <lb/>times since to the War Office and still get the same reply saying 'the necessary <lb/>inquiries are being made and a further communication will be addressed <lb/>to you as soon as these are completed'. The last of these communications I re- <lb/>ceived on Wednesday last and a letter of mine was posted to them on Tuesday <lb/>night so our letters crossed.  I regret that there is such a delay over a small matter particularly <lb/>when it was the first thing I have attempted to put through for such a good <lb/>friend.  Any definite word I receive, as I stated before and I shall be off <lb/>straight up to Gardiner Street to look for you. <seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely  Frank Quinlan   Very Revr T.V. Nolan, S.J.,  The Presbytery,  Upper Gardiner Str.,  Dublin  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>