<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1033">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Austin Stack to Maureen Cregan, 18 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Austin Stack</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Austin Stack (1879-1929) presumably to Maureen (Mairín) Cregan, a prolific Irish children&#39;s writer who married James Ryan (1891-1970). The letter was written from Kilmainham Gaol before Stack was sent to prison in the United Kingdom. In the letter he speculates that he will get a long sentences as the Chief Crown Solicitor claimed he should have been executed (&#39;backed the wall&#39;). He complains about the use of evidence during the courts martial and hopes that Michael Collins, who had a minor role in the Rising, would get a lenient sentence, describing him as &#39;an unfortunate victim to circumstances&#39;.Austin Stack, revolutionary, politician, was commandant of the Kerry Brigade of the Irish Volunteers and made preparations to receive Roger Casement. Stack was sentenced to death for his part in the Easter Rising, but this later commuted to penal servitude for life and he was released in 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/55</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1033</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1445">Austin Stack</persName>
              <date>1916-06-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0084">Kilmainham Gaol, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Maureen Cregan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1033_img_302_1"  type="Letter"  url="cf4561fc818c46a030ef8a918ef12ce4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1033_img_302_1"/>
                Kilmainham Gaol    18th June 1916   My dear Maureen,   I am sure you will <lb/>not be able to see us again before <lb/>we are sent away. I do not know <lb/>what sentences we may receive <lb/>but I am prepared for a long term <lb/>as the Chief Crown Solicitor told Dr. <lb/>O'Connell on Friday night that I <lb/>should have 'backed the wall'. They <lb/>failed to make out any case against us <lb/>but what do the Court-martial care about <lb/>such trifles as legal evidence when the <lb/>authorities want people out of the way? <lb/>I hope Collins gets off light as he was <lb/>an unfortunate victim to circumstances. <lb/>He, at any rate, should have been acquitted. <lb/>But we shall survive it all with God's <lb/>help, and meet our friends again.  <seg type="closer"> Goodbye, brave little woman, and say an <lb/>occasional prayer for <lb/>Ireland's unworthy son   Austin Stack </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>