<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1849">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from A. Ross to Augustine Birrell, 30 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>A Ross</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from A. Ross to Augustine Birrell (1850–1933), the chief secretary for Ireland. In the letter Ross is asking Birrell to help put him in contact with his sister Miss Ross who works at Dublin Castle. Miss Ross worked as a cleaner in the Castle and according to the letter has no relations in Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7557/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1849</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0337">A Ross</persName>
              <date>1916-04-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1359">Cheshire, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1849_img_1303_1"  type="Letter"  url="88539cf129417e0d147036a5ca59aede.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1849_img_1303_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">A.u.s.</seg>, <lb/>This only came today. <lb/>Please let writer know <lb/>if Miss Ross is all right &amp; oblige. <lb/>A.P.M.   159, Victoria Road, <lb/>New Brighton, <lb/>Cheshire,   30 April 1916.   Dear Sir,   I trust you will pardon me <lb/>for troubling you at such a busy and <lb/>anxious time as I am utterly at a <lb/>loss to know what else to do under <lb/>existing circumstances to allay the <lb/>anxiety of myself and others here <lb/>in regard to my sister (who has no <lb/>relatives in Ireland) Miss Ross, <lb/>Housekeeper, State Apartments, Dublin <lb/>Castle, but whose present address is <lb/>3, Upper Castle Yard.   If you will kindly cause enquiries to <lb/>be made regarding her &amp; have the <lb/> result communicated to me you <lb/> will confer a great <sic>favor</sic> on   Chief Commr. <lb/>Please have <lb/>inquiry made and <lb/>communicate result to the <lb/>writer. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>