<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0819">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Basil Howe to the Earl of Aberdeen, 25 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Basil Howe</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was sent by Basil Howe to John Campbell Gordon. In this letter Basil offers his services in any capacity upon hearing of a Rising in Dublin. Basil notes his previous experience and believes he has an intimate knowledge of Ireland and the Irish peopleJohn Campbell Hamilton-Gordon, 1st Marquess of Aberdeen and Temair (1847-1934), known as The Earl of Aberdeen from 1870 to 1916, was a Scottish politician. Gordon served twice as Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/7677</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/819</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0508">Basil Howe</persName>
              <date>1916-04-25</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Campbell Gordon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0819_img_2361_1"  type="Letter"  url="ef09f2974751b964bb4c3ab772fdd0ac.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0819_img_2361_2"  type="Letter"  url="0e7f23ae0b52924bf89ab9353a253845.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0819_img_2361_3"  type="Letter"  url="9f9bdc530a68be2e6bd6b591e22eb93e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0819_img_2361_1"/>
                COPLEY,  BEDFORD.    <hi rend="underline">April 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>/16.</hi>    To His Excellency  The Earl of Aberdeen  Dublin -   Sir:   I have read with great <lb/> indignation of the Rebel Rising <lb/> in Dublin.   I have the honour to be <lb/> one of Your Excellencies, Justices <lb/> of the Peace for Dublin and although <lb/> it is seven years since I left  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0819_img_2361_2"/>
              Ireland, it is my loyal duty and <lb/> pleasure, to offer to return to Ireland <lb/> - at once, in any capacity in which<lb/> Your Excellency, may find my use.  My knowledge of Ireland <lb/> and its people, in all parts of the <lb/> country is intimate. For seven <lb/> Years I was Asst: Mech: Engineer <lb/> to the M.G.W. Ry, of Ireland, having <lb/> control of large bodies of <seg type="unclear">men</seg> and travelled with his late Majesty <lb/> King Edward round Ireland and in a <lb/> Royal Train which we built at <lb/> Broadstone. Later with the <lb/> Renard Train, which I showed <lb/> Your Excellency, I went all round <lb/> Ireland, in the interest of Transport. <lb/><seg type="unclear">As such</seg> - Board of Works Inspectors <lb/> are all familiar to me.   Further I wish to come to <lb/> your service in Dublin, as I <lb/> remember the debt of gratitude  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0819_img_2361_3"/>
              to your House, for the kindness <lb/> shown to my cousin, W. E. Hope <lb/> Your Excellencius R.D.C. of the Irish <lb/> Guards, who laid down his Life at <lb/> Zillebeche.   At present I am <lb/> doing what I can as an Inspecting <lb/> Engineer at The Royal Arsenal <lb/> Woolwich - but I am ready to <lb/> take up service under Your Excellency <lb/> and <seg type="unclear">as being an Inspector</seg> of Dublin. <seg type="closer"> Sir: Your obedient servant   <hi rend="underline">Basil Howe.</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>