<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5917">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Denis O'Driscoll to his daughter Bessie, 12 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Denis O&#39;Driscoll</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a collection of letters which Denis O&#39; Driscoll (d. 1920) wrote to his daughters Elizabeth (Bessie) and Susanna (Sue) who had earlier emigrated to Boston, Massachusetts. He writes about his health, family news and his job in the Local Government Board. Denis writes to Bessie about her brother Gerald, serving with the Royal Navy in the First World War, and the luck that he has survived unscathed since 1914. Denis comments that the war must end soon. He also mentions that to write about the rebuilding of Dublin after the Rising and the coming of Home Rule would take a letter each and that he will write again.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Denis McGrath</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5917</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0229">Denis O&#39;Driscoll</persName>
              <date>1916-07-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth O&#39;Driscoll</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1563">Boston, Massachusetts, US </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5917_img_428_1"  type="Letter"  url="b4f8391a1441a99f7b49f47a0aeb9266.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5917_img_428_2"  type="Letter"  url="db8c94c927b9fa6ecf783b77e0e48f7d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5917_img_428_3"  type="Letter"  url="7bcf184bd62e32c374c86829d1bfc795.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5917_img_428_4"  type="Letter"  url="05bcf3eaae0685b661083cd7d71a5df6.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5917_img_428_1"/>
                1 St. Mura's Tce Church Road Dublin    12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916   My dear Bessie   Since my reply and acknowledgement of your kindly favour <lb/>on 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ulto, and reposted, on account of return by <lb/>Censor on 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> there is nothing new so far as home <lb/>affairs are concerned to which I need call your attention <lb/>We continue in our usual good health and thank Heaven <lb/>and also to your kindness we have nothing of which we <lb/>could reasonably complain. Mamma is remarkably well <lb/>and she looks it. Barbara also is well — she is never <lb/>ill— and continues her employment. As to myself <lb/>I was never in better health, but there is a certain <lb/><sic>crapidness</sic>in my fingers which will not obey my will. <lb/>This is only felt in the right hand and hampers me a <lb/>good deal in my writing, but I do not in any other way <lb/>suffer any inconvenience. I don't think I have before told <lb/>you. I am in employment in the Department <lb/>of the Local Government Board. My hours of duty are from <lb/>9 A.m. to 5.30 p.m. My duties are merely nominal and so is my <lb/>pay, but then it is something and removes that despondency <lb/>which lack of employment ever produces on a capable  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5917_img_428_2"/>
              and willing man. Thus matters go better with me. <lb/>I have referred to Mamma and Barbara. I now <lb/>turn to Gerald. I have not heard directly from him <lb/>since his letter which I posted to you with that of <lb/>Finneen's on 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> ulto. but I hear of him through Maggie <lb/>from whom I learn that he continues well, and is studying <lb/>hard to qualify for a higher position. I enclose Finnie's <lb/>last letter which speaks for itself, and in passing I <lb/>cannot too deeply impress upon you my gratitude to him <lb/>for his constant and filial devotion to me when in the <lb/>thick of battle - and Finnie is I know in the very teeth <lb/>of it - he manages to send me word from the few <lb/>moments he has to recoup human nature. I most <lb/>earnestly thank God for his safety so far and I pray <lb/>earnestly for a continuance of the Divine Protection. <lb/>When it is considered that he has been in the forefront <lb/>of danger since the first shot in this terrible war was <lb/>fired, now two years ago, I cannot but think that God <lb/>has in His mercy something good in store for him. Could <lb/>you only see the sorry spectacle which the invalids from <lb/>this war presents who return alive, then indeed you <lb/> would  conclude that the Power Divine favours your Brother  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5917_img_428_3"/>
              Putting the matter outside of wounds by the enemy <lb/>the frostbites of the feet which took place in the <lb/>first winter; the shattering of the nervous system <lb/>as the result of heavy artillery fire, the gassing, <lb/>and liquid fire poured upon our troops by the <lb/>Devil's devices and the Germans — taking all these <lb/>into consideration together with the fact that he like <lb/>his compatriots has no bed to lie on, it is simply <lb/>wonderful that for the couple of days he was allowed <lb/>to run home he could have presented such a specimen <lb/>of splendid young manhood. By the time this <lb/>reaches you, you will see by the papers that the <lb/>end of the war is not far off. The Allies in general <lb/>and the British in particular are punishing the Germans <lb/>in such a manner that they cannot last much longer <lb/>The process of the war I shall not further enter into <lb/>here. You will learn all this from the papers, but as <lb/>I write the Allies are doing splendidly. The outstanding <lb/>subjects of which I know you would like me to treat <lb/>are the rebuilding of Dublin and the Coming of Home <lb/>Rule; but as to do either of these subjects justice would <lb/>take a letter each to itself I must for tonight put it off  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5917_img_428_4"/>
              I was speaking to Cecilia Kelly a couple of days <lb/>ago, and she told me that Mollie had received a letter from <lb/>you and that they were all much pleased. When on <lb/>that evening I arrived home I found our Mollie <lb/>awaiting me, and she told me that she had received a <lb/>parcel from you but no letter. She seemed very <lb/>much pleased of your attention and kindness and <lb/>said that she would write to you in a day or two's <lb/>time. I never saw Mollie looking better, of which <lb/>I am very glad, as her state is, I learn from some <lb/>hints from her Mother <hi rend="underline">interesting</hi>.  Mollie was pregnant with the mother of this transcriber. May Healy was born on the 20th October 1916.  Be sure you forward to Sue Finnie's letter and <lb/>I wish you good night Bessie. I shall wait till <lb/>the night post comes along, and if I get nothing <lb/>which would cause me to prolong this I close <lb/>with love of those at home, and the love and <lb/>blessing of your father. <seg type="closer">  Denis O'Driscoll </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>