<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0497">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major J. Crean to the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Crean</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Major James Crean to Lord Wimborne (1873-1939) regarding the arrest of members of the National Volunteers by the military authorities. Crean stresses that the Military Authorities should be made aware of the distinction between the National and Irish Volunteer groups. Ivor Churchill Guest, 1st Viscount Wimborne was appointed the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in 1915. Guest worked closely alongside Sir Matthew Nathan (1862-1939) in the administration of Ireland. Following the suppression of the Rising, Guest, under pressure, was forced to resign as Lord Lieutenant. A later inquiry into the Rising exonerated Guest and held Augustine Birrell (1850-1933) chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Guest would continue to serve as Lord Lieutenant until 1918.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSORP/1916/7472/4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/497</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1299">James Crean</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1374">Ivor Churchill Guest</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0497_img_1864_1"  type="Letter"  url="50db6eef253995dade3aa40d6ed934b4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0497_img_1864_2"  type="Letter"  url="3eb99d51e8b4f8555e8e31b331653400.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0497_img_1864_1"/>
                Inspector General's Office,  44 PARNELL SQUARE,  DUBLIN.    Date, 4th. May, 1916.     His Excellency,  The Lord Lieutenant,  Dublin Castle.   May it please your Excellency,   Several cases have been reported to me of Officers and <lb/> other members of the National Volunteers who have been arrested by the <lb/> Military authorities and who are still detained.  In drawing your Excellency's attention to this matter I fully <lb/> recognise the serious difficulties the Military Authorities have , and the <lb/> impossibility of avoiding the arrest of perfectly innocent persons, In the <lb/> course of my inquiries regarding several persons who are under arrest <lb/> I discovered that amongst some senior officers of the Military the opinion <lb/> prevailed that the Sinn Feiners and the National Volunteers were branches <lb/> of the same body. As there is not the remotest ground for such belief I <lb/> hope your Excellency will agree that it would be advisable that the Military <lb/> Authorities <lb/> should know that such is not the case and that there is no <lb/> connection whatever between the National Volunteers (under the leadership <lb/>of Mr John Redmond M.P. ) and the Sinn Fein Volunteers.  I would ask Your Excellency to make representation to such author- <lb/> ity as you may think proper regarding the matter referred to.   I might further add that in the case of arrests of suspects and where  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0497_img_1864_2"/>
              the person states that he is a member of the National Volunteers <lb/> I shall be glad to place at the disposal of authorities <lb/> responsible officers who will be in a position to verify or <lb/> otherwise the statements made by suspected persons and furnish <lb/> information which the Military authorities may require regarding same. <seg type="closer"> I have the honour to be, <lb/> Your Excellency's obedient servant  J. Crean Major <lb/> Acting Inspector General. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>