<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5218">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from S O'Brien to Ellen Jnr Daly, 15 March 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>S O&#39;Brien </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry County Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/9/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5218</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1248">S O&#39;Brien </persName>
              <date>1923-03-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0360">Kingstown, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Ellen Jnr Daly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5218_img_None_1"  url="d6d8c00bfceed210b2f655d59672be2a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5218_img_None_2"  url="7d0fa096469fef97ed1a4041c2682bbe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5218_img_None_3"  url="a495696b5385017d4c20525564ef832b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5218_img_None_4"  url="3be36d873b819763cd2a0d5ef43c2e5b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5218_img_0_1"/>
             P41/9/3   March, 15/23    Kingstown<lb/>Ireland    My dear Ellie,   I am sure you are<lb/>heartbroken at the awful news,<lb/>but I hope and trust<lb/>he is better off. He was far<lb/>better prepared than if he<lb/>were outside and shot<lb/>without a priest being near!  I went up to see Susie<lb/>to-day. She has a cold<lb/>but I was not allowed in    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5218_img_0_2"/>
             as there were some others in<lb/>the ward. I was speaking<lb/>to the Sister and she said<lb/>it would be better that I<lb/>did not see her. I think<lb/>you should not write her<lb/>until she is alright.The<lb/>nuns will break it to her.<lb/>She had a letter from Jon<lb/>this morning &amp; had one<lb/>from <seg type="unclear">Con</seg> also.  I got a letter from poor<lb/>Charlie in the beginning of<lb/>the month, we were always    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5218_img_0_3"/>
             arguing about the country, but I never for a<lb/>moment thought the worst would happen to him<lb/>who I admired so much.  I asked the nuns  not to give Susie any<lb/>letters until she was alright. I will go up<lb/>again soon to see her.  Now I hope you will all bear up, think<lb/>of all our Lord and his Blessed Mother<lb/>suffered.  I feel sure he is up in Heaven<lb/>praying for us all.  If you have a photograph of him 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5218_img_0_4"/>
             keep it for me or send it to<lb/>me sometime.  Trusting your mother and<lb/>all are well.   Yours very sincerely<lb/>S O'Brien . 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>