<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4279">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 11 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender writes of his plans for upcoming leave. 

Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.&#34;</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfred Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/216</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4279</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-11</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4279_img_3643_1"  type="Letter"  url="833a384d4094db3189734f48d7cde13d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4279_img_3643_2"  type="Letter"  url="f3ee4b3bd1c98ad5cd394a079f730a8e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4279_img_3643_1"/>
             11April   My p r    No more letters <lb/> from a b w , till he <lb/>knows whether he is able <lb/> to tell you news.   I have put in for leave <lb/> from Friday next 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <lb/> to cross by early morning <lb/> boat on that day.   If I get it I hope <lb/> not to return till Sunday <lb/> morning 23<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>.   I leave all arrangements <lb/> to you but suggest <lb/> <seg type="unclear">Bayly</seg> wood I know Rex <lb/> would be delighted &amp; if <lb/> he comes too so much
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4279_img_3643_2"/>
            <lb/>the better in spite of p r <lb/> squeals!   You may have to <lb/> take one of the maids <lb/> or both? Jessie could <lb/>advise.   much too excited <lb/> to write   WBS,   P.S. I can get nothing <lb/> definite today &amp; may not <lb/> be able to go till next week.    WBSpender   P.S. I think in spite of Lent <lb/> we might go to one theatre perhaps. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>