<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0855">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 19 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender admonishes Lillian for believing he could have delayed reading her &#39;Xmas greetings&#39; letter for the six days until Christmas Day. He assures her that he will send her a Christmas letter of his own on the 25th. Spender refers to a proposal he has made to the Ninth Royal Irish Rifles, mentions a boar hunt upon which two of his fellow staff members and the General have gone, recounts a tour he went on himself the previous day. and gives details of the internal relationships and politics of his office. Spender jokes about a nickname Lillian has given his sister - &#39;little bear&#39; - and protests that he &#39;thought all my sisters were flowers&#39;. He mentions briefly the progress of the war, but will not go into details as Lillian knows &#39;my views about Douglas Haig&#39;. He finishes with a few brief comments about his chances of promotion, a letter he has written to his mother, and his Sunday lie-in.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/111</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/855</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0855_img_2415_1"  type="Letter"  url="2fd7810bbdaf6010b7a2235a6bd4547d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0855_img_2415_2"  type="Letter"  url="2a3006c818d4a340663ca0a5c9029093.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0855_img_2415_1"/>
                19. Dec 15   <hi rend="underline">My</hi> Pr.   If a little pr imagined for a minute that a bw would be content <lb/>to put away a letter for 6 days she is an even more curious creature <lb/>that even he thought. However he is very good, &amp; this letter will be <lb/>reread on the 24 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> !   Whilst I believe I can quite well defer m Xmas greetings <lb/>till Tuesday, you will take notice that the BW will endeavour hard <lb/>not to forget about a pr on the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, unless of course he is very busy!   I shall not be able to write tomorrow as I am going up to <lb/>see the 107 Bge I hope. At any rate I have made the suggestion <lb/>to the 9 RIR, &amp; trust they make take the proposal - not as a beastly <lb/><seg type="unclear">ban</seg> - but as a sign that they are not entirely forgotten by the remainder <lb/>of the Ulster Div.  I am alone in the office as  the 2  Ro have gone out on a boar <lb/>shoot with the General. I was not very keen as it is sunday &amp; <lb/> I proposed my visit to the 107<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>as my return.   Yesterday Richardson &amp; I went with the General on a <lb/>tour. Russell took the view that the Gen' would not want us <lb/>but I rather took the line that we ought to be with him <lb/>when he was doing this particular work, &amp; as a matter of fact <lb/>he seemed quite  well  pleased that we should. There is something <lb/> up between the Gen' &amp; Russell which I cannot understand, unless it <lb/>is that the latter's politeness is getting on the former's nerves. <lb/> Russell is certainly rather dumped at present &amp; it is possible that the Gen'  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0855_img_2415_2"/>
              has told him that he does not<lb/> recommend him for higher appointment<lb/> which is probably the<lb/> case with us all. Mayne has decided to relinquish his job in order<lb/> to become ADC again to Sir A Murray who is going our to the Mediterranean<lb/> probably as C in C I am sorry he is going.  Tell Sue that I did not know she was a 'little bear' I thought all<lb/> my sisters were flowers, I certainly married one of the family as such, &amp; found<lb/> â to my horror of course! â that she changed into an animal. Are the others<lb/> also going to do this? My leave will be even more uncertain till you reply  &amp; reassure me   Don't write more than a <seg type="unclear">p c</seg> when you have a headache old<lb/> thing. I shan't grumble.  They are very busy <seg type="unclear">hunting</seg> at the front, supposed to be for us, but all<lb/> plans may change now. I will not write about the changes as you know<lb/> my views about Douglas Haig. I hear Butler is to be chief of Staff! He is a<lb/> good fellow but we never expected this. If I wrote to him I could probably get a<lb/> lift but think I prefer to remain an obscure wild animal with a clean paw<lb/> in this respect. Only 6 years ago he was acting as my Chief of Staff on a staff ride!<lb/>  I have written a stupid letter to mother but she will<lb/> understand that I write under difficulties. I will answer the 3<lb/> other letters for the New Year, unless I turn up?  The General was to have started on his boar hunt in the dark<lb/> I took the opportunity of a laze bed till nearly 8, &amp; only just missed<lb/> him when I came down!  I hope to send you later Xmas wishes, &amp; you will<lb/> also have time to send me another batch perhaps? Any how I<lb/> shan't forget the little animal which keeps disturbing me  <seg type="closer"> Your b w  Wilfrid B Spender </seg>  19 Dec   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>