<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0919">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Alice Katherine Wynne to Sophia (Sophy) Sarah Wynne, 15 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Alice Katherine Wynne</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Alice Katherine Wynne (1833-1928) to her cousin Sophia (Sophy) Sarah Wynne in which she references the health of her husband (Albert Augustus Wynne). She also goes into great detail about the contents of a letter received from her son Charlie (1895-1917) describing his lack of food, lack of sleep due to night watch duties in the trenches and of minor injuries hospitalised him for a short while.Alice Katherine Wynne was born to Reverend John George Wynne and Emily Goold. She was married to Albert Augustus Wynne and was the mother of five children, among them Charles Wyndham Wynne. Charles served as a captain in the Royal Garrison Artillery in the First World War. He died of wounds received at Armentieres, June 1917.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>TCD MS 10247/1/510, TCD MS 10247/1/510</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/919</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1267">Alice Katherine Wynne</persName>
              <date>1916-10-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1162">The Cottage, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Sophia (Sophy) Sarah Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0919_img_261_1"  type="Letter"  url="4b7d6d952034e610f37c4a3ec39dd799.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0919_img_261_2"  type="Letter"  url="bfcb6c348829068df718002ee4758a24.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0919_img_261_3"  type="Letter"  url="74efc99ced9d714bb4f5bdc9541ed6b2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0919_img_261_4"  type="Letter"  url="ea2e0f10830d16499a35192d4ad81798.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0919_img_261_5"  type="Letter"  url="8da71585482b55c962b5ba2289efbe23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0919_img_261_6"  type="Letter"  url="88537298326f1cc78e999e72fc8e2c34.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0919_img_261_1"/>
                The Cottage   Sund. Oct-15-1916  My dearest Sophy,   This is a day of quiet so I <lb/>must take advantage of it to write <lb/>to you. I am afraid that you <lb/>will feel the sudden change to <lb/>cold that we had last night.   Albert is I think, better, he <lb/>has more intervals of comfort <lb/>but cannot get to bed before <lb/>about 2 o'clock. Last night at that <lb/>hour he had a wretchedly bad <lb/>attack &amp; was induced to inhale <lb/>an ' <seg type="unclear">arugl</seg>' capsule which he likes <lb/>to keep as a refuge when he is <lb/>really bad. It relieved him won— <lb/>derfully &amp; he had the best <lb/>night he has had for some <lb/>weeks. a 'delightful sleep'. We <lb/>had a long letter from Charlie <lb/>yesterday as far as we can make <lb/>out he had one nights sleep in <lb/>a weeks. Then he was tramping  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0919_img_261_2"/>
              <lb/>2. <lb/> all day &amp; dead tired &amp; sleepy <lb/> at 9 so he went to bed, there <lb/> was call up at 10. to <seg type="unclear">waken</seg><lb/> night duty at the battery every <lb/> time he sat down he felt he <lb/> was dropping off to sleep so <lb/> walked about till 9 o'clock the <lb/> next morning ( I forgot to say that <lb/> the day before he did the <lb/> 30 miles tramp through trenches <lb/> half had no supper the evening <lb/> before &amp; no breakfast that <lb/> morning!) Then the Captain <lb/> came up &amp; while C. was waiting <lb/> to be relieved he was talking <lb/> to him when suddenly every — <lb/> thing went round. &amp; the next <lb/> thing he knew he was on <lb/> a stretcher he has no idea <lb/> how he fainted, They <lb/> took him off for a long way <lb/> in a Med X van to hospital  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0919_img_261_3"/>
              <lb/>3. <lb/> he was so dead tired he <lb/> slept all the way &amp; is very <lb/> indignant with the Capt for <lb/> sending him to hospital but <lb/> I think it was the one sensible <lb/> thing in the whole show <lb/> it really is irrational to use <lb/> up men in such a way —   On one day I was left in <lb/> charge of a live battery <lb/> ( he had never seen the guns <lb/> before) &amp; orders came to fire <lb/> on an enemy tramway <lb/> but after 5 rounds the mist <lb/> came down so that the ob— <lb/>server could not see &amp; they had <lb/> to stop to C's great sorrow <lb/> They seem to have been <lb/> moved backwards &amp; for— <lb/> wards in the apparently  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0919_img_261_4"/>
              <lb/>4 <lb/>aimless way that they are <lb/> walked about &amp; as C expresses <lb/> it they 'scavenged' 3 positions <lb/> for their battery &amp; were <lb/> not allowed to occupy any <lb/> of them. I am sure the <lb/> work was very arduous <lb/> &amp; the whole thing an en— <lb/> acting experience to the <lb/> boy which no doubt added to <lb/> the complete exhaustion <lb/> helped to finish him, he <lb/> wrote from hospital. up <lb/> &amp; dressed on the 9 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the day <lb/>after he was brought there <lb/> &amp; was very comfortable <lb/> &amp; they were going to have <lb/> a concert that evening <lb/> &amp; he said he was 'right <lb/> as rain ' &amp; hoped to be sent  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0919_img_261_5"/>
              <lb/>5 <lb/>back next day he was only <lb/> concerned at being taken a— <lb/> way from his battery. He <lb/> has been laying his telephone <lb/> lines. He says their present <lb/> position is quite a good one <lb/> &amp; they have billets in the one <lb/> house left standing &amp; there <lb/> is a grand work = sleep, they <lb/>are making a splendid 'ob— <lb/> servation park' &amp; he hopes they <lb/> may be left there to use it <lb/> but it is doubtful whether <lb/> they will not be moved on <lb/> I know you like to hear <lb/>of him, so have sent you <lb/>all the particulars. poor <lb/><seg type="unclear">miss</seg> Baird is weather bound <lb/> here by these awful gales <lb/> She is dangerously seasick <lb/> &amp; it is sad if she is to lose the  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0919_img_261_6"/>
              <lb/>6 <lb/>good of her holiday by a bad <lb/> crossing we have quite lost <lb/> our hearts to her. I think she <lb/> is really happy at finding her— <lb/> self in a home once more <lb/> She has been over here for five <lb/> years away from her family <lb/> &amp; is often homesick — There <lb/> was a wire from May this <lb/> morning to say that Jack <lb/> had arrived yesterday, &amp; they <lb/> might perhaps read this <lb/> tomorrow afternoon. Will <lb/> you dear S. send this on to <lb/> Corris as it takes a long time <lb/> to give Charlie's news &amp; it will <lb/> save me writing it out again <lb/> We are much looking forward <lb/> to having Jack &amp; May with <lb/> us for a bit. The wind has been <lb/> so wild that the trees are nearly <lb/> leafless before they have turned   Following is from the first page <seg type="closer"> ever your very <lb/>loving   Alice <hi rend="underline">K. Wynne</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>