<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0790">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 8 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender scolds Lillian for straining her eyes and neck by writing letters late at night, and recommends that she hire a typist to relieve herself of the bulk of her clerical work. He asks Lillian to send him some blank cheques, and thanks her for some recently received parcels. Spender mentions his concern for his mother&#39;s health, as well as a visit Lillian will be making to the Carsons. Spender also briefly refers to theological questions, specifically the tenets of Swedenborgianism. Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender remained in contact with the Ulster Unionist leadership, and consistently opposed Home Rule and the six-county solution. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund. This letter is part of a series of correspondence from Sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/380</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/790</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-08T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0790_img_2331_1"  type="NULL"  url="3165ce016739e2b8d5b46830218b1537.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0790_img_2331_2"  type="NULL"  url="7ce8e09141552cd7e77da55b333c4740.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0790_img_2331_3"  type="NULL"  url="e08189dc80584cb32c3c7189a463110d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0790_img_2331_4"  type="NULL"  url="fa6c8bcccab5827c0633aa6ff822733d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0790_img_2331_1"/>
                8 Aug   My pr   2 Long letter today but I'm afraid you <lb/>will find a very cross bw unless you give up <lb/>writing at night, even to him. No really old <lb/>thing I would rather dispense with the greater <lb/>part of your letters than think of you straining <lb/>your eyes &amp; head in bed trying to be kind <lb/>to a bw. We both have our work to do <lb/>and don't need to be in constant letter <lb/>communications now. This is not a scolding <lb/>but it will become one unless you are good <lb/>in future. <hi rend="underline">Please send me some more  blank  cheques <lb/>at once !</hi> As regards your work I think you <lb/>ought to find some typing firm near which  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0790_img_2331_2"/>
              will relieve you of all your mere copying work and <lb/>surely you can find a small printer to undertake <lb/>some of it at a reasonable cost. If necessary send <lb/>to the WMN, who do job printing. Anything to <lb/>save you unnecessary clerical labour and if you <lb/>don't like to charge to the funds this very <lb/>fair claim we will make it part of our contriâ <lb/>bution.   So glad the family are pleased I knew they <lb/>must be, but was afraid that perhaps there was <lb/>something upsetting which prevented them from <lb/>telling you â Such a nice letter from Elsie <lb/>which I won't answer. I hope to get off one <lb/>of my reports as my dispatch is going to take me <lb/>all my time â what is spare â for several weeks.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0790_img_2331_3"/>
              Parcels have come many thanks. Nice letter <lb/>from Henry has come â scented paper ! not much <lb/>like war ! â He has taken on Farnham's work <lb/> as Comp Comdt because Gen' think Saunderson <lb/>will be too lazy ! So far they seem to have <lb/>got on all right but Farnham will be missed.  I'm sorry Mater is back in town in <lb/>this hot weather why doesn't she go to <lb/>Rex's. Perhaps she will in September.  As regards the massage I should quite <lb/>approve if it does lasting good, but am rather <lb/>afraid of things which like drugs sometimes <lb/>mean continuation or bad effects. If one <lb/>or twice a year it acts as a tonic well <lb/>&amp; good. You will understand I think.  So glad you were asked again by the Carsons  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0790_img_2331_4"/>
              I expect they are too much absorbed in each other <lb/>to notice the pr's moods &amp; know she is a bit tired.  I know nothing of <seg type="unclear">Swedinborgian</seg> tenets something <lb/>for the future perhaps. The one thing I cannot believe <lb/>is that a life or 20,40 or 60 years in this world <lb/>is to settle one's existence in all eternity, or that <lb/>future life can mean idleness which is rather  the teaching of <lb/>some pulpits.    I was surprised at the Japanese enclosure &amp; <lb/>thought it was a suggestion for a trip after the <lb/>war. this bw &amp; pr to go &amp; live on a Jap estate <lb/>for 2 or 3 years to save up for a rabbit hutch perhaps.  Must end now but may be able to <lb/>write some more not to be posted till tomorrow <lb/>tho'. <seg type="closer"> Your bw  WBSpender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>