<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0127">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dr Charles F. Judd concerning William Kelly, 4 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charles F. Judd</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Dr. Charles F. Judd (1888-1922) to state that William Kelly (1862-1921), a staff clerk at the Royal Irish Constabulary, was suffering from acute gastritis and had been under Dr Judd&#39;s care from the 20 April and was not considered fit for duty until the 3 May. The letter also encloses a document concerning the movements of William Kelly from the 22 April to 1 May signed by William Kelly.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/22041916/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/127</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0634">Charles F. Judd</persName>
              <date>1916-05-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0127_img_1212_1"  type="Letter"  url="c97794407389467150ed531a23844621.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0127_img_1212_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="95b502a1d7ed894d3b6131b8fe59e731.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0127_img_1212_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="20c35f5b135ac1a4d1d7e573e835ad01.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0127_img_1212_1"/>
                Coin du Chemin,  Foxrock,  Co. Dublin.   Phone Foxrock 83.   4.V.16    Mr William Kelly, Coolgarriff, <lb/> Stillorgan, has been ill, suffering <lb/>from Acute Gastritis &amp; <seg type="unclear">Tumeric</seg><lb/>Colitis, and under my care <lb/> since 20th April last. He was <lb/>not, in my opinion, fit for duty <lb/>till 3rd May 1916. <seg type="closer"> Charles M. Judd <hi rend="underline">M.D.</hi> </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0127_img_1212_2"/>
               Movements and occupations of Wm. Kelly, <lb/><hi rend="underline">Staff Officer, <hi rend="underline">R.I.</hi> Constabulary Office.</hi>  22nd. Apl. 1916. Spent the day in bed sick at my house, <lb/>Coolgariff, Stillorgan. Was attended by Doctor. <lb/>Slept at my house  23rd. Apl. 1916.(Sunday) Ditto.  24th.. Apl. 1916.(Monday) Ditto.  25th.. Apl. 1916.(Tuesday) Ditto.  26th. Apl. 1916 (Wednesday) Ditto.  27th. Apl. 1916 (Thursday) Got up about 11 a.m. spent the forenoon in my <lb/> garden. Called to Wm. Waters, Stillorgan, late <seg type="unclear">A.I.G</seg>. <lb/>in the afternoon to ask for news about R.I.C. Office. <lb/> Spent the rest of the afternoon in my Garden. Slept <lb/>at home.  28th Apl. 1916 (Friday) Spent the day up to about 3.p.m. in my house and <lb/> garden. Went for a walk afterwards to Sandyford <lb/>and back. Spent the evening and night in my house.  29th. Apl. 1916. (Saturday) After breakfast went to Blackrock to get provisions <lb/>in the shops there. After dinner went for a bicycle <lb/> ride for about an hour. Spent the rest of the day and <lb/>night at my house.  30th. Apl. 1916. (Sunday) Went to Divine Service at 8 o clock a.m. Spent the <lb/>rest of the day up to about 3.p.m. in my house and <lb/> garden. Went for a walk in the afternoon to Sandyford <lb/>and back. Slept at home that night.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0127_img_1212_3"/>
              1st. May 1916 (Monday) - After breakfast called to Mr. Waters' house at <lb/>Stillorgan, but did not see him as he was out. <lb/> Remained in my garden during the rest of the <lb/>forenoon.  I certify that the above is a true <lb/> account of my movements and occupations <lb/>during the period from noon on 22nd. April to <lb/> noon on 1st. May 1916. I attach a Medical <lb/>Certificate as to my illness. <seg type="closer"> William Kelly. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>