<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2181">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Eugene Callanan to Sir Robert Chalmers, 5 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Eugene Callanan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Eugene Callanan (1862-1931), secretary for Cork County Council. The letter was addressed to the Under-Secretary for Ireland, Sir Robert Chalmers (1858-1938). Chalmers was sent to Ireland as under-secretary, replacing Sir Matthew Nathan who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell , his chief secretary following the Easter Rising in 1916. 
This letter concerns a motion adopted by the Cork County Council the previous week. The motion requests that the members of the council be permitted to act on the Committees of Management of Tramways and Light Railways in the county of Cork on the understanding that they will not expect payment for doing so. </p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/9653</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2181</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1123">Eugene Callanan</persName>
              <date>1916-06-05</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0381">Cork County Council, Secretary&#39;s Office, Court House, Cork, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0268">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1931</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2181_img_1628_1"  type="Letter"  url="692628991c6d32f68ca25802c58ef293.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2181_img_1628_1"/>
             Cork County Council <lb/> SECRETARY'S OFFICE <lb/> COURT HOUSE <lb/> CORK,   June 5th, 1916   Dear Sir:   I beg to transmit for the consideration of His <lb/> Excellency, the Lord Lieutenant, the following motion <lb/> adopted by the Cork County Council at last meeting:   "That we request the Lord Lieutenant in <lb/> "Council to make an Order enabling Members of <lb/> "the County Council to act on the Committee of <lb/> "Management of Tramways and Light Railways in <lb/> "the County, on their understanding to accept neither <lb/> "fee nor remuneration for so acting."   I am, Sir, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,    <hi rend="underline">E Callanan</hi>   <lb/> Secretary.  The Under Secretary, <lb/>The Castle, <lb/>Dublin.    Inform that the County Council <lb/> should formally submit a <seg type="unclear">Memorial</seg> <lb/> <seg type="unclear">L. Th. M.</seg> stating the reasons for <lb/> their application &amp; the names of <lb/> the Railways in respect of which <lb/> the application is made  <lb/> E. Aof. <hi rend="underline">8-11-16.</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>