<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2119">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert Pim To John Sweetman, 16 September 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert Pim</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is addressed to John Sweetman (1844-1936). Sweetman was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. In 1915 he spoke out against conscription and was arrested in the aftermath of the 1916 Rising.
The letter was written by Herbert Moore Pim (1883-1950). Pim published a pamphlet series entitled &#39;Tracts of our times&#39;, including writings by Patrick Pearse, and in early 1916 founded the literary and political monthly, &#39;The Irishman&#39;. He joined the Volunteer muster in Coalisland at Easter 1916, and was arrested after the Rising and deported to Reading gaol. He was released in September 1916.
In this letter Pim writes that he wanted to visit Sweetman but that he was informed by Mrs O&#39;Neill that Sweetman was in the country. Pim mentions that he attended a conference in Dublin as an element of the movement was anxious to combine the forces known as Sinn Féin. The majority considered a formation of such an association imperative. Pim believes that Sinn Féin proper should adapt itself to the new conditions and embrace everyone who is roughly called a Sinn Féiner.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Family Papers, Collection List No. 156; Ms.47,589/12/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2119</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1003">Herbert Pim</persName>
              <date>1916-09-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0204">65 University Road, Belfast, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1950</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2119_img_1570_1"  type="Letter"  url="99607fad07897f78d2dba89e3b25e49e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2119_img_1570_2"  type="Letter"  url="f088ae2efadf30c6b6838bde23c91f5c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2119_img_1570_1"/>
             16<hi rend="superscript">th Sept. 1916.</hi>   Dear Mr. Sweetman,   I am very grateful for <lb/>your letter. It is remarkable that when <lb/>recently in Dublin I tried to arrange <lb/> with Mrs McNeill to ask you <lb/>to meet me at her house, as I did <lb/>not know your address. But she <lb/>said you were in the country. I <lb/>shall certainly give myself the <lb/> pleasure of calling on you when <lb/>I'm south again.   I had a conference with a number <lb/>of representations people in Dublin, <lb/> because the northern element was <lb/>anxious for some associations <lb/> or League which would combine
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2119_img_1570_2"/>
            the various forces know a <lb/> Sinn Fein. I support the opinion <lb/> of the majority &amp; see that the foundation of an <lb/> association was imperative; but, <lb/> if possible, that what ahead <lb/><seg type="unclear">just</seg> should be used, rather <lb/> than that a new League shd. be <lb/> found. Personally I am <lb/> inclined to suggest that Sinn <lb/>Fein proper should adopt itself <lb/> to the new conditions, &amp; embrace <lb/> everyone who is roughly called <lb/> a Sinn Feiner. That would mean <lb/> an adjustment of finances; because <lb/> a sub. of 5/- is out of the question in <lb/> most cases. Let branches be <lb/> found everywhere, &amp; an entrance <lb/> fee of 5/- be paid,  &amp; of  this the submitted <lb/> is Headquarters, is simply of the kind.     I enclose my newly adjusted <lb/> paper. Please send me your opinion of <lb/> what I have outlined.    <seg type="foreign">Slan agus beannacht</seg> ,  Herbert <hi rend="underline"> M Pim</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>