<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3162">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">A letter from Peter Mooney to Miss Mooney on an unknown date.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Peter Mooney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Orphaned at age 7, Peter Mooney and his sister Katie Mooney were raised by their uncle William and his wife Mary in Caulstown. While there are no surviving enlistment papers for Peter, his War Badge Index Record shows his enlistment date as 18 October 1915. He served with the Royal Artillery and later transferred to the Royal Engineers where he was promoted to the rank of Sergeant. He served in several places at the Western Front, including Ypres, St. Omer and Passchendael. Peter and Kate were avid correspondents. This letter part of a collection of over ninety surviving letters.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Mooney Family Papers</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3162</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0428">Peter Mooney</persName>
              <date>1915</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Miss Mooney</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0102">Caulstown, Sunboyne, Co. Meath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3162_img_2583_1"  type="Letter"  url="85b2c84e7db7f440c7e7e34068e9064f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3162_img_2583_2"  type="Envelope"  url="d5917afb44797392f90fccb07894f1ab.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3162_img_2583_1"/>
             I hope Mary Martin is in her usual<lb/>good health again, it would be very<lb/>bad if anything happened to her now.<lb/>I suppose that is the reason I did<lb/>not hear from them before now. Michael<lb/>Braken will go to hell altogether now that<lb/>he has such a good price for his land.<lb/>I am sure Connolly will hold a tight<lb/>grip on him now. I was glad to hear<lb/>Father Brady received my letter alright.<lb/>I hope to hear from him soon. I do<lb/>not want anything in the way of clothing<lb/>as I have enough to last me for a long<lb/>time to come + too much surplus stuff causes<lb/>a large amount of cursing when we come<lb/>to pack up. I will write to Micky O’Neill<lb/>in a few days he will be surprised to<lb/>have a letter from me I am sure.<lb/>Tell Miss Bondam &amp; her sister I wish to be<lb/>remembered to them and I know they say<lb/>an odd prayer for me may God Bless<lb/>them they are so good. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3162_img_2583_2"/>
             Miss Mooney. <lb/> Caulstown. <lb/>Dunboyne. <lb/>Co. Meath 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>