<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1617">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother Mary Martin, 18 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Marie Helena Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Martin (1866-1955) in Dublin. Marie Martin, later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM). In this letter from the theatre of war, Marie writes home to her mother to talk about family matters. Firstly Marie thanks her mother for sending a picture that she cherishes, Marie goes on to explain that she is very happy in Malta and enjoys the work she does. She describes part of the life she has and how she has many friends who work along side her. Martin then asks about the well being of various family members. Marie includes the plans she has for Christmas while in Malta.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>BF120</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1617</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0238">Marie Martin </persName>
              <date>1915-12-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1504">St. George&#39;s Hospital, Malta</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0990">Greenbank, Monkstown, Dublin, Co. Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1975</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1617_img_1080_1"  type="Letter"  url="a4123afb0368c0cd7ad89767ae31b223.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1617_img_1080_2"  type="Letter"  url="c3783b6f0d1146d98801481bad0100ec.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1617_img_1080_3"  type="Letter"  url="279a359d1c51b937872f6272bd9066be.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1617_img_1080_4"  type="Letter"  url="c00b243af0bd7ebb28fdfc10568b95ce.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1617_img_1080_5"  type="Letter"  url="66dfb950664820149527bb32b5f4e096.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1617_img_1080_6"  type="Letter"  url="07094c9d40d1d70a2646f5e924e81ef5.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1617_img_1080_1"/>
             20   B/F/1/20   <lb/> 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <hi rend="underline">December 1915</hi>    My own dearest Mother,   I received your most welcome letter<lb/>dated the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dec: also the Photo which gave<lb/>me more joy than anything else possibly could<lb/>have, I kissed it &amp; rekissed it &amp; long for the day<lb/>when we shall be together again, it will be so<lb/>nice having it always before me out here. I think<lb/>it very good &amp; you look absolutely sweet in it<lb/><sic>ofcourse</sic> it will never in my mind be as nice as<lb/>you really are, it is inclined to make you look<lb/>older than you really do but on the whole I<lb/>love it &amp; will always treasure it.  I am very glad in a way to hear Aunt Lily<lb/>is coming out especially if it makes your mind<lb/>easier but I think honestly for her sake &amp; mine<lb/>I would just as soon we were not at the same<lb/>Hospital, also as there are better than this place, I<lb/>think it would be nicer for her to go to a place<lb/>which is in better running order. <sic>also</sic> I think<lb/>she would find the running about very trying—<lb/>However whatever is best happy as has been<lb/>my case so far, I am happy here because I<lb/>love the work, although at times we are over worked.<lb/>The place seems to agree with me as I am<lb/>looking very well &amp; have got fat— My Staff<lb/>sister is a dear &amp; very fond of me &amp; seems to appreciate    
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1617_img_1080_2"/>
             2  <lb/> wait  my efforts which are poor enough  Charlies letter was a delight to read, he is a<lb/>splendid boy &amp; such spirit, it is too bad about<lb/>Singleton, perhaps he will be sent here for a bit<lb/>on his way home, he seems to have had a<lb/>nasty time of it— How splendid it would be<lb/>if Charlie has his Captaincy, I sent him 11/-<lb/>worth of food stuff yesterday, I hope he will get<lb/>them alright, I suppose he does not know I am<lb/>in Malta.  How delighted they all must be at Clyde R<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> over<lb/>Uncle Charlies return, I had a very nice long letter<lb/>&amp; cheque for Xmas from him, he writes in the best<lb/>of form, I am glad he went home Granny would<lb/>have missed him very much—  I had my second dose of <sic>innocutation</sic> against<lb/>Para-Typhoid, the day before yesterday, but we got<lb/>no extra time off this time <sic>infact</sic> I went on<lb/>immediately afterward, my arm has <sic>be</sic> so bad<lb/>yesterday &amp; to-day, I have done all the nurses a<lb/>good turn for when the D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> was passing my block<lb/>this morning he asked to see my arm which is<lb/>terrible red &amp; swollen &amp; when he saw it he went<lb/>straight up to the Major &amp; said we were to have<lb/>24 hours off after the next . <sic>does</sic>, so some day<lb/>next week I shall have a nice long day to write<lb/>you a very long letter &amp; tell you all about our little<lb/>doings in Matla for Xmas, 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1617_img_1080_3"/>
             3  You would have <sic>laughted</sic> at us last night<lb/>six of us <sic>arrange</sic> to meet at a certain place at<lb/>7 O'ck &amp; then go on to dine at a Hotel, which we<lb/>all understood, two V. A. D said they would go &amp; engage<lb/>table at which ever<seg type="del">y</seg> Hotel they thought best well we<lb/>all met at the so called hour to find they had<lb/>done nothing about a table, so we said we would<lb/>chance it, so the six of us tramped to Hotel  <lb/>hoping to be lucky but when we arrived all the<lb/>Tables were engaged so we <sic>ask</sic> the Manager, a very<lb/>polite Maltese could he not put up a table somewhere<lb/>for us &amp; a Lady who was evidently staying there<lb/>offered to allow 2 of us to sit at their table, so the<lb/>manager explained very nicely it was not the room<lb/>that was worrying him but that was very sorry but<lb/>there was not en<seg type="del">y</seg>ough for us to eat so we marched<lb/>out like a flock of sheep &amp;just met another V.A.D<lb/>who said well if you go &amp; join the Nurses Club<lb/>you'll get your dinner so off we marched again<lb/>with light hearts but when we got there they said<lb/>we could not get dinner till to-morrow as our names<lb/>had to be sent up etc, anyhow we all signed our<lb/>names &amp; left 2/6 our subscription for a month<lb/>as we thought it might turn in useful some other<lb/>time, <seg type="del">but</seg> by this it was about 7.45 &amp; our old<lb/>friend Blackney the Tea Shop closes at 8 <seg type="unclear">were</seg><lb/>we generally make our meal of eggs &amp; sausages<lb/>but woe &amp; behold all they could give us were. scones     
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1617_img_1080_4"/>
             4  <lb/>&amp; Tea, with a girl reminding us every 1/2 min: we<lb/>close at 8 O'ck so you can <sic>image</sic> our rush &amp; meal—<lb/>we were all very cross as it spoilt our whole<lb/>evening really. Did I ever tell you the Plum<lb/>Pudding arrived safely, I am now only waiting<lb/>to hear if you were able to collect &amp; how much<lb/>for my poor men for Xmas, I am hoping it<lb/>may arrive before to-morrow as I am going into<lb/>Valletta with Sister after tea to do the Xmas Shopping<lb/>for the men, it would be so nice if we remain as<lb/>we are just now, so few are <sic>no</sic> diets, it would make<lb/>it very easy to give them a nice Tea - or something<lb/>of the sort. Did I tell you we have a New M. O.<lb/>a ripper as far as the men are concerned<lb/>he gets them plenty to eat &amp; <sic>infact</sic> orders them<lb/>anything they want he makes it a little harder<lb/>for me but that does not matter so long as they<lb/>are pleased &amp; I <seg type="del">h</seg> am able to do it—  It is very late at night &amp; I should really be going<lb/>to sleep. but I am so happy &amp; excited to-night we<lb/>got a new convoy in &amp; they nearly all turned<lb/>out to be Irish &amp; mostly 1s<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Division, one<lb/>young boy has been attached to the 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Dublins<lb/>&amp; says he remembers Charlie who he left well<lb/>about <seg type="unclear">2</seg> weeks ago this has cheered me up<lb/>so &amp; it will be so nice having some <sic>ofmy</sic><lb/>own dear country men to look after especially<lb/>if they are in either Tommy or Charlie's regiment    
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1617_img_1080_5"/>
             5  I have one 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Connaught man who did not<lb/><sic>accually</sic> know Tommy as he was not with them<lb/>at the beginning but he <sic>know</sic> Massy &amp; says<lb/>he is well &amp; Adg now. Captain Cooper has<lb/>gone home on sick leave also Harvey. &amp; when<lb/>he left Dick, had not turned up. I had very<lb/>little time to talk to them as naturally I<lb/>was terrible busy we got 22 new ones &amp; most<lb/>of them have frost bitten feet which had to<lb/>be done up— some poor things with their<lb/>toes practically eaten away, their description<lb/>of the place is something awful<lb/>&amp; the cold seems appalling, they say the<lb/>ground is something terrible to get over &amp;<lb/>A. S. C <!-- Army Service Corps -->find it nearly impossible for the<lb/>transports, I really have not had time to<lb/>get particulars but will in a few days &amp;<lb/>shall write you all the news perhaps some<lb/>of the other Blocks will have some of<lb/>C. own men. I have asked every one<lb/>to find out. I am as happy as I can<lb/>be &amp; am looking forward if only the<lb/>money turns up to give them a jolly<lb/>Xmas, it will be so nice having so many<lb/>Irish they do make such a difference on<lb/>the wards with their hearty laughs &amp; jokes.<lb/><sic>Ofcourse</sic> all the old men give me a hot<lb/>time of it now—    
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1617_img_1080_6"/>
             6  Well I shall end this now as it is<lb/>very late &amp; have a busy morning to<lb/>face. I shall write very soon again &amp;<lb/>tell you every thing.  Every time I look at the Photo I like<lb/>it better &amp; better. The men say a good<lb/>number of R. <seg type="unclear">D.</seg> F. <!-- Most likely RDF meaning the Royal Dublin Fusiliers with whom Charlie served -->Came on the ship to<lb/>Malta so shall call when out to-morrow<lb/>at Wounded <seg type="unclear">Bivuak</seg> to see if I know any<lb/>so as to get real <sic>new</sic> of the old boy Charlie.<lb/>With all kinds of good wishes for the<lb/>New Year.  <lb/> Your most loving &amp; grateful<lb/>daughter.<lb/><hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>