<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4465">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Colonel F.A. Heygate Lambert, 18 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Colonel F.A. Heygate Lambert authorizing the release of 72 prisoners from Frongoch internment camp.

In 1916 Col. F.A. Heygate Lambert (1857-1929) was serving as the Commandant of Frongoch Internment Camp. Lambert served in the camp until the last of the prisoners were released in December 1916. In the Spring of 1917 he went to Ypres to command a battalion of the Labour Corps.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI/CSO/RP/1916/13388/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4465</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-07-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0929">F.A. Heygate Lambert</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1722">Frongoch, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4465_img_3812_1"  type="Letter"  url="142af6322ed7cc1f44313f29517763cc.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4465_img_3812_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="a6a6be37d9a991d17d33e668c317a423.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4465_img_3812_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="e4d6af37e1e077d28fa8cc8410c89820.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4465_img_3812_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="7fd2d60a5dd38fae6de6cff3b27d4024.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4465_img_3812_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="fc8e75bc997f7dbca32c50463969c5d0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4465_img_3812_1"/>
             <lb/>313106/  18th July 1916    Sir   I am directed by the Secretary of State to inform<lb/>you that, on the recommendation of the Advisory Committee<lb/>he authorises the release from internment of the 72 persons<lb/>named in the accompanying lists, this being the third<lb/>group of prisoners whose release he has authorised  These releases should be carried out in accordance<lb/>with the instructions already sent you.     I am  Sir  Your obedient servant  <lb/>The Commandant,<lb/>Prisoners of War Camp,<lb/>Frongoch<lb/>nr. Bala,<lb/>N. Wales. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4465_img_3812_2"/>
            <lb/>Tipperary Cases <lb/>1062 B Benn, William Church St. Tipperary  <lb/>1064 A Droghan, Francis  Irish Town, Clonmel  <lb/>1523 A Dunne, Arthur Enniscorthy  <lb/>1064 D Halpin, Thomas  Clonmel  <lb/>1081 Henehan, Patrick J.  Main St. Tethard  <lb/>1064 B Mackey, Domnic  Clonmel   <lb/>1062 A Maloney, Patrick J.  Tipperary  <lb/>1064 C Morrisey, John  Clonmel   <lb/>1066 B O'Neill, James  Clonmel   <lb/>1062 C Rogers, Thomas F. Tipperary  <lb/>1064 E RYAN, James  Clonmel  <lb/>1063 RYAN, William Ed.  Tipperary  <lb/>1066 SHEEHAN, Michael  Dundrum  <lb/>706 WALSHE, Daniel P.  Tethard  <lb/>1382 GANTLEY, Patrick J.  Roscrea  <hi rend="underline">Tyrone Cases.</hi> <lb/>773 Carberry, Charles  Donaghmore  <lb/>961 DUNCAN, Patrick  Strabane  <lb/>768 GRIEVE, James  Strabane  <lb/>1012 McCRORY, Hugh  Dunmoyle  <lb/>Advie release. <lb/>Signed on behalf of the Advisory Committee.  July 17th 1916.  (Signed) JOHN SANKY  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4465_img_3812_3"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">Clare Cases</hi> <lb/>891 COMER, Patrick Killasloe <lb/>891 HEALY, Denis Bodyke <lb/>655 HENIR, Hugh Ballybough <lb/>519 KELLY, Timothy Feakle <lb/>1300 MALONE, John Feakle <lb/>953 O'DONNELL, Arthur Ennis <lb/><hi rend="underline">Kildare Cases</hi> <lb/>1150 COSGRAVE, Michael Coolearrigen <lb/>1209 KIRWIN, Patrick Maynooth <lb/>908 A MORAN, Edmund Ballysex <lb/>1204 C O'RYAN, Oliver Maynooth <lb/>1207 D REGAN, WIlliam Maynooth <lb/>1585 A TYRELL, Timothy Maynooth <lb/><hi rend="underline">Kilkenny Cases</hi> <lb/>735 BARRY, Denis Kilkenny <lb/>715 DENN, William Kilkenny <lb/>737 GIBBONS, John Freshford <lb/>1466 LALOR, James Kilkenny <lb/>734 STEPHENS, William Kilkenny <lb/>740 TREACY, Thomas Kilkenny <lb/> Advise release <lb/> Signed on behalf of the Advisory Committee <lb/> July 17th 1916.   (Signed) JOHN SANKY. 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4465_img_3812_4"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">Donegal Cases.</hi> <lb/>1013 Cassidy, J. Ballybofey <lb/>1013 KELLY, Daniel Cashelmagore, Gortshook. <lb/><hi rend="underline">Down Cases</hi> <lb/>903 KELLY, Robert Newry <lb/>1113 RANKIN, Patrivk Newry <lb/><hi rend="underline">Fermanagh Cases</hi> <lb/>1460 McGUIRE, Patrick J. Derrygonelly <lb/><hi rend="underline">King's County</hi> <lb/>1216 FOLEY, Michael Patrick Edenderry <lb/><hi rend="underline">Leitrim</hi> <lb/>1079 DALY, John Manor Hamilton <lb/>1079 A DOLAN, JAmes Nicholas Manor Hamilton <lb/>1079 C GILGUNN, Thomas Manor Hamilton <lb/>1078 MAGUIRE, Bernard JOhn Glenfane <lb/>1078 O'LOUGHLIN, Thomas Manor Hamilton <lb/><hi rend="underline">Longford</hi> <lb/>1181 A CAWLEY, John Granard <lb/>1181 A CUSACK, Paul V. Granard <lb/><hi rend="underline">Meath</hi> <lb/>933 LYNAM, Christopher Dunboyne <lb/>1208 LYNCH, Patrick Kells <lb/><hi rend="underline">Monaghan</hi> <lb/>942 DALY, Patrick J. Carrickmacross <lb/>941 LOUGHRAN, William James Carrickmacross <lb/>142 B NOLAN, Thomas Carrickmacross <lb/>942 O'BRIAN, James Carrickmacross <lb/>942 D REILLY, Patrick Carrickmacross <lb/>943 WARD, Thomas Carrickmacross <lb/><hi rend="underline">Queen's County</hi> <lb/>712 FRAWLEY, John Wolfhill <lb/><hi rend="underline">Roscommon</hi> <lb/>902 BRENNAN, John Carrowkeel <lb/>902 GERAGHTY, George Roscommon <lb/>1257 B CASSIDY, MIchael Strokestown <lb/>901 DOORLY, Edward Roscommon <lb/>901 DOORLY, John James Rosommon <lb/>901 SMYTH, Patrick Roscommon <lb/>770 B MARTIN, Edward Athlone <lb/>927 O'HARA, Thomas F. Ballaghadereen <lb/><hi rend="underline">Westmeath</hi> <lb/> 764 MALONE, Thomas Tyrellspass <lb/><hi rend="underline">Cork</hi> <lb/>1463 BUCKLEY, William Banteer
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4465_img_3812_5"/>
            <lb/><hi rend="underline">Cork (Contd)</hi> <lb/>552 O'CALLAGHAN, Cornelius Millstreet <lb/>913 FOLEY, Joseph Castleownbere <lb/>Advise release <lb/>Signed on behalf of the Advisory Committee  July 17th 1916.   (signed) JOHN SANKY 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>