<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1535">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff to Lady Clonbrock, 12 August 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mrs. Arthur Goff</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Mrs. Arthur Goff, honorary secretary of the Dundrum Prisoners of War Organisation, to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Mrs. Goff had a similar role to Lady Clonbrock in the Irish Women&#39;s Association, formed in London in the Spring of 1915 for the purpose of providing food and comforts for prisoners of war belonging to Irish Regiments. 
Mrs. Goff has been asked to look after a named POW by his former employer. She normally looks after Royal Dublin Fusiliers and here she is asking lady Clonbrock what is being done for him - presumably she is writing to Lady Clonbrock because the prisoner is a Connaught Ranger. She is trying to avoid overlap between the two organisations.
In a note on the back of the letter, Lady Clonbrock writes that she told Mrs. Goff to check with the IWA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35,796/11/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1535</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1236">Mrs. Arthur Goff</persName>
              <date>1916-08-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0673">Belfort House, Dundrum, Co. Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1535_img_1003_1"  type="Letter"  url="12f543c13b1b3efa1085b9a8d556e21a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1535_img_1003_2"  type="Letter"  url="791498caf3ee290331543d1faf0c537f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1535_img_1003_1"/>
             Aug 12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>1916   Dundrum <lb/>Co.Dublin.   Dear Lady Clonbrock   I am so sorry to trouble you again, but I <lb/> have been asked to look after <lb/>8105 Pte James Gaffney by his former <lb/>employer. As I want if possible not to overlap <lb/>can you tell me what is being done for him   I have been asked particularly to find out whether <lb/>he is getting bread.   Sincerely yours   <seg type="unclear">Elle Mari</seg> Goff. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1535_img_1003_2"/>
             From Mrs Goff<lb/>Att. James Gaffney<lb/>tell her that she<lb/>must write to G.W.A.<lb/>&amp; give more<lb/>information. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>