<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0389">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Devlin to Margaret O'Brien, 12 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Devlin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Joseph Devlin to Margaret O&#39;Brien regarding the incorrect internment of Margaret&#39;s husband&#39;s remains. According to Devlin the remains are on grounds not provided for by the Public Health Act and for that reason the application should be made to Lord Lieutenant, Ivor Guest (1873-1939).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/5613/9083/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/389</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0915">Joseph Devlin</persName>
              <date>1916-05-12</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Margaret O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1252">The Green, Midleton, Co. Cork, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0389_img_1651_1"  type="NULL"  url="bb2205ab6b1665bd1875e3b0381d1973.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0389_img_1651_1"/>
                LOCAL GOVERNMENT BOARD, DUBLIN.    12th May, 1916.  <lb/>No. 21,438 : 1916, <lb/>Midleston Urban District.  Madam,   I am directed by the Local Government Board for <lb/> Ireland to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of <lb/> the 26th ultimo, and, in reply I am to state that if, <lb/> as would appear to be the case, the remains of your <lb/> late husband are interred in a Burial Ground not pro— <lb/>vided under the Public Health Acts, you should address <lb/> your application for the disinterment of the remains to <lb/> His Excellency the Lord Lieutenant. <seg type="closer"> I am, <lb/> Madam, <lb/> Your obedient Servant,  Joseph Devlin <lb/> Assistant Secretary.   Mrs Margaret O'Brien,  The Green,  Midleton.  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>