<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1539">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Lady Mayo to Lady Clonbrock, 28 December, 1915.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Geraldine Sarah Bourke</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Geraldine Sarah Bourke (née Ponsonby), Lady Mayo (1863-1944) to Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton), Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Lady Clonbrock, wife of Luke Gerald Dillon, 4th Baron Clonbrock (1834-1917) was a member of the Irish Women&#39;s Association. Formed in London in the Spring of 1915, the IWA&#39;s purpose was to provide food and comforts for prisoners of war belonging to Irish Regiments. Lady Mayo(1863-1944), was a committee member in The Royal Dublin Fusiliers&#39; County Kildare Committee. The Committee dealt with parcels for RDF prisoners of war abroad.
This letter concerns Private Joseph Connolly, a Connaught Rangers P.O.W., who has been the subject of ongoing correspondence. Even though Lady Mayo&#39;s organisation only looks after Dublin Fusiliers, she sent  parcels to this man on request because his mother was old and poor and couldn&#39;t send him much. The writer now wants the know if Lady Clonbrock&#39;s organisation will take him over.
The enclosed letter mentioned has not survived.
A note on the letter, presumably by Lady Clonbrock, reads notes the response given to Lady Mayo&#39;s letter.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54; Ms. 35.796/11/15</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1539</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1240">Geraldine Sarah Bourke</persName>
              <date>1915-12-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0928">Palmerstown, Straffan, Co. Kildare, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1944</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1539_img_1007_1"  type="Letter"  url="4ea86c53bf9db709f7d3ec0dd7201818.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1539_img_1007_2"  type="Letter"  url="3fd2d7b520e7b6df1235628dbe165e6a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1539_img_1007_3"  type="Letter"  url="6cc01553f709f1893d8e32f64d7a056b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1539_img_1007_1"/>
             Returned <lb/> letters &amp; said <lb/> J. C. had been on <lb/>county list for months <lb/>&amp;all C.R. Prisoners were <lb/>well looked after — <lb/>Dec. 31 — <lb/>1915   Telegraph <lb/>Johnstown, Kildare   Station <lb/>Sallins.   Palmerstown, <lb/>Straffan, <lb/>Co. Kildare.   Dec 28.   Dear Lady Clonbrock   I was sent the name of <lb/> 3237 Pt. Joseph Connolly <lb/>Connaught Rangers <lb/>no. 5 kompagnie group 34 <lb/><seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign">Zivilgefangenen</seg></seg> <seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign">Langer</seg></seg> <lb/><seg type="foreign"><seg type="unclear">Senne 1 Sennelagerbec</seg></seg> <lb/><seg type="unclear"><seg type="foreign">Panerborn</seg></seg>— Germany <lb/>asking to have parcels sent <lb/>to him as he only had <lb/>an old mother who was <lb/>too poor to send him much.   As my Committee only
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1539_img_1007_2"/>
            look after the Dublin Fusiliers <lb/>we <sic>cd.</sic> not help from <lb/> our fund —but in case <lb/>he was in want, I sent <lb/>him myself a parcel <lb/>on Dec. 7 &amp; 18 containing <lb/>tea, coffee &amp; milk, condensed <lb/>milk, cheese &amp; herrings in <lb/> tomatoe sauce &amp; another <lb/>will go on Thurs next — <lb/>also bread from Berne <lb/>for 6 weeks from Dec 7  Will your committee <lb/>now take him on?   I enclose the letters from <lb/>Mrs. Shaw about him.   Yours Sincerely   Geraldine Mayo 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1539_img_1007_3"/>
            <!-- marginal note on separate page --> 1915 <lb/>Joseph Connolly <lb/>has been on county <lb/><hi rend="underline">list for months</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>