<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1592">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Agnes MacNeill to Madam O'Rahilly, 17 August, 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Agnes MacNeill</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Agnes (Taddie) MacNeill (1874-1953), wife of Eoin MacNeill (1867-1945), to Nancy O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1961). Nancy O&#39;Rahilly was a member of the Provisional Council of Cumann na mBan at the founding in 1914 and the wife of Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly, self-described as &#39;The&#39; O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916). The O&#39;Rahilly fought in the Easter Rising and was shot in Parnell/Moore Street on 28 April 1916 and died some time later. Nancy was pregnant at the time of her husband&#39;s death – the child was born three months later.
Eoin MacNeill was chief-of-staff of the Irish Volunteers at the time of the Easter 1916 Rising, although he took no part in it and even tried to prevent it.
Mrs MacNeill is glad to hear that Nancy is beginning to feel strong - she has heard what a lovely strong boy the baby is.
She would like to visit but she is not in town very often. She remarks on how what they have experienced has changed their perspective, in that they see life in a very different way now.
She goes on to list her children and what each one is doing - leaving home for education or work purposes - and leaving the house very quiet.
She asks to be remembered to her to Nancy&#39;s sister and Sighle Humphreys.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Humphreys Papers, P106/120/58</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1592</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0568">Agnes MacNeill</persName>
              <date>1916-08-17</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0264">Woodtown Park, Rathfarnham, County Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1534">Nancy O&#39;Rahilly</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1953</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1592_img_1058_1"  type="Letter"  url="8af6829df9356f35fef3d1ad8964cc4e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1592_img_1058_2"  type="Letter"  url="75d2089c35aedfcea0c8753df0c7ffce.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1592_img_1058_3"  type="Letter"  url="7623f51e9403f514aa6bf5e6de728a88.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1592_img_1058_1"/>
             WOODTOWN PARK, <lb/>RATHFARNHAM, <lb/>CO. DUBLIN.   August 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1916   My Dear Madam O’Rahilly,   I was as glad to see <lb/><sic>your</sic> writing again and I know <lb/>that you are beginning to feel <lb/>strong again. I heard from <lb/>many people what a lovely <lb/>strong boy the baby is - God <lb/>bless him.   I will be delighted to <lb/>go and see you the first
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1592_img_1058_2"/>
            day I am in town but <lb/>I am hardly ever in town <lb/>now. What we have all <lb/>come through makes one <lb/>see life in a very different <lb/>way.   You mention the happy past <lb/>Oh! how far away that <lb/>seems now, and the <lb/>dear friends we will <lb/>never meet again. How <lb/>little you or I ever dreamt <lb/>this would be the end.   Seamus is going to live with <lb/>my Mother. Mayra &amp; <seg type="unclear">Bryan</seg> <lb/>are going to Aran to Miss Folan <lb/>Niall is with a solicitor. <lb/><seg type="unclear">Eihblin</seg> will go to Muckross to <lb/>board &amp; Brian, <seg type="unclear">Loughlackagh</seg> <lb/>to school. We will soon <lb/>have a very quiet house. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1592_img_1058_3"/>
             Please remember me <lb/>To your sister and M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Humphreys   Your sincere friend   Agnes MacNeill 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>