<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1409">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 29 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.James has returned from seeing May and missed her, speaks of getting the house ready for her to move into and finalising the arrangements. He has been invited to attend a conference of the National Health Insurance Commissions in England and in loath to do so because of Zeppelins.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection>NULL, NULL</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1409</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-03-29T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2073">Rathmines, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1409_img_808_1"  type="Letter"  url="a88c1404464e2fe4792991ef4bff4287.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1409_img_808_2"  type="Letter"  url="8ac3216d301eeee76402ac571457a236.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1409_img_808_3"  type="Letter"  url="805a9f9efa01f040e76a13afe94658c8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1409_img_808_1"/>
                29th March, 1916.   My dearest May,   I got back all right last <lb/>night very glad to see the fire after a <lb/>very cold and not particularly cheery journey. <lb/>There were very few people in the train so that <lb/>we ran through without a stop from Enfield. <lb/>That was about the only comfort in an otherwise <lb/>depressing journey. I found every body very well <lb/>and looking out for news but I'm afraid <lb/>I'm a bad hand at news. My mother was <lb/>anxious to know if we had definitely fixed <lb/><hi rend="underline">the day</hi> but I had to disappoint her in that <lb/>also. I wish you'd try and induce your mother  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1409_img_808_2"/>
              to fix it for the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> June. That's the day I'm <lb/>looking forward to myself and I shall be <lb/>awfully disappointed if the marriage doesn't take <lb/>place then. I must start to make preparations <lb/>for it now. There's a good deal in the way of <lb/>painting and papering that I should like to see <lb/>done and I must try and induce my landlord <lb/>to do the house up generally for your reception. <lb/>Of course I must have it looking its best when <lb/>my dear bride comes home to it. When a man <lb/>gets a <seg type="unclear">prize</seg> (that's what Ray called you wasn't it) <lb/>he must get a proper setting for it. I must at <lb/>any rate have <hi rend="underline">our</hi> bedroom done up and I <lb/>had it in mind before going down to ask you  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1409_img_808_3"/>
              about it but forget it some how. My mother <lb/>was suggesting that you should use the small <lb/>room in front as a dressing room and that I <lb/>should get a large wardrobe to be made for it that <lb/>would hold your clothes. The one in <hi rend="underline">our</hi> room <lb/>is small enough for my own clothes at present <lb/>and would be quiet unsuitable for you. We can <lb/>talk it over when you come up at Easter and <lb/>whatever you decide on can be <lb/>arranged. It will be an extra pleasure in <lb/>making my own arrangements to have the <lb/>additional job of fixing a nest for you. <lb/>I hope you weren't lonely last night. I haven't yet <lb/>had the time to get lonely although I feel the loss of <lb/>you every moment but I suppose I'll be as <lb/>restless and dissatisfied as ever after another day or so. <lb/>I'm writing this under <seg type="unclear">forced</seg> draught today as I  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>