<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0798">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 15 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender expresses admiration at how Lillian remains constantly fresh when writing letters, and makes several allusions to the pet names the couple have for each other (&#39;Brown Wolf&#39; and &#39;Pink Rabbit&#39;). Spender updates Lillian on the progress of his report, and regrets his departure from the Ulster Division, as leave has been specifically approved for that Division. He asks Lillian to send on the letter to his family.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/387</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/798</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-08-15</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0798_img_2339_1"  type="NULL"  url="54f676c6770454c32ab381294b75d931.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0798_img_2339_2"  type="NULL"  url="9b0cdd2431edc38fb405f1308dc4021c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0798_img_2339_3"  type="NULL"  url="54f676c6770454c32ab381294b75d931.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0798_img_2339_1"/>
                15 Aug   My pr   I ought to be out, but it is raining, so <lb/>I will begin a screed though I am not as fresh as <lb/>the pr always appears to be in spite of her many <lb/>hours at the desk. I like to see the way in <lb/>which your committee think it necessary to <lb/>get your approval â even in regard to St Janes' <lb/>Palace. â I shall certainly write to  you  there when <lb/>I am quite sure of the address! â I am so <lb/>glad that a Wolf's paw marks has the same <lb/>effect as Cockles  (?)  pink pills according to the <lb/>patient, but I'm afraid the bw riffs rather <lb/>suspiciously as the compliment!   I had a great wrestle this morning and <lb/>have completed the 34<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> page of my tome though  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0798_img_2339_2"/>
              <lb/>very far from satisfied with it. It will need a <lb/>lot of polish and I know a pr would make such <lb/>an excellent chamois leather! I hear leave has <lb/>been <sic>aproved</sic> specially for the Ulster and one or <lb/>two other divisions â boohoo why did I leave? â   Today's afternoon wire caused such a lot <lb/>of head scratching â literally â I think we were <lb/>nearly an hour as I rather stuck my toes in <lb/>at one or two phrases which <seg type="del">it</seg> were proposed.  I am cogitating whether it is fair to put <lb/>in the German written remarks about the extraordin- <lb/>ary disproportion between the Saxon &amp; Prussian troops <lb/>being employed in this battle, when I guess that <lb/>the figures may have been reversed at Verdun. <lb/>It would <seg type="del">make</seg>  have  considerable effect in the <lb/>Saxon wireless stations!  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0798_img_2339_3"/>
              <seg type="postscript"> At top of page 1  There is <lb/>a lot in <lb/>this letter <lb/>which ought <lb/>to have been <lb/>reserved for <lb/>a family <lb/>letter. Can't <lb/>you send it <lb/>on?? <lb/>certainly the <lb/>last page </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>