<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0302">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Fogarty to Alice Stopford Green, 1916 July 26.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Fogarty</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a copy of letter from Michael Fogarty (1859-1955), bishop of Killaloe, to Alice Stopford Green (1847-1929), Irish historian and nationalist. Stopford Green was a close friend of Sir Roger Casement (1865-1916) and one those involved in the campaign to reprieve Casement&#39;s sentenced to death for treason after he had been arrested on Banna Strand in County Kerry on the eve of the Easter Rising. Fogarty writes to enclose a petition on behalf of Casement and writes in strong support of Casement, noting that no public interest would be served by Casement&#39;s execution. The letters also notes that the signatures of a number of other clergy will follow. Fogarty was said to have been opposed to the Easter Rising but later wrote against the partition of Ireland and of &#39;hideous atrocities&#39; committed by the British on Irish nationalists.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No. A15, Ms. 13,088 (9)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/302</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1434">Michael Fogarty</persName>
              <date>1916-07-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0697">Killaloe, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0989">Alice Stopford Green</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Culture and the Arts</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0302_img_1523_1"  type="Letter"  url="da3654891d35b820612289945cb30187.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0302_img_1523_1"/>
              Copy of Letter from the Bishop of Killaloe    Ennis    26th July 16   Dear Mrs Stopford Green   I enclose petition for Sir Roger Casement with <lb/> my signature attached.  I have never met Sir Roger Casement, I know <lb/> nothing of him except through the press. I regard <lb/> him as a most pure and exalted enthusiast for <lb/> what is right and noble regardless of money <lb/> or pleasure.  Men of that fine strain are becoming very scarce <lb/> in English life. Why destroy them in cold blood <lb/> If the English <sic>Govnmt </sic>insist on his Execution - <lb/> well revenge may be gratified, but no <lb/> public interest will be <seg type="unclear">sewed</seg> thereby in Ireland, <lb/> but quite the other way of that there <lb/> is no doubt whatever. <seg type="closer"> Sincerely yours  M. Fogarty <lb/> Bishop of Killaloe<lb/> Signatures follow of  D ODonnell  Bishop of Raphoe<lb/> Robert Brown  Bishop of Cloyne<lb/> William Miller  bishop of <seg type="unclear">Eumenia</seg><lb/> (Stillorgan Dublin)</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>