<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5605">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Herbert Pim to John Sweetman, 21 October 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Herbert Pim</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from Herbert Moore Pim (1883-1950) to John Sweetman (1844-1936). Pim was a political activist and writer. He had joined the Irish Volunteers in 1914, published a pamphlet series entitled &#39;Tracts of our times&#39;, including writing by Patrick Pearse, and in early 1916 founded the literary and political monthly, &#39;The Irishman&#39;. Sweetman was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. In 1915 he spoke out against conscription and was arrested in the aftermath of the 1916 Rising.
This letter refers to politics and the Sinn Fein movement with Pim mentioned that the Sinn Fein revival would prevent internal dissent and &#39;Invincible methods&#39;, i.e. violence.  It also refers Sir John Griffith and his son, former and current chief engineers at Dublin Port and to potato blight which had set in in Connacht, suggesting reducing the export of foodstuffs and sending them to the West of Ireland instead.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Family Papers, Collection List No. 156; Ms. 47,589 /12</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5605</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1003">Herbert Pim</persName>
              <date>1916-10-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0407">65 University Road, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1950</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5605_img_699_1"  type="Letter"  url="494c2bd45585e0644c9a50470d7ca565.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5605_img_699_2"  type="Letter"  url="361af3ff2974d3d813bad78dac975622.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5605_img_699_1"/>
             65, University Road, Belfast   21st October 1916    My dear Mr. Sweetman,   I am extremely obliged for your valuable<lb/>letter which I shall publish in the issue of 29th inst.  You must forgive me for not replying to your first letter;<lb/>but really the amount of correspondence which has poured into<lb/>this house would frighten any white man. We have taken the<lb/>public fancy with a vengeance. The Nation League went down at the<lb/>first blow; Judge in this week's <hi rend="underline">Irish Nation</hi> , says he must<lb/>stand aside, although doing so means a great sacrifice. <sic>Seen</sic><lb/>we shall have all the 'safe' men and all the advanced men crowding<lb/>into the Sinn Fein movement; but by that time the right people<lb/>will be in command in each district. I am issuing five little<lb/>tracts at once, price  ; and instructions for the formation of<lb/>clubs will be published in the next issue. Belfast is at work,<lb/>&amp; has <seg type="del">conrad</seg> secured suitable premises. I see you refer to<lb/><hi rend="underline">Mr.</hi> John W. Griffith in your letter for publication, and to Sir<lb/>John Griffith in your letter to me. Is this a case of father &amp;<lb/>son? Where does Sir John Griffith reside? &amp; could you<lb/>communicate with him on my behalf? He might be inclined to<lb/>write me at your suggestion. I see in this Sinn Fein revival<lb/>a safety valve for national aspiration, which will prevent internal<lb/>disturbance and dissention, &amp; will avoid invincible methods.    I think the Coal question, the Harbour Board question<lb/>&amp; the coming potato famine in Connacht are the most important at the<lb/>moment. Blight has set in all over Connacht. The Harbour boards<lb/>can  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5605_img_699_2"/>
              can be compelled to reduce the expert of foodstuffs, &amp; public<lb/>opinion must send those foodstuffs to the West. We have our hands<lb/>full. Wait until the time of the bag meetings comes, &amp; you<lb/>will see the largest gathering in Phoenix Park that ever was known<lb/>or ever will be known. And the fine thing will be that the meeting<lb/>will represent a dynamic force, not a mere gathering of listeners;<lb/>but a body of men whose activity for Ireland's welfare will become<lb/>evident in each action of their future life in Ireland<lb/><lb/> Yours very sincerely,<lb/>Herbert Pim  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>