<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0753">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 30 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from sir Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, Lady Lillian Spender, née Dean, (1880-1968). This letter mainly consists of Wilfrid&#39;s declarations of affection for Lillian, as he alludes to the &#39;pink paw marks&#39; he looks forward to finding on his letters. This refers to Wilfrid&#39;s pet-name for Lillian, &#39;P.R.&#39;, which appears to stand for &#39;Pink Rabbit&#39;. His own pet-name is &#39;B.W.&#39;, or &#39;Brown Wolf&#39;. Wilfrid also takes pleasure in the idea of the censor reading his words to Lillian. He finishes the letter with the news that Germany is willing to give up Alsace-Lorraine and an indemnity to France as part of a possible peace, but states that he is not optimistic.Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War. Lady Lillian served in the Ulster Volunteer Nursing Corps during the war, and was an organiser of the Ulster Division Comforts Fund.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/330</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/753</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-06-30</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0753_img_2282_1"  type="NULL"  url="6ca03781770d5e81f9efa7cab5c0ea64.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0753_img_2282_2"  type="NULL"  url="707358cb6439edb71b3d28de75b668ce.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0753_img_2282_1"/>
                30 June   My P R   Only a scrap with my <seg type="unclear">folks</seg> letter <lb/>as I am soon bound for my rabbit â <lb/>protected hole where I intend to pass the <lb/>night &amp; to remain part of tomorrow.  It is uncertain where I shall be tomorrow <lb/>evening but I am fairly certain not to <lb/>be able to write for a couple of days now  It was a great joy to get 4 letters <lb/><hi rend="underline">of course</hi> rather a disappointment that <lb/>there were pink paw marks! I think of you now <lb/>poor p r with <seg type="unclear">Mr V</seg> &amp; do hope you <lb/>won't get a fearful head before you move <lb/>nor be tired out by the move. I agree that <lb/>your partner is having a very easy time in <lb/>the move. I hope she doesn't let you be the maid <lb/>of all work. Most kind of Uncle Gay give him  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0753_img_2282_2"/>
              my warm thanks. Terrific <seg type="unclear">glaring</seg> almost<lb/> hols for the <seg type="unclear">pit mates</seg> ! All the same when<lb/> the p r is taking a little relaxation the b w wishes<lb/> her to do it comfortably. Great growls at next<lb/> page in this letter. The p r 's <seg type="unclear">white</seg> imagination<lb/> would have pink wolf pawmarks about if it<lb/> were possible. You may well blush at the<lb/> censor reading this but I am not responsible<lb/> What a pity Mr Bain doesn't now censor<lb/> your letters.  All kinds of optimistic reports about<lb/> including that Germany has offered Alsace<lb/> Lorraine &amp; an indemnity to France! Next<lb/> she will be offering Hamburg to England in a <lb/> few days or something equally wild <hi rend="underline">if</hi> we<lb/> have any success at all. I don't like optimistism<lb/> now. <seg type="closer"> Your  b w<lb/> W B Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>