<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4179">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John to James Shaw, 2 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Shaw Papers, D1962-2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4179</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0924">John</persName>
              <date>1916-01-02</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">James Shaw</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4179_img_3552_1"  type="Letter"  url="4ccfe982827486818b8d9f5f1d5abf14.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4179_img_3552_2"  type="Letter"  url="d9c3e021cf196bd9d073826ee3eca17d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4179_img_3552_1"/>
             2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Jan 1915   Dear James,   Many thanks for your very nice <lb/>card received to day I hope all your <lb/>people are well. I had one letter <lb/>from my <seg type="unclear">ma</seg> &amp; <seg type="unclear">Liam</seg> <seg type="unclear">Mike</seg> since he left <lb/>you. They are all getting along fine. <lb/>I thought they would have got a <lb/>few days  leave  at <seg type="unclear">Exmas</seg> I am getting along <lb/>fine here and we all had a good <lb/>time at <sic>Exmas</sic>. I am <sic>shure</sic> it is <lb/>very dull about Portstewart now <lb/>with all the boys away. I see Stuart <lb/>Henry has gone to  . There is some <lb/>talk about us getting leave but I <lb/>don't know whether it will come <seg type="unclear">up</seg> <lb/>or not. If I do get home I will miss <lb/>my old chum. I wish we could <lb/>both manage to be home at the same
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4179_img_3552_2"/>
            but it is a terrible watch now <lb/>for the names. They would <lb/>neither surrender nor retire.   The world might call it foolhardy  glorious!  <lb/>but it i;s such conduct that <lb/>purifies the poor world, and <lb/>raises it to a higher level <lb/>and lives in History for generations <lb/>to come. Please convey our <lb/>heart felt congratulations to <lb/>your husband and accept <lb/>them yourself also from us.   Don't these verses fit them? <lb/>And now we feel that all around <lb/>Have angels walked the well known ground <lb/>Not winged &amp; strange beyond your ken <lb/>But in the form of common men <lb/>God's messengers from Heaven's own sphere <lb/>Unrecognised — because so near.   Believe me sincerely yours <lb/>Gertrude Cd Clements 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>