<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1283">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Susan Fitzgerald to Michael Gorman, 23 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Susan Fitzgerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Susan Fitzgerald (d. 1980) to Michael Gorman. The letter was written from Susan&#39;s home and she mentions minding some of family&#39;s children, a cold she picked up in Dublin, a photograph he had sent, the weather and a plan to meet with Michael. She also refers to an exam in London that Michael was unable to travel to.Michael Gorman was one a large Catholic family living at a farm in Ballinalug, County Laois (then Queen&#39;s County). Susan Fitzgerald was one a Church of Ireland family living in Raheenahone House near Stradbally, County Laois, also in the Slieve Bloom mountains. At the time the letter was written they were involved in a courtship but owing to the religious difference the love affair had to be kept secret. Eventually both were in Dublin: he in the Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin (where he eventually became Professor of Agricultural Botany and Biochemistry) and she as a volunteer nurse in the Royal Hospital in Baggot Street. They eventually went to London to marry.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Michael Gorman</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1283</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1259">Susan Fitzgerald</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1800">Raheenahone House, Stradbally, County Laois</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Michael Gorman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1251">Albert Agricultural College, Glasnevin, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1283_img_489_1"  type="NULL"  url="fdf53e5d070c4fac3eaca98a18d0b7cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1283_img_489_2"  type="NULL"  url="454e11f8fe9f51d5c907a5fe719c3ef8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1283_img_489_3"  type="NULL"  url="1bb36b070289715fa820f2644dc18171.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1283_img_489_4"  type="NULL"  url="465bd06f0ab2ed9b59a2a2a0fcf98418.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1283_img_489_1"/>
              Writing at the top of the page written sideways  I quite forgot to <lb/> bring the pink shoes when coming <lb/> home. Will you please <lb/> let me have them. <lb/>I hope it isnt too much trouble <lb/>Love <lb/>Sue  <hi rend="underline">Sunday</hi>  Beginning of letter    Raheenahone House  Stradbally  Queens Co   My dearest Mickie   I have been <lb/> threatening to write <lb/>to you all last week <lb/>and I made several <lb/>attempts on yesterday <lb/> but didn't succeed. <lb/>Mother &amp; Fannie went <lb/>to Dublin for the day <lb/>&amp; I was asked to <lb/>keep an eye on the  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1283_img_489_2"/>
               write very soon a <hi rend="underline">long letter</hi>  kids, <hi rend="underline">so</hi> I <hi rend="underline">had</hi> a very <lb/>busy time trying to keep <lb/>them out of mischief. <lb/>They are very wild, but <lb/> most delightful, especially <lb/> the boy. We expect <lb/>to have them here another <lb/> week, &amp; I'll be sorry <lb/> when they leave. I <lb/> got a bad cold coming <lb/>home from Dublin, &amp; <lb/> I haven't been outside <lb/> the house since, but my <lb/> throat is nearly all <lb/> right again. <lb/>I was sorry <lb/> to hear you <seg type="del">where</seg> are <lb/>unable to get across <lb/>to London for your exam <lb/>this time. It might be <lb/>just as well, especially <lb/>when you had such <lb/>a short time to work <lb/>for it; and as you say, <lb/>if you go up next year <lb/>you'll have far more <lb/>confidence.  Thanks for the latest <lb/> style in photography <lb/> It's simply too funny! <lb/> M.R. is splendid also <lb/> [So of <seg type="unclear">hits</seg>] aren't we having <lb/> glorious weather. I hope <lb/> June will be as nice,  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1283_img_489_3"/>
              particularly the first <lb/>week-end. I may be <lb/>able to make some <lb/>arrangement to see you <lb/>in Maryboro' &amp; we can <lb/>talk about your holiday <lb/>week-ends etc then. I <lb/>suppose Maryboro' is the <lb/>best place. You see I'll <lb/>have to drive. Im not <lb/>able to walk or cycle <lb/><hi rend="underline">yet</hi>.I'm taking a long <lb/>time to get really well. <lb/>Did you hear from McAuley <lb/>since? I replied to his letter <lb/>at last. Indeed I owe several <lb/><seg type="del">letters</seg> &amp; I'm leading such <lb/>an idle life.It makes me <lb/>quite lazy sitting out most of <lb/>the day reading &amp; darning <lb/>at present I'm making a very pretty <lb/>costume.I hope it isn't a failure <lb/> when finished. Did you get your new suit <seg type="closer"> Heaps of love from  Sue. </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1283_img_489_4"/>
                Mr. J. Gorman Esq.  Albert College  Glasnevin  <hi rend="underline">Dubin</hi>    
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>