<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5798">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from May Fay to James Finn 23 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>May Fay</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancee Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June and the letters were written between them during that period. He lived in Dublin, she lived in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. He tells how he &#34;had his eye on her&#34; for a long time but waited until she was old enough. Throughout the series of letters you can see how their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters and how her confidence grows.
The series is not complete; it is interrupted by visits to each other’s homes and by obviously missing letters. They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child, my father. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him: this explains their survival. Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats, so that she ended up quite comfortable off!
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him, trying to demand he be carried in to meetings. 
Neither May nor James were politically active though, like many in the Civil Service, James was obviously somewhat activated, learning Irish, probably Gaelic League, and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in it. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
James had sent May a copy of  Padraic Pearse&#39;s last letter and she is moved. The letter also  mentions Casement.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5798</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date>1916-05-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0075">Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1976</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5798_img_896_1"  type="Letter"  url="e32674d8c1e1b9edc875c4c4ac2414ed.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5798_img_896_2"  type="Letter"  url="d2844f98071efc19560e852ea23131dc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5798_img_896_1"/>
             <seg type="unclear">Loghinstown</seg><lb/>Ballinea   <hi rend="underline">25 May 1916</hi>    My dearest James,   Many thanks for your letter this morning<lb/>I need not tell you how delighted i was to get copy of<lb/>Pearce's letter. Johnnie had told me you had it &amp; I must<lb/>say I was feeling a little bit jealous you never told me<lb/>about it but it seems you did not think me altogether<lb/>wanting in interest in such things I am sending Jennie<lb/>a copy of it. By an article I saw (on I don't what paper)<lb/>I have great hopes Casement will turn Catholic that would<lb/>be grand I say a special prayer for his conversion always<lb/>we could easily order the car if you wished you<lb/>need not worry about the car for me Mother will see<lb/>about one, but only for the fashion of it I think it is foolish<lb/>to take a car out for Mullingar to bring me up to Loughnasathy.  I have great sympathy with your Mother to have<lb/>the house so long upset Johnnie said there was difficulty<lb/>in getting the paper. You should have got one like me<lb/>I did <sic>cealing</sic> &amp; walls  and left the room pretty square in one<lb/>afternoon the <sic>cealing</sic>turned out beautiful &amp; white but that<lb/>was only a chance if <seg type="unclear">is</seg>was black it was all the same<lb/>I wold only give it the one coat 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5798_img_896_2"/>
             This is a very wet day here I hope we will have a better<lb/>day for our marriage. Mrs.<seg type="unclear">Sweeny</seg>told me to tell your<lb/>Mother she would have written only waiting to have some<lb/>news of Johnnie she (Mrs S) is gone to <seg type="del">pro</seg>reception for<lb/>Bab Lennon today. Good bye now dearest James<lb/> Best love from your loving <lb/> May<lb/><seg type="unclear">GD</seg> <lb/>I forgot to ask you how you came by the copy of Pearce's letter<lb/>I am returning with many many thanks. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>