<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1377">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Mary O'Leary, 3 February 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Mary O&#39;Leary (b. 1894), a dress maker from Kerry, regarding her application to dressmaker in Killarney District Asylum.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/3755/5</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1377</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-02-03</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary O&#39;Leary</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1509">Scartaglen, Farranfore, County Kerry, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1377_img_732_1"  type="Letter"  url="a8a8c3cf72b1c31b60a93d5d50795e70.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1377_img_732_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="7349d7e4c0a66d1b71da57518bbaac1d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1377_img_732_3"  type="NULL"  url="dda55eb1bd896f1e2f76372e0846b9b5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1377_img_732_4"  type="NULL"  url="85f1ee253c4fa9537db02d06d34f9e22.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1377_img_732_1"/>
                3rd February, 1916   252  Madam,   I am directed by the Inspectors to acknowledge <lb/> the receipt of your communication of the 1st instant, <lb/> and to inform you that the appointment of a Dressmaker <lb/> and Nurse in the Killarney District Asylum is vested <lb/> solely in the Committee of Management, to which body <lb/> any representations you may wish to make on the <lb/> subject should be addressed. <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/>Madam, <lb/>Your Obedient Servant,   Miss Mary O'Leary,   Scartaglen   Farranfore,   Co. Kerry  </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1377_img_732_2"/>
              252   Scartaglen,   Farranfore,   Co. Kerry    1/2/'16   Sir,   May I most respectfully call your <lb/> attention to the appointment of <lb/> 'Dressmaker and Nurse', which has been <lb/> carried through at the last meeting <lb/> of Committee of Management, 'Killarney <lb/> District Lunatic Asylum'.  The meeting was held on the 27 Inst <lb/> and out of three applicants one was <lb/> only qualified as regards age; Miss Cremmin <lb/> was therefore duly elected as Seamstress <lb/> for a month pending observations from <lb/> Matron and R.M.S.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1377_img_732_3"/>
              <hi rend="underline">2</hi><lb/>Miss Cremmin had only one testimonial <lb/> accompanying her application, and <lb/> that one was from a local dressmaker <lb/> certifying that Miss Cremmin gave a <lb/> few months apprenticeship, she <lb/> produced no more credentials - May <lb/> I point out, Sir, that the advertisement <lb/> issued for this important position <lb/> was :- 'that the lady elected should <lb/> be able to cut material, sew for the <lb/> female part of the house, possess a <lb/> knowledge of Nursing &amp; <sic>Housewifery</sic>, <lb/> and keep book-accounts, also responsible <lb/> for same when Matron is absent.'  Miss Cremmin, Sir, does not show <lb/> at present <hi rend="underline">any</hi> qualifications what- <lb/>so-ever, and many of the members <lb/> of the Committee visibly expressed  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1377_img_732_4"/>
              <hi rend="underline">3</hi><lb/>the opinion that Miss Cremmins <lb/>was literally unqualified for the <lb/> position and yet she was 'dumped' <lb/> into a job that honestly she <lb/> knows nothing about.  May I also point out Sir, that <lb/> Miss Cremmins mother died in <lb/> the Asylum some time ago, and at <lb/> present her aunt and first cousin <lb/> are there.  The facts are really valid and <lb/> I was one of the applicants fully <lb/> qualified only a fortnight short <lb/> of the age.  Thanking you in anticipation <lb/> for a favourable reply. <seg type="closer"> Signed - Mary O'Leary. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>