<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5534">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman, 18 January 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Fr. Martin Mahoney</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Fr. Martin Mahoney to John Sweetman. Mahoney, a parish priest in Minnesota, edited the Catholic weekly &#39;Manifestos&#39;. Sweetman (1844-1936) was a member of Sinn Féin and patron to Arthur Griffith. In 1915 he spoke out against conscription and was arrested in the aftermath of the 1916 Rising.
The letter refers mainly to political matters in the news and business.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sweetman Collection, Collection List 154; Ms. 47,604/8.</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5534</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0410">Fr. Martin Mahoney</persName>
              <date>1916-01-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1659">Mendota, Minnesota, US</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0883">John Sweetman</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0439">Drumbaragh Estate, Kells, County Meath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5534_img_63_1"  type="Letter"  url="8ea3880aa9ba904064c649989a3b4d99.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5534_img_63_2"  type="Letter"  url="40e74a3a25ae7cb804450557960470a9.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5534_img_63_3"  type="Envelope"  url="ea8cd08382f86a9cdbaeabc8902703ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5534_img_63_4"  type="Letter"  url="df35e701c2a776fd74bac0518f6b75cb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5534_img_63_1"/>
             Mendota Minn   1.18.16    Dear Mr Sweetman:  Upturns here an<lb/>envelope addressed to you with some cuttings<lb/>cut, I <seg type="unclear">want</seg> to <seg type="del">deleted text</seg> let you see how<lb/>this side learns about your side. I'll<lb/>stick this in it &amp; let it off to you. First<lb/>I want to let you know how tickled<lb/>was my self-conceit when reading last<lb/>night the last to hand Leader, where as<lb/>I thought Moran, &amp; says only in other words<lb/>let us have initiative <seg type="unclear">etc.</seg> what <hi rend="underline">I</hi> have<lb/>repeatedly said to you, til it can be<lb/>ended, let go on the <sic>Govt's</sic> &amp; Plunkett's<lb/>&amp; all the others tomfooling, and do<lb/>the the right thing without them, 2 or 3<lb/>or more gather together, I may without<lb/>irreverance say in God's name, and<lb/>act as if educated &amp; governmented in<lb/>Hungary, stocking rivers, testing<lb/>seed, buying in sufficient quantity<lb/>wrappers for butter, &amp; so on &amp; on. Confound<lb/>it, cannot any man with an idea<lb/>or 2, and - what no rightly sober man    Todays dispatch says that at a <seg type="unclear">S D R</seg> James meeting tomorrow the main <sic>addressance</sic> be by<lb/>Plunkett. He's likely on another junket across the continent at public expense.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5534_img_63_2"/>
             can lack, a 1/2 crown to hire <seg type="del">deleted text</seg><lb/>a typewriters' time &amp; carbon sheets for<lb/>an hour, get his thought &amp; proposal<lb/>before a score of the most likeminded<lb/>neighbors or contemporaries? <hi rend="underline"><seg type="foreign">Vivida vis<lb/>animi! Veritas prevalebit!</seg></hi>  That priest whose howls    the Doyle book   so tickled Moran,<lb/>has taken 3 or 4 issues of the L. and maybe on<lb/>all 3 pages to say with Irish generosity<lb/>of word-flux and hullaballooing<lb/>what I believe will effect no more than<lb/>even <hi rend="underline">I</hi> could with one Leader column in<lb/>which to condense &amp; put before all the<lb/>people the boiled-down offensiveness of<lb/>the wretched work. But with true<lb/>constructive genius I should keep enough<lb/>of my column free to name &amp; boast the<lb/>book that ought to replace Doyle's, that<lb/>is Cobbett's Advice to Young Men. By the way<lb/>only this afternoon a young woman who while<lb/>staying with me here this Summer, had read the<lb/>book, almost began, &amp; certainly wound up her<lb/>call, by requesting me to get her Cobbett's Grammer.<lb/>How often have you seen the Advice, or even the Mentor<lb/><seg type="unclear">yet?</seg>  Regards to Mrs S.<lb/> Yours very Sincerely <lb/>Martin Mahoney. 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5534_img_63_3"/>
             Mr John Sweetman<lb/>Kells,<lb/>Ireland<lb/> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_5534_img_63_4"/>
            Censor <lb/>586.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>