<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4221">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edmund Blayney Clarke to Augustine Birrell, 29 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edmund Blayney Clarke</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edmund Blayney Clarke following up on his previous correspondence regarding his recommendation as an architect to rebuild Dublin after the damage done during Easter week 1916. He encloses a letter of recommendation from Sir William Emerson (3 December 1843 – 26 December 1924), a British architect, who remained President of the Royal Institute of British Architects (RIBA), 1899 to 1902, and worked extensively in India.

Birrell served as the chief secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish education system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares and, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred. Birrell offered his resignation on 1 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/9228</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4221</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0008">Edmund Blayney Clarke</persName>
              <date>1916-05-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0548">England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4221_img_3591_1"  type="Letter"  url="4fd3035dfad12a1634116fa085b68f6c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4221_img_3591_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="757f048a011f4625e7a84ffcd3b022df.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4221_img_3591_1"/>
              CHIEF SECRETARY'S<lb/>9228 - 31. MAY. 1916<lb/>OFFICE    May 29th 1916     To The Right Honble Earl Wainborne K.G. etc.<lb/>Viceroy of Ireland.<lb/>Vice-Regal. Lodge. Dublin     Your Excellency, <lb/>I trust Your Excellency will pardon me<lb/>writing again. Some few days ago I ventured to write<lb/>and ask Your Excellency to favour me with the<lb/>opportunity of submitting designs and estimates for some<lb/>of the new buildings in Dublin. At the same time<lb/>I wrote to Sir William Emerson for a recent letter of<lb/>recommendation to Your Excellency, and I have the honor<lb/>to enclose a copy of the letter which arrived to-day.   I have the honor to remain:    Your Excellency's Obedient Servant    E<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Blayney Clarke     
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4221_img_3591_2"/>
              Carlton Chambers <lb/> 4 Regent Street. W.    May 27th 1916   This is to state that I consider Mr. Edmon<lb/>B. Clarke is a quite competent man to<lb/>design and to carry out any buildings<lb/>that may be required of him.<lb/>I have known him for many years.   (signed)  <hi rend="underline"> <hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">W</hi></hi><hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline">m</hi></hi></hi><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="underline"> Emerson</hi></hi> </hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>