<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0861">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender to his wife Lady Lillian Spender, 23 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Bliss Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Wilfrid Bliss Spender (1876-1960) to his wife, lady Lillian Spender (1880-1968). In this letter, Spender states that he is getting &#39;a little tired&#39; of sending Christmas wishes, mentions the visit a comrade, Richardson, and suggests that one possible plan for his (Spender&#39;s) upcoming leave could be for himself and Lillian to go to a house in Wiltshire owned by his brother Rex. Spender refers to a speech by David Lloyd George (1863-1945), the then Minister for Munitions, in which he suggested that the war could continue for another year, or more. Spender urges Lillian not to tire herself out writing letters to him, and gives news of the progress of the fighting.Sir Wilfrid Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Lady Spender&#39;s Correspondence, D1633/1/1/118</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/861</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0931">Wilfrid Bliss Spender</persName>
              <date>1915-12-23</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0861_img_2420_1"  type="Letter"  url="84d9521b0debbe4b59b87cfec96b1fd2.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0861_img_2420_2"  type="Letter"  url="5f5e0d08a120244c2d9da9d86563bdec.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0861_img_2420_1"/>
                23 Dec 15   My pr   I believe this is really my Xmas letter but I am getting<lb/> a little tired of sending Xmas greetings even to a pr when I know<lb/> she now takes them — &amp; a lot of other things too — quite for granted.<lb/> However I'll wish her one more wish which I know, &amp; hope it<lb/> may come true.  Richardson is off &amp; I am sorry that as he will only be<lb/> one day in town he will not be able to look you up, tho' he took<lb/> your <seg type="del">tel</seg> N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> in case there may be a chance later. I think<lb/> his wife who lives at 18 Park Avenue <seg type="unclear">Bidford</seg> &amp; who often comes<lb/> up to town (!) would <seg type="del">probably</seg> be glad to see you, but probably<lb/> not till after he returns.  I wonder if Rex's old place in the New Forest would<lb/> do for us. I'm not quite sure of the address but think it<lb/> was <seg type="unclear">Mrs</seg> Olding. Olding's farm Redlynch near Downton<lb/> Wiltshire. It is a delightful part of the country &amp; a comfortable <lb/> farm. It might be worth writing (?) &amp; if you do so don't<lb/> forget to enquire the best means of getting there. I'm afraid I am<lb/> giving a tired little pr a great deal to do &amp; to decide, but as<lb/> she knows the will not mind what she does with him, as<lb/> long as she ......, she need not worry about troubling<lb/> unduly in making up her mind.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0861_img_2420_2"/>
              I see that Lloyd George's speech<lb/> makes it quite plain that he<lb/> does not expect the war to finish in less that 1 year &amp; that<lb/> Redmond is beginning to show his teeth more in the open. I retract<lb/> anything I have said about his possibly being an honest patriot.  Squiffy will try to put things off again on hearing his master's voice<lb/> but I have some faint hope that this may prove too much for L G <lb/> &amp; that the former may have to go but I'm afraid this is too<lb/> good to be true &amp; there is always <seg type="del">the</seg> his  £9000 or £10000 to think<lb/> of. If I were a millionaire I think I would pension him off<lb/> for the sake of the country tho' few men ( or women ) deserve it<lb/> less.  I don't like your being so tired now writing me letters, I<lb/> quite understand about the times. All I mean to say is that<lb/> if you have anything urgent for the post it is best to post it<lb/> a good deal earlier in the afternoon is possible but I don't want<lb/> you to worry about the letters for me any more than you<lb/> want me to do for you.  The place I was at in the trenches was heavily shelled just<lb/> after I left ( ? my motor) but no one was hurt &amp; the village itself<lb/> was past hurting. News of a big French victory ( at any rate <lb/> it sounds like a bit victory with 1200 prisoners ) has just come in.<lb/> It is very necessary that the French should get encouragement just now  My dear love to the family &amp; best Xmas wishes!! <seg type="closer"> Your bw  WB Spender </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>