<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0424">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Waters to John Francis Hogan, 2 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Waters</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from John Waters to John Francis Hogan (1858–1918). In this letter Rev Waters (b. 1871) is asking Hogan for information about the programme of examination for a bachelor of arts degree in Theology at Maynooth so his students can prepare themselves properly. John Francis Hogan was a priest, author, and president of St Patrick&#39;s College, Maynooth. During the Easter Rising a group of Volunteers from the town of Maynooth entered the college to seek a blessing before setting off for Dublin. Hogan reputedly refused to give his blessing to their ‘foolish and most ill-advised expedition’ and urged them to return home. They in turn refused; responding to their spiritual needs, he blessed them, while remaining totally opposed to their activities. He subsequently addressed the students on the need to show proper respect for authority.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>St Patrick&#39;s College, Maynooth</repository>
                  <collection>John F. Hogan Papers, 21/12/35</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/424</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1228">John Waters</persName>
              <date>1916-07-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0927">Holy Cross College, Clonliffe, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Francis Hogan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Faith</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0424_img_1738_1"  type="Letter"  url="a60aeecb74ce993ace9096ae445b8179.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0424_img_1738_2"  type="Letter"  url="07f44d1db5f348c8c1f832cc05763cdc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0424_img_1738_1"/>
              12/35    Holy Cross College,  Clonliffe,  Dublin   July <hi rend="underline">2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> 16 </hi> My Dear Monsignor Hogan,   Some of our students <lb/>who are going down to Maynooth <lb/>next year would naturally join <lb/>your <hi rend="underline">Ba class 2</hi>nd year, as <lb/>they have already done the Ba <lb/>course 1st year (corresponding to the <lb/>old 2 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Arts) at University College.   There is no programme publish- <lb/>ed of Subjects for Examination <lb/>for <lb/>this class in Maynooth â as far  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0424_img_1738_2"/>
              I know. In the ' <seg type="foreign">Ordo</seg>,' there is the <lb/>programme of Examination for <lb/>admission into Ba degree class <lb/><hi rend="underline">First</hi> year, and into <hi rend="underline">First years <lb/>Theology </hi>, but none for admission <lb/>into the class between these two, i.e., <lb/>into <hi rend="underline">Ba degree class second year.</hi><lb/>There is no <seg type="unclear">bad</seg> to candidates <lb/>coming to Maynooth for this class.   I should feel very grateful if you <lb/>would send me information about <lb/>the programme, as our students <lb/>would like to prepare themselves <lb/>for the Examination. If you kindly send <lb/>me the details I will communicate <lb/>these to students.  <seg type="closer">  Kindest Regards <lb/>Yours Sincerely  <lb/> <hi rend="underline">John Waters</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>