<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5314">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from John Earls to Mrs. Forth 18 March, 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Earls</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Forwards a letter from the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland. T. P. Gill, on behalf of the  Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland, asks that his deepest sympathies be extended to Captains Forth&#39;s family. 

</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Belfast College of Technology, BCT/8/2/43</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5314</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0494">John Earls</persName>
              <date>1919-03-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1370">Municipal  Technical Institute, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mrs. Forth</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2002">Ravenswood, Knockbreda Park, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5314_img_None_1"  url="48da882835bf03b36f7fae8b1f0a3271.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5314_img_None_2"  url="149c23723eb09ed63494ea743fcaaa94.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5314_img_0_1"/>
              18th March 1919    Mrs Forth,<lb/>Ravenswood<lb/>Knockbreda Park<lb/>BELFAST    Dear Mrs. Forth,   I am enclosing you herewith copy of a letter which has<lb/>been received from the Department of Agriculture and Technical<lb/>Instruction for Ireland.  As I said in acknowledging receipt of the letter, I<lb/>think that the request contained in the concluding lines could<lb/>not be complied with in a more appropriate manner than by send<lb/>ing you a copy of the complete letter.  Besides conveying a message of sympathy to you and<lb/>your family, it is the official expression to the Committee of<lb/>the Department's appreciation of Captain Forth's great work and<lb/>of their deep regret at his death   I am,<lb/>Yours faithfully   A.O.N. 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5314_img_0_2"/>
              DEPARTMENT of AGRICULTURE and TECHNICAL<lb/>INSTRUCTION for IRELAND<lb/>Upper Merrion Street<lb/>DUBLIN    18th March 1919   No. T 2720-19   Sir   I have to acknowledge the receipt of your letter<lb/>of the 3rd instant, announcing the death on the evening<lb/>of the 28th Ultim, of Captain F. G. Forth., F.R.C.Sc. I<lb/>Principal of the Municipal Technical Institute and Sec<lb/>retary to the County Borough of Belfast Technical<lb/>Instruction Committee. It is with deep regret that<lb/>the Department have received this intelligence.  Captain Forth's wide knowledge and experience as<lb/>an educationist were very valuable assets to those respons<lb/>ible for the work of developing techical instruction in<lb/>Belfast, and being devoted as they were to the advancement<lb/>of technical instruction not in Belfast only but throughout<lb/>the country, his death represents a very serious loss to the<lb/>cause of technical education in Ireland. The Department<lb/>desire to associate themselves most sincerely with the<lb/>Technical Instruction Committee of Belfast in regretting<lb/>the death of so valuable an officer, and they would ask<lb/>that you will be good enough to convey to his relatives an<lb/>expression of their deep sympathy.   I am<lb/>Sir<lb/>Your obediant Servant<lb/>(Sgt) T P GILL<lb/>Secretary    J. Earls Esq<lb/>Acting Vice Principal<lb/>Municipal Technical Institute<lb/>Belfast  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>