<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4632">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the Librarian, R.C.P.I. to T. Cowley Stephen, 13 November 1918</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Librarian, R.C.P.I.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-2-14-56</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4632</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0384">Librarian, R.C.P.I.</persName>
              <date>1918-11-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1334">Royal College of Physicians of Ireland, 6 Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">T. Cowley Stephen</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0722">Manchester, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4632_img_3972_1"  type="Letter"  url="d6033a88e9c9e9ba390b63f54058a1dc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4632_img_3972_1"/>
             6 KILDARE Street,   13th November 18   Dr. T. Cowley Stephen, <lb/>Withington, <lb/>Manchester.   Dear Sir,   In reply to you letter of the 10th inst., I send you <lb/>herewith a copy of the Regulations and forms of application. <lb/>In case of urgency the President might grant you special <lb/>examination during the first week in December but for such <lb/>examination you should forward to the Registrar you application <lb/>and papers required by the By-Laws early next week. I <lb/>have forwarded the Regulations &amp;c., to you brother at the <lb/>address you give and trust that they will reach him safely.   I <sic>inclose</sic> the stamps you sent for the telegram.   Yours faithfully,  <lb/>Librarian, R.C.P.I.
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>