<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1135">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Robert Young to Edward Carson, 9 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Robert Young</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Robert Young (1856-1933) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use &#39;all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin.&#39; Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. Young, linen merchant, politician and philanthropist, was a prominent Unionist.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1135</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1100">William Robert Young</persName>
              <date>1916-07-09</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1656">Galgorm Castle, Ballymena, Co. Armagh, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1135_img_3706_1"  type="Letter"  url="28e4fcffb80b9805cb10f721b5d18790.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1135_img_3706_2"  type="Letter"  url="e403a1a2d6afebb6cd581974c9d86c5c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1135_img_3706_1"/>
                GALGORM CASTLE,  BALLYMENA.    July 9. 1916   Dear Sir Edward,   You know Conor Scott of <lb/>Omagh — old man with a skull cap <lb/>who attended so many of our Unionist <lb/>Council Meetings. I have had a long <lb/>correspondence with him on the <lb/>proposed 'settlement' — You will I <lb/>think be amused with the closing <lb/>sentence of his last letter <seg type="unclear">very</seg><lb/>'Oh what a blessed thing it was that <lb/>the apprentice Boys of Derry did <lb/>not consult a lawyer before they <lb/>closed the city gates with the cry <lb/>then first <seg type="unclear">roused</seg> of <hi rend="underline">'no surrender'</hi>  The humour of it I think will appeal <lb/>to you — and Lady Carson — <lb/>Remember he is a staunch Unionist <lb/>and supporter of yours, but can — <lb/>not swallow the settlement —   I hope you are getting through  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1135_img_3706_2"/>
              your present arduous work <lb/>successfully —   What a glorious name the Ulster <lb/>Division has made for the Province. <lb/>What terrible losses among our <lb/>friends — Poor Harry Macnaughten, <lb/>under 21, and the fourth holder <lb/>of the <seg type="unclear">Batoronetcy</seg> dead inside <lb/>5 years.  <seg type="closer"> Yours sincerely <lb/>Willie R. Young  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>