<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2622">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Duffin to Maria Duffin, 29 December 2015</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Emma Duffin (1883-1979) to her mother Maria (1854-1954) detailing how Emma spent Christmas with the men on her ward. Emma also writes about a nephew of Sir Edward Carson who she finds common yet he is hailed as a gentlemen among the English. 

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who was a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Family Papers, D2109/9/4/C/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2622</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1134">Emma Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-12-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1586">15th General Hospital, Alexandria, Egypt</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2622_img_2048_1"  type="Letter"  url="0ef8c0a3212fc5e4cc7694953970b729.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2622_img_2048_2"  type="Letter"  url="97cd0d37ade2d3f02246d0f48fe5fbd1.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2622_img_2048_1"/>
             15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Gen. Hosp. Alex.   Dec. 29/15.   My dearest Mamma   Your letter of the 15<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> &amp; Helen's have just <lb/> arrived! I am writing this in bed as usual in a hurry <lb/>before settling down. Celine Russell went off today &amp; <lb/>Matron let me go down to see her on board. Poor thing I <lb/> feel so sorry for her, &amp; will miss her very much.   I am still in my tents, but hear there are to be some changes <lb/> soon so may get moved. We had a very strenuous Xmas <lb/> day, amusing patients all day &amp; at an orderlies' concert in <lb/> the evening. I wrote to Ruth yesterday &amp; told her I think <lb/> all my news, but your letter must be answered, you are so <lb/> good about writing. We had a wet Xmas day, rather <lb/> unfortunate in a country where it so seldom rains! The poor <lb/> men look so wretched holding up their petticoats &amp; wrapping <lb/> newspapers around their Tarbouche to keep the red from running. <lb/> The Col. &amp; M.Os gave us tea in the mess on Xmas day, and <lb/> the manager of the hotel here gave us a Xmas tree with a present <lb/> for each of us which I think was noble, and had an orchestra <lb/> to play as well during the dinner. When the plum puddings <lb/> came in the lights were put out &amp; it was funny to see the <lb/> servants tearing in each rushing to his table to get the pudding <lb/> there while it was still lit, unfortunately they had mixed a <lb/>little methylated spirits with the brandy with great effect as
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2622_img_2048_2"/>
            <hi rend="underline">2</hi> <lb/>regards the flames but not improving to the flavour. <lb/> We had strawberries, think of it, very few &amp; very small still <lb/> strawberries! Molly &amp; John Carson asked me <lb/>to spend Xmas there but that was out of the question, they <lb/> gave me a pair of silk stockings. Talking of <lb/> Carsons I am not in the least surprised to hear Capt. <lb/> Carson's people are  , he is quite a common man, <lb/> though amongst the English people here I have no doubt is <lb/> consideded a gentleman, I never believed he was a nephew <lb/> of Sir Edward's, I was told he was, &amp; asked him &amp; he said <lb/> yes, but you can take nothing he says seriously, he would <lb/> tell you the next day he had never heard of him. I am <lb/> amused at your enquiries. I am sure you were afraid <lb/> I was interested in him, if you saw him you would not be <lb/> alarmed, he is a typical common North of Ireland <lb/> man very amusing, &amp; they say very clever, but I would doubt <lb/> that. He asked me to go to tea with him &amp; I refused and <lb/> at present he is sulky &amp; Won't speak to me, I tell you <lb/> all this because I can read between the lines that you are <lb/> alarmed, things written in letters often give a wrong <lb/> impression and after Dorothy's affair I suppose you are in the <lb/> <seg type="foreign">qui vive</seg>. By the way I am sure you are worried about <lb/> her. I am afraid it does not sound very promising.   It is awfully good of you to send me a blouse dearest it will be <lb/> most useful. By the way I have spent all the money you sent 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>