<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5166">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to Elizabeth Tyrrell 13, October</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>William Upton Tyrrell is staying in a large dugout with papered walls. He expresses gratitude for a book and a magazine he received and requests coffee.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5166</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1917-10-13</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0769">France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Elizabeth Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5166_img_None_1"  url="0c01d5d50d8bcfb6f4b39186ab2e18cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5166_img_None_2"  url="f19f222efb5cc2aab1c32a20d758c8a8.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5166_img_0_1"/>
              13 October 17    My dear Mamy   No news but just a line as<lb/>usual. We are out of the front<lb/>trenches and are now a long way<lb/>back though still living in a big<lb/>deep dug out. We have got our<lb/>valises up so are very comfortable<lb/>indeed. I did not get the apples yet<lb/>but expect them and the parcel<lb/>Minnie mentioned today. This is<lb/>the time for parcels. Where we are<lb/>now the best things to put in parcels<lb/>are cakes and sweets. There is a<lb/>canteen in a big town just behind<lb/>and we can send down there<lb/>every day for stuff. We get fish<lb/>fresh vegetable and almost any<lb/>tinned stuff we want but no<lb/>cakes or toffee. A tin of lobster is 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5166_img_0_2"/>
             also a very good thing and<lb/>that chicken &amp; ham or tongue.<lb/>When I say we get tinned things<lb/>I mean fruit etc. Not  danties <lb/>like chicken. Also I like cafe'au<lb/>lait very much. I always make<lb/>it for myself on a Tommy cooker.<lb/>The walls of this dug out are<lb/> covered  with pictures out of all the<lb/>Illustrated papers and is quite<lb/> showy.   No news at all<lb/>I will write to Hunter very soon<lb/>The weather is alternately very<lb/>wet and then very fine.  Thanks very much for the book<lb/>and magazine. Just what I did<lb/>want badly.   Best love from<lb/>your most affec Son<lb/>Willie.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>