<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1501">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Philip J. McArdle to John Dillon, 21 May 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Philip J. McArdle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Philip J. McArdle to John Dillon (1851-1927). The writer delivers an account of a conversation he had on board a boat in Greenore, Co. Louth, with a soldier from the Royal Irish Rifles. The soldier recognised Francis Sheehy-Skeffington in a front page picture of the newspaper which Mr. McArdle had been given and this gave rise to the conversation. It emerged that the soldier had been part of the firing squad at Portobello Barracks which executed Sheehy-Skeffington and two others. He described the shooting of Sheehy-Skeffington, saying that he was shot as he lay on the ground. He named the officer in charge as Adjutant Morgan and said that all of the firing party were from Victoria Barracks.John Dillon was an Irish Party MP in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down &#39;with so much blood and so much savagery&#39;, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to her husband&#39;s murder and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>TCD Ms. 6837/22a, TCD Ms. 6837/22a</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1501</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0001">Philip J. McArdle</persName>
              <date>1916-05-21</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0044">12 Harberton Road, Highgate, London W., England.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1501_img_959_1"  type="Letter"  url="7e06a1b92b5d75792ce1030d245d6bdd.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1501_img_959_2"  type="Letter"  url="b2f7dba5da32d44c6c9a313d19fcc834.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1501_img_959_3"  type="Letter"  url="fc4c3cacc268c155ef97afc85e9e0276.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1501_img_959_4"  type="Letter"  url="c6e34b05160fad2ec331467ccdd6b9cb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1501_img_959_1"/>
                12 Harberton Road  Highgate  London W.    21st May 1916   Dear Mr. Dillon   I am in receipt of your <lb/>letter of the 18th May &amp; as you wish <lb/> to have details of this conversation, <lb/> I shall endeavour to put it on paper <lb/>as best I can.  I was sitting in the <lb/>cabin of the Greenore boat where there <lb/> was a good number of Soldiers &amp; some <lb/> one near handed me the 'Sketch' of the <lb/> day to have a look at it. As I was <lb/> about to open it, I noticed on the front <lb/>page a photo of Mr Sheehy-Skeffington, <lb/> evidently addressing a gathering. <lb/>Whilst looking at it , a soldier on my <lb/> left bent over in some surprise, &amp; <lb/> said 'Hello, I saw that fellow; he was <lb/> shot along with three others in <lb/>Portobello barracks'! I said, is that so? <lb/>'Oh yes, I was one of the firing party &amp;  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1501_img_959_2"/>
              <lb/>a devil of a job we had with them', he <lb/>answered. ' We placed them along <lb/>some brick walls &amp; shot them, one <lb/> after another, at breakfast time.' <lb/>There were eight of us in the <lb/>firing party.  That fellow there' (pointing <lb/> to the picture of Sheehy-Skeffington) when <lb/> he heard the first discharges, fell <lb/> insensible &amp; when it came his turn <lb/> we tried to stand him; but it was <lb/> no use, so we had to shoot him on <lb/> the ground.'  He then went on to say, that <lb/> he deserved to be shot, although in his <lb/>opinion he got no trial &amp; he seemed <lb/> to think too that the officer '<hi rend="underline">would <lb/>get into a row over it.</hi> I said I thought <lb/> the officer was not an Englishman. <lb/> As no, he answered, I know him well, he <lb/>belongs to near Newtownards, - it <lb/>was Adjutant Morgan. We were all <lb/> Belfast men who shot them - all <lb/>from the Victoria Barracks'!  I was rather nervous about <lb/>questioning him too sharply &amp; went <lb/> cautiously. I got <seg type="unclear">news</seg>, however that Mr  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1501_img_959_3"/>
              <lb/>Sheehy-Skeffington would eat nothing <lb/> after being taken. This the soldier <lb/> put down as a fear of his being <lb/> poisoned &amp; appeared never to have <lb/> heard of a hunger-strike. Several <lb/>of his remarks were very strange <lb/> &amp; made his story appear extremely <lb/> likely. He appeared to be puzzled, <lb/>for instance, that the bullets <lb/> passed through the bodies of the <lb/> victims, &amp; smashed the bricks <lb/> behind.  This soldiers name was <lb/> Morrison, as I learned from some of his <lb/>comrades remarks; he was going to <lb/> Grantham from the Victoria Barracks, <lb/> Belfast &amp; belonged to the Royal Irish <lb/> Rifles. Looking up the Army list <lb/>on reaching here I found that a Lieut. <lb/>Morgan was attached to the 3rd Batt. <lb/> Royal Irish Rifles  Such is a brief account of the <lb/>affair &amp; I regret that I could not <lb/> see you personally as I think it would <lb/> be more satisfactory  You have information, no <lb/> doubt, which will enable you to set a  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1501_img_959_4"/>
              <lb/>proper value on the story; to me, <lb/> of course, it is simply mysterious <lb/>I shall be thankful though <lb/> to have your opinion of it &amp; shall <lb/>be glad, at any time, to give you <lb/> further details. <seg type="closer"> I am <lb/>Yours truly  <hi rend="underline">Phil. J. McArdle</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>