<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0018">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Cis M. Coyle to James Ryan, 11 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Cis M. Coyle</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Cis M Coyle to James Ryan (1891-1970) on 11 July 1916. This letter was written while Ryan was a prisoner in Frongach in Wales. She refers mainly to mutual friends at home and fellow prisoners of Ryan&#39;s.James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Dr James Ryan Papers, P88/27(6)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/18</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0736">Cis M. Coyle</persName>
              <date>1916-07-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0473">58 Aughrim Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0981">Frongach, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0018_img_1047_1"  type="Letter"  url="a2e37863afc22c3fd576d30bf27cb971.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0018_img_1047_2"  type="Letter"  url="c8a0c7c11fbd4cc6cb24a2e3a09a98f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0018_img_1047_3"  type="Letter"  url="1db7d91d039fca4b3b658e02eae7f856.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0018_img_1047_4"  type="Letter"  url="eed18d0e46aa94128d2dbd57b0f88c3d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0018_img_1047_1"/>
                58 Aughrim St    July 11th. 1916   Tuesday  My dear Jim   I hope you are <lb/> very well and that <lb/> you like the change <lb/> to Camps. Did you <lb/> see the Councillor at <lb/> all since he went <lb/> to Frongoch? I suppose  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0018_img_1047_2"/>
              <lb/>there are a great <lb/> number of you in Camp. <lb/> Are you all to-gether?  Liam has not written <lb/> to me since he went <lb/> to Wales. I hope he is <lb/> not ill. Kathleen <lb/> Morrin is with me <lb/> to-day. She came up <lb/> to see a Dr with her <lb/> arm. She got a bad  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0018_img_1047_3"/>
              <lb/>fall off her bicycle <lb/> She says to tell you <lb/> she is sorry you are <lb/>not here to cure <lb/> it for her. All friends <lb/> wish to be remembered <lb/> to you. How is <lb/>Michael Kelly? Tell <lb/>him I was enquiring <lb/>for him and also <lb/>tell all my other <lb/>friends in exile.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0018_img_1047_4"/>
              I believe a lot of the <lb/> Irish prisoners have <lb/> been tried, have you <lb/>been before the Advisory <lb/>Committee yet? Is there <lb/>any chance of your <lb/>getting home soon <lb/> I wonder. Good bye <lb/>for the present with <lb/>kindest regards from <lb/>all. <seg type="closer"> Very Sincerely Yours  Cis M Coyle </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>