<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5715">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 4 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Finn</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. He lived in Dublin, she in Westmeath; he was 20 years older than her at 39 and had become acquainted with her during his regular visits to his relative Mrs Mary Seery, her neighbour. Throughout the series their relationship develops from the first somewhat tentative letters.
They were not to be married long: in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him.
Despite many offers and her difficult finances she never married again. She took in lodgers and trained (and practised) as a midwife, chiropodist, and public health nurse while raising her children. She proved to be an excellent entrepreneur, charmed bank managers into giving her loans (against the norm of the time) and bought properties one after another, many of which were broken up into flats.
James Finn was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him.
Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, James learned Irish and as can be read in the letters after Easter, he knew many who more caught up in the Easter Rising. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.
James is concerned not having had a letter for a few days. There is big concern in the civil service as the British Governement plan increasing daily work hours from 7 to 8 hours.  James works much longer hours anyway though he starts work quite late, seems to have a bit of a free hand! Speaks of the &#34;affair&#34; in Tullamore involving the Volunteers.  he claims to have insider information.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5715</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0500">James Finn</persName>
              <date>1916-04-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1063">Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0367">May Fay</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1114">Togherstown, Ballinea, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5715_img_817_1"  type="Letter"  url="aa24cc47fa4c5ecd957b7b8ef1a95e41.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5715_img_817_2"  type="Letter"  url="191a3e199a8ab308289e6892996f1d4d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5715_img_817_3"  type="Letter"  url="39bcc73a6ee21522882b8513f83aec9f.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5715_img_817_1"/>
             4 April, 1916.   My dearest May,   I was <hi rend="underline">awfully</hi> disappointed<lb/>today at not getting a line from you and<lb/>now I am inclined to be alarmed for fear<lb/>you are knocked up or anything of that sort.<lb/>I hope that is not the case and that I may<lb/>have a line from my dearest girl tomorrow<lb/>to say that she is all right. Will you<lb/><hi rend="underline">please</hi> write me a line by return if<lb/>you haven’t already done so to say if there<lb/>is anything up.  I have no news at all to-day.<lb/>There is some considerable excitement and talk 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5715_img_817_2"/>
             in the office today (and I suppose in all<lb/>Dublin Government offices) over an increase in<lb/>the daily attendance of the clerical staff in<lb/>all Government Departments from 7 to 8 hours.<lb/>It doesn’t affect me personally very much because<lb/>I have never been able since I came here<lb/>to get away at the normal hour of departure<lb/>(4:45 pm) but while I have done that<lb/>voluntarily all right, I don’t feel obliged to<lb/>the authorities (the British Government in this<lb/>case) for increasing my attendance compulsorily<lb/>by an extra hour. I don’t however intend<lb/>to come in any earlier in the morning than<lb/>I do at present and as you know that is   not very early. So they can take it or leave it<lb/>at that. In the case of the rank and file<lb/>however it is a real hardship and I expect<lb/>there will be a good deal of soreness, but their<lb/>resentment or protests are not in any case<lb/>likely to do them any good, because the great<lb/>British Public whom they would have to appeal<lb/>to (the Irish Public don’t count in these days of<lb/>small nationalities) think that all Civil Servants<lb/>have nothing to do and are paid handsomely<lb/>for doing it.  I have no other news. In connection<lb/>with the Tullamore affair I hear that the<lb/>local recruiting sergeant organised the mob that<lb/>assaulted the Volunteers and paid a lot<lb/>of them half a crown apiece for the job.<lb/>This is from the horse’s mouth and will be    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5715_img_817_3"/>
            proved up to the hilt at the inquiry. <lb/>Regards to all and warmest love and <lb/>kisses to my dear girl   Your loving   <hi rend="underline">James</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>