<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1754">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Stewart Collis to John Gordon, 28 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Stewart Collis</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by William Stewart Collis (1860-1947) a solicitor from the firm Collis &amp; Ward. The letter is addressed to Attorney General John Gordon (1849-1922). Gordon had been appointed attorney general in 1915 but vacated the position a year later. His successor, James Campbell (1851-1931), took over on Monday 24 April, the first day of the Easter Rising.
The letter contains Collis&#39; bid to apply for the position of chief crown solicitor following the death of Malachy Kelly (1851-1916). With this letter Collis has included thirteen testimonials from 1889 when he was applying for the position of solicitor to the Irish Land Commission.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/5728/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1754</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1055">William Stewart Collis</persName>
              <date>1916-03-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">John Gordon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_1"  type="Letter"  url="da6d470b0edb0eaeae30fb80fa19e381.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="37196234575e67a679d79ee01a641717.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="b19d9d595d2b5db9fa924a83e4ca5058.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="755d07aa6f4da3e7f8f6f3072c54fad8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_5"  type="Enclosure"  url="53912eb35fe8b61d65dfe7d36d7b6a05.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_6"  type="Enclosure"  url="98691a40f1e5bae00b04aa5ff7f2d5c7.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_7"  type="Letter"  url="19e325f0377f7c3227d6a4e076063d47.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_8"  type="Enclosure"  url="4bad11264dc2e0def00ae1848de2df1d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_9"  type="Enclosure"  url="7926fa94d70eb38ecb5e6d664774cc02.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_10"  type="Enclosure"  url="9a94c82f9d82f70d6ba91ef50dbc6229.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_11"  type="Enclosure"  url="1d1e7a7178e5ffd77498ef81c45ad312.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_12"  type="Enclosure"  url="d914fcccd4fa6749aa888cdae1bf5e23.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_13"  type="Enclosure"  url="1638ee9c5e975da3954da825c9636944.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1754_img_1210_14"  type="Enclosure"  url="5c62f8f18afc9c7dd47094aa219859fd.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_1"/>
             13, Clare Street,<lb/>Dublin,   28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> March 1916 <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr Attorney General,   I beg to apply for<lb/>the appointment of Chief Crown<lb/>Solicitor for Ireland which has<lb/>become vacant by the death of<lb/>Sir Malachy Kelly.  I enclose a few of<lb/>the testimonials I received<lb/>in 1889, when I was applying<lb/>for the position of Solicitor<lb/>to the Irish Law Commission.  Since that, 26 years ago, I<lb/>have had a large practice<lb/>in almost every branch of<lb/>the profession.  I am a Justice of the<lb/>Peace &amp; have some knowledge<lb/>of Criminal Law.   I am<lb/>Yours truly <lb/> WS Collis <lb/><lb/> The Rt Hon.<lb/>The Attorney General<lb/>Dublin Castle.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_2"/>
             From the Right Hon. Mr. Justice Madden, then Attorney<lb/>General for Ireland, M.P<lb/>Law Room,<lb/>Dublin Castle,   October 29, 1899. <lb/><lb/> My Dear Mr. Collins,   I willingly comply with your request that I should<lb/>state your professional ability and character.  I have had many opportunities of observing the manner<lb/>in which you conduct your professional business, and I have<lb/>formed a high opinion of your legal knowledge and capacity.<lb/>I have always found you devote yourself most zealously to the<lb/>interests of your clients.   Yours faithfully, <lb/> D.H Madden       W.Stewart Collins, Esq.  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_3"/>
             20 Hatch Street, Dublin,    31st October , 1889.   I have great pleasure in testifying to my knowledge of Mr.<lb/>Wm. S. Collis, B.A, who is a candidate for the post of Solicitor<lb/>to the Land Commission. He was admitted a Solicitor in 1882,<lb/>after a most distinguished examination, in which he won Gold<lb/>Medal and Findlater Scholarship. Since that date he has been<lb/>in excellent practice and has a considerable experience in nearly every<lb/>branch of his profession. He is able, energetic and prudent, and is<lb/>a gentleman of the highest honour and integrity. I have no doubt<lb/>that if appointed he would give the Land Commission and those<lb/>with whom he had to do business every satisfaction.   T.G. Overend, Q.C  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_4"/>
             From the Solicitor for the Church Representative Body,<lb/>Trinity College, Dublin Metropolitan Police, etc.<lb/>18 Stephens Green, North,<lb/>Dublin,   29th October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> My Dear Collis,   I have very great pleasure indeed in saying that<lb/>I believe your appointment to the office of solicitor to the<lb/>Land Commission would give general satisfaction to the pro-<lb/>fession, and send to the Commissioners an officer whose<lb/>capabilities and knowledge of his business would enable him<lb/>to discharge efficiently the duties of his office, and to the<lb/>public one with whom they could communicate with confidence<lb/>and pleasure.   Believe me,<lb/>Very faithfully yours, <lb/> John Maunsell <lb/><lb/> W.S. Collis, Esq, 3 Westmoreland Street.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_5"/>
             20, Fitzwilliam Square,<lb/>Dublin,   October 30th, <lb/> My Dear Collis,   Having heard that you area a candidate for the vacant<lb/>office of Solicitor to the Irish Land Commission, it gives me<lb/>great pleasure to state my opinion of your fitness for the office.  I have been associated with you professionally in a very<lb/>large number of cases of every nature--many of them of a<lb/>very heavy and responsible character, and have had constant<lb/>opportunities of testing your ability and character as a Solicitor.<lb/>You are one of the few Solicitors whom I know who can<lb/>grapple with heavy business of a complicated nature, and I<lb/>am satisfied that your sound judgement and practical common-<lb/>sense, added to your legal knowledge and high sense of honour,<lb/>make you in every way qualified to fill the responsible position<lb/>of Solicitor to the Irish Land Commission.   Faithfully yours <lb/> Charles L. Matheson. <lb/> W.S. Collis Esq.  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_6"/>
             Ulster Club, Belfast.  I have known Mr W Stewart Collis for several years,<lb/>and have had frequent opportunities of observing the way in<lb/>which he conducts the legal proceedings entrusted to him. In<lb/>my opinion he is possessed of very high attainments and<lb/>qualifications for his profession.  His knowledge is extensive, and he is most painstaking<lb/>and accurate in the management of his cases. I have observed<lb/>that he is invariably guided in his practice by the principals which<lb/>regulate the conduct of a man of honour and a gentleman.   Henry Fitzgibbon.  <lb/> October 29th, 1889.  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_7"/>
             From the Right Hon. Sir Edward Carson, Q.C., M.P.<lb/>80, Merrion Square,<lb/>Dublin,   October 30th, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Collis,   I have much pleasure in bearing testimony to your<lb/>fitness for the appointment of Solicitor to the Land<lb/>Commission.  I have had the opportunity at the profession of judging of<lb/>your ability and zeal, and I cannot speak too highly of your<lb/>qualification.  I wish you every good luck.   Yours truly, <lb/> EDWARD CARSON.  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_8"/>
             Graves C. Colles, of the firm of Meade, Colles and Co.<lb/>31, Kildare Street, Dublin,   30th October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Collis,   In accordance with your request I can confidently<lb/>testify as to your capability and energy in carrying out business<lb/>matters entrusted to you, having had ample opportunity for<lb/>forming such an opinion during the time you served your<lb/>apprenticeship in this office. Your character during the time<lb/>I have had the pleasure of knowing you has always been that<lb/>of an honest upright gentleman.   Yours faithfully.   GRAVES C. COLLES. <lb/><lb/> W.S. Collis, Esq.  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_9"/>
             From Sir. Benjamin Whitney,<lb/>46, Kildare Street Dublin,   29th, October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr. Collis,   I am very glad to learn that you are a candidate<lb/>for the post of Solicitor to the Land Commission. Know-<lb/>ing you as I do, I have much pleasure in stating that I believe<lb/>you to be exceedingly well qualified for the post. What is<lb/>wanted is, I believe, a clever, steady, hard working and<lb/>energetic man, and in these respects I feel confident that you<lb/>are suitable.  I trust you may be successful and feel sure that your<lb/>appointment would give great satisfaction to the members of<lb/>our profession, who desire to see the post filled by the man<lb/>best qualified to do the work.   Yours very truly, <lb/> BENJAMIN WHITNEY. <lb/><lb/> William S. Collis, Esq., B.A.,<lb/>Westmoreland St.  
            <pb n="10" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_10"/>
             From Mr. Serjeant Campion , K.C.<lb/>13, Hatch Street,   October 30th, 1889.   I have had the pleasure of being acquainted with Mr. W.<lb/>STEWART COLLIS for several years.  He is a gentleman of high character, and, in my opinion,<lb/>of considerable ability. In the discharge of his professional<lb/>duties, I have always found him most competent and zealous,<lb/>and I have no doubt he would prove worthy of confidence in<lb/>any position in which he might be placed.   W. BENNETT CAMPION.  
            <pb n="11" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_11"/>
             65. Merrion Square, Dublin.   29th October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr. Collis,   I understand you are a candidate for the office of<lb/>solicitor to the Land Commissioners.  From my experience of you in several heavy cares, as a<lb/>solicitor, I am satisfied with your professional capacity, and of<lb/>your fitness for any office requiring intelligence and knowledge<lb/>of your business. Hoping to hear of your appointment.   I am,<lb/>Yours very truly, <lb/> C.H. HEMPHILL. <lb/> W.Stewart Collis, Esq.  
            <pb n="12" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_12"/>
             25 Clare Street, Dublin,   31st October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr. Collis,   In reference to your Candidature for the office of Solicitor<lb/>to the Irish Land Commission, I have no hesitation in bearing<lb/>my testimony to your fitness to fill the post with credit to your-<lb/>self, and satisfaction to the public. My firm has been engaged<lb/>in important legal matters with you, and always found that they<lb/>were conducted with ability and despatch.   I am ,<lb/>Yours very truly, <lb/> Robert O. Longfield. <lb/> W.S. Collis, Esq.  
            <pb n="13" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_13"/>
             66 Lower Leeson Street, Dublin,   31st October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr. Collis,   I have much pleasure in stating that in my opinion you are<lb/>well qualified in every respect to fill the post of Solicitor to the<lb/>Land Commission. Having experienced your energy, accuracy,<lb/>and ability in the discharge of your ordinary professional duties,<lb/>I consider that your selection to fill the vacancy caused by the<lb/>death of the late Mr. Browning, ought to give much satisfaction<lb/>to all those who are brought into business relations with the<lb/>Commissioners.  I hope that you will get the post.   Believe me,<lb/>Yours faithfully, <lb/> David Colquhoun. <lb/><lb/> W.S.Collis, Esq.,<lb/>3 Westmoreland-street  
            <pb n="14" facs="L1916_1754_img_1210_14"/>
             51, Merrion Square,<lb/>Dublin,   29th October, 1889. <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr.Collis,   Without respect to the high honours you gained when<lb/>entering our profession, I have much pleasure in certifying ,<lb/>from the knowledge I have had of you in business, that you<lb/>are well qualified to fill the post of Solicitor to the Land<lb/>Commission.   Yours faithfully, <lb/> RICHARD S. REEVES. <lb/> W. S. Collis, Esq.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>