<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0265">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Joseph Dowdall to Augustine Birrell, 18 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Joseph Dowdall</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Joseph Dowdall (b.1865), an electrician living in Dublin city. The letter was addressed to Augustine Birrell. In the letter Dowdall claims that he is being followed by two German spies. He reports that both are &#39;aliens&#39; but refuse to acknowledge their nationality. He believes the to men are reporting back to the German government in Dublin, London and the Continent. Dowdall writes that he will be willing to make a full statement about the men should Birrell consider it prudent to investigate.Birrell (1850-1933) served as the chief secretary of Ireland from 1907 to 1916. Birrell was a liberal politician praised for his reforms of the Irish education system. The Easter Rising caught him unawares and, occupied in London, there was little he could do. A later inquiry into the Rising held Birrell chiefly responsible for the events that occurred leading to his resignation on 1 May 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers, CSO RP/1916/8036/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/265</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0422">Joseph Dowdall</persName>
              <date>1916-04-18</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0686">18 Terrace Place, Buckingham Street, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0265_img_1451_1"  type="Letter"  url="b62a9b16ce62fd3d391969ca2e5fb148.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0265_img_1451_1"/>
              Under Secretary<lb/><hi rend="underline">SMP</hi><lb/>20/4/16  Ch.  <lb/>will you   see<lb/> Mr. Dowdall<lb/> if you ascertain<lb/> that he is a<lb/> reliable person.<lb/> <lb/>21/4  Supt. G. <seg type="unclear">dim</seg><lb/><seg type="unclear">Wam</seg> 2/5/16    18 Terrace Place  Buckingham St  Dublin    18/4/16  <lb/><hi rend="underline">To</hi><lb/> The Right honourable Mr. Birrell.<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Sir</hi> <lb/>  I deem it my duty as an Irishman and<lb/> a supporter of his majesties Government,<lb/> to communicate to you the fact, that<lb/> for over 12 months past I have under<lb/> observation in this City two men whom<lb/> not only do I believe are German Spies but<lb/> that they are in constant touch <seg type="del">between</seg><lb/> with the German Government in Dublin,<lb/> London &amp; The Continent. Both these men<lb/> are aliens, but neither <sic>admitt</sic> their true nationality,<lb/> one is aged about 26 years the other about 30 years<lb/> one at least is in Dublin since his boyhood.<lb/> I refrain from giving further details for<lb/> the present lest this letter might not<lb/> reach you. But I am prepared to make<lb/> a full statement of all I know should<lb/> you deem it prudent to make an<lb/> appointment in Dublin or elsewhere. <lb/> I am an Electrical Engineer and am<lb/> personally <sic>know</sic> by The Right Honourable<lb/> The Recorder of Dublin and Mr J Mulhall<lb/> vice President Prisons Board in Ireland. <lb/><seg type="closer"> I beg to remain Sir<lb/> yours most respectfully <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Joseph Dowdall</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>