<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3139">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Olive Duffin to her mother, Maria Duffin, November 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Olive Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Olive Duffin to her mother Maria Duffin (1854-1954).

This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/9/4/B/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3139</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1281">Olive Duffin</persName>
              <date>1915-11</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2125">7 West Cliff, Eastbourne, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3139_img_2558_1"  type="Letter"  url="f520d486537d9f071c888f108684cb2b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3139_img_2558_2"  type="Letter"  url="992a8a3f45e834c09e5e7fec1ce81a24.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3139_img_2558_3"  type="Letter"  url="5694571177a8b5833d68b4e10308f73e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3139_img_2558_1"/>
             D2109/9/4/B   7  <seg type="unclear">South</seg> Cliff<lb/>Eastbourne     Sunday<lb/>Nov. 1915 <lb/><lb/> Dearest Mamma,   Your letter arrived on Saturday this<lb/>time. Thanks for E's letter which I was so glad to<lb/>get — we should hear again soon from her, that one took<lb/>a very short time to come! I send on D's to you but let<lb/>me have it back. I had a long letter from Edmund<lb/>which was nice to get, please thank him him as I am not<lb/>writing to him yet. I've not heard from Celia for<lb/>some time but Miss R has asked her to to <seg type="unclear">send</seg> her  <lb/>day be again if she cares to. Let me know your news of<lb/>Terry surely you must have heard from him by now.<lb/>It is splendid his getting the Staff job.   It must keep you busy communicating with all the family<lb/>indeed it must feel funny to have the house to yourself<lb/>all morning but I expect you have lots to do.  My time gets piled up in an astonishing manner. I<lb/>am trying to paint. Miss R in the morning, a difficult<lb/>task, but Miss Hollins asked me to do it. Cousin<lb/>Annie sent me a kind &amp; odd letter enclosing 2 little<lb/>snapshots of <seg type="unclear">Elle's</seg> childeren whch she wants miniatures<lb/>done of, qute impossible to make what I call a 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3139_img_2558_2"/>
             D2109/9/4/B  miniature likeness from, but I shall attempt some sort<lb/>of little sketch on ivory! I did one of Humphrey Hollins<lb/>as a little boy from an old snapshot, I am sure it was<lb/>not a bit like him, Miss R admitted it was not very, but<lb/>she seems just as pleased with it as a little memoriam<lb/>and wears it in a locket.  The Walker Gallery in Liverpool have accepted 2 I sent<lb/>them. I have nothing to send to the Belfast Art Gallery<lb/>as all I have done lately are ones I would not care<lb/>to ask for, (I see Eustace Gordon is Secretary).  I have madde Emma's old   dress into a really<lb/>very pretty semi-  frock and it will be very useful<lb/>to me. I've not done any shopping here in the<lb/>clothes line but the shops are good and no doubt<lb/>expensive. I have still the remains of my old blue<lb/>  &amp; my blue serge quite good.     I do a little work at the Red X. supply depot, rolling<lb/>bandages etc.  come when  are us<lb/>visitors here Miss R takes more attention. She is<lb/>greatly interested in all the various doings of the<lb/>family. She sent some music to D for her soldiers<lb/>and sends a graphic on to Celia. She has presented<lb/>me with a rubber hot water bottle &amp; cover, she<lb/>is greatly distressed that I won't wear 'legs' a long   
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3139_img_2558_3"/>
             D2109/9/4/B  Ribbed wooly garments which she delights to knit &amp;<lb/>present to friends.  Mildrid leaves <seg type="unclear"></seg>  tomorrow for a short period<lb/>&amp; goes to Cnl Forbes mother in London, but will be<lb/>back soon I am sure. <seg type="del">It is</seg> Mrs Crosbie is always<lb/>threatenning to ask me to play tennis with her son<lb/>whom I have not yet met, &amp; I have avoided doing so<lb/>but   the season will be over    Miss Randall is back but I've not seen her &amp; head she<lb/>is fearfully busy. I get funny &amp; affectionate<lb/>letters from Francine Ville from Paris. She's<lb/>now secretary to a Minister &amp; so pleased to be an<lb/>dependant again of the Lakeham Regime!  I have a lot to write &amp; Stanley   &amp; Henry<lb/>Hollins came to lunch, &amp; I generally help to enter—<lb/>tain them in the afternoon     home.      Best love dearest from<lb/>Your loving<lb/>Olive   Thank H for her.<lb/>I had a letter from Nell Hamilton asking for news<lb/>&amp; sending love to all the family. Maurice is at the<lb/><seg type="unclear"></seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>