<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0437">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Marie Martin to her mother, Mary Martin, 20 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Marie Martin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Marie Martin (1892-1975) to her mother Mary Lewis Martin (1866-1955). Marie begins by writing that this is the first long letter she has written in some time. She describes the work conditions in the medical tents. She also writes about her sadness at the death of her brother, Charlie who had been missing in action since December 1915.Marie Helena Martin later known as &#39;Mother Mary&#39;, was a volunteer nurse during the First World War. She served in field hospitals in Malta, Leeds, and France working for the British army and later went on to become the founder of the Medical Missionaries of Mary (MMM).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Medical Missionaries of Mary</repository>
                  <collection>France Letters, B/F/1/53</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/437</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0709">Marie Martin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-20</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1543">Hardelot, France</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Mary Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1257">Monkstown, Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0437_img_1772_1"  type="Letter"  url="b5ab9e9f9a9e019cceffa9943812be36.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0437_img_1772_2"  type="Letter"  url="49169d6f2f08d21f553e85281257a666.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0437_img_1772_3"  type="Letter"  url="7333372776df27ae8635c4b903d230f4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0437_img_1772_4"  type="Letter"  url="c9ddfd76622b6d0b2e4970ca3b370cf3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0437_img_1772_5"  type="Letter"  url="32b8f4e56536254a2d2253df602b2839.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0437_img_1772_1"/>
                20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916   My very dearest Mother   It is ages since I wrote <lb/> you a long letter but we have <lb/> been fairly busy and did not get <lb/> very much off duty time,<lb/> however things are slack again,partly <lb/> owing to an epidemic of Diarrhea<lb/> which has been affecting both <lb/> staff and patients.They are trying to get <lb/> to the bottom of it. S. 8 opened<lb/> about a week ago and we had some<lb/> quite bad cases but am glad to <lb/> say most of them have gone to<lb/> England as their wounds will take<lb/> some time to heal. We have S. 9 <lb/> also under our care so that when<lb/> we are full up there is a fair <lb/> amount of work to be done. My<lb/> Tent is beginning to look fairly  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0437_img_1772_2"/>
              straight. I have got to the stage of<lb/> leaving flowers in it so it looks<lb/> quite homely. I am off this morning<lb/> as sister is having a <seg type="unclear">half</seg> &amp; will<lb/> have to keep an eye on <seg type="unclear">S.7</seg><lb/> but there is no one had so the<lb/> work is not hard.  I am so glad to think you are<lb/> having a change, don't be in a <lb/> hurry back. It cheered me up <lb/> greatly to hear you were feeling <lb/> more yourself also to get A. Mays<lb/> letter saying she was taking care<lb/> of you. Although I have not written<lb/> very often lately, you have been<lb/> constantly in my mind.  Really it is terribly sad about <lb/> poor Charlie. I really do not know <lb/> what to think. All the stories<lb/> seem so different. There is one thing <lb/> we may feel sure of &amp; that is  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0437_img_1772_3"/>
              he seems to have been one of the<lb/> bravest &amp; most consciencious the way<lb/> he stuck to his duty &amp; men. How <lb/> proud a mother you must feel to<lb/> have such a son. I only know how<lb/> I feel about him. Poor Charlie,<lb/> how we shall all miss him. It is<lb/> not now so much but when we<lb/> all gather together when the war<lb/> is over, which I hope will be<lb/> very soon. I still keep praying<lb/> he may turn up, although it<lb/> looks so hopeless. I shall have<lb/> some masses said for him here.<lb/> I hope you have had good<lb/> news of Tommy. I must try &amp; write<lb/> to him today if I get time.<lb/> I have heard no more of Gerald <lb/> G. but hope also to write to him<lb/> to-day. I think I shall send on <lb/> the letter about Charlie. he was<lb/> so fond of him. How the men<lb/> all loved him as everyone who  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0437_img_1772_4"/>
              knew him did. Also Gerald R. How<lb/> is he. I was so glad to hear in<lb/> your last letter that U. Frank &amp;<lb/> A. Lissy were something better.<lb/> The heat really has not been very<lb/> trying til yesterday and today<lb/> when it is really very warm, but<lb/> I am really glad to think of you<lb/> having such fine weather, which<lb/> means you can sit out &amp; enjoy<lb/> the air without tiring yourself.<lb/> Please thank A. May a 1000 times<lb/> for her letter. I will answer her<lb/> soon. Tell her she could have done<lb/> nothing to please me more as I<lb/> was very anxious about you &amp; it<lb/> relieved me to hear from someone<lb/> who say you how you were looking.<lb/> Your hands will be full again<lb/> with all the boys home. I suppose<lb/> Ger &amp; Jack will remain at home<lb/> for good.  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0437_img_1772_5"/>
              Don't forget to ask that M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Boase<lb/> out, He is quite nice &amp; I am<lb/> sure plays tennis. I have not<lb/> written to him yet.  This place is getting quite <seg type="del">fu</seg><lb/> lively,<lb/> as a great number of French<lb/> people are opening their houses.<lb/> Certainly the B.O do have a time<lb/> with the french girls.  I think I must close now, Time is<lb/> getting on. I only got off at 10.30 &amp;<lb/> must be ready for dinner at 12 0'<sic>ck</sic><lb/> I want to write several letters, one<lb/> to Dinnie Fitzgerald asking him to<lb/> send Red Cross stuff. <seg type="closer"> So <seg type="foreign">au-revoir</seg> With my very fondest<lb/> love to you &amp; all<lb/> Your ever loving &amp; faithful daughter  <hi rend="underline">Marie</hi>  x</seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>