<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3241">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Monsieur Hymans to Sir Edward Grey, 6 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Monsieur Hymans</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-10257-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3241</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">French</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0325">Monsieur Hymans</persName>
              <date>1916-06-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0562">Legation de Belgique, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Edward Grey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3241_img_2660_1"  type="Letter"  url="01553f0d018ba935c07219e27ee2eb81.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3241_img_2660_2"  type="Letter"  url="41ef10ccca9cad0f8d6cec4337b804db.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3241_img_2660_1"/>
            <seg type="foreign"> Copie. <lb/>(109706) <lb/>30Z <lb/>No. 5529.   LEGATION DE BELGIQUE, <lb/>Londres  <lb/> le 6 Juin, 1916  <lb/> Monsieur le Secrétaire d'Etat   Mon Gouvernement vient d'apprendre que la <lb/>municipalité de Dublin se propose d'étudier un projet <lb/>de transformation du centre de cette ville. projet qui <lb/>serait mis à execution á l'occasion de la reconstruction <lb/>de la Sackville Street et des rues adjacent<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>s détruites <lb/>au cours des récents événments.   Le Ministre des Travaux Publice de Belgique, qui <lb/>se préoccupe de l'aménagement de nos villes et com— <lb/>munes détruites, serais désireux de connaître, en detail, <lb/>les différentes solutions qui seraient étudiées par la <lb/>municipalité.   J'ai l'honneur de recourir aux bons offices de <lb/>Votre Excellence en vue d'obtenir que ces renseigne— <lb/>ments puissant être mis à ma disposition par les <lb/>Autorités Britanniques compétentes, si toutefois la <lb/>chose est possible.    Je saisis cette occasion de renouveler à Votre <lb/>Excellence les assurances de la plus haute considéra— <lb/>tion avec laquelle j'ai l'honneur d'être   Son très humble et <lb/>obeisant serviteur, <lb/>(Signé) Hymans.   Son Excellency   Sir Edward Grey, Bart; K.G., M.P.,   &amp;c. ,&amp;c. ,&amp;c. , </seg>
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3241_img_2660_2"/>
             In any further communica- <lb/>on this subject, please <lb/>quote <lb/>No 1003/C/1916   The Under-Secretary of State <lb/>Foreign Office <lb/>London  <lb/>Reference to previous correspondence:- <lb/>Letter from <hi rend="superscript">to</hi> Foreign Office:  The Under-Secretary for state for Foreign Affairs presents <lb/>his compliments to the Under-Secretary for <lb/>Ireland — and is directed by the Secretary of <lb/>State for Foreign Affairs to transmit the accompanying copies of <lb/>a letter  June 6 which has been received from the <lb/>Belgian Minister respecting the <lb/>reconstruction of destroyed parts <lb/>of Dublin.   The Secretary of State would be glad to be advised <lb/><lb/>what answer should be returned to M. Hymans  <lb/>Foreign Office <lb/> June 10, 1916  <lb/><seg type="del">Similar letter sent to</seg>
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>