<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0344">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Clair Ní Modhráin to Eamonn O'Modhráin, 30 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Clair Ní Modhráin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Clair Ní Modhráin (b. 1891) to her brother, Eamonn Modhráin. Clair writes about letters sent to and received by the family and notes that their mother is &#39;managing wonderfully well&#39;. She also writes that a &#39;chap&#39; going over to visit his brother had tried to visit Eamonn but did not succeed.Eamonn Modhráin (1881-1954) had been arrested after the Easter Rising and imprisoned, spending time in Wakefield Prison and Frongach Internment Camp. This letter was sent while he was in Wakefield. Eamonn and Clair&#39;s brother Lewis (Louis) (1893-1959) was also imprisoned in Wakefield at this time although he was soon released.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>O&#39;Modhráin Family</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/344</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0640">Clair Ní Modhráin</persName>
              <date>1916-05-30</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1527">Eamonn O&#39;Modhráin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1424">Wakefield Prison, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0344_img_1579_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa4a11103845fcef54f1362498353f2e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0344_img_1579_2"  type="Letter"  url="95c5cd37a6f8ca0ed02f241caca8014d.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0344_img_1579_1"/>
                30.5.16   My dear Eamonn,   We posted today a parcel each for <lb/>you &amp; Louie. Hope they will reach you <lb/>safely without delay. The letters take <lb/>at least a week to come from England   Louie mentioned he got a letter from <lb/>Maire, that seems to be the only <lb/>one that reached you, although we <lb/>wrote almost every day but I <lb/> suppose there are so many to be <lb/>delivered some of them get lost.   We had another letter from <lb/>Maire to day. She got your letter <lb/> on Friday.   We were home on Sunday  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0344_img_1579_2"/>
              and found all well. Mother is <lb/>managing wonderfully well. <lb/>Louie's letter was a great relief <lb/>to her. He mentioned you were <lb/>alright as regards clothes. You <lb/>must be a great toff in your old <lb/> hat.   Una asked a chap who was going <lb/>over to see his brother to see you, <lb/>but he did not succeed.   I must write a line to Louie <lb/> now.  <seg type="closer"> With warmest love <lb/> Your loving sister   Clair </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>