<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5844">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Mabel FitzGerald to the Governor, Dartmoor Prison, 22 June 1916.</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Mabel FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is Mabel FitzGerald (née Washington McConnell) (1884-1958), wife of politician and intellectual Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947), to the governor of Dartmoor prison, Major E. Reade.
Desmond FitzGerald had served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Mountjoy, Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland.
Mrs FitzGerald is replying to the Governor&#39;s letter regarding Michael Joseph O&#39;Rahilly&#39;s missing bicycle and advises that the family has already located it. The O&#39;Rahilly (1875-1916) was killed on Parnell/Moore Street during the evacuation of the GPO during the Easter Rising. Both Fitzgerald and O&#39;Rahilly had tried to prevent the Rising but joined once it began. FitzGerald had borrowed the bicycle before the Rising.
She asks the Reade to tell her husband that their elder son has had a successful adenoid operation and it fully recovered. The operation was performed by Oliver Gogarty (1878-1957).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>FitzGerald Papers, P80/1604/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5844</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1316">Mabel FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-06-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1746">2 Loretto Villas, Bray, County Wicklow, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0369">The Governor, Dartmoor Prison</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1395">Dartmoor, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="death">1957</item>
               <item n="tag">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5844_img_943_1"  type="Letter"  url="6a751b8d93e79a224c150c0e1b05a09e.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5844_img_943_1"/>
             2 Loretto Villas, <lb/>Bray <lb/>Co Wicklow, <lb/>Ireland.   Copy   22nd June, 1916   The Governor, <lb/>The Prison, <lb/>Dartmoor   Sir,   I must thank you for your communication of a message <lb/> from my husband telling me the whereabouts of The O'Rahillys <sic>bicy</sic> <lb/> : please let him know that the family recovered it some little t <lb/> time ago by chance.   I should be glad if you would tell my husband that <lb/> owing to sudden and growing deafness our older boy had to have an <lb/> operation for Adenoids last week and that is was performed very <lb/> <sic>skilfully</sic> by a Dublin Specialist, Dr Oliver Gogarty and was a com <lb/>plete success; the child  has  recover<seg type="del">ing</seg> ed  his hearing <seg type="del">s</seg>and is now in exc ellent  <lb/>ent he a lth.   Yours truly   Mabel Fitzgerald 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>