<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5363">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Charlie Daly to Sinéad Ring, 1 February 1923</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Charlie Daly</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Kerry Library Archives</repository>
                  <collection>Charlie Daly Collection, P41/23/8</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5363</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1307">Charlie Daly</persName>
              <date>1923-02-01</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1004">Drumboe Castle, Stranorlar, Co Tirconaill, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None"> Sinéad Ring</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0417">77 Harcourt Street, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1923</item>
               <item n="tag">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
               <item n="topic">Civil War (1922-1923)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5363_img_4646_1"  type="Letter"  url="c9f17f9947e2af3ea1e39c23ae95c44b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5363_img_4646_2"  type="Letter"  url="922b4291890846987d88a412d3313e05.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5363_img_4646_3"  type="Letter"  url="455a7b678aae8d11d991073369cdf8d0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5363_img_4646_1"/>
             P41/23/8   Drumboe Castle<lb/>Stranorlar Tirconail    Feb. 1st ‘23    <seg type="unclear">A a cara dil</seg>   Got your letter this evening. I had just begun<lb/>to think that you were rather long without writing. I see<lb/>that twas the delay in my letter that was the reason.<lb/>Usually I write you on the same day that your letters<lb/>come but then of course they are often delayed.  Not at all I wasn’t in the least nice  about<lb/>those yarns and twas silly of you to think so.<lb/>Of course you can. I don’t help better  such a funny<lb/>thing out. I can imagine how twas enjoyed. Did<lb/>you tell Free? When I saw it in the paper that <seg type="unclear">Francis</seg><lb/> had been brought to Dublin from Kerry I guessed<lb/>that Tomás &amp; the lads would be among them. I had<lb/>a letter from my mother last week telling me about<lb/>her visit to them and that they expected to be sent to<lb/>Mountjoy. I wrote him some time ago. I don’t know<lb/>if he had my letter before he left. I’ll chance him<lb/>with another at his new address. I had several<lb/>letters today including from<seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>O’Brien, Dan Cahill, Rita   (of  ) and Father
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5363_img_4646_2"/>
             Brennan over a dozen altogether. Fr. Brennan had<lb/>heard of our court martial and wrote to tell me<lb/>that he was praying and saying Masses for us. I don’t<lb/>know if you have yet heard that we have been tried.<lb/>Perhaps you may by then as I wrote my mother last<lb/>week &amp; told her. I ought have told you when I<lb/>wrote last but I didn’t know at the time if I<lb/>would be permitted tell. Besides I was in no<lb/>hurry to inform anybody for I knew that would<lb/>be known soon enough. A fortnight has elapsed<lb/>  the C.M. and we haven’t heard the result<lb/>yet. Don’t worry about us but pray that every<lb/>thing will come alright. Although we don’t know<lb/>what our fate may be we are not worrying one<lb/>bit. The thought of sudden death has so often<lb/>been before us for the past few years that we are<lb/>not afraid of its possibility now and we trust<lb/>on   and our friends prayers either to bring us<lb/>out safe or give us a happy death. One good<lb/>thing anyway we have every opportunity to prepare<lb/>for death should it be that. Ask the Rev. Mother<lb/>the nuns &amp; your companions to pray for us. I<lb/>suppose the Rev. Mother   my visit out there.    
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_5363_img_4646_3"/>
             Fr. Brennan said he might be in Dublin this week.<lb/>So you may meet him. I don’t know where he puts<lb/>up there but probably at the “Shelbourne”. He says<lb/>that they are taking the news of my trial alright at<lb/>home. That’s the way I want you all to take it<lb/>whatever else may come and there’s no use anyway<lb/>of worrying beforehand. We here are in as<lb/>good spirits as ever and in fact better <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>  as it may seem. While not deluding ourselves<lb/>with hopes that might be false at the same time<lb/>we aren’t   in gloomy foreboding.    I answered those letters of Nellie <seg type="unclear"></seg><lb/>  some time ago and I heard they got them<lb/>alright. Yes they have become very good at<lb/>the Irish. I was surprised at their letters. That<lb/>little book you sent was very good. You can<lb/>send me any good ones you come across. Also<lb/>send me some of the good weeklies such as “Ireland’s<lb/>Eye”. N Ring sent me this months “Dublin Opinion”. I<lb/>had a letter from Mollie   a few days ago.        Beannacht De ort        [Signature.] 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>