<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2484">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Diarmid Coffey from Dermod O’Brien about the Irish Question</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dermod O&#39;Brien</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letters to Diarmid Coffey from Dermod O’Brien about “working  out a scheme of settlement of the Irish Self Government question&#34;. Edward Lysaght&#39;s suggestions for a settlement are mentioned, as is getting the leaders of the various political parties on board.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 46,307 /11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2484</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1530">Dermod O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date>1916-08-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0284">Diarmid Coffey</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2484_img_192_1"  type="Letter"  url="421513c7ddde2d883485ef6de2ead1c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2484_img_192_2"  type="Letter"  url="711b3b1f671aa4c5d66bb7c1911d4eef.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2484_img_192_3"  type="Letter"  url="07e727147f0a05317a809d4229df9fa0.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2484_img_192_1"/>
             18 August 1916   UNITED ARTS CLUB. <lb/>44, S<hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">T</hi></hi> STEPHEN'S GREEN, <lb/>DUBLIN.   My dear Coffey,   I am sending you herewith <lb/> a copy of the agenda for <lb/>our next meeting together <lb/>with the I. Times report <lb/> of the debate on L. MacDon <lb/> nell's amending Bill, <lb/> and I hope you may be <lb/>able to be present.    Edward Lysaght suggested <lb/>your name as that of a <lb/> person who would not only
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2484_img_192_2"/>
            interested in any attempt <lb/> at working out a scheme <lb/> of settlement of the Irish <lb/>self gov- question but <lb/> also be willing to put <lb/>in work.    We are really a committee <lb/> of investigation I hope <lb/> and have no idea of <lb/> being of any or of running <lb/> counter to any political <lb/>party, but ready to work <lb/> out details, making <lb/> questions receive them <lb/> &amp; offer the result for <lb/> consideration to the <lb/> leaders of the political <lb/> parties, always in <lb/> hope of thereby getting <lb/> them to agree for the <lb/> good of Ireland.   This may be a counsel
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2484_img_192_3"/>
            of perfection of which <lb/>we are bound to fall far <lb/> short but we shall have <lb/> gained something if we <lb/> can get even a few to <lb/>do some thinking, which <lb/> the politician has for <lb/> long given up trying.   Yours sincerely   Dermod <hi rend="underline">O'Brien</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>