<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1316">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Michael Collins to Nancy O'Brien, 27 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Michael Collins</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Michael Collins (1890-1922) to his cousin Nancy O&#39;Brien (who later married his brother) written from Frongach Internment Camp in Wales. In the letter he discusses conditions at the camp and the release of Irish prisoners, although he does not think he will be counted as one of their number. He also refers to mutual friends. Michael Collins served as aide-de-camp to Joseph Plunkett in the GPO during the Rising and was imprisoned in Frongach. He went on to become Minister for Finance in the First Dáil, IRA Director of Information and President of the Provisional Government.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Michael Collins Papers, 420/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1316</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1129">Michael Collins</persName>
              <date>1916-07-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1247">Frongach Internment Camp, Wales</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Nancy O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1316_img_610_1"  type="Letter"  url="580bb3bec85edf0b31161671fc542a36.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1316_img_610_2"  type="Letter"  url="259d924935152dd3fc2cabf73212c013.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1316_img_610_1"/>
                26/7/16   My Dear Nancy,   Honestly I don't know whether or not <lb/><sic>Ive</sic> written to you since receiving a letter from you <lb/> about a week ago. In any case since coming to <lb/> this place my correspondence has gone all awry for <lb/> as <sic>Ive</sic> told you already we are only allowed two <lb/> letters weekly &amp; when you add to this several <lb/> others sent away surreptitiously, many of which <lb/> have not been delivered â the muddle <lb/> is clearly understood.  Taking all things into account <lb/> I suppose we have no reason to complain - at <lb/> any rate I <sic>dont.</sic> Of course the huts may be <lb/> overcrowded &amp; the visiting arrangements very inadequate <lb/> &amp; several other things but even so, in this weather <lb/> &amp; pretty surroundings there are compensations and <lb/> we might very easily have been lying cold and <lb/> stiff or in Dartmoor etc â Just at this moment <lb/> I suppose you are about to depart for the south. <lb/> How <sic>Id</sic> like to be going! Has Hannie returned <lb/> yet? Well I hope you'll have a right good time <lb/> &amp; if you meet anybody who takes an <lb/> interest in me you - can say how well I  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1316_img_610_2"/>
              am &amp; for some time my <seg type="del">I</seg> only concern was <lb/> about these proposals. <sic>Im</sic> glad to see that <lb/> this particular business has been dropped. <lb/> Surely John E &amp; Co must be dispirited now, although <lb/> there are a lot of damn fools knocking about. At <lb/> present there is great excitement in this 'compound' <lb/> about the releases - about 40 or 50 daily. One never <lb/> knows what mistake a Gov Dep might might make; &amp; <lb/> between you and me I <sic>dont</sic> think I'm likely to see the <lb/> shores of Erin for some time.  Now how are your colleagues going <lb/> on? Have written several times to Susan, often <lb/> some of the letters  those already alluded to  may not have arrived, but have <lb/> not had a note from her for some time. Dolly has <lb/> not written either but she sends the Independent &amp; <lb/><sic>Id</sic> be obliged if <sic>youd</sic> just say a word of thanks to her <lb/> on my behalf. Your <sic>cigarets</sic> came alright &amp; were <lb/> very good. The grub is much better than we were used <lb/> to in S â But its not possible to get such thing as as fruit <lb/> or any kind of decent cake etc. There is a Canteen <lb/> - a dry one unhappily! where we may get some things <lb/> in addition to the allowances. I suppose you know <lb/> Eugene O'Keeffe is here - very well and in good form. <seg type="closer"> Much love  Michael </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>