<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1088">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to Thomas Kirkpatrick, 22 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sir Arthur Stanley</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Arthur Stanley to Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick informing Kirkpatrick that he would gladly meet with Sir John Moore and Sir Arthur Chance while they are in London. Sir Arthur Stanley (1869-1947) was a philanthropist. In 1916 Stanley founded the College of Nursing with Dame Sarah Swift and became the first chairman of the college council. Additionally, Stanley served as chairman of the British Red Cross Society&#39;s committee from 1915 and was actively involved with the Star and Garter Home for Disabled Sailors and Soldiers.From 1910 until 1954 Thomas Kirkpatrick (1869-1954) served as the registrar for the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland. He also served as the general secretary of the Royal Academy of Medicine in Ireland. He took a particular interest in what were then termed venereal diseases; to encourage his patients (many of whom were prostitutes) to attend, he held a clinic for women at a discreet early morning hour to facilitate anonymity.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>RCPI-2-3-3-15-23, RCPI-2-3-3-15-23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1088</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0219">Sir Arthur Stanley</persName>
              <date>1916-05-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1511">83 Pall Mall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0544">Thomas Percy Kirkpatrick</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1042">Royal College of Physicians, Kildare Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Medicine</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1088_img_3237_1"  type="Letter"  url="6c501533a2d907dfb85d1d5f11bcd690.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1088_img_3237_1"/>
                83, PALL MALL,  LONDON, S.W.    22nd May 1916   Dear Sir,   I beg to acknowledge with thanks receipt of your <lb/> letter dated the 19th instant.   I will gladly avail myself of the opportunity of <lb/>seeing Sir John Moore and Sir Arthur Chance while they <lb/>are in London this week. I am writing to the General <lb/>Medical Council office to ask them to be kind enough to <lb/>make an appointment.  <seg type="closer"> Yours faithfully  <hi rend="underline">Arthur Stanely.</hi>   T. Percy Kirkpatrick Esq.,  Royal College of Physicians of Ireland,  Kildare Street,  Dublin  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>