<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3403">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William P. Triston to the Under Secretary of Ireland, 12 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William P. Triston</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from William Triston to the under secretary of Ireland enclosing the petition of  Mary Murphy for permission to continue trading while awaiting a new publican&#39;s licence.

Sir Robert Chalmers was sent to Ireland as replacement under-secretary for Sir Matthew Nathan, who had resigned along with Augustine Birrell, his chief secretary, following the outbreak of the Easter Rising in 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-12885</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3403</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0081">William P. Triston</persName>
              <date>1916-07-12</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0078">1 Dame Street, Dublin, Ireland </placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Robert Chalmers</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3403_img_2814_1"  type="Letter"  url="fc24db31a2849bb195d56ba1942f7245.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3403_img_2814_2"  type="Enclosure"  url="1da7f604a7ab462a12d58f0972c07e88.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3403_img_2814_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="fd81e13661b1108a273c25c6a1301a11.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3403_img_2814_1"/>
             1, Dame Street, <lb/>Dublin   12th July 1916  <lb/><hi rend="underline">re- Mrs Mary Murphy</hi>  Sir,   I enclose Petition herein and I will <lb/>be obliged if you will kindly bring the <lb/>Petition forward at the earliest opportunity.   I am, Sir, <lb/>Your obedient servant   William P. Triston   The Under <sic>Sectretary</sic> <lb/>Dublin Castle <lb/><hi rend="underline">DUBLIN</hi>   I Ack &amp; f.a. <lb/>II J.h. <lb/>For report <lb/>Eof <lb/><hi rend="underline">13-VII-16</hi> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3403_img_2814_2"/>
             <hi rend="underline">TO THE LORDS JUSTICES <lb/>ACTING FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF IRELAND, DURING <lb/>THE VACANCY IN THE OFFICE OF LORD LIEUTENANT <lb/>OF IRELAND.</hi>   May it please your Excellencies.   The Petition of Mary Murphy of Duke Street, Athy in the <lb/>County of Kildare, sheweth as follows:-   Your Petitioner is the owner of a house and premises in <lb/>Duke Street, Athy to which was attached a seven-day retail <lb/>Publican's Licence.   Your Petitioner let the licence and premises with the licence <lb/>attached to a Joseph Clarke in September 1914 and in January 1915 <lb/>he got a Transfer of the Licence at Quarter Sessions in his own <lb/>name.   The said Joseph Clarke got the usual Renewable Certificate <lb/>signed by the Magistrate at the Annual Licencing Petty Sessions <lb/>on the 28th day of September 1915 in his own name and very shortly <lb/>afterwards he surrendered the premises to your Petitioner. He <lb/>did not apply at the Annual Licencing Quarter sessions on the <lb/>15th day of October 1915 for the Confirmation of the Transfer <lb/>granted to him at the previous Quarter sessions as he had sur- <lb/>rendered the premises to your Petitioner and your Petitioner had <lb/>not sufficient time in which to apply to the Quarter/Sessions in <lb/>October 1915 for a Transfer as the time between the Surrender and <lb/>the said Quarter Sessions was too short. The Licence Duty for <lb/>the current year has been duly paid but the Excise Authorities <lb/>state they cannot issue the Licence in your Petitioners name or <lb/>in Joseph Clarke's name, because Joseph Clarke did not get the <lb/>Transfer of the Licence confirmed or because your Petitioner did <lb/>not apply for a Transfer at the October Quarter Sessions 1915.   The Magistrates at Petty Sessions are ready and willing to <lb/>grant me a Transfer of the Licence and the Police Authorities <lb/>have no objection to the Transfer but as the Excise Authorities <lb/>will not issue the Licence, the Magistrates have no document on
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3403_img_2814_3"/>
            <lb/>which to indorse the Transfer. The next Quarter Sessions for <seg type="del">xx</seg> <lb/>District will not be held until the 20th day of October next and <lb/>if your Petitioner is not allowed to trade in the meantime the <lb/>Licence will be lost which will mean a considerable loss to your <lb/>Petitioner's Income.   Your Petitioner therefore prays <lb/>that your Excellencies may be <lb/>pleased to give your Petitioner <lb/>liberty to trade and carry on <lb/>the business of Publican in said <lb/>licenced house and premises until <lb/>the next Annual Licencing Quar- <lb/>ter Sessions for the District to <lb/>be held at Kildare on the 20th <lb/>day of October 1916; and your <lb/>Petitioner will ever pray.   <hi rend="underline">William P. Triston</hi>  <lb/>Solicitor for Petitioner  1 Dame Street <lb/>Dublin   12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>