<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0557">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Philip C. MacDermot to Henry Arthur Wynne, 29 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Philip C. MacDermot</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Philip MacDermot (b. 1863), the crown solicitor for Roscommon, to Sir Henry Arthur Wynne referring to a case of cattle driving off &#39;Mathers Lands&#39; in Ballinasloe. According to the letter one of the participants in the drive, Harvey, has not yet been arrested. Wynne does not see this as a problem as Harvey is a &#39;tramp labourer&#39; who seems to merely have joined in the drive with the crowd.Wynne (1867 – 1945) was appointed to the vacant position of Chief Crown Solicitor following the death of Sir Malachy Kelly (1851-1916).</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13077-4, NAI-CSO-RP-1916-5620-13077-4</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/557</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1081">Philip C. MacDermot</persName>
              <date>1916-07-29T00:00:00</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0885">Boyle, County Roscommon, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0815">Henry Arthur Wynne</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0557_img_1942_1"  type="Letter"  url="2685dee00331ff1c6be58cd9e017e641.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0557_img_1942_1"/>
                OFFICE OF CROWN SOLICITOR FOR CO. ROSCOMMON  BOYLE.    29th July 1916  <lb/> Cattle Driving off Mather lands. <lb/>Ballinasloe Prosecutions  Dear Sir   I am in receipt of your letter of yesterday's date. <lb/>From what the district inspector writes to me about Harvey, it will <lb/>not matter much if the police are not are not able to arrest him, as he is <lb/>a tramp Labourer and he is in no way interested in the dispute, and <lb/>appears (the District Inspector tells me) to have merely joined <lb/>in the Cattle Drive with the crowd, but probably he may be found <lb/>before next Saturday.   I note that I am to send Brief to Mr John Cusack, I am <lb/>writing to him telling him that he will get it in a few days, <lb/>probably by Tuesday's post. The District Inspector has the file <lb/>of evidence, I have telegraphed to him to return it to me toâday <lb/>and I shall set to having it briefed on Monday as you are aware <lb/>it is rather long and probably I will not have it finished until <lb/>Tuesday.  What fee is Mr Cusack to get?   I expected a telegram from the District Inspector as to what <lb/>was done at Ballinasloe toâday, but I have not heard from him so <lb/>far.  Since writing this for telegram from the D.I. the cases were adjourned to 5th <lb/>August. Pat Murray too ill to attend. Harvey has been arrested <lb/>&amp; his case also adjourned: all out on bail  <seg type="closer"> Yours truly  <hi rend="underline">Philip C. MacDermot</hi>   Chief Crown Solicitor,  Dublin Castle  </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>