<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1397">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sir John Maxwell to Lord French, 16 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>John Grenfell Maxwell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from sir John Maxwell (1859-1929) to sir John French, first Earl of Ypres (1852-1925), commander of all British forces on home service. This letter refers primarily to the suppression of the Rising. Maxwell refers to an &#39;intemperate and groundless&#39; speech made by John Dillon MP (1851-1927). This is likely Dillon&#39;s demands for an end to executions in the House of Commons on 10 and 11 May 1916. He further discusses debate in the House and in the media. Maxwell admits that there have been &#39;one or two regrettable incidents&#39;, particularly the killing of pacifist Francis Sheehy Skeffington (1878 – 1916) by Captain Bower Colthurst, but remarks that in general the men had behaved with ‘commendable moderation’. He is, however, critical of the Irish administration (‘rotten from A to Z’) and the police.Sir John Henry Grenfell Maxwell was appointed commander in chief of the British forces in Ireland after the outbreak of the Easter Rising. Before 1916, Maxwell briefly held command of British troops in Egypt, where he successfully organised defences against a Turkish attack in February 1915 and presided over the huge expansion of his command as Egypt became a major British imperial military base. In March 1916, having been superseded as general officer commanding in Egypt, he was recalled home when the Easter Rising broke out. Sir John Denton Pinkstone French, first Earl of Ypres, was a British officer. Upon the outbreak of war, French was appointed Field Marshal of the British Expeditionary Force (BEF). Although popular with his men, the failure of his offensives, Neuve-Chapelle and Loos, to break the German lines and his criticism of the home government led to his replacement as Field Marshal by sir Douglas Haig (1861-1928) in late 1915. French was appointed Commander in Chief of the Home forces in January 1916.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>De Valera Papers, P150/512</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1397</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0174">John Grenfell Maxwell</persName>
              <date>1916-05-16</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1917">Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0358">John Denton Pinkstone French</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1397_img_782_1"  type="Letter"  url="852e22e922fcd34aad7e67ed72bf6163.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1397_img_782_2"  type="Letter"  url="9da3bff65d938ff21e96cd85a078a59f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1397_img_782_3"  type="Letter"  url="ea235ca4514f7b7ed86397b58bd022a0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1397_img_782_4"  type="Letter"  url="6bc401035e6cee6b9aa57f53bc2d6d12.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1397_img_782_1"/>
              <hi rend="underline">copy</hi>    Headquarters Irish Command,  Parkgate, Dublin.    <hi rend="underline">16-5-16</hi>   Dear Lord French,   I think on the whole <lb/> it will be better if you postpone <lb/> your visit to Ireland.  Give the troops &amp; the situation time <lb/> to settle down if this is possible. <lb/> Dillons intemperate &amp; groundless speech <lb/> has raised the whole Irish question <lb/> &amp; we will have to be very careful â <lb/> These courts are keeping me in Dublin. <lb/> I must be here. The Prime Minister is <lb/> filling his head with facts, how he will <lb/> use them is his affair &amp; we must <lb/> 'wait &amp; see'.  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1397_img_782_2"/>
              There is no doubt that there have been <lb/> one or two most regrettable incidents! <lb/>The Skeffington case will be very tiresome <lb/> &amp; give rise to much feeling for and <lb/> against! He must be tried by Court <lb/> Martial - I have asked for L<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi><seg type="unclear">Highmore</seg> as <lb/> President, for we must have an experienced officer <lb/> to deal with these excitable Irish KCs etc <hi rend="superscript">s</hi> etc. <lb/>The Prime Minister insists on its being tried in <lb/> open court. In all about 4 cases have come <lb/> to light which may necessitate trial, as much <lb/> to give the accused a fair <seg type="del">trial</seg>chance as <lb/> anything else. With inexperienced officers, NCOs, <lb/> &amp; young soldiers, the house to house fighting &amp; sniping <lb/> etc. gave many the jumps, but on the whole I am <lb/> of the opinion the troops behaved with <lb/> commendable moderation. The proof of <lb/> this is that now fighting is over,  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1397_img_782_3"/>
              <lb/>they mix with the population as before <lb/> except perhaps in the worst slums of Dublin. <lb/> One thing is quite certain, Great Britain does <lb/> not understand &amp; will not have Martial Law - <lb/> It is a bogey but thank God we have the <lb/> Defence of the Realm act. But with <lb/> Parliament sitting &amp; Ministers answering rotten <lb/> questions - 'J.G.Maxwell in Ireland, with <lb/> plenary powers is what the French would <lb/> call <seg type="foreign">'un facon de parler'</seg>  There is no use trying to do what will <lb/> be undone in Parliament. If such <lb/> speeches as Dillons are allowed to be <lb/> made public because they are delivered <lb/> in the House of Commons you can not <lb/> well take action against an Irish <lb/> newspaper for doing the same â  In my humble judgement the <lb/> Government of Ireland is rotten from  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1397_img_782_4"/>
              <lb/>from A to Z. there are lots of pomps &amp; <lb/>vanities which really please no one but <lb/> no grip on the country or its idiosyncrasies <lb/>any where. The Irish Constabulary is a <lb/> farce, a magnificent body of men certainly, <lb/> but singularly out of sympathy with the <lb/> people, and centralised in the North. <lb/> In my opinion you will never rule Ireland <lb/> from Dublin Castle, there is far too much <lb/> reporting &amp; nothing happening, because no one <lb/> has authority to act on even trivial things, <lb/> which ought to be settled out of hand.  One thing all Irishmen seem to know &amp; that <lb/> is law, and if one does not watch it, they <lb/> catch you out at once.  I ought to pop over &amp; see my sick wife <lb/> but I don't see my way to, unless I can <lb/> escape on Saturday &amp; return Sunday. <seg type="closer"> Sincerely  <hi rend="underline">J.G.Maxwell</hi> </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>