<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_2696">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Dorothy to Maria Duffin, 22 March 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Dorothy Duffin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is part of a rich correspondence between various members of the Duffin family, a large prosperous family living in Strandtown, Belfast. Several family members served in the war, including Major Terence Duffin, who served as a staff officer with 107 Brigade, and later with Royal Irish Rifles; Major Charles G Duffin MC, Royal Field Artillery; and their sisters Emma, Celia and Dorothy who served as Voluntary Aid Detachments (VADS) in Egypt and France, and with the YMCA.

Dorothy tells of time spent with her sister Celia in London and a visit to St. John&#39;s Gate. She has been seeking employment and she made enquiries about a VAD clerkship. She has written a second time to Mrs. Arnold-Foster looking for a letter of introduction for the Admiralty.

She encloses letters written by her sister Emma who is a VAD in Alexandria, Egypt.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Duffin Papers, D2109/10/1/C/31/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/2696</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1065">Dorothy Duffin</persName>
              <date>1916-03-22</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0232">Ardeevin, Epsom, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0664">Maria Duffin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1066">Dunowen, Belfast, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2696_img_2117_1"  type="Letter"  url="61e5ebcbd6d7d50237b13e8b3a6321f6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2696_img_2117_2"  type="Letter"  url="0595a3e2ad336be49e3e7acc5a1e3723.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2696_img_2117_3"  type="Letter"  url="0ca8ee81bcbb8fb24143a88d2ed78146.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_2696_img_2117_4"  type="Letter"  url="48746014a61bb5510eedaa6767995082.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_2696_img_2117_1"/>
             <hi rend="underline">Wednesday</hi> <lb/>22.3.16   Ardeevin. Epsom   Dearest Mamma   Celia stayed Monday night<lb/> here &amp; we had a day together yesterday.<lb/> She expects to get another day off next<lb/> week as work is slack they are being <lb/> given a litter extra. She looked very well<lb/> &amp; cheerful. We made an expedition to<lb/> St John's Gate &amp; interviewed Lady <seg type="unclear">Oliver</seg><lb/> who was covered with orders etc. She<lb/> was very pleasant &amp; told Celia she thought<lb/> there was little chance of her getting<lb/> <seg type="unclear">abroad</seg> but she will consult her Matron<lb/> but said she knew what Celia's Matron<lb/> was! I asked about V A D clerkships<lb/> they have to sign on for <hi rend="underline">a</hi> <hi rend="underline">year</hi> get<lb/> £1 a week &amp; pay for their keep &amp; lodgings<lb/> &amp; I presume washing. I don't think it is<lb/> much good. St John's Gate was a nice<lb/> place to see. So old &amp; interesting. We lost<lb/> ourselves once or twice but managed to<lb/> meet Uncle Edmund for lunch at the<lb/> Haymarket Stores. then we  went  on to St
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_2696_img_2117_2"/>
            James theatre ( treated by Aunt F) &amp; saw<lb/> <seg type="unclear">George</seg> Alexander in ' The Banker'.<lb/> It was most melodramatic but quite<lb/> amusing. I shall try to meet Celia<lb/> again next week. To-morrow Aunt<lb/> F proposes going to town with me &amp;<lb/> seeing various people ( addressed given<lb/> me by Miss Sherlock) I wish she would<lb/> not trouble to come with me but<lb/> she is kindness itself. I think she<lb/> &amp; Uncle Edmund like having me .<lb/> <hi rend="underline">The baby</hi>  Gill Eggar  has taken a great fancy<lb/> to me — a nice wee plain thing<lb/> Emmie has cabled that she has<lb/> settled to remain in <seg type="unclear">India</seg> for the<lb/> present. I do wonder when we shall<lb/> hear about our Emma.   To-night we dine with the <seg type="unclear">club women</seg><lb/> for whom I have no liking.   Aunt F thinks the best time for <lb/> your visit would be the beginning of<lb/> May. In April the <seg type="unclear">Henley</seg> children
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_2696_img_2117_3"/>
            &amp; Harry's may be here &amp; Uncle Edmund<lb/> expects to get his holiday the second<lb/> half of May when he &amp; Aunt F will<lb/> go away all plans are however a<lb/> little vague but Aunt F is most<lb/> anxious you should come so I do hope<lb/> you'll make the effort.   I have written to Mrs Arnold <seg type="unclear">Foster</seg><lb/> again asking for a possible introduction<lb/> at the Admiralty what my next <lb/> step should be. I expect it is the<lb/> best sort of job going but requires<lb/> push.   What a <seg type="unclear">tragedy</seg> about Colonel Hill — <seg type="unclear">Turner</seg><lb/> What is the mystery? I remember the<lb/> night he dined with us he asked me<lb/> to sing <seg type="foreign">'La Vie est Vaine'</seg>!   I trust   <seg type="unclear">Mrs Swiney</seg> will <seg type="del">be</seg>  <lb/> well &amp; if you hear of Mrs <seg type="unclear">Power</seg><lb/> let me know. I want to send her<lb/> a cheque when she is out of hospital   I am glad poor Marjorie is with Charlie<lb/> though I expect she will have long hours
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_2696_img_2117_4"/>
            alone while he is at work. You <lb/>do not say <hi rend="underline">where</hi> they are?   I had a very kind letter from Mrs <lb/><seg type="unclear">Donnet</seg> asking me there &amp; I think <lb/>I shall go when I leave this. Olive <lb/>urges me to     She says the <lb/>Colonel is better but unfit for work.   The weather is wet here but we <lb/>shall be going out for a parole <lb/>soon! <hi rend="underline">Harry</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline"><seg type="unclear">Jamie</seg></hi>  Garrett  have both <lb/>been seedy but I think I am to <lb/>be taken over to Cormac shortly. <lb/>Aunt Fanny could have you here <lb/><hi rend="underline">now</hi> but I fancy May will be better.   I enclose letters from Emma returned <lb/>by Olive. Perhaps you would like to <lb/>put the one to me in your book, <lb/>it is interesting.   Best Love   <hi rend="underline">Dorothy</hi> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>