<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5249">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Upton Tyrrell to William J.H. Tyrrell 6, January, 1919</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Upton Tyrrell</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>References the rise of Sinn Fein.
</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>OPW-Maynooth University Archive &amp; Research Centre at Castletown</repository>
                  <collection>Ballindoolin Archive, Folder 1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5249</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0461">William Upton Tyrrell</persName>
              <date>1919-01-06</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">William J.H. Tyrrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1321">Ballindoolin House, Ballindoolin, Edenderry, Kings Co., Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1979</item>
               <item n="topic">Personal Relations</item>
               <item n="topic">1917-1919</item>
               <item n="topic">The Rising Tide (1917-1919)</item>
               <item n="topic">War of Independence (1919-1921)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5249_img_None_1"  url="6fdb4d6b3e467d1395414549f87cc687.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5249_img_None_2"  url="65514b67b29ef06e749267a7cdcc4088.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5249_img_0_1"/>
              6/1/19   My dear Daddy  <sic>Iwas</sic> delighted to get your letter of the<lb/>30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> today. I hope you will have a good<lb/>shoot on the 8<hi rend="superscript">th </hi>&amp; I will be thinking of you<lb/>all day and wishing I was there too. I am afraid<lb/>I was much too optimistic about leave in my<lb/>last letter as now I don't expect I will get it<lb/>before the end of the month at the earliest.<lb/>There were two others to go before me who had<lb/>been forgotten altogether so that will make<lb/>mine a fortnight later but that can't be<lb/>helped and so we must make the best of it.  I wish I could bring Nellie over when I come<lb/>too as I want you to know her soon but<lb/>I am afraid it will be quite impossible this<lb/>time. You could not have her work at the<lb/>bank. I saw all about th Sinn Feiners in the<lb/>papers and I also see great articles in the<lb/>English papers about what they are threatening<lb/>to do. If there is a general strike on [??] 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5249_img_0_2"/>
             get home I suppose I will have to walk from<lb/>Dublin and wont we be able to telegraph to you<lb/>to come to meet me. I will get home somehow<lb/>anyway. I hope the Sinn Feiners have not<lb/>pinched my gun on its way. Where was it<lb/>coming from. If I do get leave shall I bring<lb/>a few cartridges from London <hi rend="underline">if I can get them.</hi>  Be sure and tell me that when you next<lb/>write. I spent today seeing Waterloo thoroughly<lb/>and [??] did everything. I saw just where<lb/>Wellington &amp; Napoleon &amp; all the other big wigs<lb/>slept and had breakfast and <seg type="del">every</seg> all that<lb/>sort of thing. We came to the conclusion that it<lb/>was as well for those people that there were no<lb/>aeroplanes in those days. I could not find any<lb/>dud shells or anything like that for a souvenier  No news &amp; must shut up with very best<lb/>love to all.   Your most affectionate Son<lb/>Willie  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>