<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_3867">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, 28 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Francis Fletcher-Vane</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Major Francis Fletcher-Vane (1861-1934) to Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946) regarding a full enquiry into the circumstances surrounding the death of Francis Sheehy Skeffington. Vane outlines the ways in which procedure was ignored or altered following Skeffington&#39;s death and determines that this is reasoning enough for a full inquiry. Cane also mentions that he has written a letter to the Freeman&#39;s Journal regarding the rebels chivalry in South Dublin Union during the rebellion.

Major Sir Francis Patrick Fletcher-Vane was a British officer in command of Portobello Barracks. When he learned about the activities of Captain J.C.Bowen-Colthurst during Easter Week he reported the matter to his superiors but, sensing a cover-up, he went to London and reported it directly to Lord Kitchener and Maurice Bonham Carter, Private Secretary to the Prime Minister. Although Bowen-Colthurst was court-martialled and found guilty, Vane was &#39;retired&#39; from the military for his actions.

Hanna Sheehy Skeffington (1877-1946), suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the founder of the Irish Women’s Franchise League and a founding member of the Irish Women Workers’ Union. She was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916. She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband, Francis (1878-1916), and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full details of his execution emerged.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Sheehy Skeffington Papers, Collection List No. 47; Ms 33,608/1-3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/3867</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0659">Francis Fletcher-Vane</persName>
              <date>1916-07-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1846">National Liberal Club, Whitehall Place, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Hanna Sheehy Skeffington</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1934</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Law and Judiciary</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3867_img_3247_1"  type="Letter"  url="24728ebdc3efe413780e80a97f486e1e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3867_img_3247_2"  type="Letter"  url="afa8d9252144a5d57e326da08d5990e4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_3867_img_3247_3"  type="Letter"  url="2471aedf097ba6750c0f2d3479c636ac.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_3867_img_3247_1"/>
              NATIONAL LIBERAL CLUB, <lb/>WHITEHALL PLACE, S.W.     Thank you so much for the <lb/>Songs. I am having them type <lb/>written and put into a book.     28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July 1916     My Dear Mrs Skeffington,    I am right up to my neck in it now — <lb/>2 Questions to be asked on Tuesday next <lb/>in the House and neither question can <lb/>be answered for I have the documentary <lb/>evidence. You realise of course that <lb/>this is all working for the object that <lb/>we all have in view. Namely a full <lb/>enquiry. They are even in a worse <lb/>Dilemma over me than even the infinitely <lb/>cruel one of yours. Although Gotto work in <lb/>together. In your poor husband's case <lb/>they can say — "well very unfortunate. a " <lb/>"madman at large — we did not of course" <lb/>"know of it. Very lamentable et cet". <lb/>All this flummary is dispelled when I <lb/>put in my oar, because I make it clear
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_3867_img_3247_2"/>
            <lb/>that there was <seg type="unclear">connivance</seg> in the murders <lb/>up to the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May — not by the Government but <lb/>by the Irish |Command, as clear as daylight. <lb/>Then of course the deliberate suppression of <lb/>the report of the Brigadier of the 178<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Brigade <lb/>on my action in the field by Sir J. Maxwell. <lb/>You will hardly follow me here without some <lb/>explanation. It is absolutely the universal <lb/>custom in the Army that when a General <lb/>Officer Commanding in the field reports to <lb/>a superior office (in this case Sir. J. Maxwell) <lb/>on the conduct of officers in his command, <lb/>and when the Superior General <seg type="del">is w</seg> was <lb/>not present — that the report of the <lb/>officer seen in command goes into the <lb/>Privy Council verbatim.   Now Sir J. Maxwell was not even in <lb/>Ireland when the Brigadier reported on <lb/>my action, and not in command. <lb/>But he suppresses the report and <lb/>sent a private one of his own which was
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_3867_img_3247_3"/>
            <lb/>adverse to me — and by that adverse one <lb/>I was "relegated to unemployment."   You will see the bearing of this in connection <lb/>with your case if you will think it out. <lb/>Sir John Maxwell did an unheard of thing in <lb/>the Army, so as to <seg type="del">prevent</seg> try to prevent, <lb/>in an imbicile manner, my having the <lb/>influence which naturally this report <lb/>of the Brigadier would have obtained <lb/>for me.   He tried in fact to suggest that I was in <lb/>sympathy with the rebels, by suppressing <lb/>a fact which would, <seg type="del">were</seg> had it been <lb/>published, have denied the possibility of it. <lb/>Of course the report has been called for, <lb/>and he altogether forgot that I have <lb/>enough influence, or aim, to break him <lb/>if I will.   Of course I have called for the report and <lb/>have demanded that whan the P.M. and <lb/>Lord Kitchener said on my reporting the murders, <lb/>should be produced.   On the whole the interest of Justice and <lb/>Truth goes well —and if it goes well, <lb/>in spite of <seg type="del">the</seg> brutality and stupidity, <lb/>the cause of Ireland will go well, and <lb/>this is what your husband wanted !!   I wrote a note to the Freemans Journal <lb/>as to my experience of the chivalry of the <lb/>rebels in the fight at the S.Dublin Union. <lb/>I hope they will be allowed to publish it.   The Inquiry must come soon, and do <lb/>not forget St.W.M.Gibbon, I.S.C who <lb/>can give valuable evidence.   Love to Owen, tell him to be as his Father <lb/>was, a Knight Errant.    Yours sincerely <lb/> Francis Patrick Vane  <lb/>of Hutton.  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>