<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0691">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from James Davidson to his mother, Clara Mary Davidson, 19 January 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>James Davidson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from James Davidson (1877-1916) to his mother, Clara. Davidson writes of his recent illness as well as his work with the Machine Gun Company. He asks his mother if she could request a different cake be sent to the men as they only ever get plain cakes. He hopes he might be in line for leave soon.This letter is part of a large correspondence from Captain James Davidson to his parents. Davidson, who was Managing Director of the Sirocco Engineering Works in Belfast, served with 13 Royal Irish Rifles and the Machine Gun Corps. His letters describe his experiences while training in England and serving in France. He was killed on 1 July 1916, the first day of the Battle of the Somme.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Davidson Family Papers, D3642/B/8/24</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/691</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1196">James Davidson</persName>
              <date>1916-01-19</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0171">In the Field</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">S.C. Davidson </persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1506">Seacourt, Bangor, Co. Down</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0691_img_2182_1"  type="Letter"  url="a7cb4cd6efc9b34b2c56a11084bc081e.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0691_img_2182_2"  type="Letter"  url="9ac97d9e95793f9ffc9745261674390c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0691_img_2182_3"  type="Letter"  url="6e6fd3d7e0102a609acb5fdec2cc62f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0691_img_2182_4"  type="Envelope"  url="d34aa2a02f93680e77f9607d5710bbcb.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0691_img_2182_1"/>
                19/1/16   My dearest Mother —    I have been troubled with <lb/>my throat for some days past &amp; today had to stay <lb/> in bed as it was feeling so sore &amp; inflamed when <lb/> I wakened. This evening it is a good deal <lb/> easier &amp; I got up, so am in hopes that by tomorrow <lb/> it will be nearly all right again.  I think it <lb/> is an unhealthy place here &amp; then the weather <lb/> has been awfully wet which does not improve <lb/> matters.  I think it must be almost a <lb/> week since I wrote last. I have been having a <lb/> busy time of it as I got instructions from the <lb/> Division that the Machine Gun Company for this <lb/> Brigade was to be formed almost at once &amp; to make <lb/> all necessary preparations. At present, the machine <lb/> guns of course are with the Batts. but the new <lb/> organisation is to withdraw them &amp; form a <lb/> separate unit.  It will be a very nice little <lb/> command for me once it is organised &amp; <lb/> running smoothly but like all new things in <lb/> the Army practically no information is available <lb/> &amp; one is left to get over all the difficulties in <lb/> the best way one can.  The Company is <lb/> 150 strong with 16 guns &amp; transport etc  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0691_img_2182_2"/>
              <lb/>&amp; no less than 52 horses. I shall have <lb/> 8 officers &amp; they are all good chaps so we <lb/> should be quite a happy little mess. Dermot <lb/> Neill son of S.O. Neill will be second in Command <lb/> &amp; I could not have wished for a better.  I have been getting things arranged as far as <lb/> possible but there is still such a lot to be done <lb/> &amp; it is going to be a very troublesome job for <lb/> me for some time. You see I have so <lb/> far not had any experience of the running <lb/> of a Company &amp; though we shall be a very <lb/> small unit there will be just the same <lb/> number of returns &amp; books to be kept as a <lb/> full Batt.    I dont suppose the Company <lb/> will be formed for a week or so yet, possibly <lb/> more, but I shall then be leaving the Brigade <lb/> H.Q.<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> &amp; remain with the Company. I don't <lb/> know yet what the Company is to be called <lb/> but in the meantime letters addressed as at <lb/> present will find me.   In your last <lb/> letter you asked about stockings — I have <lb/> plenty of these thanks Mother dear &amp; indeed <lb/> have no need of anything except a small <lb/> bottle of quinine. I have been taking a good <lb/> deal for my throat &amp; almost finished my <lb/> small supply.   With regard to the parcel  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0691_img_2182_3"/>
              <lb/>from Malcomsons which arrives each week <lb/> would you please tell them to send some <lb/> different kind of cake. They send the same <lb/> one almost every time. A gingerbread would <lb/> be very nice or one of the plainer kind.  My new orderly is now installed &amp; doing <lb/> very well — a great improvement on the <lb/> previous one who had become too careless — <lb/> so I am glad i made the change.  Must stop now &amp; get back back to bed — <lb/> do hope I shall be quite better tomorrow as <lb/> we have to do a staff ride with the General <lb/> tomorrow.  Hoping all are well &amp; <lb/> with fondest love. <seg type="closer"> Your loving son  James </seg><seg type="postscript"> I was hoping there would be a chance of getting <lb/> leave home soon but if the M.G. Coy. is really <lb/> formed at an early date I am afraid I won't <lb/> be able to get away for some time. If <lb/> there is any delay about the formation I <lb/> will try &amp; obtain my leave as soon <lb/> as possible. Jim. </seg> 
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0691_img_2182_4"/>
               On Active Service Wed 23<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="superscript">rd</hi></hi> Janry/16   Mrs. S.C. Davidson  Seacourt  Bangor  Co. Down  Ireland   J.Davidson   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>