<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0930">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Aidan Nolan to Lady Clonbrock, 29 December 1915</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Aidan Nolan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from a prisoner of war, Aidan Nolan, Connaught Rangers, to Lady Clonbrock (1839-1928). Nolan was incarcerated in Limburg, Germany at the time. Nolan writes to thank Lady Clonbrock for the parcel of socks she sent him.Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS 35,796 /14 (15) (Collection List 54), MS 35,796 /14 (15) (Collection List 54)</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/930</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0870">Aidan Nolan</persName>
              <date>1915-12-29</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0667">Limburg, Germany</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lady Clonbrock (Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton)</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1862">Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0930_img_270_1"  type="Letter"  url="142c5a0663fe2aac8ce6f9ca189351ff.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0930_img_270_2"  type="Letter"  url="e035e65e116bc314914b25d9c2855a45.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0930_img_270_1"/>
               Kriegsgefangenenlager <lb/>  Limburg,      November 27th 1915   Lady Clonbrock   I hasten to acknowledge receipt of your most <lb/> welcome parcel of socks. I cannot say how delighted <lb/> I was to get them as the weather is getting rather cold. We are <lb/> having plenty of snow this week, hence the value of <lb/> warm clothing. I earnestly trust Your Ladyship <lb/> will accept this card as all the gratitude which <lb/> a grateful prisoner can show again thanking Your <lb/> Ladyship. <seg type="closer"> I am Gratefully Yours  Pte Aidan Nolan </seg>  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0930_img_270_2"/>
               <lb/>Gefangenenlager <lb/>Limburg (Lahn). <lb/>This is my address: <lb/>KriegsgefangenenâSendung <lb/>9454. Pte Aidan Nolan Conn. Rangers <lb/> II. Bat. 6 Comp. No. 709 <lb/>Limburg (Lahn) Germany <lb/>(Answer on Post-Card or by open letter, please).  Right side  lb/>Feldpostbrief <lb/>KriegsgefangenenâSendung <lb/>Address:   Lady Clonbrock  Clonbrock,  Ahascragh,  County Galway  Ireland.     
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>