<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_5484">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from J.H. Morgan to Herbert Samuel, 4 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>J.H. Morgan</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>The letter is from the lawyer John Hartman Morgan (1876-1955) to Herbert Samuel (1870-1963), secretary of state for the Home Office. Morgan was an expert in constitutional law and was working with the British propaganda department on German atrocities but served as counsel for Sir Roger Casement (1864-1916) in his treason trial, with whom he had corresponded previously. Casement had been imprisoned in London after he had been arrested while landing on the coast of Kerry in a submarine on the eve of the Easter Rising. A campaign was launched featuring many prominent figures such as W.B. Yeats and George Bernard Shaw to secure a reprieve for Casement but he was hanged on 3 August 1916.
The letter was written the day after Casement&#39;s death and Morgan requests the return of Casement&#39;s body to his cousin, Gertrude Bannister, for burial in Ireland. He argues that Casement had already suffered the highest punishment possible and that the &#39;pitiful request&#39; of his relative should be granted on human grounds. Casement&#39;s remains were not, in fact, returned to Ireland until 1965, when he was interred in Glasnevin Cemetery in Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Roger Casement Papers, Collection List No A15; Ms. 13,078 /7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/5484</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0580">J.H. Morgan</persName>
              <date>1916-08-04</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2051">1 Mitre Court Building, Temple, London, UK</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1103">Herbert Samuel</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0856">Home Office, Whitehall, London, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1955</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5484_img_517_1"  type="Letter"  url="b0c3ad45815aab83eb610996228a7951.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_5484_img_517_2"  type="Letter"  url="612dea273df8a908b15558538893e8be.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_5484_img_517_1"/>
             1 Mitre Court Buildings. <lb/> Temple. E. C.   4th August 1916.   Dear Mr Samuel,   The day before yesterday I called at the House <lb/> of Commons to see you in order to support the request of <lb/> Miss Gertrude Bannister that the body Roger Casement might <lb/> be handed over to her for private burial. I did this because I <lb/> was deeply moved by the distress of a noble woman whose unflinching <lb/> devotion to her cousin through the long-drawn agony <lb/> of his trial was such as to provoke my profound admiration &amp; <lb/> respect. I did not - indeed as Counsel I could not - support <lb/> the movement for a reprieve. But he has paid the full <lb/> penalty - he has not only died a felon's death on the scaffold <lb/> but before dying he was publicly degraded of all his honours, <lb/> a step for which I believe there is no precedent in any treason <lb/> case in the last 300 years. The law has therefore exacted its uttermost.   Under these circumstances it is surely not asking <lb/> too much to ask that the pitiful request of his relatives be <lb/> granted. Roger Casement is now beyond the reach of human <lb/> vengeance; it cannot matter to him whether his body remains in <lb/> a felon's grave in Pentonville or not. But it matters a great <lb/> deal to this unhappy lady sorrowing under a sorrow almost too <lb/> grievous for any man or woman to bear. I cannot conceive
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_5484_img_517_2"/>
            petition which it would be easier for the authorities to <lb/> grant &amp; harder for any humane person to refuse. It is not <lb/> for me to urge any questions of policy though I can imagine <lb/> few things more likely to exasperate Irish opinion than an <lb/> implacable severity which wounds the living while it is quite <lb/> powerless to harm the dead. Moreover there is a very strong <lb/> feeling abroad - the "Times" gives expression to it this morning <lb/> that someone in authority "inspired" a campaign of malignant <lb/> &amp; studied calumny against the prisoner which was not only <lb/> not necessary to the course of Justice but calculated to per- <lb/>vert it. It is surely highly undesirable that any impression <lb/> of ruthlessness should get abroad.   But be that as it may, I do beg of you on grounds of <lb/> humanity to reconsider your decision. Miss Bannister is, <lb/> I understand, prepared to give every guarantee as to privacy.   Yours sincerely,    (Sgd) J.H.Morgan.   The Rt.Hon. Herbert Samuel.M.P. <lb/> Secretary of State. <lb/> The Home Office. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>