<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4282">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Wilfrid Spender to Lillian Spender, 13 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Wilfrid Spender</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Sir Wilfrid Spender (1876 - 1960) to his wife, Lillian (1880-1968). Spender was a member of the British Army until 1913 when controversy surrounding his signature of the Ulster Solemn League and Covenant resulted in his resignation. Spender was called up for military service in 1914 and from 1915 served in the 36th (Ulster) Division. Throughout the war, Spender wrote a collection of letters to his wife Lady Lillian Spender. The letters date mainly from 1915 to 1918, when Sir Wilfrid was serving in France. The letters concern politics, the Irish question, personal life, and Wilfrid&#39;s experience of the Great War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Letters from Sir Wilfrid Spender to Lady Spender, D1633/1/1/220</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4282</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0667">Wilfrid Spender</persName>
              <date>1916-04-13</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Lillian Spender</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1960</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4282_img_3646_1"  type="Letter"  url="b4b1cb6d46adee9ad46dbbac0b4d5ba8.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4282_img_3646_2"  type="Letter"  url="80aa34251811f15e904cbb79b1d926c2.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4282_img_3646_1"/>
             Ap.13.   Dear Lil   Thanks for your interesting <lb/>comments on the political situation.   I am ashamed ! The padded <lb/>statement by Squiffy is <lb/>advisedly to stifle all allusions <lb/>to freespeaking.   The papers on the other <lb/>side write as if it was <lb/>traiterous to want to put <lb/>men into the Government <lb/>who would carry on the war <lb/>more vigorously. They threaten <lb/>all kinds of rifts. We have <lb/>got to go slow so that the <lb/><sic>conscientous</sic> objector may not <lb/>riot, or the pro german <lb/>refuse to pay his usual <lb/>subsidies to free trade <lb/>politics! 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4282_img_3646_2"/>
             I sometimes feel as if <lb/>I should like to chuck all <lb/>interest in political life &amp; <lb/>let our Tammany schemers <lb/>rip, but this is not only <lb/>what they want but <lb/>exactly the real danger to <lb/>our country no less real <lb/>than the German menace.   I suppose something accounts <lb/>for the stopping of leave. <lb/>Perhaps it is to give the Huns <lb/>a fright as they must have <lb/>used up most of their reserves <lb/>at Verdun, tho' they have <lb/>still plenty more behind I <lb/>fancy under training.   Your   Wilfrid B Spender 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>