<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1509">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington to John Dillon, 28 October 1916. </title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>A letter from Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington (1877-1946) to John Dillon (1851-1927). Sheehy-Skeffington encloses particulars, prepared by her landlady, on the visits by detectives to her lodgings. She also encloses the official Police reply to her complaint regarding the visits and the requirements regarding Aliens Form A.R.-E. Referring to the search for her property, she says that the enquiries (by Sgt. Ahern) referred to in the Police reply, ended in July. She also alleges police attempts to contact a number of people to try to get information regarding her whereabouts under false presences. Enclosed here is the memo prepared by Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington on the enquiry in Bowen-Colthurt&#39;s sanity. The enclosed letters mentioned in this letter have all survived.Hanna Sheehy Skeffington, suffragette, nationalist, language teacher, was the widow of Francis Sheehy-Skeffington (who was summarily executed on 26 April 1916). She was active during the Rising, bringing food to the Volunteers in the G.P.O. and the College of Surgeons. Four days passed before she found out what had happened to her husband and it wasn&#39;t until almost two weeks later that the full detail emerged. John Dillon was an Irish Party M.P. in the House of Commons. In a speech in the House on 11 May 1916 he strongly condemned the British handling of the Rising which had been put down “with so much blood and so much savagery”, and called for an immediate end to executions. Mr. Dillon assisted Mrs.Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington in her plea for a public inquiry and in various correspondence relating to the incident and raids on her home.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Trinity College Dublin</repository>
                  <collection>, Ms. 6837/32/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1509</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0617">Hanna Sheehy-Skeffington </persName>
              <date>1916-10-28</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1322">43 Moyne Road, Ranelagh, Dublin, Ireland.</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0477">John Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1509_img_967_1"  type="Letter"  url="e8fc54c6e96887ea0866ed9c983be604.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1509_img_967_2"  type="Letter"  url="f533cd03cd21d55bf906e00e941b0724.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1509_img_967_3"  type="Letter"  url="a25598470fbbab47df615391aebe4cb4.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1509_img_967_1"/>
                43 Moyne Rd.    28.10.16   Dear Mr. Dillon,   I enclose particulars which my landlady has <lb/> written with dates of the various visits &amp; inquiries. <lb/>You will see then Sergt. <hi rend="underline">McGahey's</hi> visits had no reference <lb/> to 'permit', but only to my movements while Constable <lb/>Devine called on <hi rend="underline">Oct 9th</hi> for her permit, as she has <lb/> to return this after visiting her husband in <hi rend="underline">Oldcastle </hi><lb/> (not England)  which she did on Oct-7 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. The visits about me <lb/>began on Oct 11 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; lasted till Oct 19 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &amp; had no <lb/>reference to her or her husband. It is clear that <lb/> Devine has all this entered in <seg type="del">th</seg> his note-book <lb/> which he can produce: in it he has also my <lb/>sister's address &amp; my father's, as he took both. <lb/>My sister can identify the men who watched <lb/> the house (&amp; the ambulance) &amp; she tells me <lb/> she saw one of these men in uniform last <lb/> Friday outside Rathmines Police Station. When <lb/>I returned I found my landlady quite terrorized <lb/> &amp; apparently fearful of taking me back until <lb/> she had obtained Sergt. McGahey's permission! <lb/>I also enclose copy of police reply to my formal <lb/>complaint: you will see that in it admission is <lb/><seg type="del">not</seg> made as to some questions re No.7 dealing  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1509_img_967_2"/>
              <lb/>with 'permanent residence'. As I have given up my house it is <lb/>obvious that there's no 'permanent residence' at present. <lb/> I suppose it is useless to expect truth from the <lb/> police, but I hope these inquiries will prevent <lb/> further persecution &amp; am greatly obliged to you &amp; <lb/> Mr. O'Connor for following the matter up.   I should add that Hearn's inquiries re <lb/>my property terminated <hi rend="underline">last July</hi>. He was sent <lb/>by the police to trace some of it in various <lb/> barracks.   In addition bogus messages were sent (by <lb/>the police, I have no reason to doubt) to my <lb/>solicitor, to the <seg type="del">Collage of Science</seg> College of Science &amp; to my <lb/>sister in the name of personal friends <lb/> of mine for my address 'on urgent business' <lb/> &amp; I find an inquiry from these friends <lb/> that they knew nothing of the matter â <lb/>it was done over the 'phone.   I enclose as requested mem. re Balch. I <lb/>shall be glad to have <hi rend="underline">blue book</hi> of evidence <lb/> published, as it is vital for any debate. <lb/>Would it be possible to get the medical evidence produced <lb/> at Courtmartial also published?  <seg type="closer"> Yours Sincerely  H.S. Skeffington </seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1509_img_967_3"/>
              Notes re Inquiry.   <hi rend="underline">Dr. Balce</hi>,  Chief  Medical Officer in charge of Portobello <lb/> Barracks Hospital is stated to have refused <lb/> to certify Colthurst insane. Balch had for <lb/> years been attached to Portobello &amp; is a man <lb/> of standing in the profession. The only Portobello <lb/> Barracks medical man called <seg type="del">was a given</seg> to <lb/> testify to Colthurst's mental state at Courtmartial <lb/> was a junior Officer called McTurk who ad- <lb/>mitted inexperience &amp; had no special qualifications.   Balch was suddenly deprived of his post <lb/> in Portobello &amp; transferred to 'Sierra Leone' <lb/> to his great surprise &amp; disappointment. This <lb/> happened between the Courtmartial &amp; the <lb/>Inquiry. It was found that he was of <lb/> Austrian descent &amp; this seems to have <lb/> been brought up against him as a pretext <lb/>for sudden transfer. Inquiries made re above <lb/> at Inquiry were ruled out 'as outside the scope of <lb/>inquiry.'   [The above is information that came knowledge <lb/> of my legal advisers from an authoritative source.]  <seg type="closer"> H.S.S. </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>