<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0323">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Emma Armstrong to Lady Clonbrock, 2 August 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Emma Armstrong</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Emma Armstrong to Augusta Caroline Dillon, Lady Clonbrock (1840-1928), asking Clonbrock if she can use her influence to have a soldier named Cawley transferred from the front to home service. Cawley&#39;s father is getting too old to work and only has a young son at home; his daughters bar one are married and three sons have been killed in the war. She also mentions the health of her husband and the upcoming Chelsea Flower Show.Augusta Caroline Dillon (née Crofton) was the wife of Luke Gerald Dillon (1834-1917), the 4th Baron of Clonbrock, Co. Galway and the daughter of Lord Crofton of Mote Park (Edward Henry Churchill Crofton, 3rd Baron), Co. Roscommon. Aged 75 at the outbreak of war, Lady Clonbrock, worked closely with the Irish Women&#39;s Association to send basic necessities to Irish POWs. Many of her care packages went to members of the Connaught Rangers imprisoned in Limburg near Cologne.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Clonbrock Estate Papers, Collection List No. 54;, Ms. 35,796/10/7</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/323</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0896">Emma Armstrong</persName>
              <date>1916-08-02</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0328">Mount Pleasant Avenue, Ballinasloe, County Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0483">Augusta Caroline Dillon</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1381">Ahascragh, County Galway, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0323_img_1547_1"  type="Letter"  url="027d878ffb8d10e42103746498674313.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0323_img_1547_2"  type="Letter"  url="03405d41138422e8d82eaa572dbb5d14.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0323_img_1547_1"/>
                Mrs. E.G.Armstrong,  Mount Pleasant Avenue, Ballinasloe,  Co. Galway.    Aug 2 1916   Dear Lady Clonbrock   I wonder if you could with any <lb/>influence while you are in London to <lb/>get young Cawley â Oliver Royal Engineers <lb/>transferred to home service â I enclose <lb/>his letter â I wrote some months ago <lb/>&amp; the War Office reply was they sympathised <lb/>greatly with his father but could not do anything â  Old Cawley is not old enough to get <lb/>old age pension â &amp; is getting too old <lb/>to do much in the way of chimney <lb/>sweeping â his wife died of consumption <lb/>about six months after the war broke out <lb/>&amp; <hi rend="underline">1</hi> married &amp; <hi rend="underline">2</hi> unmarried sons of his <lb/>have been killed in this war â &amp; he has <lb/>only a small boy about 14 or 15 living with <lb/>him â his daughters are married except <lb/>a delicate girl in the Millhouse Infirmary.  My husband is not very strong <lb/>yet, but is better. I wonder will any  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0323_img_1547_2"/>
              of you be home for the Flower Show â  We expect Jacky here on or before the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>for a few days &amp; then she is going on to <lb/>Mayo â <seg type="closer"> Yours very sincerely  <hi rend="underline">Emma Armstrong</hi> </seg> Cawley <hi rend="underline">R. Eng :</hi> Mrs. Armstrong  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>