<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0732">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Maudie Davin to James Ryan, 6 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Maudie Davin</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Maudie Davin to James Ryan (1891-1970). She apologises for not having written sooner. She tells him about her new house, the efforts to raise money for the National Aid and a new dress she got for one of the National Aid picnics. She warns him jokingly not to be writing affectionate letters to women other than Maureen (Máirín Cregan).James Ryan studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                  <collection>James Ryan Papers, P88/26</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/732</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0612">Maudie Davin</persName>
              <date>1916-07-06</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0581">3 Gross Kevin St., Dublin</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0447">James Ryan</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0732_img_224_1"  type="Letter"  url="35d5c8ebe6123f18cb42535e27d2d4db.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0732_img_224_2"  type="Letter"  url="3dbba56846545e9c6a79fcfae9cd83f5.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0732_img_224_3"  type="Letter"  url="7b0d37520931ab689824177032b7f664.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0732_img_224_4"  type="Letter"  url="a8ac50c1b2ad295987ef8d389d0fa6bc.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0732_img_224_1"/>
                3 Cross Kevin St.    6 <hi rend="superscript"><hi rend="underline">th</hi></hi> July 1916    My Dear Jim,   What you must think of  me  is beyond my <lb/> imagination, never having written you a line yet, well <lb/> anyway the old saying holds good in this case 'Better <lb/> late than never', I hope you don't collapse with <lb/> joy (!!!!!!!) when this reaches you, if you think it might <lb/> be too much for you I would advise you to only <lb/> read about one paragraph a day !!! As you see <lb/> by the address we are living in Kevin (Castle!!! as <lb/> I call it ) St. you remember that <hi rend="underline">charming</hi> spot <lb/> we brought you down to one Saturday we caught <lb/> you giving the 'Evil Eye' to all the 'nice things' in <lb/> Grafton St !!! of course we only let you look at the <lb/> outside, for fear if you came inside you might <lb/> get dazzled with the splendour and luxury ( <seg type="unclear">I</seg>.O.J) <lb/><hi rend="underline">or</hi>, more likely, get <hi rend="underline">lost</hi> particularly as Maureen <lb/> was there!! now, now Jim, I didn't say it might <lb/> be an echo of ' <hi rend="underline">Harrington</hi><hi rend="underline">College</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">Dance</hi>', it was a wonder you didn't get a bill <lb/> from the owners for a new step on the stairs!!! <lb/> or for that matter a whole flight!!!!!! of course that <lb/> was <hi rend="underline">last</hi> year, this year I suppose you would  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0732_img_224_2"/>
              <lb/> like a little change!! I believe Maureen's 'nose <lb/> is out of joint' you're awfully fickle, some <lb/>priest came into your sister a few days ago <lb/>and told her about some girl who 'had a <lb/> few <hi rend="underline">very affectionate</hi> letters from Jim'. A <lb/>certain friend told me she felt horribly <lb/>'taken in' !!!! now take a little advice from an <lb/>'auld pal' and don't be breaking hearts!! but <lb/> excuse me, a new idea has just crossed my <lb/> mind, perhaps you are only just practicing, <lb/>as I daresay when you come home you will <lb/>be writing these <seg type="foreign">'billet doux'</seg> to the wardresses!!   Now to change the subject, we had a couple <lb/> of great picnics for the National Aid 'any amount <lb/> doing' !!! and the cream of the joke was that I <lb/>got a <hi rend="underline">new dress</hi>, the secret of it was that I was <lb/>in great humour and wanted to 'knock down some <lb/>thing good', but it was white voile (you that sort of <lb/>soft stuff!) with enormous big dark blue dots on it, <lb/>you <seg type="del">call</seg> could positively hear me coming in it, <lb/>but all the fellows called me ' <seg type="foreign">pierrot</seg>' and wanted <lb/> to know where was my cap, weren't they <lb/>real cheeky!!! I felt horribly put out (I don't think). <lb/>Godfrey (I'm sure the spelling is wrong but never <lb/>mind!) O'Donnell was there and he's the best gas <lb/>out, I enjoyed him immensely, I remember one  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0732_img_224_3"/>
              time I was up in the <sic>diggs</sic> with Maureen, the <lb/> time she was on the Leinster Road (certainly you <lb/> remember all things connected with <hi rend="underline">that</hi>) and she <lb/>showed me the University College book, and there <lb/> was a programme of a concert <seg type="del">and</seg> in it and our <lb/> friend G. O'Donnell was down for a song 'I am <lb/> a <hi rend="underline">little</hi> Catholic' the underlined word written in <lb/> Italics. I absolutely howled when I saw it, knowing <lb/> the <hi rend="underline">little</hi> Catholic. Of course all this must be fearfully <lb/> dry for the censor, what a pity I haven't time to <lb/> make a sketch of G. O'D so that he might join in <lb/> the joke. Don't forget to give my <hi rend="underline">love</hi> to anyone in <lb/> the camp that you think I might know or who <lb/> might know me, especially S. Peeson, D McCullogh, <lb/> Jack Gogan ( I know him since he was a kid!!). I <lb/> will be writing to them very soon. Maureen will be in <lb/> this evening, that is provided she <sic>dosent</sic> go <hi rend="underline">teaing</hi><lb/> with a certain <hi rend="underline">architect</hi>, Mums the word now Jim, <lb/> just a few little words dropped and I added up <lb/> one and one and made two, I may after a while add <lb/> two and two and possibly make four, so I would <lb/> advise you not to <sic>loose</sic> any time coming home or <lb/> the bird might have flown, and I guess you <lb/> wouldn't like your little heart to be broken!!! <lb/>would you????!!! I will be doing the Feil Ceoil on the <lb/> 17 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to 22 <hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> or so of this <seg type="del">week</seg>,  month  so if you would say <lb/>  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0732_img_224_4"/>
              a weenie, weenie prayer for me I am sure I <lb/> will do better than I would if you didn't say it.   I must now ring off, I am sure you <lb/> are bored stiff by this, my <hi rend="underline">love</hi> to those I told <lb/> you (provided they accept it!! if not you can keep it <lb/><hi rend="underline">all,</hi> along with your own share, for yourself, what <lb/> joy for you!!!!!!!)  <seg type="closer"> From <lb/>Yours sincerely.   <hi rend="underline">Maudie Davin</hi>. </seg><seg type="postscript"> P.S. Please excuse my bad writing and mistakes <lb/> but as usual I am in a hurry. <lb/>M. D.  </seg> Mrs. Frank Aiken   
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>