<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0274">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Sarah Harden to Donald Harden, 27 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Sarah Harden</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Sarah Harden (1870-1929) to her nephew Donald Harden who was then in England. The letter was written during and after the Easter Rising, which had begun on 24 April. Sarah began writing on 27 April and continued to add to the letter until 3 May by which time the postal system has resumed work. She gives a detailed description of her activities during the Rising, what she had seen and heard, rumors and stories told to her by others and refers regularly to friends, relations and neighbours.Sarah Harden was a clerk at the Mission Homes in Dublin and lived on Gratton Street with her two sisters (Aunt K. and Aunt J.) in the letter.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Genevieve Harden, Private Collection</repository>
                  <collection>Genevieve Harden, Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/274</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0872">Sarah Harden</persName>
              <date>1916-04-27</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0973">24 Gratton Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Donald Harden</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0548">England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_1"  type="Letter"  url="dc2fce21f93b8245c88fee4cf4d033cb.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_2"  type="Letter"  url="30a8bb6b1ad89eebd4eee0e015c181fe.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_3"  type="Letter"  url="7b068ebfb93d3274329da91a9c941855.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_4"  type="Letter"  url="6aa18ca643409c4255f9a7111e05b35b.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_5"  type="Letter"  url="2174d48552fd70017ea5038c403e791d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_6"  type="Letter"  url="846cc70346cf3f4c0d8b2abda312d6c6.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_7"  type="Letter"  url="26a5ef8847eb9d2f14bb5f4af6c71d89.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_8"  type="Letter"  url="5d5f3ade57a8d51a1eb0e65f5fe9d4a4.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0274_img_1473_9"  type="Letter"  url="04db0a57abfa82e36fd38c1d25239e57.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_1"/>
                24 Grattan St  .   April 27. 1916.   My dear Donald,   I suppose you are all wondering <lb/>what has become of us &amp; only hope you have not <lb/>all been in a fright about us. Well we are in <lb/> the thick of it I may say but are hoping things <lb/> may be all right in a day or two. On Monday <lb/> Aunt K. &amp; I were having a good holiday clean <lb/>up when we were told the Sinn Feiners had taken <lb/> possession of all the Railways had seized the <lb/>G.P.O. St. Stephen's Green, Jacob's factory, &amp; several <lb/> other places including Bolands bread factory <lb/> quite close to us across the street from Sir P. Dunne's <lb/> all through the day we heard odd shooting &amp; <lb/> of course there were great crowds up &amp; down. <lb/> Aunt K. went out for a walk in the aft. with <lb/>Aunt J &amp; coming home down Northumberland <lb/> Rd she saw 3 Ambulances &amp; plenty of evidence <lb/>of people wounded. The S.F. had taken a corner <lb/> house &amp; fired on several people. all that eve <lb/>no policemen or soldiers to be seen near this. <lb/> Mr B. came down on Tuesday &amp; also Mr. Steele <lb/>each had plenty of news, also Aunt K. met  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_2"/>
              Ms. Murray as she was coming from the Aunts she <lb/>had called up to see if they were nervous about us <lb/> &amp; found they were not at all as they knew nothing <lb/>Ms M. had been all over the place &amp; told her Trinity <lb/> was held by O.T.C. till relieved by military. I went <lb/>out for a short walk Tuesday aft. with Mrs. Green <lb/> we three are all alone here except that Aunt J. <lb/>comes over each night. I was able to buy 1/2 lb butter <lb/> but most of the shops were shut &amp; barred to <lb/>prevent looting which we heard had started <lb/> in Sackville St. We had a pretty quiet night <lb/>on Wed. seemed quiet enough at the start, but <lb/> at 12:30 yesterday  morning  the real noise commenced <lb/>near here, the S.F.s had St. Stephens Schools walls a large <lb/> house this side of Canal. Daddy will know which if <lb/>you tell him it was the corner one where Mrs Cooper <lb/> of Sandymount started a boarding house after her <lb/>husband died. Well the military had guns on <lb/> Baggot St. bridge &amp; thundered on from 12.30 <lb/>until 8.30 when we heard great cheers &amp; shouts <lb/> afterwards found that the corner house had been <lb/>set on fire it blazed away for a long time &amp; we hear <lb/> they got 30 prisoners there. Today they started the <lb/>guns again about 12.30 but they have not gone <lb/> on so continuously though plenty of smaller <lb/>shots are heard from all directions. Mrs. Brid <lb/> did not get down  at  all we suppose no one is allowed  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_3"/>
              to pass in. The military are in  Mount  St. &amp; we hear <lb/> have taken this Street. The others have a  corner  house <lb/> opposite Boy's Home. The boys have been most of <lb/>the time in the gardens Mrs Irwin says it is the <lb/> only place where she can keep them quiet. We <lb/>hear today that the soldiers from Beggars Bush are <lb/> knocking down houses between them and Bolands <lb/>so as to be able to shell it next. Yesterday morning <lb/> a shell from a munition opposite Custom House <lb/>knocked Liberty Hall to the ground. On the <lb/> whole as you may imagine our holiday is not <lb/>all that we would wish. No post either in or out <lb/> no trams no trains &amp; today no breadman &amp; I have <lb/>a nasty cold. We don't know what Dona is doing but <lb/> expect John W. knows something of what is going on <lb/>&amp; will keep her there. I didn't think they could cross <lb/> Dublin very easily we have only seen a glimpse <lb/>of Tuesdays &amp; Wednesdays I. Times &amp; there is no news <lb/> of course only Royal Proclamation, telling everyone <lb/>to stay indoors as much as possible. We are very <lb/> thankful that Miss Staples went to Sandycove last <lb/>week &amp; Miss A. to England. They must be very <lb/> uneasy without any letters. I had a cake to send <lb/>you when we got address but it is half eaten now. <lb/> I hope you are quite well again  April 29. I was too sick yesterday with my cold to <lb/>go on with this but feel a bit better today.  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_4"/>
              Aunt K. spent Tuesday aft. with Aunt Jo &amp; had <lb/>to make a great rush to get back here at all. <lb/>She tried to come by herself at 5 o'clock but the soldiers <lb/>were preparing to fire in the Street &amp; would not <lb/>let her cross, then she &amp; Aunt J. got ready their tea <lb/>&amp; had only just started when the soldiers came in <lb/>to the house to search for S.F.s it seems they had <lb/>taken some empty houses &amp; the soldiers were <lb/>trying to find out exactly where they were. <lb/>Aunt K. asked the soldier in their room could she <lb/>get over to Grattan St. &amp; he said yes if she went <lb/>at once so they both took up what they could <lb/>carry in the way of eatables &amp; none of us have <lb/>been out since. Last night the firing over our <lb/>heads &amp; down the Street was terrific we hardly <lb/>slept at all. we get little or no news. Mrs Irwin <lb/>&amp; her boys stay in their garden a good bit &amp; she <lb/>sometimes hears a bit of what is going on. Her <lb/>top rooms <seg type="del">are</seg> cannot be used as the bullets <lb/>are flying through. <seg type="del">What</seg> we are having great <lb/>cooking of soda bread as we have had no bread <lb/>since Wednesday. Mrs Irwin got some tinned milk <lb/>&amp; <seg type="unclear">gains</seg> &amp; flour from a small shop in G. Canal St. <lb/>The owner had closed up for fear of looting but was <lb/>glad enough to sell to her. The big guns are not <lb/>firing so much today but the rifles are going like <lb/>mad every now &amp; then, there is a barricade  
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_5"/>
              <lb/>across the top of street &amp; we hear the soldiers <lb/>are gradually getting possession of all the city <lb/>there were 60 soldiers wounded in P. Dunnes on <lb/>Thursday &amp; to judge by the cries a lot of people in <lb/>the streets have been shot. We also hear that <lb/>the ladies in Merrion Sqre are nursing the <lb/>wounded soldiers as the Hospitals are so full. <lb/>Bolands factory is still in S.F. hands.  Sunday April 30. Last night we were all so tired out <lb/>that we slept pretty well, except Mrs. Green, but <lb/>the firing <seg type="del">was</seg>must have been very bad. One <lb/>bullet came into the bathroom, broke the blind <lb/>stick &amp; made it fly up then across to the door &amp; seems <lb/>to be embedded in the wall. No one attempted <lb/>to cross the street this morning to go the Mass. The <lb/>soldiers kept all indoors &amp; the shooting was <lb/>very bad. However at 1.30 a man S.F. was seen <lb/>walking <seg type="del">from</seg> up the street bareheaded carrying <lb/>a white flag &amp; before many minutes were <lb/>gone the whole street was filled. We all <lb/>rushed out &amp; shortly after about 80 S.F.s <lb/>marched round the corner by Boys' Home <lb/>&amp; were halted in front of Office, the man <lb/>with the white flag met them &amp; they all laid <lb/>down their arms &amp; marched to one side of <lb/>street the farthest from us &amp; held up their hands, <lb/>a few soldiers came down with  
            <pb n="6" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_6"/>
              <lb/>bayonets fixed etc. &amp; marched them <lb/>all up towards <seg type="unclear">Slpis</seg> then other soldiers <lb/>came down &amp; all arms &amp; kit were examined <lb/>&amp; carried off. We hear the G.P.O. &amp; north <lb/>side of city surrendered yesterday &amp; <lb/>the rumour goes that the R.C. Archbishop <lb/>&amp; a priest went to Bolands &amp; other centres <lb/>&amp; gave them a message from the Authorities <lb/>to the effect that if they did not surrender <lb/>the city would be blown up at once by <lb/>warships in the River. Things are much <lb/>quieter tonight but shooting still goes on <lb/>we hear it is a distillery behind Bolands <lb/>that some are still holding. Priests &amp; doctors in white coats &amp; red cross are up &amp; down <lb/>with the Ambulance motors. One of our neighbours <lb/>of the Terrace down side of house gave us a loaf <lb/>this morning &amp; Mrs.Irwin gave us each a thick slice <lb/>of hot ham for dinner. We were going to have ½ a <lb/>goose egg each Aunt K. &amp; I but the ham was a <lb/>greater treat as we have had nothing but eggs <lb/><seg type="del">one</seg> since Tuesday. I don't think we will be anxious <lb/>on soda bread again in a hurry. &amp; are hoping to <lb/>see our bread &amp; milk men in the morning. <lb/>Poor Aunts we don't know how they are feeling <lb/>not hearing a word from us &amp; we are afraid to <lb/>go out yet for fear we might be kept out. Aunt  
            <pb n="7" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_7"/>
              <lb/>K is writing to <seg type="unclear">Gleneely</seg> and we are wondering <lb/>if you will all wade through our letters <lb/>it is hard not to repeat ourselves. We hear <lb/>Sackville St is in ruins and a good many of the <lb/>people who lost their lives were shot while <lb/>looting the shops &amp; stores. Leeson St and Baggot St <lb/>have not suffered, but, St Stevens green is like <lb/>a wilderness &amp; trenches dug all over it. We <lb/>are looking forward to seeing Mr Baird in the <lb/>morning. I am sure he is in a very anxious <lb/>state about us all. Townsend St Has suffered <lb/>a good deal but the soldiers took possession of <lb/>it almost from the beginning. We are very <lb/>thankful to think the worst is over.  Monday May 1st. Last night was almost the worst <lb/>we had. Though i am glad to say I slept through <lb/>it all. Mrs Green says it was dreadful. We <lb/>made up the last flour &amp; eat our last potato at <lb/>dinner &amp; were proposing to have porridge for <lb/>tomorrow, when all stopped suddenly. Mrs <seg type="unclear">Lu</seg><lb/>saw a group of men marching from Hollies St. headed <lb/>by a white flag and almost at once the street <lb/>became alive with people. About 2 o'c Celeste <lb/>Ledony came down the street in Red Cross cap etc. <lb/>She is helping in Merrion Square to nurse the wounded <lb/>&amp; she came to see if we were alive. She only stayed at <lb/>the gate a couple of minutes &amp; came back then  
            <pb n="8" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_8"/>
              <lb/>less than 1/2 hour with some cold mutton <lb/>6 eggs &amp; 6 scones which she had got for us from <lb/>Mrs Finney the Doctor's wife, we were glad <lb/>to get the things &amp; since then the soldiers <lb/>dragged down a bread cart &amp; sold the bread <lb/>for 3 a loaf, so  we  were able to get one. We <lb/>hear there are snipers all over the city <lb/>&amp; the streets have now been cleared &amp; we <lb/>have been told no lights are to be seen after <lb/>7.30. So we are preparing to go to bed in the <lb/>dark, &amp; get up to breakfast about 6. We <lb/>are going to try the daylight saving bill!!! <lb/>I hope we will soon get word of the Aunts, <lb/>No one as far as we can hear can get in or <lb/>out of town except the Red Cross people, <lb/>but we think Rathmines is quiet beyond <lb/>Portobello &amp; Ranelagh was all right on <lb/>Tuesday.  Wed. May 3. I walked up to the Aunts new house <lb/>yesterday they are most uncomfortable only <lb/>1/2 moved as the vans did not come to finish, <lb/>them &amp; also they had been very short of <lb/>food in Rathmines they were glad to hear we were <lb/>all right. Today I walked down town to see the <lb/>ruins, it is dreadful but already people are <lb/>trying to start work again. I called to see how <lb/>Uncle James was he has been ill for the past  
            <pb n="9" facs="L1916_0274_img_1473_9"/>
              <lb/>2 weeks he is better now &amp; the sisters say will <lb/>soon be alright. I saw both him &amp; Aunt Maggie <lb/> &amp; Dora. They are having a bad time with snipers <lb/>there have several bullets through their <lb/> windows. Things seem very quiet tonight &amp; today <lb/>the trains were running from Balls Bridge to <lb/> Kingstown. Our breadman came this morning but <lb/>our milkman did not. Aunt K got a bit of <lb/> meat for tomorrow. No posts have come yet <lb/>but we posted a p.c. to Daddy yesterday &amp; papers today <lb/> &amp; tomorrow I hope to post this, With love to you <lb/>all. <seg type="closer"> Your loving Aunt   Sarah </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>