<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4320">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Nevil Macready to Edward Carson, 8 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Nevil Macready</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Nevil Macready (1862- 1946) to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War. General Sir Cecil Frederick Nevil Macready,  British Army officer, was known affectionately as Make-Ready (close to the correct pronunciation of his name). He served in senior staff appointments in the First World War and was the last British military commander in Ireland.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/17/11</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4320</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1136">Nevil Macready</persName>
              <date>1916-06-08</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1225">5 Eaton Place, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1946</item>
               <item n="tag">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">World War I (1914-1918)</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4320_img_3680_1"  type="Letter"  url="fa08b03a887b3e6f4de7584bf375df46.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4320_img_3680_1"/>
             Ulster <lb/>Division   8th June, 1916.   Dear Sir Edward,   Sir William Robertson passed me your note of the <lb/>5th. So far as I am aware there is no proposition at all <lb/>to break up the Ulster Division, but there are one or two, <lb/>points about its organisation which are a little difficult, <lb/>and I understand that recruiting in Ulster is almost at a <lb/>standstill, for reasons which perhaps could be explained <lb/>better by word of mouth.   Would it be possible for you to spare a quarter <lb/>of an hour one day at your convenience, preferably early <lb/>next week, to talk over the welfare of the Ulster Division <lb/>with my Director of Recruiting and myself.   Yours sincerely,   G N Macready   The Rt. Hon. <lb/>Sir Edward Carson, M. P., <lb/>5 Eaton Place, <lb/>S. W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>