<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0034">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from William Pearse to Éamonn Bulfin, 24 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>William Pearse</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a mobilisation order sent by William Pearse (1881-1916) to Éamonn Bulfin (1892-1968) on 21 April 1916. The order was for the planned Easter Rising on Monday, 24 April. Bulfin and the rest of the Irish Volunteers had received orders to mobilise on Easter Sunday for manouevres. Unbeknownst to the rank and file, these manouevres were to be used as a cover for the beginning of the Easter Rising but were countermanded by Eoin MacNeill, chief of staff of the Irish Volunteers, when he became aware of the plans. The leaders of the Rising then decided to go ahead with the Rising but to postpone it for a day. This order is a copy of the orginal order for Easter Sunday but has been edited in the hand of William Pearse to reflect the change of plans. The Rising went ahead on 24 April with significantly reduced numbers. William Pearse was a sculptor and brother of Patrick Pearse, one of the leaders of the Easter Rising. William held the rank of captain on the headquarters staff of the Dublin Brigade of the Irish Volunteers and Bulfin was a member of the Rathfarnham company and had been one of the first pupil&#39;s in Patrick Pearse&#39;s bilingual school for boys, St Enda&#39;s. William Pearse was executed for his part in the Rising on 4 May and Éamonn Bulfin was imprisoned in Stafford and Frongach.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Éamonn Bulfin Collection, BMH CD/99/2</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/34</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0853">William Pearse</persName>
              <date>1916-04-24</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1994">2 Dawson Street, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Éamonn Bulfin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0713">St. Enda's College, Rathfarnham, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0034_img_1065_1"  type="Letter"  url="49c5335d4ba8a41b9a3e8c5bce21d4f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0034_img_1065_2"  type="Letter"  url="2557b26562bde5e43cabf66f3eb287f0.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0034_img_1065_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="708cdf9644c1a9c9d440f4c93d38b99b.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0034_img_1065_1"/>
                <hi rend="underline">IRISH VOLUNTEERS</hi>  Headquarters:  2. Dawson Street,  DUBLIN.    <seg type="del">21st</seg> 2th April 1916.     Lieut. E Bulfin  St Enda's  <lb/>Sent at <hi rend="underline">7 a.m.</hi><lb/><hi rend="underline">DUBLIN BRIGADE EASTER MANOEUVERS 1916</hi>  Your will report yourself to me at temporary Head<lb rend="hyphen"/>quarters Beresford Place at the hour of <seg type="del">4 pm on</seg> 10a.m. <lb/> today 24th <seg type="del">Sunday next, 23rd</seg> inst. (Easter <seg type="del">Sunday</seg> Monday ) and hold yourself <lb/>in readiness tonight on the staff of Commandant P.H. Pearse <lb/> Acting G.O.C, Dublin Brigade, during the Easter Manoeuvers.  You will provide yourself with a bicycle, a street <lb/>map of Dublin city, a road map of the Dublin District, and <lb/> a field message book. You will carry full arms and <lb/> ammunition, full service equipment (including overcoat) <lb/>and rations for <seg type="del">eight hours</seg> one day   You will acknowledge receipt of this order by <lb/> by <seg type="del">hand</seg> bearer  to us at <seg type="del">St Enda's College, Rath<lb/> farnham</seg> Liberty Hall   the annexed form duly filled in and signed. <seg type="closer"> <hi rend="underline">William Pearse</hi> <lb/>Capt.<hi rend="underline"/><lb/>Acting Chief of Staff </seg> 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0034_img_1065_2"/>
                Headquarters:-  2.Dammon Street.  D U B L I N    24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> April. 1916   Lieut. E. Bulfin<lb/> St.Enda's<lb/> Sent at 7 a.m.<lb/><hi rend="underline">DUBLIN BRIGADE: EASTER MANOEUVERS, 1916.</hi>  You will report yourself to me at temporary Head<lb rend="hyphen"/>quarters. Beresford Place. st the 10 a.m.<lb/> to-day, 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>  inst. Easter monday and hold yourself<lb/> in readiness to act on the Staff of Commandant P.H. Pearse.<lb/>Acting G.O.C. Dublin Brigade, during the Easter Manoeuvers.  You will provide yourself with a bicycle, a Street<lb/>map of Dublin City, a read map of Dublin District, and <lb/> a field message book. You will carry full arms and<lb/>ammunition, full service equipment (including overcoat)<lb/> and rations for   one day  You will acknowledge of this order by<lb/> , by   to as at <seg type="del">St.Enda's College, Rath<lb/> farnham</seg>Liberty Hall the annexed  duly filled in and  . <seg type="closer"> William Pearse <lb/> Capt.<lb/> Acting Chief of Staff</seg> 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0034_img_1065_3"/>
              Mobilisation Order received by Lieut.  Eamonn Bulfin on Easter Monday <lb/>April 24, 1916. The alterations are in Willie Pearse's hand.<lb/><sic>Lent</sic> by Eamonn Bulfin. E.W. 48 (Loan) (A)  
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>