<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4359">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Edward Carson to William Martin, 17 July 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Edward Carson</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Edward Carson (1854-1935) to William Martin (1855-1933). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/18/1/23</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4359</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date>1916-07-17</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0725">William Martin</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1328">Hilden, Co. Monaghan, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1935</item>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4359_img_3715_1"  type="Letter"  url="3cbe09012ad333640731d77f79331f95.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4359_img_3715_2"  type="Letter"  url="abb29800fa0ba87d5e46c2befe4c8c2d.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4359_img_3715_3"  type="Letter"  url="0ffb6071b12e31e4ca52dd36fdf53591.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4359_img_3715_4"  type="Letter"  url="0bbc98031c7cceb339f74409e9ceb395.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4359_img_3715_5"  type="Letter"  url="8d97a3758f709c4e0f6f730404595494.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4359_img_3715_1"/>
             HOUSE OF COMMONS   July 17.1916.   Dear Mr. Martin,   I am very greatly obliged for your letter &amp; <lb/>the enclosures. I greatly appreciate the <lb/>resolution which  notwithstanding <lb/>Major Somerset Saunderson's letter  the Monaghan delegates <seg type="del">have</seg> <lb/>passed on the 13th .July,. Noone <lb/>has suffered more than I have from the <lb/>knowledge that it was impossible to include <lb/>the 3 counties in the proposed settlement &amp; <lb/>I know well how deeply disappointed all <lb/>our friends in those 3 counties must <lb/>necessarily have been &amp;  I  therefore  value  <seg type="del">I</seg> all the <lb/>more <seg type="del">appreciate</seg> the resolution referred <lb/>to. Will you thank the others for me <lb/>&amp; say how deeply impressed I am by <lb/>their expression of confidence in myself.   As regards Major Saunderson's letter it is <lb/>I fear a tissue of misapprehension from <lb/>beginning to end. He makes no reference to <lb/>the statement made by the Prime Minister on <lb/>behalf of all his collegues in the Cabinet on
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4359_img_3715_2"/>
            the 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>May <seg type="del">which expressed the <seg type="unclear">unconscious</seg> <lb/>desire for</seg>  that  a settlement of the future Government <lb/>of Ireland  should be arranged as a matter of Imperial  <seg type="del">&amp; refer to the Imperial</seg> Emergency <lb/><seg type="del">which had <seg type="del">arise</seg> arisen</seg>. Nor does he <lb/>refer to the fact that the Home Rule Act, <lb/>comprising the whole of Ireland <seg type="del"> been</seg> <lb/>is now upon the Statute book, and that <lb/>no member of the Cabinet <lb/> so far as I know  has stated that it <seg type="del"> </seg>  is any longer <seg type="del">the</seg> possible <lb/><seg type="del">policy of</seg> for  the Unionist party to try and have <lb/>it repealed._ [Major Saunderson is also <lb/><seg type="unclear">under</seg> a misapprehension when he states that <lb/>I told the delegates at Belfast that <lb/>the particular proposals had the unanimous <lb/>assent of the Cabinet. The statement I <lb/>made, — which is borne out by the shorthand <lb/>note, <seg type="del">which is</seg> now before me, and by the resolution <lb/>which was passed ,— was that the Cabinet <lb/>desired a settlement, and had  unanimously  appointed <lb/> Lloyd George to <seg type="del"> </seg> <lb/>negotiate one, and that the terms I put
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4359_img_3715_3"/>
            forward were those submitted to me by <lb/>Mr.Lloyd George after communication with <lb/>the Prime Minister —    Major Saunderson in his letter says that <lb/>"five Unionist members of the Government are <lb/>opposed to the settlement", — <seg type="del">but</seg>  as to this I can only <lb/>say that no member of the Government has <lb/>suggested to me <seg type="del">that</seg>at any time that I <lb/>should resubmit the proposals to the Ulster <lb/>Unionist Council. <seg type="del">and</seg> Had they done so <lb/>I should certainly have considered the <lb/>matter  See back <seg type="del">&amp; How little any part of Ulster <lb/>could expect from a settlement after the <lb/>war is shown by the fact that the Irish <lb/>Unionist Alliance, with whose deputation <lb/>Major Saunderson was joined — have passed <lb/>a resolution deprecating the leaving <lb/>out of the six counties. Major Saunderson <lb/>had every opportunity of stating his views <lb/>— as I encouraged him to do — to the <lb/>meeting of the Council in Belfast and I <lb/>fully resent his attempt to create <lb/>a <seg type="del"> </seg> feeling that I have been</seg>
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_4359_img_3715_4"/>
             Moreover, the statement of Lord Selbourne <lb/>— the only Minister who has definitely dissented <lb/>from the proposals — that  the  Home Rule <seg type="del">must</seg>  Act  <lb/>cannot be repealed, shows how little is to be <lb/><seg type="del">expected from</seg> gained by <seg type="del">any</seg> rejection of <lb/>the suggested settlement.   After making every allowance for <seg type="del">Major Saunderson's</seg> <lb/>the Soreness which Major Saunderson as a Cavan <lb/>delegate evidently feels, I must say that I <lb/>resent his <seg type="del"> </seg> attempt to create the impression <lb/>that I have been deceived, or that the Ulster Council <lb/>was misled in coming to the conclusion contained <lb/>in their resolution — an impression which is in <lb/>no way confirmed, as Major Saunderson seems <lb/>to suppose, by the Statements of Lord Lansdowne <lb/>&amp; Lord Selbourne in the House of Lords.   <seg type="del">If the Irish Unionist Alliance</seg> <lb/>The extent to which Major Saunderson misunderstands <lb/>the whole situation may be <seg type="unclear">seen</seg> in his astonishing <lb/>Statement that the course of events has "made it <lb/>appear that the Ulster Unionists have accepted <lb/>the principle of Home Rule". He must have <lb/>entirely forgotten the terms of the Ulster Councils' <lb/>Resolution to which he was himself a party   If Major Saunderson desires to have <lb/>the proceedings in Belfast reversed, I suggest <lb/>that his proper course is to call —
            <pb n="5" facs="L1916_4359_img_3715_5"/>
             PAGE 4 OF 4.  <lb/><seg type="del">deceived or that the Ulster Council has <lb/>been deceived in coming to the conclusion <lb/>contained in <seg type="del">par</seg> their resolution and <lb/>it seems to me to be particularly cruel <lb/>to-day at a time when the hearts &amp; homes <lb/>of so many in Ulster are now sorrowing <lb/>for the brave men who have won glory <lb/>for the Province. </seg>   <seg type="del">If Major Saunderson desires to he can</seg> <lb/>calla public meeting in Belfast <seg type="del">&amp;</seg> and lay <lb/>his views before the Ulster people, <seg type="del">and</seg> to whom  he <lb/>can explain <seg type="del">to them</seg> how he proposes to <lb/>get <seg type="del">on</seg> better terms than I have been able <lb/>to <seg type="del">as</seg>  obtain . <seg type="del">&amp; of</seg>  If  he can persuade them of the <lb/>truth of the allegations contained in his letter <lb/>I shall most willingly, if I am so requested, <lb/>makeway for him or for any other leader <lb/>that the Ulster people may choose.   Yours very truly.   William Martin Esq <lb/>Hilden. Monaghan. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>