<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4313">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter to Edward Carson, 15 May 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter to Edward Carson (1854-1935). Carson was a prominent Unionist Politician. Originally a practicing solicitor from Dublin, Carson&#39;s opposition to the proposed third Home Rule bill made him the figure head of Unionism throughout the island. He was the centerpiece of the speaking tour that culminated in Ulster Day (28 September 1912), when just under half a million signed Ulster&#39;s solemn league and covenant pledging to use ‘all means which may be found necessary to defeat the present conspiracy to set up a home rule parliament in Dublin’. Carson inaugurated the Larne gunrunning in 1914 which armed the UVF, many of whom Carson would encourage to join the British Army throughout the First World War.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Carson Papers, D1507/A/16/19</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4313</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName ></persName>
              <date>1916-05-15</date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0539">Edward Carson</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1490">House of Commons, Westminster, London, S.W., England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="tag">Politics</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4313_img_3674_1"  type="Letter"  url="25aeaa502a3df6ab50de61418c747ab3.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4313_img_3674_2"  type="Letter"  url="b21853a0045d55d4a823d52ffc00243f.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4313_img_3674_3"  type="Letter"  url="88f44b12421720450db11be2f1e88634.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4313_img_3674_1"/>
             Bangor,   15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> May, 1916.  Dear Sir,   The apparent presumption in our addressing you <lb/>directly is lessened by the fact that we believe the Ulster <lb/>Volunteers generally are interested in the subject matter <lb/>of this letter in the same manner as ourselves.   When the present war broke out Ulster Unionists had <lb/>been for some time the victims of the most lying slanders <lb/>from the Radical Press the mouthpiece of the Government and <lb/>also from members of the Government itself which had even <lb/>gone so far as to use His Majesty's Ships and Soldiers in an <lb/>attempt to terrorise us. The Home Rule Bill, to resist <lb/>which we had banded ourselves together, had been made an Act <lb/>of Parliament,notwithstanding all our protests,and if there <lb/>a section of the people in the Empire who were entitled <lb/>to hold aloof - as our adversaries were wont to do, and took <lb/>no little credit for it, before they were paid their price <lb/>for coming in or pretending to come into the Empire with the <lb/>rest - it was Ulster Unionists.   You, however, gave the lead of the Empire first and <lb/>that all the above considerations should be subordinated to <lb/>this supreme interest, and your lead was followed, with the <lb/>result that there are now thousands of our fellow volunteers <lb/>with the colours, while other assistance given by Unionist <lb/>Ulster ranks first in this Country.   There have been some very disquieting rumours of <lb/>late especially since the Nationalist Rebellion - as we <lb/>prefer to call it, for we all know perfectly well that the <lb/>present so called Sinn Feiners are nothing more than Mr. <lb/>Redmond's former followers who refused to put on the loyal <lb/>mask along with him when he had got his Home Rule Bill - the <lb/>more important of which is that some sort of negotiations
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4313_img_3674_2"/>
            <lb/>are going on with the object of setting up immediately a Home <lb/>Rule Parliament.   This may be and probably is untrue but it opens up a <lb/>possibility as to which the Ulster Volunteers are much concern- <lb/>ed and they are anxious to know exactly to what extent they <lb/>are going to be lead on this principle of the Empire first. <lb/>Their loyalty has already been strained very considerably in <lb/>the circumstances above mentioned and the question they are <lb/>asking themselves is whether it is going to be strained <lb/>further, and is the good of the Empire to be again pleaded for <lb/>the purpose of inducing them to make further sacrifices in <lb/>the shape of surrendering principles,which are part of them- <lb/>selves, tearing up their convenants, and submitting to a Home <lb/>Rule Parliament without demur.   In other words we are anxious to know the entire <lb/>length to which our Leaders would have us go in the interests <lb/>of the Empire, so that we can consider the matter carefully <lb/>and make up our minds whether we are prepared to be led to <lb/>such a length or not.   We would like if you would kindly agree to the <lb/>publication of this correspondence as being the easiest <lb/>way of informing our fellow Volunteers of it, but of course <lb/>we will not publish it unless you wis.   We enclose the card of one of the signatories to <lb/>whom the favour of your reply may be sent,and we would be <lb/>glad if your reply would comprise a statement of your <lb/>opinion as to the real nature of what we have called the <lb/>Nationalist Rebellion. We are concerned in a remark made <lb/>by you in the House from which it might be inferred that <lb/>you were under the impression the Rebellion was entirely <lb/>outside the Nationalist movement and could not be traced
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_4313_img_3674_3"/>
            <lb/>to it in any way.   We are, Dear Sir, <lb/>Yours faithfully.   Jos. C, Stuart 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Batt. Down U.V.F. <lb/>Jos. Templeton 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Batt Down U.V.F. <lb/>Stirling <seg type="unclear">Lent</seg> <lb/>1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Batt<hi rend="superscript">in</hi> Nth Down <seg type="unclear">Regt</seg> <lb/>VVF   The Right.Hon.Sir Edward Carson,K.C. M.P. <lb/>House of Commons, <lb/>Westminster, <lb/>London,W. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>