<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1977">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Richard Creighton to Augustine Birrell, 25 April 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Richard Creighton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter was written by Richard Creighton (b.1846), a clerk of the union and rural district council for Gorey. It was addressed to Augustine Birrell (1850-1933). Birrell was the chief secretary for Ireland from 1907 until his retirement in 1916 following the aftermath of the Easter Rising, for which Birrell accepted responsibility.
In the letter Creighton mentions that he will be forwarding a resolution concerning the poisoning of dogs in the town of Gorey, County Wexford.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Chief Secretary&#39;s Office Registered Papers; CSO RP/1916/7403/1</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1977</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1176">Richard Creighton</persName>
              <date>1916-04-25</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1779">Gorey, County Wexford, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0534">Augustine Birrell</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2014">Dublin Castle, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="tag">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Industry and Public Administration</item>
               <item n="topic">Country and City Life</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1977_img_1424_1"  type="Letter"  url="17cc4816e4a1929c5df6ec2bb9998625.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1977_img_1424_1"/>
             April 25th 1916   The Right Hon, <lb/>The Chief Secretary for Ireland, <lb/>Dublin Castle.   Hon Sir,   I am directed by the Gorey Board of <lb/>Guardians to forward you copy of a resolution <lb/>passed by them at their last meeting in <lb/>reference to the poisoning of dogs in the <lb/>town of Gorey. Quite a large number <lb/>have been poisoned during the last few <lb/>weeks.   I am, <lb/>Hon Sir, <lb/>Your obedient Servant   RCreighton. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>