<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_0228">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Kate English in Dunsink Cottage to Patrick English, c. June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Kate English</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This letter is from Kate English to her son Patrick. This letter was written by Kate shortly after she found out that Patrick had been sent to Wales. Kate immediately asks for all the details concerning when and for how long she can visit in addition to any items Patrick might like her to bring over. In the letter Kate reassures Patrick that she and all the family are well and look forward to his return. This letter was written by Kate (b. 1855) to Patrick English (1894-1970) while he was interned. Patrick had been stationed in the G.P.O for the Rising. Following the surrender he was sent to Stafford Prison before being moved to Frongoch internment camp in Wales.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Patrick English</repository>
                  <collection>Private Collection</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/228</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0077">Kate English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1552">Castleknock, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0178">Patrick English</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Female</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0228_img_1390_1"  type="Letter"  url="07b44341e18bdc85da88e45ad1f10f5c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0228_img_1390_2"  type="Letter"  url="ce87f77ed655eba71d33f54a54b7f281.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0228_img_1390_3"  type="Letter"  url="baa8601a2d35b72ee6314fbe01ba5458.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_0228_img_1390_4"  type="Letter"  url="07b44341e18bdc85da88e45ad1f10f5c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_0228_img_1390_1"/>
                Dunsink Cottage,  Castleknock  Co. Dublin    My dearest Patrick,    I have just received <lb/> a card from Fr. Moore telling <lb/> me you have gone on to Wales what <lb/> I want you to do is to write <lb/> at once and tell me what way <lb/> you are situated tell me what <lb/> is visiting hours &amp; days and how <lb/> long can I stay with you, for go <lb/> to see you I will. I will bring on <lb/>your shoes &amp; socks and tell me <lb/> do you want shirts I am bringing  
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_0228_img_1390_2"/>
              <lb/>the cocoa and any <lb/> other little things that <lb/> you would like tell me <lb/> I wont wait until August <lb/> as I think the doolans are <lb/> not going until then. I think <lb/><seg type="unclear">darie</seg> is going to come with <lb/> me so I won't be too bad <lb/> I am not one bit nervous <lb/> strange to say I am grand <lb/> and I hope you dear self <lb/> is just the same I got masses <lb/> offered for you and we are <lb/> all praying for you night <cb/><lb/> noon &amp; morning and please <lb/> God we will be together <lb/> and happy again. How is <lb/> Mick Cosgrove and all the <lb/> lads I hope to see everybody <lb/> when I go we will have <lb/> a jolly time if we can. <lb/> dear Son cheer up and don't <lb/> be fretting about me I am all <lb/> right and have a grand <lb/> job waiting on you the minute <lb/> you arrive. No more slaving <lb/> 25 shillings per week we <lb/> will be as happy as the day  
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_0228_img_1390_3"/>
              <lb/>a long. Jamesy Larie Katie <lb/> Nellie and all the rest of the <lb/> long tail family sends their <lb/> best love to you, not forgetting <lb/><hi rend="underline">Cathleen na Houle</hi> James is <lb/> working in Mooneys its very <lb/> hard to get work now a days <lb/> Lawrence has got a very good <lb/> boy he minds me well. Annie <lb/> was home for a few days she <lb/> looks fine. She sends her best <lb/> love to you tell Jo Mooney she <lb/> sends her love to him and best <lb/> wishes to all the lads I think <lb/> I have no more to say only no <lb/> matter what you do write at <lb/> once by return and tell me <lb/> all particulars. I will be watching  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_0228_img_1390_4"/>
              every post to see what <lb/>news from you good <lb/>bye dear &amp; god <lb/>may bless you. Write <lb/>me meet soon.  <seg type="closer"> From your loving Mother <lb/> K. English </seg> 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>