<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_4018">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Desmond FitzGerald to Arthur Patrick O'Brien, 26 June 1916</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Desmond FitzGerald</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>Letter from Desmond FitzGerald to Arthur Patrick O&#39;Brien written on behalf of Earnest Blythe.  The letter contains details of Mr. Blythe&#39;s desires to get into a camp with the other deportees and his request that Laurence Ginnell also be informed of his desires.  The author refers to George Gavan Duffy&#39;s defence of Roger Casement.  

Desmond FitzGerald (1888-1947) was a poet and a journalist belonging a group of Irish poets now known as the Imagists. Following his marriage to Mabel Washington McConnell (1884–1958) he became involved with Irish politics, arranging meetings for the Irish Volunteers. He later served in the GPO during the Easter Rising, being placed in charge of the garrison&#39;s food supply. He initially escaped arrest after the Rising but was soon rounded up and imprisoned in Mountjoy, Dartmoor, Maidstone, Lewes and Portland. 

In the wake of the 1916 Rising, Arthur Patrick O&#39;Brien founded the Irish National Relief Fund in London to provide assistance to the families of Irish rebels.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>MS8434:17-4-a MS8434:17-4-b</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/4018</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-0538">Desmond FitzGerald</persName>
              <date>1916-06-26</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-0227">128 Earlham Grove, Forest Gate, London, United Kingdom</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Arthur Patrick O&#39;Brien</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName ></placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1947</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Politics</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4018_img_3402_1"  type="Letter"  url="1d3a9c51e3823fcf55c8ee2b28f2311a.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_4018_img_3402_2"  type="Letter"  url="3c5bbf79930c8d57db94ace9dea5ba7c.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_4018_img_3402_1"/>
             128 Earlham Grove<lb/>Forest Gate   June 26th 1916 <lb/><lb/> Dear Mr. O'Brien,   I saw Ernest Blythe on<lb/>Saturday. As he is most anxious to<lb/>have his case taken up without delay<lb/>and as there is no Committee Meeting on<lb/>Wednesday at which to report this, I<lb/>hasten to do it now.  He is most desirous of getting into a<lb/>camp with the other deportees, and I see<lb/>no reason why that should not be secured<lb/>to him without a little push.  He feels powerless to do anything for<lb/>himself and leaves everything in our<lb/>hands. He did ask, however that<lb/>McGinnell might be told of his desires.<lb/>He has also written my sister-in-law<lb/>to the same effect  She writes me today to say that before<lb/>moving in the matter herself, she will<lb/>await my news of what the London<lb/>Committee will do in the matter.<lb/>I give her suggestions:<lb/>I think the case ought to be put 
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_4018_img_3402_2"/>
             in the hands of a Solicitor at once. As<lb/>Mr. Gavan Duffy is too busy over Sir Roger<lb/>Casement, I think he should be asked<lb/>to name another man who would do it.<lb/>Of course it does not necessarily entail any<lb/>sympathies with our people. Just to<lb/>state the case, and make the Authorities<lb/>feel that it would be less trouble to do<lb/>something to satisfy these troublesome<lb/>people than to leave things alone.<lb/>The I imagine other channels could<lb/>be worked, M.P's etc.  I have written Mabel telling her that<lb/>I would communicate with you at once.<lb/>She will therefore take no steps until she<lb/>hears from me again.  <lb/>I am,<lb/>Yours Sincerely,  Katherine Fitzgerald. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>