<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1611">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from Harry Boland to his mother, Kate Boland [1917]</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
            <author>Harry Boland</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>This work was originally published by Maynooth University in Ireland in <date>2017</date>. In 2026 this data, stored in a relational database was extracted and converted into this TEI/XML document.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="summary">
               <p>This is a letter from Harry Boland to his mother Catherine &#39;Kate&#39; Boland (née Woods, c. 1861-1932). Boland was a keen member of the GAA, the Irish Republican Brotherhood and the Dublin Brigade of the Irish Volunteers. During the Easter Rising he was a member of the rebel garrison in the GPO and, despite having no officer rank, was sentenced to ten years&#39; penal servitude. He was imprisoned in Dartmoor, Lewes and Maidstone.
The letter was written on toilet paper and smuggled out by Boland when he was being transferred from Lewes to Maidstone. He writes that he is being trasnferred and described the civil disobedience carried out by the prisoners in Lewes. They had sent in a petition demanding to be treated as prisoners of war.
Enclosed is a note from one of the investigators for the Bureau of Military History, who collected the collection of which this letter is a part, describing how the letter was written and found its way to Kate Boland. Also enclosed is a typed copy of the note added to the letter by the lady who forwarded it to Dublin.</p>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Military Archives of Ireland</repository>
                  <collection>Bureau of Military History Contemporary Documents, Mrs Sean O&#39;Donovan Collection; BMH CD/196/2/3</collection>
                  <idno>https://letters1916.ie/item/1611</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="en">English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <correspDesc>
           <correspAction type="sent">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-1056">Harry Boland</persName>
              <date>1916</date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-1995">Lewes, England</placeName>
           </correspAction>
           <correspAction type="received">
              <persName key="#letters1916_person-None">Catherine Boland</persName>
              <date></date>
              <placeName key="#letters1916_place-2075">15 Marino Cresent, Clontarf, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
           </correspAction>
        </correspDesc>
        <textClass>
         <keywords>
            <list>
               <item n="gender">Male</item>
               <item n="death">1922</item>
               <item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
               <item n="topic">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
            </list>
         </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The data in these XML files was generated based on a data dump from the Magellan database (https://github.com/Maynooth-Center-for-Digital-Humanities/Magellan). Each database record has been converted to a JSON file (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/json). The element section of the JSON file contains the TEI-encoded contents of the letters. The TEI XML has been cleaned and made well-formed using a Python script (https://github.com/letters1916static/letters-data/tree/main/src).</p>
         </projectDesc>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1611_img_1075_1"  type="Letter"  url="e089086c3558550e40fa515b4d450d31.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1611_img_1075_2"  type="Letter"  url="a75c8db226f45f3c28a275cdb661475c.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1611_img_1075_3"  type="Enclosure"  url="204437fa0abec0e6024db567126a5c68.jpg"/>
      <graphic xml:id="L1916_1611_img_1075_4"  type="Enclosure"  url="5df6cbef748d975eb6eb455fed8948cf.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <ab>
            <pb n="1" facs="L1916_1611_img_1075_1"/>
              Friend. Send on this note to Mrs Boland. <lb/>15 Marino Crescent, Clontarf, Dublin, Ireland <lb/>and earn the prayers of her son who ask this <lb/>favour of you.     My Dear Mother.  <lb/>I cast this note in the lap of the Gods in the hope <lb/>that some good angel will send it to you. <lb/>I am on my way to some other Prison in Irons, <lb/>Just left Lewes after a terrible time since last <lb/>Whit Monday at 8.0' am when our leaders <lb/>presented our demand to the prison authorities <lb/>asking that we be treated as 'Prisoners of War' <lb/>refusing to do any work or obey any orders <lb/>  as we were treated as criminals. We <lb/>then marched to our cells in a quiet soldierly <lb/>manner. We got no answer to our <lb/>request and we were not allowed from <lb/>our cells not even to Mass on Sunday <lb/>nor did we take any exercise except what <lb/>we could take in our narrow stuffy <lb/>cells. We waited patiently and quietly <lb/>for exactly one week. And so on Monday <lb/>night each man broke 3 panes of glass <lb/>in his window. As a result of the <lb/>'broken' windows our leaders were <lb/>'removed' on Tuesday mid-day. We <!-- There seems to be a missing line here -->
            <pb n="2" facs="L1916_1611_img_1075_2"/>
            <lb/>then we were left behind wrecked our <lb/>cells and broke all the glass which we <lb/>left. The noise was terrific and we are <lb/>all being sent to other prisons. We <lb/>have sworn to do no work  or  to obey any <lb/>orders whatever until the Government <lb/>treat us as soldiers. We fought a clean <lb/>fair fight and should be treated as <lb/>honourable men not as criminals.   Dear Mother, do not worry too much. <lb/>With God's help I will keep my health, <lb/>my spirits are high, <seg type="unclear">Good wish</seg>. <lb/>Give my love to my Dear Sister, <lb/>Brothers and Aunt. Pray for the <lb/>good soul who directs this to you. <lb/>You won't hear from me again <lb/>until my time comes.    Your loving son  <lb/> Harry . 
            <pb n="3" facs="L1916_1611_img_1075_3"/>
             <hi rend="underline">leatan mionuairisce</hi> <!-- notepaper heading --> <lb/>BUREAU OF MILITARY HISTORY 1913 - 1921 <!-- official stamp -->   The attached is a photostat copy of a <lb/>letter written by Harry Boland to his mother <lb/>on the two sides of a piece of lavatory <lb/>paper with a fountain pen which he managed <lb/>somehow to obtain before being transferred <lb/>from Lewes Gaol to Maidstone Prison.   He was brought in chains from Lewes Gaol <lb/>in a cab accompanied by four warders and <lb/>while travelling through the streets of <lb/>Lewes, he succeeded in throwing the letter <lb/>through the window of the cab. The letter <lb/>was picked up on the street by a girl whose <lb/>mother forwarded it to the address indicated <lb/>in the letter with an unsigned covering note <lb/>of her own, a typed copy of which is also <lb/>attached.   Both documents are in the possession <lb/>of Mrs. Sean O'Donovan, a sister of Harry <lb/>Boland.    <seg type="unclear">Son</seg>Ciosain   30.7.51     Investigation employed by <lb/>the Bureau of Military <lb/>History  
            <pb n="4" facs="L1916_1611_img_1075_4"/>
            <!-- The following is a note from the finder of the letter -->  This letter was picked up in the street by <lb/>my daughter and as I have two sons doing <lb/>their bit it is with pleasure I forward it to <lb/>you as the writer wished. 
         </ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>