<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">About the Project</title>
            <title type="sub">Letters 1916-1923</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna, AT</pubPlace>
            <date>2026</date>
            <availability>
               <p>This is an open access work licensed under Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial 4.0 International license (CC BY-NC 4.0).</p>
            </availability>
            <ptr target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The following institutions have graciously allowed us to include images of letters and photographs in the Letters of 1916-1923 project:
            <list>
            <item>American Irish Historical Society</item>
            <item>Butte-Silver Bow Public Archives</item>
            <item>Chicago History Museum</item>
            <item>Cloyne Diocesan Archives</item>
            <item>Conradh na Gaeilge</item>
            <item>Cork City and County Archives</item>
            <item>Cork Public Museum</item>
            <item>Drogheda Museum, Millmount</item>
            <item>Irish Capuchin Provincial Archives</item>
            <item>Limerick Diocesan Archives</item>
            <item>Local History &amp; Archives Department, Kerry Library, Tralee</item>
            <item>Longford County Library and Archives</item>
            <item>Irish Distillers Pernod Ricard Archive</item>
            <item>Irish Jesuit Archives</item>
            <item>The Jackie Clarke Collection</item>
            <item>Archives and Special Collections, James Hardiman Library, NUI Galway</item>
            <item>Manchester Central Library</item>
            <item>Maynooth University, Library</item>
            <item>Medical Missionaries of Mary</item>
            <item>Merseyside Record Office Liverpool</item>
            <item>Military Archives of Ireland</item>
            <item>New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division</item>
            <item>National Archives of Ireland</item>
            <item>National Library of Ireland</item>
            <item>National Museum of Ireland</item>
            <item>Public Record Office of Northern Ireland (PRONI)</item>
            <item>Redemptorist Provincial Archive</item>
            <item>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew</item>
            <item>Royal College of Physicians of Ireland</item>
            <item>Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland (RCSI) Heritage Collections</item>
            <item>St.Patrick's College Maynooth, Archives</item>
            <item>Trinity College Dublin, Manuscripts and Archives Research Library</item>
            <item>University Archives of UCC</item>
            <item>University College Cork Library Archives Service</item>
            <item>University College Dublin, UCD Archives</item>
            <item>Wexford County Archive</item>
            </list></p>
            <p>More than 2,000 transcribers participated in a crowdsourced transcription project to transcribe the letters. Currently, more than 3,000 letters have been transcribed, validated, and made available for publication.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>Letters 1916-1923 is Ireland's first participatory digital humanities project. Begun in September 2013 as Letters 1916, it expanded its collection period to the end of the Civil War through a generous grant from the Irish Research Council.</p>
         <p>Letters 1916-1923 is a window into what life was like in Ireland a century ago, told in the voices of those who lived through it. This digital collection includes letters held at institutions in Ireland and abroad alongside those in private collections. There are hundreds of letters connecting thousands of lives, commenting on topics from politics to romance, from public administration to medicine. Letters 1916-1923 adds a new perspective to the events of the period, a confidential and intimate glimpse into early 20th-century life in Ireland, as well as how Ireland was viewed abroad.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
